Genesis

3 Now the serpent proved to be the most cautious of all the wild beasts of the field that Jehovah God had made. So it began to say to the woman: “Is it really so that God said YOU must not eat from every tree of the garden?” 2 At this the woman said to the serpent: “Of the fruit of the trees of the garden we may eat. 3 But as for eating of the fruit of the tree that is in the middle of the garden, God has said, ‘YOU must not eat from it, no, YOU must not touch it that YOU do not die.’” 4 At this the serpent said to the woman: “YOU positively will not die. 5 For God knows that in the very day of YOUR eating from it YOUR eyes are bound to be opened and YOU are bound to be like God, KNOWING good and bad.”

6 Consequently the woman saw that the tree was good for food and that it was something to be longed for to the eyes, yes, the tree was desirable to look upon. So she began taking of its fruit and eating it. Afterward she gave some also to her husband when with her and he began eating it. 7 Then the eyes of both of them became opened and they began to realize that they were naked. Hence they sewed fig leaves together and made loin coverings for themselves.

8 Later they heard the voice of Jehovah God walking in the garden about the breezy part of the day, and the man and his wife went into hiding from the face of Jehovah God in between the trees of the garden. 9 And Jehovah God kept calling to the man and saying to him: “Where are you?” 10 Finally he said: “Your voice I heard in the garden, but I was afraid because I was naked and so I hid myself.” 11 At that he said: “Who told you that you were naked? From the tree from which I commanded you not to eat have you eaten?” 12 And the man went on to say: “The woman whom you gave to be with me, she gave me fruit from the tree and so I ate.” 13 With that Jehovah God said to the woman: “What is this you have done?” To this the woman replied: “The serpent—it deceived me and so I ate.”

14 And Jehovah God proceeded to say to the serpent: “Because you have done this thing, you are the cursed one out of all the domestic animals and out of all the wild beasts of the field. Upon your belly you will go and dust is what you will eat all the days of your life. 15 And I shall put enmity between you and the woman and between your seed and her seed. He will bruise you in the head and you will bruise him in the heel.”

16 To the woman he said: “I shall greatly increase the pain of your pregnancy; in birth pangs you will bring forth children, and your craving will be for your husband, and he will dominate you.”

17 And to Adam he said: “Because you listened to your wife’s voice and took to eating from the tree concerning which I gave you this command, ‘You must not eat from it,’ cursed is the ground on your account. In pain you will eat its produce all the days of your life. 18 And thorns and thistles it will grow for you, and you must eat the vegetation of the field. 19 In the sweat of your face you will eat bread until you return to the ground, for out of it you were taken. For dust you are and to dust you will return.”

20 After this Adam called his wife’s name Eve, because she had to become the mother of everyone living. 21 And Jehovah God proceeded to make long garments of skin for Adam and for his wife and to clothe them. 22 And Jehovah God went on to say: “Here the man has become like one of us in knowing good and bad, and now in order that he may not put his hand out and actually take fruit also from the tree of life and eat and live to time indefinite,—” 23 With that Jehovah God put him out of the garden of E′den to cultivate the ground from which he had been taken. 24 And so he drove the man out and posted at the east of the garden of E′den the cherubs and the flaming blade of a sword that was turning itself continually to guard the way to the tree of life.

Genesis

4 Now Adam had intercourse with Eve his wife and she became pregnant. In time she gave birth to Cain and said: “I have produced a man with the aid of Jehovah.” 2 Later she again gave birth, to his brother Abel.

And Abel came to be a herder of sheep, but Cain became a cultivator of the ground. 3 And it came about at the expiration of some time that Cain proceeded to bring some fruits of the ground as an offering to Jehovah. 4 But as for Abel, he too brought some firstlings of his flock, even their fatty pieces. Now while Jehovah was looking with favor upon Abel and his offering, 5 he did not look with any favor upon Cain and upon his offering. And Cain grew hot with great anger, and his countenance began to fall. 6 At this Jehovah said to Cain: “Why are you hot with anger and why has your countenance fallen? 7 If you turn to doing good, will there not be an exaltation? But if you do not turn to doing good, there is sin crouching at the entrance, and for you is its craving; and will you, for your part, get the mastery over it?”

8 After that Cain said to Abel his brother: “Let us go over into the field.” So it came about that while they were in the field Cain proceeded to assault Abel his brother and kill him. 9 Later on Jehovah said to Cain: “Where is Abel your brother?” and he said: “I do not know. Am I my brother’s guardian?” 10 At this he said: “What have you done? Listen! Your brother’s blood is crying out to me from the ground. 11 And now you are cursed in banishment from the ground, which has opened its mouth to receive your brother’s blood at your hand. 12 When you cultivate the ground, it will not give you back its power. A wanderer and a fugitive you will become in the earth.” 13 At this Cain said to Jehovah: “My punishment for error is too great to carry. 14 Here you are actually driving me this day from off the surface of the ground, and from your face I shall be concealed; and I must become a wanderer and fugitive on the earth, and it is certain that anyone finding me will kill me.” 15 At this Jehovah said to him: “For that reason anyone killing Cain must suffer vengeance seven times.”

And so Jehovah set up a sign for Cain in order that no one finding him should strike him. 16 With that Cain went away from the face of Jehovah and took up residence in the land of Fugitiveness to the east of E′den.

17 Afterward Cain had intercourse with his wife and she became pregnant and gave birth to E′noch. Then he engaged in building a city and called the city’s name by the name of his son E′noch. 18 Later there was born to E′noch I′rad. And I′rad became father to Me·hu′ja·el, and Me·hu′ja·el became father to Me·thu′sha·el, and Me·thu′sha·el became father to La′mech.

19 And La′mech proceeded to take two wives for himself. The name of the first was A′dah and the name of the second was Zil′lah. 20 In time A′dah gave birth to Ja′bal. He proved to be the founder of those who dwell in tents and have livestock. 21 And the name of his brother was Ju′bal. He proved to be the founder of all those who handle the harp and the pipe. 22 As for Zil′lah, she too gave birth to Tu′bal-cain, the forger of every sort of tool of copper and iron. And the sister of Tu′bal-cain was Na′a·mah. 23 Consequently La′mech composed these words for his wives A′dah and Zil′lah:

“Hear my voice, YOU wives of La′mech;

Give ear to my saying:

A man I have killed for wounding me,

Yes, a young man for giving me a blow.

24 If seven times Cain is to be avenged,

Then La′mech seventy times and seven.”

25 And Adam proceeded to have intercourse again with his wife and so she gave birth to a son and called his name Seth, because, as she said: “God has appointed for me another seed in place of Abel, because Cain killed him.” 26 And to Seth also there was born a son and he proceeded to call his name E′nosh. At that time a start was made of calling on the name of Jehovah.

Genesis

5 This is the book of Adam’s history. In the day of God’s creating Adam he made him in the likeness of God. 2 Male and female he created them. After that he blessed them and called their name Man in the day of their being created.

3 And Adam lived on for a hundred and thirty years. Then he became father to a son in his likeness, in his image, and called his name Seth. 4 And the days of Adam after his fathering Seth came to be eight hundred years. Meanwhile he became father to sons and daughters. 5 So all the days of Adam that he lived amounted to nine hundred and thirty years and he died.

6 And Seth lived on for a hundred and five years. Then he became father to E′nosh. 7 And after his fathering E′nosh Seth continued to live eight hundred and seven years. Meanwhile he became father to sons and daughters. 8 So all the days of Seth amounted to nine hundred and twelve years and he died.

9 And E′nosh lived on for ninety years. Then he became father to Ke′nan. 10 And after his fathering Ke′nan E′nosh continued to live eight hundred and fifteen years. Meanwhile he became father to sons and daughters. 11 So all the days of E′nosh amounted to nine hundred and five years and he died.

12 And Ke′nan lived on for seventy years. Then he became father to Ma·hal′a·lel. 13 And after his fathering Ma·hal′a·lel Ke′nan continued to live eight hundred and forty years. Meanwhile he became father to sons and daughters. 14 So all the days of Ke′nan amounted to nine hundred and ten years and he died.

15 And Ma·hal′a·lel lived on for sixty-five years. Then he became father to Ja′red. 16 And after his fathering Ja′red Ma·hal′a·lel continued to live eight hundred and thirty years. Meanwhile he became father to sons and daughters. 17 So all the days of Ma·hal′a·lel amounted to eight hundred and ninety-five years and he died.

18 And Ja′red lived on for a hundred and sixty-two years. Then he became father to E′noch. 19 And after his fathering E′noch Ja′red continued to live eight hundred years. Meanwhile he became father to sons and daughters. 20 So all the days of Ja′red amounted to nine hundred and sixty-two years and he died.

21 And E′noch lived on for sixty-five years. Then he became father to Me·thu′se·lah. 22 And after his fathering Me·thu′se·lah E′noch went on walking with the true God three hundred years. Meanwhile he became father to sons and daughters. 23 So all the days of E′noch amounted to three hundred and sixty-five years. 24 And E′noch kept walking with the true God. Then he was no more, for God took him.

25 And Me·thu′se·lah lived on for a hundred and eighty-seven years. Then he became father to La′mech. 26 And after his fathering La′mech Me·thu′se·lah continued to live seven hundred and eighty-two years. Meanwhile he became father to sons and daughters. 27 So all the days of Me·thu′se·lah amounted to nine hundred and sixty-nine years and he died.

28 And La′mech lived on for a hundred and eighty-two years. Then he became father to a son. 29 And he proceeded to call his name Noah, saying: “This one will bring us comfort from our work and from the pain of our hands resulting from the ground which Jehovah has cursed.” 30 And after his fathering Noah La′mech continued to live five hundred and ninety-five years. Meanwhile he became father to sons and daughters. 31 So all the days of La′mech amounted to seven hundred and seventy-seven years and he died.

32 And Noah got to be five hundred years old. After that Noah became father to Shem, Ham and Ja′pheth.

Genesis

9 And God went on to bless Noah and his sons and to say to them: “Be fruitful and become many and fill the earth. 2 And a fear of YOU and a terror of YOU will continue upon every living creature of the earth and upon every flying creature of the heavens, upon everything that goes moving on the ground, and upon all the fishes of the sea. Into YOUR hand they are now given. 3 Every moving animal that is alive may serve as food for YOU. As in the case of green vegetation, I do give it all to YOU. 4 Only flesh with its soul—its blood—YOU must not eat. 5 And, besides that, YOUR blood of YOUR souls shall I ask back. From the hand of every living creature shall I ask it back; and from the hand of man, from the hand of each one who is his brother, shall I ask back the soul of man. 6 Anyone shedding man’s blood, by man will his own blood be shed, for in God’s image he made man. 7 And as for YOU men, be fruitful and become many, make the earth swarm with YOU and become many in it.”

8 And God went on to say to Noah and to his sons with him: 9 “And as for me, here I am establishing my covenant with YOU men and with YOUR offspring after YOU, 10 and with every living soul that is with YOU, among fowls, among beasts and among all living creatures of the earth with YOU, from all those going out of the ark to every living creature of the earth. 11 Yes, I do establish my covenant with YOU: No more will all flesh be cut off by waters of a deluge, and no more will there occur a deluge to bring the earth to ruin.”

12 And God added: “This is the sign of the covenant that I am giving between me and YOU and every living soul that is with YOU, for the generations to time indefinite. 13 My rainbow I do give in the cloud, and it must serve as a sign of the covenant between me and the earth. 14 And it shall occur that when I bring a cloud over the earth, then the rainbow will certainly appear in the cloud. 15 And I shall certainly remember my covenant which is between me and YOU and every living soul among all flesh; and no more will the waters become a deluge to bring all flesh to ruin. 16 And the rainbow must occur in the cloud, and I shall certainly see it to remember the covenant to time indefinite between God and every living soul among all flesh that is upon the earth.”

17 And God repeated to Noah: “This is the sign of the covenant that I do establish between me and all flesh that is upon the earth.”

18 And Noah’s sons who came out of the ark were Shem and Ham and Ja′pheth. Later Ham was the father of Ca′naan. 19 These three were Noah’s sons, and from these was all the earth’s population spread abroad.

20 Now Noah started off as a farmer and proceeded to plant a vineyard. 21 And he began drinking of the wine and became intoxicated, and so he uncovered himself in the midst of his tent. 22 Later Ham the father of Ca′naan saw his father’s nakedness and went telling it to his two brothers outside. 23 At that Shem and Ja′pheth took a mantle and put it upon both their shoulders and walked in backwards. Thus they covered their father’s nakedness, while their faces were turned away, and they did not see their father’s nakedness.

24 Finally Noah awoke from his wine and got to know what his youngest son had done to him. 25 At this he said:

“Cursed be Ca′naan.

Let him become the lowest slave to his brothers.”

26 And he added:

“Blessed be Jehovah, Shem’s God,

And let Ca′naan become a slave to him.

27 Let God grant ample space to Ja′pheth,

And let him reside in the tents of Shem.

Let Ca′naan become a slave to him also.”

28 And Noah continued to live three hundred and fifty years after the deluge. 29 So all the days of Noah amounted to nine hundred and fifty years and he died.

Genesis

12 And Jehovah proceeded to say to A′bram: “Go your way out of your country and from your relatives and from the house of your father to the country that I shall show you; 2 and I shall make a great nation out of you and I shall bless you and I will make your name great; and prove yourself a blessing. 3 And I will bless those who bless you, and him that calls down evil upon you I shall curse, and all the families of the ground will certainly bless themselves by means of you.”

4 At that A′bram went just as Jehovah had spoken to him, and Lot went with him. And A′bram was seventy-five years old when he went out from Ha′ran. 5 So A′bram took Sar′ai his wife and Lot the son of his brother and all the goods that they had accumulated and the souls whom they had acquired in Ha′ran, and they got on their way out to go to the land of Ca′naan. Finally they came to the land of Ca′naan. 6 And A′bram went on through the land as far as the site of She′chem, near the big trees of Mo′reh; and at that time the Ca′naan·ite was in the land. 7 Jehovah now appeared to A′bram and said: “To your seed I am going to give this land.” After that he built an altar there to Jehovah, who had appeared to him. 8 Later he moved from there to the mountainous region to the east of Beth′el and pitched his tent with Beth′el on the west and A′i on the east. Then he built an altar there to Jehovah and began to call on the name of Jehovah. 9 Afterward A′bram broke camp, going then from encampment to encampment toward the Neg′eb.

10 Now a famine arose in the land and A′bram made his way down toward Egypt to reside there as an alien, because the famine was severe in the land. 11 And it came about that as soon as he got near to entering Egypt, then he said to Sar′ai his wife: “Please, now! I well know you are a woman beautiful in appearance. 12 So it is bound to happen that the Egyptians will see you and will say, ‘This is his wife.’ And they will certainly kill me, but you they will preserve alive. 13 Please say you are my sister, in order that it may go well with me on your account, and my soul will be certain to live due to you.”

14 So it happened that, as soon as A′bram entered Egypt, the Egyptians got to see the woman, that she was very beautiful. 15 And the princes of Phar′aoh also got to see her and they began praising her to Phar′aoh, so that the woman was taken to the house of Phar′aoh. 16 And he treated A′bram well on her account, and he came to have sheep and cattle and asses and menservants and maidservants and she-asses and camels. 17 Then Jehovah touched Phar′aoh and his household with great plagues because of Sar′ai, A′bram’s wife. 18 With that Phar′aoh called A′bram and said: “What is this you have done to me? Why did you not tell me that she was your wife? 19 Why did you say, ‘She is my sister,’ so that I was about to take her as my wife? And now here is your wife. Take her and go!” 20 And Phar′aoh issued commands to men concerning him, and they went escorting him and his wife and all that he had.

Genesis

14 Now it came about in the days of Am′ra·phel king of Shi′nar, Ar′i·och king of El·la′sar, Ched·or·la·o′mer king of E′lam, and Ti′dal king of Goi′im, 2 that these made war with Be′ra king of Sod′om, and with Bir′sha king of Go·mor′rah, Shi′nab king of Ad′mah, and Shem·e′ber king of Ze·boi′im, and the king of Be′la (that is to say, Zo′ar). 3 All these marched as allies to the Low Plain of Sid′dim, that is, the Salt Sea.

4 Twelve years they had served Ched·or·la·o′mer, but the thirteenth year they rebelled. 5 And in the fourteenth year Ched·or·la·o′mer came, and also the kings who were with him, and they inflicted defeats on the Reph′a·im in Ash′te·roth-kar·na′im, and the Zu′zim in Ham, and the E′mim in Sha′veh-kir·i·a·tha′im, 6 and the Hor′ites in their mountain of Se′ir, down to El-pa′ran, which is at the wilderness. 7 Then they turned about and came to En-mish′pat, that is, Ka′desh, and defeated the whole field of the A·mal′ek·ites and also the Am′or·ites who were dwelling in Haz′a·zon-ta′mar.

8 At this point the king of Sod′om went on the march, and also the king of Go·mor′rah and the king of Ad′mah and the king of Ze·boi′im and the king of Be′la (that is to say, Zo′ar), and they drew up in battle order against them in the Low Plain of Sid′dim, 9 against Ched·or·la·o′mer king of E′lam and Ti′dal king of Goi′im and Am′ra·phel king of Shi′nar and Ar′i·och king of El·la′sar; four kings against the five. 10 Now the Low Plain of Sid′dim was pits upon pits of bitumen; and the kings of Sod′om and Go·mor′rah took to flight and went falling into them, and those who remained fled to the mountainous region. 11 Then the victors took all the goods of Sod′om and Go·mor′rah and all their food and went on their way. 12 They also took Lot the son of A′bram’s brother and his goods and continued on their way. He was then dwelling in Sod′om.

13 After that a man who had escaped came and told A′bram the Hebrew. He was then tabernacling among the big trees of Mam′re the Am′or·ite, the brother of Esh′col and brother of A′ner; and they were confederates of A′bram. 14 Thus A′bram got to hear that his brother had been taken captive. With that he mustered his trained men, three hundred and eighteen slaves born in his household, and went in pursuit up to Dan. 15 And by night he resorted to dividing his forces, he and his slaves, against them, and thus he defeated them and kept in pursuit of them up to Ho′bah, which is north of Damascus. 16 And he proceeded to recover all the goods, and he recovered also Lot his brother and his goods and also the women and the people.

17 Then the king of Sod′om went out to meet him after he returned from defeating Ched·or·la·o′mer and the kings that were with him, to the Low Plain of Sha′veh, that is, the king’s Low Plain. 18 And Mel·chiz′e·dek king of Sa′lem brought out bread and wine, and he was priest of the Most High God. 19 Then he blessed him and said:

“Blessed be A′bram of the Most High God,

Producer of heaven and earth;

20 And blessed be the Most High God,

Who has delivered your oppressors into your hand!”

At that A′bram gave him a tenth of everything.

21 After that the king of Sod′om said to A′bram: “Give me the souls, but take the goods for yourself.” 22 At this A′bram said to the king of Sod′om: “I do lift up my hand in an oath to Jehovah the Most High God, Producer of heaven and earth, 23 that, from a thread to a sandal lace, no, I shall take nothing from anything that is yours, in order that you may not say, ‘It was I who made A′bram rich.’ 24 Nothing for me! Only what the young men have already eaten, and the share of the men who went with me, A′ner, Esh′col and Mam′re—let them take their share.”

Genesis

15 After these things the word of Jehovah came to A′bram in a vision, saying: “Do not fear, A′bram. I am a shield for you. Your reward will be very great.” 2 At this A′bram said: “Sovereign Lord Jehovah, what will you give me, seeing that I am going childless and the one who will possess my house is a man of Damascus, E·li·e′zer?” 3 And A′bram added: “Look! You have given me no seed, and, look! a son of my household is succeeding me as heir.” 4 But, look! the word of Jehovah to him was in these words: “This man will not succeed you as heir, but one who will come out of your own inward parts will succeed you as heir.”

5 He now brought him outside and said: “Look up, please, to the heavens and count the stars, if you are possibly able to count them.” And he went on to say to him: “So your seed will become.” 6 And he put faith in Jehovah; and he proceeded to count it to him as righteousness. 7 Then he added to him: “I am Jehovah, who brought you out of Ur of the Chal·de′ans to give you this land to take it in possession.” 8 To this he said: “Sovereign Lord Jehovah, by what shall I know that I shall take it in possession?” 9 In turn he said to him: “Take for me a three-year-old heifer and a three-year-old she-goat and a three-year-old ram and a turtledove and a young pigeon.” 10 So he took all these to himself and cut them in two and put each part of them so as to match the other, but the birds he did not cut in pieces. 11 And the birds of prey began to descend upon the carcasses, but A′bram kept driving them away.

12 After a while the sun was about to set, and a deep sleep fell upon A′bram, and, look! a frightfully great darkness was falling upon him. 13 And he began to say to A′bram: “You may know for sure that your seed will become an alien resident in a land not theirs, and they will have to serve them, and these will certainly afflict them for four hundred years. 14 But the nation that they will serve I am judging, and after that they will go out with many goods. 15 As for you, you will go to your forefathers in peace; you will be buried at a good old age. 16 But in the fourth generation they will return here, because the error of the Am′or·ites has not yet come to completion.”

17 The sun was now setting and a dense darkness came and, look! a smoking furnace and a fiery torch that passed in between these pieces. 18 On that day Jehovah concluded with A′bram a covenant, saying: “To your seed I will give this land, from the river of Egypt to the great river, the river Eu·phra′tes: 19 the Ken′ites and the Ken′iz·zites and the Kad′mon·ites 20 and the Hit′tites and the Per′iz·zites and the Reph′a·im 21 and the Am′or·ites and the Ca′naan·ites and the Gir′ga·shites and the Jeb′u·sites.”

Genesis

17 When A′bram got to be ninety-nine years old, then Jehovah appeared to A′bram and said to him: “I am God Almighty. Walk before me and prove yourself faultless. 2 And I will give my covenant between me and you, that I may multiply you very, very much.”

3 At this A′bram fell upon his face, and God continued to speak with him, saying: 4 “As for me, look! my covenant is with you, and you will certainly become a father of a crowd of nations. 5 And your name will not be called A′bram anymore, and your name must become Abraham, because a father of a crowd of nations I will make you. 6 And I will make you very, very fruitful and will make you become nations, and kings will come out of you.

7 “And I will carry out my covenant between me and you and your seed after you according to their generations for a covenant to time indefinite, to prove myself God to you and to your seed after you. 8 And I will give to you and to your seed after you the land of your alien residences, even the entire land of Ca′naan, for a possession to time indefinite; and I will prove myself God to them.”

9 And God said further to Abraham: “As for you, you are to keep my covenant, you and your seed after you according to their generations. 10 This is my covenant that YOU men will keep, between me and YOU men, even your seed after you: Every male of YOURS must get circumcised. 11 And YOU must get circumcised in the flesh of YOUR foreskins, and it must serve as a sign of the covenant between me and YOU. 12 And every male of YOURS eight days old must be circumcised, according to YOUR generations, anyone born in the house and anyone purchased with money from any foreigner who is not from your seed. 13 Every man born in your house and every man purchased with money of yours must without fail get circumcised; and my covenant in the flesh of YOU men must serve as a covenant to time indefinite. 14 And an uncircumcised male who will not get the flesh of his foreskin circumcised, even that soul must be cut off from his people. He has broken my covenant.”

15 And God went on to say to Abraham: “As for Sar′ai your wife, you must not call her name Sar′ai, because Sarah is her name. 16 And I will bless her and also give you a son from her; and I will bless her and she shall become nations; kings of peoples will come from her.” 17 At this Abraham fell upon his face and began to laugh and to say in his heart: “Will a man a hundred years old have a child born, and will Sarah, yes, will a woman ninety years old give birth?”

18 After that Abraham said to the true God: “O that Ish′ma·el might live before you!” 19 To this God said: “Sarah your wife is indeed bearing you a son, and you must call his name Isaac. And I will establish my covenant with him for a covenant to time indefinite to his seed after him. 20 But as regards Ish′ma·el I have heard you. Look! I will bless him and will make him fruitful and will multiply him very, very much. He will certainly produce twelve chieftains, and I will make him become a great nation. 21 However, my covenant I shall establish with Isaac, whom Sarah will bear to you at this appointed time next year.”

22 With that God finished speaking with him and went up from Abraham. 23 Abraham then proceeded to take Ish′ma·el his son and all the men born in his house and everyone purchased with money of his, every male among the men of the household of Abraham, and he went to circumcising the flesh of their foreskins in this very day, just as God had spoken with him. 24 And Abraham was ninety-nine years old when he had the flesh of his foreskin circumcised. 25 And Ish′ma·el his son was thirteen years old when he had the flesh of his foreskin circumcised. 26 In this very day Abraham got circumcised, and also Ish′ma·el his son. 27 And all the men of his household, anyone born in the house and anyone purchased with money from a foreigner, got circumcised with him.

Genesis

20 Now Abraham moved camp from there to the land of the Neg′eb and took up dwelling between Ka′desh and Shur and residing as an alien at Ge′rar. 2 And Abraham repeated concerning Sarah his wife: “She is my sister.” With that A·bim′e·lech king of Ge′rar sent and took Sarah. 3 Afterward God came to A·bim′e·lech in a dream by night and said to him: “Here you are as good as dead because of the woman whom you have taken, since she is owned by another owner as his wife.” 4 However, A·bim′e·lech had not gone near her. Hence he said: “Jehovah, will you kill a nation that is really righteous? 5 Did not he say to me, ‘She is my sister’? and she—did not she too say, ‘He is my brother’? In the honesty of my heart and with innocency of my hands I have done this.” 6 At that the true God said to him in the dream: “I too have known that in the honesty of your heart you have done this, and I was also holding you back from sinning against me. That is why I did not allow you to touch her. 7 But now return the man’s wife, for he is a prophet, and he will make supplication for you. So keep living. But if you are not returning her, know that you will positively die, you and all who are yours.”

8 So A·bim′e·lech got up early in the morning and proceeded to call all his servants and to speak of all these things in their ears. And the men got very much afraid. 9 Then A·bim′e·lech called Abraham and said to him: “What have you done to us, and what sin have I committed against you, in that you have brought upon me and my kingdom a great sin? Deeds that should not have been done you have done in connection with me.” 10 And A·bim′e·lech went on to say to Abraham: “What did you have in view in that you have done this thing?” 11 To this Abraham said: “It was because I said to myself, ‘Doubtless there is no fear of God in this place, and they will certainly kill me because of my wife.’ 12 And, besides, she is truly my sister, the daughter of my father, only not the daughter of my mother; and she became my wife. 13 And it came about that, when God caused me to wander from the house of my father, then I said to her, ‘This is your loving-kindness which you may exercise toward me: At every place where we shall come say of me: “He is my brother.”’”

14 Following that A·bim′e·lech took sheep and cattle and menservants and maidservants and gave them to Abraham and returned to him Sarah his wife. 15 Further A·bim′e·lech said: “Here my land is available to you. Dwell where it is good in your eyes.” 16 And to Sarah he said: “Here I do give a thousand silver pieces of money to your brother. Here it is for you a covering of the eyes to all who are with you, and before everybody, and you are cleared of reproach.” 17 And Abraham began to make supplication to the true God; and God proceeded to heal A·bim′e·lech and his wife and his slave girls, and they began bearing children. 18 For Jehovah had tightly shut up every womb of the house of A·bim′e·lech because of Sarah, Abraham’s wife.

Genesis

21 And Jehovah turned his attention to Sarah just as he had said, and Jehovah now did to Sarah just as he had spoken. 2 And Sarah became pregnant and then bore a son to Abraham in his old age at the appointed time of which God had spoken to him. 3 Accordingly Abraham called the name of his son who had been born to him, whom Sarah had borne to him, Isaac. 4 And Abraham proceeded to circumcise Isaac his son when eight days old, just as God had commanded him. 5 And Abraham was a hundred years old when Isaac his son was born to him. 6 Then Sarah said: “God has prepared laughter for me: everybody hearing of it will laugh at me.” 7 And she added: “Who would have uttered to Abraham, ‘Sarah will certainly suckle children,’ whereas I have given birth to a son in his old age?”

8 Now the child kept growing and came to be weaned; and Abraham then prepared a big feast on the day of Isaac’s being weaned. 9 And Sarah kept noticing the son of Ha′gar the Egyptian, whom she had borne to Abraham, poking fun. 10 So she began to say to Abraham: “Drive out this slave girl and her son, for the son of this slave girl is not going to be an heir with my son, with Isaac!” 11 But the thing proved to be very displeasing to Abraham as regards his son. 12 Then God said to Abraham: “Do not let anything that Sarah keeps saying to you be displeasing to you about the boy and about your slave girl. Listen to her voice, because it is by means of Isaac that what will be called your seed will be. 13 And as for the son of the slave girl, I shall also constitute him a nation, because he is your offspring.”

14 So Abraham got up early in the morning and took bread and a skin water bottle and gave it to Ha′gar, setting it upon her shoulder, and the child, and then dismissed her. And she went her way and wandered about in the wilderness of Be′er-she′ba. 15 Finally the water became exhausted in the skin bottle and she threw the child under one of the bushes. 16 Then she went on and sat down by herself, about the distance of a bowshot away, because she said: “Let me not see it when the child dies.” So she sat down at a distance and began to raise her voice and weep.

17 At that God heard the voice of the boy, and God’s angel called to Ha′gar out of the heavens and said to her: “What is the matter with you, Ha′gar? Do not be afraid, because God has listened to the voice of the boy there where he is. 18 Get up, lift up the boy and take hold of him with your hand, because I shall constitute him a great nation.” 19 Then God opened her eyes so that she caught sight of a well of water; and she went and began to fill the skin bottle with water and to give the boy a drink. 20 And God continued to be with the boy, and he kept growing and dwelling in the wilderness; and he became an archer. 21 And he took up dwelling in the wilderness of Pa′ran, and his mother proceeded to take a wife for him from the land of Egypt.

22 Now it came about at that time that A·bim′e·lech together with Phi′col the chief of his army said to Abraham: “God is with you in everything you are doing. 23 So now swear to me here by God that you will not prove false to me and to my offspring and to my posterity; that, according to the loyal love with which I have dealt with you, you will deal with me and with the land in which you have been residing as an alien.” 24 So Abraham said: “I shall swear.”

25 When Abraham criticized A·bim′e·lech severely as regards the well of water that the servants of A·bim′e·lech had seized by violence, 26 then A·bim′e·lech said: “I do not know who did this thing, neither did you yourself tell it to me, and I myself have also not heard of it except today.” 27 With that Abraham took sheep and cattle and gave them to A·bim′e·lech, and both of them proceeded to conclude a covenant. 28 When Abraham set seven female lambs of the flock by themselves, 29 A·bim′e·lech went on to say to Abraham: “What is the meaning here of these seven female lambs that you have set by themselves?” 30 Then he said: “You are to accept the seven female lambs at my hand, that it may serve as a witness for me that I have dug this well.” 31 That is why he called that place Be′er-she′ba, because there both of them had taken an oath. 32 So they concluded a covenant at Be′er-she′ba, after which A·bim′e·lech got up together with Phi′col the chief of his army and they returned to the land of the Phi·lis′tines. 33 After that he planted a tamarisk tree at Be′er-she′ba and called there upon the name of Jehovah the indefinitely lasting God. 34 And Abraham extended his residence as an alien in the land of the Phi·lis′tines many days.

Genesis

22 Now after these things it came about that the true God put Abraham to the test. Accordingly he said to him: “Abraham!” to which he said: “Here I am!” 2 And he went on to say: “Take, please, your son, your only son whom you so love, Isaac, and make a trip to the land of Mo·ri′ah and there offer him up as a burnt offering on one of the mountains that I shall designate to you.”

3 So Abraham got up early in the morning and saddled his ass and took two of his attendants with him and Isaac his son; and he split the wood for the burnt offering. Then he rose and went on the trip to the place that the true God designated to him. 4 It was first on the third day that Abraham raised his eyes and began to see the place from a distance. 5 Abraham now said to his attendants: “YOU stay here with the ass, but I and the boy want to go on over there and worship and return to YOU.”

6 After that Abraham took the wood of the burnt offering and put it upon Isaac his son and took in his hands the fire and the slaughtering knife, and both of them went on together. 7 And Isaac began to say to Abraham his father: “My father!” In turn he said: “Here I am, my son!” So he continued: “Here are the fire and the wood, but where is the sheep for the burnt offering?” 8 To this Abraham said: “God will provide himself the sheep for the burnt offering, my son.” And both of them walked on together.

9 Finally they reached the place that the true God had designated to him, and Abraham built an altar there and set the wood in order and bound Isaac his son hand and foot and put him upon the altar on top of the wood. 10 Then Abraham put out his hand and took the slaughtering knife to kill his son. 11 But Jehovah’s angel began calling to him out of the heavens and saying: “Abraham, Abraham!” to which he answered: “Here I am!” 12 And he went on to say: “Do not put out your hand against the boy and do not do anything at all to him, for now I do know that you are God-fearing in that you have not withheld your son, your only one, from me.” 13 At that Abraham raised his eyes and looked and there, deep in the foreground, there was a ram caught by its horns in a thicket. So Abraham went and took the ram and offered it up for a burnt offering in place of his son. 14 And Abraham began to call the name of that place Je·ho′vah-ji′reh. This is why it is customarily said today: “In the mountain of Jehovah it will be provided.”

15 And Jehovah’s angel proceeded to call to Abraham the second time out of the heavens 16 and to say: “‘By myself I do swear,’ is the utterance of Jehovah, ‘that by reason of the fact that you have done this thing and you have not withheld your son, your only one, 17 I shall surely bless you and I shall surely multiply your seed like the stars of the heavens and like the grains of sand that are on the seashore; and your seed will take possession of the gate of his enemies. 18 And by means of your seed all nations of the earth will certainly bless themselves due to the fact that you have listened to my voice.’”

19 After that Abraham returned to his attendants, and they got up and went their way together to Be′er-she′ba; and Abraham continued to dwell at Be′er-she′ba.

20 Now it came about after these things that the report got through to Abraham: “Here Mil′cah herself has also borne sons to Na′hor your brother: 21 Uz his firstborn and Buz his brother and Kem·u′el the father of A′ram, 22 and Che′sed and Ha′zo and Pil′dash and Jid′laph and Be·thu′el.” 23 And Be·thu′el became the father of Re·bek′ah. These eight Mil′cah bore to Na′hor the brother of Abraham. 24 There was his concubine too, whose name was Reu′mah. In time she herself also gave birth to Te′bah and Ga′ham and Ta′hash and Ma′a·cah.

Genesis

25 Furthermore, Abraham again took a wife, and her name was Ke·tu′rah. 2 In time she bore him Zim′ran and Jok′shan and Me′dan and Mid′i·an and Ish′bak and Shu′ah.

3 And Jok′shan became father to She′ba and De′dan.

And the sons of De′dan became As·shu′rim and Le·tu′shim and Le·um′mim.

4 And the sons of Mid′i·an were E′phah and E′pher and Ha′noch and A·bi′da and El·da′ah.

All these were the sons of Ke·tu′rah.

5 Later on Abraham gave everything he had to Isaac, 6 but to the sons of the concubines that Abraham had Abraham gave gifts. Then he sent them away from Isaac his son, while he was still alive, eastward, to the land of the East. 7 And these are the days of the years of Abraham’s life which he lived, a hundred and seventy-five years. 8 Then Abraham expired and died in a good old age, old and satisfied, and was gathered to his people. 9 So Isaac and Ish′ma·el his sons buried him in the cave of Mach·pe′lah in the field of E′phron the son of Zo′har the Hit′tite that is in front of Mam′re, 10 the field that Abraham had purchased from the sons of Heth. There Abraham was buried, and also Sarah his wife. 11 And it developed that after Abraham’s death God continued to bless Isaac his son, and Isaac was dwelling close by Be′er-la′hai-roi.

12 And this is the history of Ish′ma·el the son of Abraham whom Ha′gar the Egyptian the maidservant of Sarah bore to Abraham.

13 Now these are the names of the sons of Ish′ma·el, by their names, according to their family origins: Ish′ma·el’s firstborn Ne·ba′ioth and Ke′dar and Ad′be·el and Mib′sam 14 and Mish′ma and Du′mah and Mas′sa, 15 Ha′dad and Te′ma, Je′tur, Na′phish and Ked′e·mah. 16 These are the sons of Ish′ma·el, and these are their names by their courtyards and by their walled camps: twelve chieftains according to their clans. 17 And these are the years of Ish′ma·el’s life, a hundred and thirty-seven years. Then he expired and died and was gathered to his people. 18 And they took up tabernacling from Hav′i·lah near Shur, which is in front of Egypt, as far as As·syr′i·a. In front of all his brothers he settled down.

19 And this is the history of Isaac the son of Abraham.

Abraham became father to Isaac. 20 And Isaac happened to be forty years old at his taking Re·bek′ah the daughter of Be·thu′el the Syrian of Pad′dan-a′ram, the sister of La′ban the Syrian, as his wife. 21 And Isaac kept on entreating Jehovah especially for his wife, because she was barren; so Jehovah let himself be entreated for him, and Re·bek′ah his wife became pregnant. 22 And the sons within her began to struggle with each other, so that she said: “If this is the way it is, just why am I alive?” With that she went to inquire of Jehovah. 23 And Jehovah proceeded to say to her: “Two nations are in your belly, and two national groups will be separated from your inward parts; and the one national group will be stronger than the other national group, and the older will serve the younger.”

24 Gradually her days came to the full for giving birth, and, look! twins were in her belly. 25 Then the first came out red all over like an official garment of hair; so they called his name E′sau. 26 And after that his brother came out and his hand was holding onto the heel of E′sau; so he called his name Jacob. And Isaac was sixty years old at her giving them birth.

27 And the boys got bigger, and E′sau became a man knowing how to hunt, a man of the field, but Jacob a blameless man, dwelling in tents. 28 And Isaac had love for E′sau, because it meant game in his mouth, whereas Re·bek′ah was a lover of Jacob. 29 Once Jacob was boiling up some stew, when E′sau came along from the field and he was tired. 30 So E′sau said to Jacob: “Quick, please, give me a swallow of the red—the red there, for I am tired!” That is why his name was called E′dom. 31 To this Jacob said: “Sell me, first of all, your right as firstborn!” 32 And E′sau continued: “Here I am simply going to die, and of what benefit to me is a birthright?” 33 And Jacob added: “Swear to me first of all!” And he proceeded to swear to him and to sell his right as firstborn to Jacob. 34 And Jacob gave E′sau bread and lentil stew, and he went to eating and drinking. Then he got up and went his way. So E′sau despised the birthright.

Genesis

26 Now there arose a famine in the land, besides the first famine that occurred in the days of Abraham, so that Isaac directed himself to A·bim′e·lech, king of the Phi·lis′tines, to Ge′rar. 2 Then Jehovah appeared to him and said: “Do not go down to Egypt. Tabernacle in the land that I designate to you. 3 Reside as an alien in this land, and I shall continue with you and bless you, because to you and to your seed I shall give all these lands, and I will carry out the sworn statement that I swore to Abraham your father, 4 ‘And I will multiply your seed like the stars of the heavens and I will give to your seed all these lands; and by means of your seed all nations of the earth will certainly bless themselves,’ 5 due to the fact that Abraham listened to my voice and continued to keep his obligations to me, my commands, my statutes, and my laws.” 6 So Isaac went on dwelling at Ge′rar.

7 Well, the men of the place kept asking with respect to his wife, and he would say: “She is my sister.” For he was afraid to say “My wife” for fear that, to quote him, “the men of the place should kill me because of Re·bek′ah,” because she was attractive in appearance. 8 So it came about that as his days there extended themselves A·bim′e·lech, king of the Phi·lis′tines, was looking out of the window and taking in the sight, and there was Isaac having a good time with Re·bek′ah his wife. 9 At once A·bim′e·lech called Isaac and said: “Why, she is no other than your wife! So how is it that you said, ‘She is my sister’?” At this Isaac said to him: “I said it for fear I should die on her account.” 10 But A·bim′e·lech continued: “What is this you have done to us? A little more and certainly one of the people would have lain down with your wife, and you would have brought guilt upon us!” 11 Then A·bim′e·lech commanded all the people, saying: “Anybody touching this man and his wife will surely be put to death!”

12 Afterward Isaac began to sow seed in that land, and in that year he was getting up to a hundred measures to one, as Jehovah was blessing him. 13 Consequently the man became great and went on advancing more and more and growing great until he got very great. 14 And he came to have flocks of sheep and herds of cattle and a large body of servants, so that the Phi·lis′tines began to envy him.

15 As for all the wells that the servants of his father had dug in the days of Abraham his father, these the Phi·lis′tines stopped up and they would fill them with dry earth. 16 Finally A·bim′e·lech said to Isaac: “Move from our neighborhood, because you have grown far stronger than we are.” 17 So Isaac moved from there and encamped in the torrent valley of Ge′rar and took up dwelling there. 18 And Isaac proceeded to dig again the wells of water that they had dug in the days of Abraham his father but which the Phi·lis′tines went stopping up after Abraham’s death; and he resumed calling their names by the names that his father had called them.

19 And the servants of Isaac went on digging in the torrent valley and so they found there a well of fresh water. 20 And the shepherds of Ge′rar fell to quarreling with the shepherds of Isaac, saying: “The water is ours!” Hence he called the name of the well E′sek, because they had contended with him. 21 And they went digging another well, and they fell to quarreling over it also. Hence he called its name Sit′nah. 22 Later he moved away from there and dug another well, but they did not quarrel over it. Hence he called its name Re·ho′both and said: “It is because now Jehovah has given us ample room and has made us fruitful in the earth.”

23 Then he went up from there to Be′er-she′ba. 24 And Jehovah proceeded to appear to him during that night and to say: “I am the God of Abraham your father. Do not be afraid, because I am with you, and I will bless you and multiply your seed on account of Abraham my servant.” 25 Accordingly he built an altar there and called on the name of Jehovah and pitched his tent there, and the servants of Isaac went excavating a well there.

26 Later on A·bim′e·lech came to him from Ge′rar with A·huz′zath his confidential friend and Phi′col the chief of his army. 27 At this Isaac said to them: “Why have YOU come to me, seeing that YOU yourselves hated me and so sent me away from YOUR neighborhood?” 28 To this they said: “We have unmistakably seen that Jehovah has proved to be with you. Hence we said, ‘Let, please, an oath of obligation occur between us, between us and you, and let us conclude a covenant with you, 29 that you will do nothing bad toward us just as we have not touched you and just as we have done only good toward you in that we sent you away in peace. You now are the blessed of Jehovah.’” 30 Then he made a feast for them and they ate and drank. 31 Next morning they were early in rising and they made sworn statements one to the other. After that Isaac sent them away and they went from him in peace.

32 Now on that day it occurred that the servants of Isaac proceeded to come and report to him regarding the well that they had dug, and to say to him: “We have found water!” 33 Hence he called its name Shi′bah. That is why the name of the city is Be′er-she′ba, down to this day.

34 And E′sau grew to be forty years old. Then he took as wife Ju′dith the daughter of Be·e′ri the Hit′tite and also Bas′e·math the daughter of E′lon the Hit′tite. 35 And they were a source of bitterness of spirit to Isaac and Re·bek′ah.

Genesis

28 Consequently Isaac called Jacob and blessed him and commanded him and said to him: “You must not take a wife from the daughters of Ca′naan. 2 Get up, go to Pad′dan-a′ram to the house of Be·thu′el the father of your mother and from there take yourself a wife from the daughters of La′ban the brother of your mother. 3 And God Almighty will bless you and make you fruitful and multiply you, and you will certainly become a congregation of peoples. 4 And he will give to you the blessing of Abraham, to you and to your seed with you, that you may take possession of the land of your alien residences, which God has given to Abraham.”

5 So Isaac sent Jacob away, and he struck out for Pad′dan-a′ram, for La′ban the son of Be·thu′el the Syrian, the brother of Re·bek′ah, mother of Jacob and E′sau.

6 When E′sau saw that Isaac had blessed Jacob and had sent him away to Pad′dan-a′ram to take from there a wife for himself, and that when he blessed him he laid the command upon him, saying: “Do not take a wife from the daughters of Ca′naan”; 7 and that Jacob was obeying his father and his mother and was on his way to Pad′dan-a′ram; 8 then E′sau saw that the daughters of Ca′naan were displeasing in the eyes of Isaac his father. 9 Hence E′sau went to Ish′ma·el and took as wife Ma′ha·lath the daughter of Ish′ma·el the son of Abraham, the sister of Ne·ba′ioth, besides his other wives.

10 And Jacob continued on his way out from Be′er-she′ba and kept going to Ha′ran. 11 In time he came across a place and set about spending the night there because the sun had set. So he took one of the stones of the place and set it as his head supporter and lay down in that place. 12 And he began to dream, and, look! there was a ladder stationed upon the earth and its top reaching up to the heavens; and, look! there were God’s angels ascending and descending on it. 13 And, look! there was Jehovah stationed above it, and he proceeded to say:

“I am Jehovah the God of Abraham your father and the God of Isaac. The land upon which you are lying, to you I am going to give it and to your seed. 14 And your seed will certainly become like the dust particles of the earth, and you will certainly spread abroad to the west and to the east and to the north and to the south, and by means of you and by means of your seed all the families of the ground will certainly bless themselves. 15 And here I am with you and I will keep you in all the way you are going and I will return you to this ground, because I am not going to leave you until I have actually done what I have spoken to you.”

16 Then Jacob awoke from his sleep and said: “Truly Jehovah is in this place and I myself did not know it.” 17 And he grew fearful and added: “How fear-inspiring this place is! This is nothing else but the house of God and this is the gate of the heavens.” 18 So Jacob got up early in the morning and took the stone that was there as his head supporter and he set it up as a pillar and poured oil on the top of it. 19 Further, he called the name of that place Beth′el; but the fact is, Luz was the city’s name formerly.

20 And Jacob went on to vow a vow, saying: “If God will continue with me and will certainly keep me on this way on which I am going and will certainly give me bread to eat and garments to wear 21 and I shall certainly return in peace to the house of my father, then Jehovah will have proved to be my God. 22 And this stone that I have set up as a pillar will become a house of God, and as for everything that you will give me I shall without fail give the tenth of it to you.”

Genesis

31 In time he got to hear the words of the sons of La′ban, saying: “Jacob has taken everything that belonged to our father; and from what belonged to our father he has amassed all this wealth.” 2 When Jacob would look at the face of La′ban, here it was not with him as formerly. 3 Finally Jehovah said to Jacob: “Return to the land of your fathers and to your relatives, and I shall continue with you.” 4 Then Jacob sent and called Rachel and Le′ah out to the field to his flock, 5 and he said to them:

“I am seeing the face of YOUR father, that he is not the same toward me as formerly; but the God of my father has proved to be with me. 6 And YOU yourselves certainly know that with all my power I have served YOUR father. 7 And YOUR father has trifled with me and he has changed my wages ten times, but God has not allowed him to do me harm. 8 If on the one hand he would say, ‘The speckled ones will become your wages,’ then the whole flock produced speckled ones; but if on the other hand he would say, ‘The striped ones will become your wages,’ then the whole flock produced striped ones. 9 So God kept taking the herd of YOUR father away and giving it to me. 10 At last it came about at the time when the flock got in heat that I raised my eyes and saw a sight in a dream and here the he-goats springing upon the flock were striped, speckled and spotty. 11 Then the angel of the true God said to me in the dream, ‘Jacob!’ to which I said, ‘Here I am.’ 12 And he continued, ‘Raise your eyes, please, and see all the he-goats springing upon the flock are striped, speckled and spotty, for I have seen all that La′ban is doing to you. 13 I am the true God of Beth′el, where you anointed a pillar and where you vowed a vow to me. Now get up, go out of this land and return to the land of your birth.’”

14 At this Rachel and Le′ah answered and said to him: “Is there a share of inheritance for us anymore in the house of our father? 15 Are we not really considered as foreigners to him since he has sold us, so that he keeps eating continually even from the money given for us? 16 For all the riches that God has taken away from our father are ours and our children’s. So now everything God has said to you do.”

17 Then Jacob got up and lifted his children and his wives onto the camels; 18 and he began driving all his herd and all the goods that he had accumulated, the herd of his acquisition that he had accumulated in Pad′dan-a′ram, in order to go to Isaac his father to the land of Ca′naan.

19 Now La′ban had gone to shear his sheep. Meantime Rachel stole the teraphim that belonged to her father. 20 So Jacob outwitted La′ban the Syrian, because he had not told him that he was running away. 21 And he proceeded to run away and to get up and cross the River, he and all he had. After that he directed his face to the mountainous region of Gil′e·ad. 22 Later, on the third day, it was told to La′ban that Jacob had run away. 23 With that he took his brothers with him and went chasing after him for a distance of seven days’ journey and caught up with him in the mountainous region of Gil′e·ad. 24 Then God came to La′ban the Syrian in a dream by night and said to him: “Watch yourself that you do not go speaking either good or bad with Jacob.”

25 So La′ban approached Jacob, as Jacob had pitched his tent in the mountain and La′ban had encamped his brothers in the mountainous region of Gil′e·ad. 26 Then La′ban said to Jacob: “What have you done, in that you resorted to outwitting me and driving my daughters off like captives taken by the sword? 27 Why did you have to run away secretly and outwit me and not tell me, that I might send you away with rejoicing and with songs, with tambourine and with harp? 28 And you did not give me a chance to kiss my children and my daughters. Now you have acted foolishly. 29 It is in the power of my hand to do harm to YOU people, but the God of YOUR father talked to me last night, saying, ‘Watch yourself against speaking either good or bad with Jacob.’ 30 While you have actually gone now because you have been yearning intensely for the house of your father, why, though, have you stolen my gods?”

31 In answer Jacob proceeded to say to La′ban: “It was because I was afraid. For I said to myself, ‘You might tear your daughters away from me.’ 32 Whoever it is with whom you may find your gods, let him not live. Before our brothers, examine for yourself what is with me and take them for yourself.” But Jacob did not know that Rachel had stolen them. 33 So La′ban went on into the tent of Jacob and into the tent of Le′ah and into the tent of the two slave girls, but did not find them. Finally he went out of Le′ah’s tent and went on into Rachel’s tent. 34 Now Rachel had taken the teraphim, and she resorted to putting them in the woman’s saddle basket of the camel, and she kept sitting upon them. So La′ban went feeling through the whole tent, but did not find them. 35 Then she said to her father: “Do not let anger gleam in the eyes of my lord, because I am not able to get up before you, for the customary thing with women is upon me.” So he searched on carefully, but did not find the teraphim.

36 And Jacob became angry and began to quarrel with La′ban, and in answer Jacob went on to say to La′ban: “What is the revolt on my part, what the sin of mine, as a reason why you have hotly pursued after me? 37 Now that you have felt through all my goods, what of all the goods of your house have you found? Put it here in front of my brothers and your brothers, and let them decide between us two. 38 These twenty years I have been with you. Your female sheep and your she-goats did not suffer abortions, and the rams of your flock I never ate. 39 Any animal torn to pieces I did not bring to you. I myself would stand the loss of it. Whether one was stolen by day or was stolen by night, you would put in a claim for it from my hand. 40 It has been my experience that by day the heat consumed me and the cold by night, and my sleep would flee from my eyes. 41 This makes twenty years for me in your house. I have served you fourteen years for your two daughters and six years for your flock, and you kept changing my wages ten times. 42 If the God of my father, the God of Abraham and the Dread of Isaac, had not proved on my side, you would now have sent me away empty-handed. My wretchedness and the toil of my hands God has seen, and so he reproved you last night.”

43 Then La′ban in answer said to Jacob: “The daughters are my daughters and the children my children and the flock my flock, and everything you are looking at is mine and my daughters’. What can I do against these today or against their children whom they have borne? 44 And now, come, let us conclude a covenant, I and you, and it must serve as a witness between me and you.” 45 Accordingly Jacob took a stone and set it up as a pillar. 46 Then Jacob said to his brothers: “Pick up stones!” And they went taking stones and making a heap. After that they ate there on the heap. 47 And La′ban began calling it Je′gar-sa·ha·du′tha, but Jacob called it Gal′e·ed.

48 And La′ban proceeded to say: “This heap is a witness between me and you today.” That is why he called its name Gal′e·ed, 49 and The Watchtower, because he said: “Let Jehovah keep watch between me and you when we are situated unseen the one from the other. 50 If you go to afflicting my daughters and if you go to taking wives in addition to my daughters, there is no man with us. See! God is a witness between me and you.” 51 And La′ban went on to say to Jacob: “Here is this heap and here is the pillar that I have erected between me and you. 52 This heap is a witness, and the pillar is something that bears witness, that I will not pass this heap against you and that you will not pass this heap and this pillar against me for harm. 53 Let the god of Abraham and the god of Na′hor judge between us, the god of their father.” But Jacob swore by the Dread of his father Isaac.

54 After that Jacob sacrificed a sacrifice in the mountain and invited his brothers to eat bread. Accordingly they ate bread and passed the night in the mountain. 55 However, La′ban got up early in the morning and kissed his children and his daughters and blessed them. Then La′ban got on his way that he might return to his own place.

Genesis

35 After that God said to Jacob: “Rise, go up to Beth′el and dwell there, and make an altar there to the true God who appeared to you when you were running away from E′sau your brother.”

2 Then Jacob said to his household and to all who were with him: “Put away the foreign gods that are in the midst of YOU and cleanse yourselves and change YOUR mantles, 3 and let us rise and go up to Beth′el. And there I shall make an altar to the true God who answered me in the day of my distress in that he proved to be with me in the way that I have gone.” 4 So they gave Jacob all the foreign gods that were in their hands and the earrings that were in their ears, and Jacob hid them under the big tree that was close by She′chem.

5 After that they pulled away, and the terror of God came to be upon the cities that were round about them, so that they did not chase after the sons of Jacob. 6 Eventually Jacob came to Luz, which is in the land of Ca′naan, that is to say, Beth′el, he and all the people who were with him. 7 Then he built an altar there and began to call the place El-beth′el, because there the true God had revealed himself to him at the time of his running away from his brother. 8 Later Deb′o·rah the nursing woman of Re·bek′ah died and was buried at the foot of Beth′el under a massive tree. Hence he called its name Al′lon-bac′uth.

9 God now appeared to Jacob once again during his coming from Pad′dan-a′ram and blessed him. 10 And God went on to say to him: “Your name is Jacob. No longer is your name to be called Jacob, but Israel will your name become.” And he began to call his name Israel. 11 And God said further to him: “I am God Almighty. Be fruitful and become many. Nations and a congregation of nations will proceed out of you, and kings will come out of your loins. 12 As for the land that I have given to Abraham and to Isaac, to you I shall give it, and to your seed after you I shall give the land.” 13 After that God went up from above him at the place where he had spoken with him.

14 Consequently Jacob stationed a pillar in the place where he had spoken with him, a pillar of stone, and he poured a drink offering upon it and poured oil upon it. 15 And Jacob continued to call the name of the place where God had spoken with him Beth′el.

16 Then they pulled away from Beth′el. And while there was yet a good stretch of land before coming to Eph′rath, Rachel proceeded to give birth, and it was going hard with her in making the delivery. 17 But so it was that while she had difficulty in making the delivery the midwife said to her: “Do not be afraid, for you will have this son also.” 18 And the result was that as her soul was going out (because she died) she called his name Ben-o′ni; but his father called him Benjamin. 19 Thus Rachel died and was buried on the way to Eph′rath, that is to say, Beth′le·hem. 20 Hence Jacob stationed a pillar over her grave. This is the pillar of Rachel’s grave down to this day.

21 After that Israel pulled away and pitched his tent a distance beyond the tower of E′der. 22 And it came about while Israel was tabernacling in that land that once Reu′ben went and lay down with Bil′hah his father’s concubine, and Israel got to hear of it.

So there came to be twelve sons of Jacob. 23 The sons by Le′ah were Jacob’s firstborn Reu′ben and Sim′e·on and Le′vi and Judah and Is′sa·char and Zeb′u·lun. 24 The sons by Rachel were Joseph and Benjamin. 25 And the sons by Bil′hah, Rachel’s maidservant, were Dan and Naph′ta·li. 26 And the sons by Zil′pah, Le′ah’s maidservant, were Gad and Ash′er. These are Jacob’s sons who were born to him in Pad′dan-a′ram.

27 At length Jacob came to Isaac his father to Mam′re, to Kir′i·ath-ar′ba, that is to say, He′bron, where Abraham and also Isaac had resided as aliens. 28 And the days of Isaac came to be a hundred and eighty years. 29 After that Isaac expired and died and was gathered to his people, old and satisfied with days, and E′sau and Jacob his sons buried him.

Genesis

38 Now in the meantime it came about that when Judah went down from his brothers he pitched his tent near a man, an A·dul′lam·ite, and his name was Hi′rah. 2 And there Judah got to see a daughter of a certain Ca′naan·ite, and his name was Shu′a. So he took her and had relations with her. 3 And she became pregnant. Later she bore a son and he called his name Er. 4 Again she became pregnant. In time she bore a son and called his name O′nan. 5 Yet another time she went on to bear a son and then called his name She′lah. Now he happened to be in Ach′zib at the time she bore him.

6 In time Judah took a wife for Er his firstborn, and her name was Ta′mar. 7 But Er, Judah’s firstborn, proved to be bad in the eyes of Jehovah; hence Jehovah put him to death. 8 In view of that Judah said to O′nan: “Have relations with your brother’s wife and perform brother-in-law marriage with her and raise up offspring for your brother.” 9 But O′nan knew that the offspring would not become his; and it occurred that when he did have relations with his brother’s wife he wasted his semen on the earth so as not to give offspring to his brother. 10 Now what he did was bad in the eyes of Jehovah; hence he put him also to death. 11 So Judah said to Ta′mar his daughter-in-law: “Dwell as a widow in the house of your father until She′lah my son grows up.” For he said to himself: “He too may die like his brothers.” Accordingly Ta′mar went and continued to dwell at her own father’s house.

12 Thus the days became many and the daughter of Shu′a, Judah’s wife, died; and Judah kept the period of mourning. After that he went up to the shearers of his sheep, he and Hi′rah his companion the A·dul′lam·ite, to Tim′nah. 13 Then it was told to Ta′mar: “Here your father-in-law is going up to Tim′nah to shear his sheep.” 14 With that she removed the garments of her widowhood from her and covered herself with a shawl and veiled herself and sat down at the entrance of E·na′im, which is along the road to Tim′nah. For she saw that She′lah had grown up and yet she had not been given as a wife to him.

15 When Judah caught sight of her, he at once took her for a harlot, because she had covered her face. 16 So he turned aside to her by the road and said: “Allow me, please, to have relations with you.” For he did not know that she was his daughter-in-law. However, she said: “What will you give me that you may have relations with me?” 17 To this he said: “I myself shall send a kid of the goats from the herd.” But she said: “Will you give a security until you send it?” 18 And he continued: “What is the security that I shall give you?” to which she said: “Your seal ring and your cord and your rod that is in your hand.” Then he gave them to her and had relations with her, so that she became pregnant by him. 19 After that she got up and went and removed her shawl off her and clothed herself with the garments of her widowhood.

20 And Judah proceeded to send the kid of the goats by the hand of his companion the A·dul′lam·ite in order to get back the security from the hand of the woman, but he never found her. 21 And he went inquiring of the men of her place, saying: “Where is that temple prostitute in E·na′im along the road?” But they kept saying: “No temple prostitute has ever been in this place.” 22 Finally he returned to Judah and said: “I never found her and, besides, the men of the place said, ‘No temple prostitute has ever been in this place.’” 23 So Judah said: “Let her take them for herself, in order that we may not fall into contempt. At any rate, I have sent this kid, but you—you never found her.”

24 However, about three months later it happened that it was told to Judah: “Ta′mar your daughter-in-law has played the harlot, and here she is also pregnant by her harlotry.” At that Judah said: “BRING her out and let her be burned.” 25 As she was being brought out she herself sent to her father-in-law, saying: “By the man to whom these belong I am pregnant.” And she added: “Examine, please, to whom these belong, the seal ring and the cord and the rod.” 26 Then Judah examined them and said: “She is more righteous than I am, for the reason that I did not give her to She′lah my son.” And he had no further intercourse with her after that.

27 Now it developed that in the time of her giving birth, why, here there were twins in her belly. 28 Further, it turned out that when she was giving birth one extended his hand, and the midwife at once took and tied a scarlet piece about his hand, saying: “This one came out first.” 29 Finally it developed that as soon as he drew back his hand, why, here his brother came out, so that she exclaimed: “What do you mean by this, that you have produced a perineal rupture for yourself?” Hence his name was called Pe′rez. 30 And afterward his brother upon whose hand the scarlet piece was came out and his name came to be called Ze′rah.

Genesis

39 As for Joseph, he was brought down to Egypt, and Pot′i·phar, a court official of Phar′aoh, the chief of the bodyguard, an Egyptian, got to buy him from the hand of the Ish′ma·el·ites who had brought him down there. 2 But Jehovah proved to be with Joseph, so that he turned out a successful man and came to be over the house of his master, the Egyptian. 3 And his master got to see that Jehovah was with him and that everything he was doing Jehovah was making turn out successful in his hand.

4 And Joseph kept finding favor in his eyes and waited upon him continually, so that he appointed him over his house, and all that was his he gave into his hand. 5 And it followed that from the time he appointed him over his house and in charge of all that was his Jehovah kept blessing the house of the Egyptian due to Joseph, and Jehovah’s blessing came to be upon all that he had in the house and in the field. 6 Finally he left everything that was his in Joseph’s hand; and he did not know what was with him at all except the bread he was eating. Moreover, Joseph grew to be beautiful in form and beautiful in appearance.

7 Now after these things it came about that the wife of his master began to raise her eyes toward Joseph and say: “Lie down with me.” 8 But he would refuse and would say to his master’s wife: “Here my master does not know what is with me in the house, and everything he has he has given into my hand. 9 There is no one greater in this house than I am, and he has not withheld from me anything at all except you, because you are his wife. So how could I commit this great badness and actually sin against God?”

10 So it turned out that as she spoke to Joseph day after day he never listened to her to lie alongside her, to continue with her. 11 But it happened that on this day as other days he went into the house to do his business, and there was none of the men of the house there in the house. 12 Then she grabbed hold of him by his garment, saying: “Lie down with me!” But he left his garment in her hand and took to flight and went on outside. 13 So it occurred that as soon as she saw that he had left his garment in her hand that he might flee outside, 14 she began to cry out to the men of her house and to say to them: “Look! He brought to us a man, a Hebrew, to make us a laughingstock. He came to me to lie down with me, but I began to cry out at the top of my voice. 15 And it followed that as soon as he heard that I raised my voice and began crying out, he then left his garment beside me and took to flight and went on outside.” 16 After that she kept his garment laid up beside her until his master came to his house.

17 Then she spoke to him according to these words, saying: “The Hebrew servant whom you brought to us came to me to make me a laughingstock. 18 But it followed that as soon as I raised my voice and began to cry out, he then left his garment beside me and went fleeing outside.” 19 The result was that as soon as his master heard the words of his wife which she spoke to him, saying: “Like this and this your servant did to me,” his anger blazed. 20 So Joseph’s master took him and gave him over to the prison house, the place where the prisoners of the king were kept under arrest, and he continued there in the prison house.

21 However, Jehovah continued with Joseph and kept extending loving-kindness to him and granting him to find favor in the eyes of the chief officer of the prison house. 22 So the chief officer of the prison house gave over into Joseph’s hand all the prisoners who were in the prison house; and everything that they were doing there he proved to be the one having it done. 23 The chief officer of the prison house was looking after absolutely nothing that was in his hand, because Jehovah was with Joseph and what he was doing Jehovah was making it turn out successful.

Genesis

41 And it came about at the end of two full years that Phar′aoh was dreaming and here he was standing by the river Nile. 2 And here ascending out of the river Nile were seven cows beautiful in appearance and fat-fleshed, and they went feeding among the Nile grass. 3 And here there were seven other cows ascending after them out of the river Nile, ugly in appearance and thin-fleshed, and they took their stand alongside the cows by the bank of the river Nile. 4 Then the cows that were ugly in appearance and thin-fleshed began to eat up the seven cows that were beautiful in appearance and fat. At this Phar′aoh woke up.

5 However, he went back to sleep and dreamed a second time. And here there were seven ears of grain coming up on one stalk, fat and good. 6 And here there were seven ears of grain, thin and scorched by the east wind, growing up after them. 7 And the thin ears of grain began to swallow up the seven fat and full ears of grain. At this Phar′aoh woke up and here it was a dream.

8 And it developed in the morning that his spirit became agitated. So he sent and called all the magic-practicing priests of Egypt and all her wise men, and Phar′aoh went on to relate his dreams to them. But there was no interpreter of them for Phar′aoh.

9 Then the chief of the cupbearers spoke with Phar′aoh, saying: “My sins I am mentioning today. 10 Phar′aoh was indignant at his servants. So he committed me to the jail of the house of the chief of the bodyguard, both me and the chief of the bakers. 11 After that we both dreamed a dream in the one night, both I and he. We dreamed each one his dream with its own interpretation. 12 And there was with us there a young man, a Hebrew, a servant of the chief of the bodyguard. When we related them to him, he proceeded to interpret our dreams to us. He interpreted to each according to his dream. 13 And it turned out that just as he had interpreted to us so it happened. Me he returned to my office, but him he hanged.”

14 And Phar′aoh proceeded to send and to call Joseph, that they might bring him quickly from the prison hole. Hence he shaved and changed his mantles and went in to Phar′aoh. 15 Then Phar′aoh said to Joseph: “I have dreamed a dream, but there is no interpreter of it. Now I myself have heard it said about you that you can hear a dream and interpret it.” 16 At this Joseph answered Phar′aoh, saying: “I need not be considered! God will announce welfare to Phar′aoh.”

17 And Phar′aoh went on to speak to Joseph: “In my dream here I was standing on the bank of the river Nile. 18 And here ascending out of the river Nile were seven cows fat-fleshed and beautiful in form, and they began to feed among the Nile grass. 19 And here there were seven other cows ascending after them, poor and very bad in form and thin-fleshed. For badness I have not seen the like of them in all the land of Egypt. 20 And the skinny and bad cows began to eat up the first seven fat cows. 21 So these came into their bellies, and yet it could not be known that they had come into their bellies, as their appearance was bad just as at the start. At that I woke up.

22 “After that I saw in my dream and here there were seven ears of grain coming up on one stalk, full and good. 23 And here there were seven ears of grain shriveled, thin, scorched by the east wind, growing up after them. 24 And the thin ears of grain began to swallow up the seven good ears of grain. So I stated it to the magic-practicing priests, but there was none telling me.”

25 Then Joseph said to Phar′aoh: “The dream of Phar′aoh is but one. What the true God is doing he has told to Phar′aoh. 26 The seven good cows are seven years. Likewise the seven good ears of grain are seven years. The dream is but one. 27 And the seven skinny and bad cows that came up after them are seven years; and the seven empty ears of grain, scorched by the east wind, will prove to be seven years of famine. 28 This is the thing that I have spoken to Phar′aoh: What the true God is doing he has caused Phar′aoh to see.

29 “Here there are seven years coming with great plenty in all the land of Egypt. 30 But seven years of famine will certainly arise after them, and all the plenty in the land of Egypt will certainly be forgotten and the famine will simply consume the land. 31 And the plenty once in the land will not be known as a result of that famine afterward, because it will certainly be very severe. 32 And the fact that the dream was repeated to Phar′aoh twice means that the thing is firmly established on the part of the true God, and the true God is speeding to do it.

33 “So now let Phar′aoh look for a man discreet and wise and set him over the land of Egypt. 34 Let Phar′aoh act and appoint overseers over the land, and he must take up one fifth of the land of Egypt during the seven years of plenty. 35 And let them collect all the foodstuffs of these coming good years, and let them pile up grain under Phar′aoh’s hand as foodstuffs in the cities, and they must safeguard it. 36 And the foodstuffs must serve as a supply for the land for the seven famine years, which will develop in the land of Egypt, in order that the land may not be cut off by the famine.”

37 Well, the thing proved to be good in the eyes of Phar′aoh and of all his servants. 38 So Phar′aoh said to his servants: “Can another man be found like this one in whom the spirit of God is?” 39 After that Phar′aoh said to Joseph: “Since God has caused you to know all this, there is no one as discreet and wise as you are. 40 You will personally be over my house, and all my people will obey you implicitly. Only as to the throne shall I be greater than you.” 41 And Phar′aoh added to Joseph: “See, I do place you over all the land of Egypt.” 42 With that Phar′aoh removed his signet ring from his own hand and put it upon Joseph’s hand and clothed him with garments of fine linen and placed a necklace of gold about his neck. 43 Moreover, he had him ride in the second chariot of honor that he had, so that they should call out ahead of him, “A·vrékh!” thus putting him over all the land of Egypt.

44 And Phar′aoh further said to Joseph: “I am Phar′aoh, but without your authorization no man may lift up his hand or his foot in all the land of Egypt.” 45 After that Phar′aoh called Joseph’s name Zaph′e·nath-pa·ne′ah and gave him As′e·nath the daughter of Pot·i′phe·ra the priest of On as a wife. And Joseph began to go out over the land of Egypt. 46 And Joseph was thirty years old when he stood before Phar′aoh the king of Egypt.

Then Joseph went out from before Phar′aoh and toured about in all the land of Egypt. 47 And during the seven years of plenty the land went on producing by the handfuls. 48 And he kept collecting all the foodstuffs of the seven years that came upon the land of Egypt and he would put the foodstuffs in the cities. The foodstuffs of the field that was round about a city he put in the midst of it. 49 And Joseph continued piling up grain in very great quantity, like the sand of the sea, until finally they gave up counting it, because it was without number.

50 And before the year of the famine arrived there were born to Joseph two sons, whom As′e·nath the daughter of Pot·i′phe·ra the priest of On bore to him. 51 So Joseph called the name of the firstborn Ma·nas′seh, because, to quote him, “God has made me forget all my trouble and all the house of my father.” 52 And the name of the second he called E′phra·im, because, to quote him, “God has made me fruitful in the land of my wretchedness.”

53 And the seven years of the plenty that had obtained in the land of Egypt gradually ended, 54 and, in turn, the seven years of the famine started to come, just as Joseph had said. And the famine developed in all the lands, but in all the land of Egypt there was found bread. 55 Finally all the land of Egypt became famished and the people began to cry to Phar′aoh for bread. Then Phar′aoh said to all the Egyptians: “Go to Joseph. Whatever he says to YOU, YOU are to do.” 56 And the famine obtained over all the surface of the earth. Then Joseph began to open up all the grain depositories that were among them and to sell to the Egyptians, as the famine got a strong grip on the land of Egypt. 57 Moreover, people of all the earth came to Egypt to buy from Joseph, because the famine had a strong grip on all the earth.

Genesis

44 Later on he commanded the man who was over his house, saying: “Fill the bags of the men with food to the extent they are able to carry it and place the money of each one in the mouth of his bag. 2 But you must place my cup, the silver cup, in the mouth of the bag of the youngest and the money for his cereals.” So he did according to the word of Joseph which he had spoken.

3 The morning had become light when the men were sent away, both they and their asses. 4 They went out of the city. They had not gone far when Joseph said to the man who was over his house: “Get up! Chase after the men and be certain to overtake them and to say to them, ‘Why have YOU repaid bad for good? 5 Is not this the thing that my master drinks from and by means of which he expertly reads omens? It is a bad deed YOU have committed.’”

6 Eventually he overtook them and spoke these words to them. 7 But they said to him: “Why does my lord speak with such words as these? It is unthinkable that your servants should do anything like this. 8 Why, the money that we found in the mouth of our bags we brought back to you from the land of Ca′naan. How, then, could we steal silver or gold from the house of your master? 9 Let the one of your slaves with whom it may be found die and let us ourselves also become slaves to my master.” 10 So he said: “Let it be now exactly according to YOUR words. Thus the one with whom it may be found will become a slave to me, but YOU yourselves will be proved innocent.” 11 With that they quickly let down each one his bag to the earth and they opened each one his own bag. 12 And he went searching carefully. He started with the oldest and finished with the youngest. At last the cup was found in Benjamin’s bag.

13 Then they ripped their mantles apart and lifted each one his load back onto his ass and returned to the city. 14 And Judah and his brothers went on into Joseph’s house, and he was still there; and they proceeded to fall before him to the earth. 15 Joseph now said to them: “What sort of deed is this that YOU have done? Did YOU not know that such a man as I am can expertly read omens?” 16 At this Judah exclaimed: “What can we say to my master? What can we speak? And how can we prove ourselves righteous? The true God has found out the error of your slaves. Here we are slaves to my master, both we and the one in whose hand the cup was found!” 17 However, he said: “It is unthinkable for me to do this! The man in whose hand the cup was found is the one who will become a slave to me. As for the rest of YOU, go up in peace to YOUR father.”

18 Judah now came near to him and said: “I pray you, my master, please let your slave speak a word in the hearing of my master, and do not let your anger grow hot against your slave, because it is the same with you as with Phar′aoh. 19 My master asked his slaves, saying, ‘Do YOU have a father or a brother?’ 20 So we said to my master, ‘We do have an aged father and a child of his old age, the youngest. But his brother is dead so that he alone is left of his mother, and his father does love him.’ 21 After that you said to your slaves, ‘Bring him down to me that I may set my eye upon him.’ 22 But we said to my master, ‘The boy is not able to leave his father. If he did leave his father, he would certainly die.’ 23 Then you said to your slaves, ‘Unless YOUR youngest brother comes down with YOU, YOU may not see my face anymore.’

24 “And it came about that we went up to your slave my father and then told him the words of my master. 25 Later our father said, ‘Return, buy a little food for us.’ 26 But we said, ‘We are not able to go down. If our youngest brother is with us we will go down, because we are not able to see the man’s face in case our youngest brother is not with us.’ 27 Then your slave my father said to us, ‘YOU yourselves well know that my wife bore but two sons to me. 28 Later the one went out from my company and I exclaimed: “Ah, he must surely be torn to pieces!” and I have not seen him till now. 29 If YOU were to take this one also out of my sight and a fatal accident were to befall him, YOU would certainly bring down my gray hairs with calamity to She′ol.’

30 “And now, as soon as I should come to your slave my father without the boy along with us, when that one’s soul is bound up with this one’s soul, 31 then it is certain to occur that as soon as he sees that the boy is not there he will simply die, and your slaves will indeed bring down the gray hairs of your slave our father with grief to She′ol. 32 For your slave became surety for the boy when away from his father, saying, ‘If I fail to bring him back to you, then I shall have sinned against my father forever.’ 33 So now, please, let your slave stay instead of the boy as a slave to my master, that the boy may go up with his brothers. 34 For how can I go up to my father without the boy along with me, for fear that then I may look upon the calamity that will find out my father?”

Genesis

50 Then Joseph fell upon the face of his father and burst into tears over him and kissed him. 2 After that Joseph commanded his servants, the physicians, to embalm his father. So the physicians embalmed Israel, 3 and they took fully forty days for him, for this many days they customarily take for the embalming, and the Egyptians continued to shed tears for him seventy days.

4 Finally the days of weeping for him passed, and Joseph spoke to Phar′aoh’s household, saying: “If, now, I have found favor in YOUR eyes, speak, please, in the hearing of Phar′aoh, saying, 5 ‘My father made me swear, saying: “Look! I am dying. In my burial place which I have excavated for myself in the land of Ca′naan is where you are to bury me.” And now, please, let me go up and bury my father, after which I am willing to return.’” 6 Accordingly Phar′aoh said: “Go up and bury your father just as he made you swear.”

7 So Joseph went up to bury his father, and there went up with him all of Phar′aoh’s servants, the older men of his household and all the older men of the land of Egypt, 8 and all of Joseph’s household and his brothers and the household of his father. Only their little children and their flocks and their herds they left in the land of Go′shen. 9 There also went up with him both chariots and horsemen, and the camp came to be very numerous. 10 Then they came to the threshing floor of A′tad, which is in the region of the Jordan, and there they carried on a very great and heavy wailing and he kept up the mourning rites for his father seven days. 11 And the inhabitants of the land, the Ca′naan·ites, got to see the mourning rites in the threshing floor of A′tad, and they exclaimed: “This is a heavy mourning for the Egyptians!” That is why its name was called A′bel-miz′ra·im, which is in the region of the Jordan.

12 And his sons proceeded to do for him exactly as he had commanded them. 13 So his sons carried him into the land of Ca′naan and buried him in the cave of the field of Mach·pe′lah, the field that Abraham had purchased for the possession of a burial place from E′phron the Hit′tite in front of Mam′re. 14 Afterward Joseph returned to Egypt, he and his brothers and all those who went up with him to bury his father, after he had buried his father.

15 When the brothers of Joseph saw that their father was dead, they began to say: “It may be that Joseph is harboring animosity against us and he will be sure to repay us for all the evil that we have rendered him.” 16 So they expressed a command to Joseph in these words: “Your father gave the command before his death, saying, 17 ‘This is what YOU are to say to Joseph: “I beseech you, pardon, please, the revolt of your brothers and their sin in that they have rendered evil to you.”’ And now pardon, please, the revolt of the servants of your father’s God.” And Joseph burst into tears when they spoke to him. 18 Following that his brothers also came and fell down before him and said: “Here we are as slaves to you!” 19 Then Joseph said to them: “Do not be afraid, for am I in the place of God? 20 As for YOU, YOU had evil in mind against me. God had it in mind for good for the purpose of acting as at this day to preserve many people alive. 21 So now do not be afraid. I myself shall keep supplying YOU and YOUR little children with food.” Thus he comforted them and spoke reassuringly to them.

22 And Joseph continued to dwell in Egypt, he and the house of his father; and Joseph lived for a hundred and ten years. 23 And Joseph got to see E′phra·im’s sons of the third generation, also the sons of Ma′chir, Ma·nas′seh’s son. They were born upon Joseph’s knees. 24 At length Joseph said to his brothers: “I am dying; but God will without fail turn his attention to YOU, and he will certainly bring YOU up out of this land to the land about which he swore to Abraham, to Isaac and to Jacob.” 25 Hence Joseph made the sons of Israel swear, saying: “God will without fail turn his attention to YOU. Accordingly YOU must take my bones up out of here.” 26 After that Joseph died at the age of a hundred and ten years; and they had him embalmed, and he was put in a coffin in Egypt.

Exodus

2 Meantime, a certain man of the house of Le′vi went ahead and took a daughter of Le′vi. 2 And the woman became pregnant and brought a son to birth. When she saw how good-looking he was, she kept him concealed for three lunar months. 3 When she was no longer able to conceal him, she then took for him an ark of papyrus and coated it with bitumen and pitch and put the child in it and put it among the reeds by the bank of the river Nile. 4 Further, his sister stationed herself at a distance to find out what would be done with him.

5 After a while Phar′aoh’s daughter came down to bathe in the Nile River, and her female attendants were walking by the side of the Nile River. And she caught sight of the ark in the middle of the reeds. Immediately she sent her slave girl that she might get it. 6 When she opened it she got to see the child, and here the boy was weeping. At that she felt compassion for him, although she said: “This is one of the children of the Hebrews.” 7 Then his sister said to Phar′aoh’s daughter: “Shall I go and specially call for you a nursing woman from the Hebrew women that she may nurse the child for you?” 8 So Phar′aoh’s daughter said to her: “Go!” At once the maiden went and called the child’s mother. 9 Phar′aoh’s daughter then said to her: “Take this child with you and nurse him for me, and I myself shall give you your wages.” Accordingly the woman took the child and nursed him. 10 And the child grew up. Then she brought him to Phar′aoh’s daughter, so that he became a son to her; and she proceeded to call his name Moses and to say: “It is because I have drawn him out of the water.”

11 Now it came about in those days, as Moses was becoming strong, that he went out to his brothers that he might look at the burdens they were bearing; and he caught sight of a certain Egyptian striking a certain Hebrew of his brothers. 12 So he turned this way and that and saw there was nobody in sight. Then he struck the Egyptian down and hid him in the sand.

13 However, he went out on the following day and here there were two Hebrew men struggling with each other. So he said to the one in the wrong: “Why should you strike your companion?” 14 At this he said: “Who appointed you as a prince and judge over us? Are you intending to kill me just as you killed the Egyptian?” Moses now got afraid and said: “Surely the thing has become known!”

15 Subsequently Phar′aoh got to hear of this thing, and he attempted to kill Moses; but Moses ran away from Phar′aoh that he might dwell in the land of Mid′i·an; and he took a seat by a well. 16 Now the priest of Mid′i·an had seven daughters, and as usual they came and drew water and filled the gutters to water their father’s flock. 17 And as usual the shepherds came and drove them away. At this Moses got up and helped the women out and watered their flock. 18 So when they came home to Reu′el their father he exclaimed: “How is it YOU have come home so quickly today?” 19 To this they said: “A certain Egyptian delivered us out of the hand of the shepherds and, besides, he actually drew water for us that he might water the flock.” 20 Then he said to his daughters: “But where is he? Why is it that YOU have left the man behind? Call him, that he may eat bread.” 21 After that Moses showed willingness to dwell with the man, and he gave Zip·po′rah his daughter to Moses. 22 Later she bore a son and he called his name Ger′shom, because, he said: “An alien resident I have come to be in a foreign land.”

23 And it came about during those many days that the king of Egypt finally died, but the sons of Israel continued to sigh because of the slavery and to cry out in complaint, and their cry for help kept going up to the true God because of the slavery. 24 In time God heard their groaning and God remembered his covenant with Abraham, Isaac and Jacob. 25 So God looked on the sons of Israel and God took notice.

Exodus

3 And Moses became a shepherd of the flock of Jeth′ro, the priest of Mid′i·an, whose son-in-law he was. While he was driving the flock to the west side of the wilderness, he came at length to the mountain of the true God, to Ho′reb. 2 Then Jehovah’s angel appeared to him in a flame of fire in the midst of a thornbush. As he kept looking, why, here the thornbush was burning with the fire and yet the thornbush was not consumed. 3 At this Moses said: “Let me just turn aside that I may inspect this great phenomenon, as to why the thornbush is not burnt up.” 4 When Jehovah saw that he turned aside to inspect, God at once called to him out of the midst of the thornbush and said: “Moses! Moses!” to which he said: “Here I am.” 5 Then he said: “Do not come near here. Draw your sandals from off your feet, because the place where you are standing is holy ground.”

6 And he went on to say: “I am the God of your father, the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac and the God of Jacob.” Then Moses concealed his face, because he was afraid to look at the true God. 7 And Jehovah added: “Unquestionably I have seen the affliction of my people who are in Egypt, and I have heard their outcry as a result of those who drive them to work; because I well know the pains they suffer. 8 And I am proceeding to go down to deliver them out of the hand of the Egyptians and to bring them up out of that land to a land good and spacious, to a land flowing with milk and honey, to the locality of the Ca′naan·ites and the Hit′tites and the Am′or·ites and the Per′iz·zites and the Hi′vites and the Jeb′u·sites. 9 And now, look! the outcry of the sons of Israel has come to me, and I have seen also the oppression with which the Egyptians are oppressing them. 10 And now come and let me send you to Phar′aoh, and you bring my people the sons of Israel out of Egypt.”

11 However, Moses said to the true God: “Who am I that I should go to Phar′aoh and that I have to bring the sons of Israel out of Egypt?” 12 To this he said: “Because I shall prove to be with you, and this is the sign for you that it is I who have sent you: After you have brought the people out of Egypt, YOU people will serve the true God on this mountain.”

13 Nevertheless, Moses said to the true God: “Suppose I am now come to the sons of Israel and I do say to them, ‘The God of YOUR forefathers has sent me to YOU,’ and they do say to me, ‘What is his name?’ What shall I say to them?” 14 At this God said to Moses: “I SHALL PROVE TO BE WHAT I SHALL PROVE TO BE.” And he added: “This is what you are to say to the sons of Israel, ‘I SHALL PROVE TO BE has sent me to YOU.’” 15 Then God said once more to Moses:

“This is what you are to say to the sons of Israel, ‘Jehovah the God of YOUR forefathers, the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac and the God of Jacob, has sent me to YOU.’ This is my name to time indefinite, and this is the memorial of me to generation after generation. 16 You go, and you must gather the older men of Israel, and you must say to them, ‘Jehovah the God of YOUR forefathers has appeared to me, the God of Abraham, Isaac and Jacob, saying: “I will without fail give attention to YOU and to what is being done to YOU in Egypt. 17 And so I say, I shall bring YOU up out of affliction by the Egyptians to the land of the Ca′naan·ites and the Hit′tites and the Am′or·ites and the Per′iz·zites and the Hi′vites and the Jeb′u·sites, to a land flowing with milk and honey.”’

18 “And they will certainly listen to your voice, and you must come, you and the older men of Israel, to the king of Egypt, and YOU men must say to him, ‘Jehovah the God of the Hebrews has come in touch with us, and now we want to go, please, a journey of three days into the wilderness, and we want to sacrifice to Jehovah our God.’ 19 And I, even I, well know that the king of Egypt will not give YOU permission to go except by a strong hand. 20 And I shall have to stretch out my hand and strike Egypt with all my wonderful acts that I shall do in the midst of it; and after that he will send YOU out. 21 And I will give this people favor in the eyes of the Egyptians; and it will certainly occur that when YOU go, YOU will not go empty-handed. 22 And each woman must ask from her neighbor and from the woman residing as an alien in her house articles of silver and articles of gold and mantles, and YOU must put them upon YOUR sons and YOUR daughters; and YOU must strip the Egyptians.”

Exodus

4 However, Moses in answering said: “But suppose they do not believe me and do not listen to my voice, because they are going to say, ‘Jehovah did not appear to you.’” 2 Then Jehovah said to him: “What is that in your hand?” to which he said: “A rod.” 3 Next he said: “Throw it on the earth.” So he threw it on the earth, and it became a serpent; and Moses began to flee from it. 4 Jehovah now said to Moses: “Thrust your hand out and grab hold of it by the tail.” So he thrust his hand out and grabbed hold of it, and it became a rod in his palm. 5 “In order that,” to quote him, “they may believe that Jehovah the God of their forefathers, the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac and the God of Jacob, has appeared to you.”

6 Then Jehovah said to him once more: “Stick your hand, please, into the upper fold of your garment.” So he stuck his hand into the upper fold of his garment. When he drew it out, why, here his hand was stricken with leprosy like snow! 7 After that he said: “Return your hand into the upper fold of your garment.” So he returned his hand into the upper fold of his garment. When he drew it out of the upper fold of his garment, why, here it was restored like the rest of his flesh! 8 “And it must occur that,” to quote him, “if they will not believe you and will not listen to the voice of the first sign, then they will certainly believe the voice of the later sign. 9 Still, it must occur that, if they will not believe even these two signs and will not listen to your voice, then you will have to take some water from the Nile River and pour it out on the dry land; and the water that you will take from the Nile River will certainly become, yes, it will indeed become blood on the dry land.”

10 Moses now said to Jehovah: “Excuse me, Jehovah, but I am not a fluent speaker, neither since yesterday nor since before that nor since your speaking to your servant, for I am slow of mouth and slow of tongue.” 11 At that Jehovah said to him: “Who appointed a mouth for man or who appoints the speechless or the deaf or the clear-sighted or the blind? Is it not I, Jehovah? 12 So now go, and I myself shall prove to be with your mouth and I will teach you what you ought to say.” 13 But he said: “Excuse me, Jehovah, but send, please, by the hand of the one whom you are going to send.” 14 Then Jehovah’s anger grew hot against Moses and he said: “Is not Aaron the Levite your brother? I do know that he can really speak. And, besides, here he is on his way out to meet you. When he does see you, he will certainly rejoice in his heart. 15 And you must speak to him and put the words in his mouth; and I myself shall prove to be with your mouth and his mouth, and I will teach YOU men what YOU are to do. 16 And he must speak for you to the people; and it must occur that he will serve as a mouth to you, and you will serve as God to him. 17 And this rod you will take in your hand that you may perform the signs with it.”

18 Accordingly Moses went and returned to Jeth′ro his father-in-law and said to him: “I want to go, please, and return to my brothers who are in Egypt that I may see whether they are still alive.” So Jeth′ro said to Moses: “Go in peace.” 19 After that Jehovah said to Moses in Mid′i·an: “Go, return to Egypt, because all the men who were hunting for your soul are dead.”

20 Then Moses took his wife and his sons and made them ride on an ass, and he proceeded to return to the land of Egypt. Moreover, Moses took the rod of the true God in his hand. 21 And Jehovah went on to say to Moses: “After you have gone and returned to Egypt see that you actually perform all the miracles that I have put in your hand before Phar′aoh. As for me, I shall let his heart become obstinate; and he will not send the people away. 22 And you must say to Phar′aoh, ‘This is what Jehovah has said: “Israel is my son, my firstborn. 23 And I say to you: Send my son away that he may serve me. But should you refuse to send him away, here I am killing your son, your firstborn.”’”

24 Now it came about on the road at the lodging place that Jehovah got to meet him and kept looking for a way to put him to death. 25 Finally Zip·po′rah took a flint and cut off her son’s foreskin and caused it to touch his feet and said: “It is because you are a bridegroom of blood to me.” 26 Consequently he let go of him. At that time she said: “A bridegroom of blood,” because of the circumcision.

27 Then Jehovah said to Aaron: “Go to meet Moses into the wilderness.” With that he went and met him in the mountain of the true God and kissed him. 28 And Moses proceeded to tell Aaron all the words of Jehovah, who had sent him, and all the signs that he had commanded him to do. 29 After that Moses and Aaron went and gathered all the older men of the sons of Israel. 30 Then Aaron spoke all the words that Jehovah had spoken to Moses, and he performed the signs under the eyes of the people. 31 At this the people believed. When they heard that Jehovah had turned his attention to the sons of Israel and that he had seen their affliction, then they bowed down and prostrated themselves.

Exodus

5 And afterward Moses and Aaron went in and proceeded to say to Phar′aoh: “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel has said, ‘Send my people away that they may celebrate a festival to me in the wilderness.’” 2 But Phar′aoh said: “Who is Jehovah, so that I should obey his voice to send Israel away? I do not know Jehovah at all and, what is more, I am not going to send Israel away.” 3 However, they went on to say: “The God of the Hebrews has come in touch with us. We want to go, please, a journey of three days into the wilderness and sacrifice to Jehovah our God; otherwise he may strike at us with pestilence or with sword.” 4 At this the king of Egypt said to them: “Why is it, Moses and Aaron, that YOU cause the people to leave off from their works? Go bearing YOUR burdens!” 5 And Phar′aoh continued: “Look! The people of the land are now many, and YOU indeed make them desist from their bearing of burdens.”

6 Immediately on that day Phar′aoh commanded those who drove the people to work and their officers, saying: 7 “YOU must not gather straw to give to the people to make bricks as formerly. Let them themselves go and gather straw for themselves. 8 Moreover, the required amount of bricks that they were making formerly, YOU will further impose upon them. YOU must not make any reduction for them, because they are relaxing. That is why they are crying out, saying, ‘We want to go, we want to sacrifice to our God!’ 9 Let the service be heavy upon the men and let them work at it, and let them not pay attention to false words.”

10 So those who drove the people to work and their officers went out and said to the people: “Here is what Phar′aoh has said, ‘I am giving YOU no more straw. 11 YOU yourselves go, get straw for yourselves wherever YOU may find it, because there is to be no reducing of YOUR services one bit.’” 12 Consequently the people scattered about over all the land of Egypt to gather stubble for straw. 13 And those who drove them to work kept urging them, saying: “Finish YOUR works, each one his work, day for day, just as when straw was available.” 14 Later on the officers of the sons of Israel, whom Phar′aoh’s taskmasters had set over them, were beaten, these saying: “Why is it YOU did not finish YOUR prescribed task in making bricks as formerly, both yesterday and today?”

15 Consequently the officers of the sons of Israel went in and began to cry out to Phar′aoh, saying: “Why do you deal this way with your servants? 16 There is no straw given to your servants and yet they are saying to us, ‘Make bricks!’ and here your servants are beaten, whereas your own people are at fault.” 17 But he said: “YOU are relaxing, YOU are relaxing! That is why YOU are saying, ‘We want to go, we want to sacrifice to Jehovah.’ 18 And now go, serve! Though no straw will be given to YOU, yet YOU are to give the fixed amount of bricks.”

19 Then the officers of the sons of Israel saw themselves in an evil plight at the saying: “YOU must not deduct from YOUR bricks one bit of anyone’s daily rate.” 20 After that they encountered Moses and Aaron, who were standing there to meet them as they came out from Phar′aoh. 21 At once they said to them: “May Jehovah look upon YOU and judge, since YOU have made us smell offensive before Phar′aoh and before his servants so as to put a sword in their hand to kill us.” 22 Then Moses turned to Jehovah and said: “Jehovah, why have you caused evil to this people? Why is it that you have sent me? 23 For from the time that I went in before Phar′aoh to speak in your name, he has done evil to this people, and you have by no means delivered your people.”

Exodus

8 Then Jehovah said to Moses: “Go in to Phar′aoh, and you must say to him, ‘This is what Jehovah has said: “Send my people away that they may serve me. 2 And if you keep refusing to send them away, here I am plaguing all your territory with frogs. 3 And the Nile River will fairly teem with frogs, and they will certainly come up and enter into your house and your inner bedroom and upon your couch and into the houses of your servants and on your people and into your ovens and into your kneading troughs. 4 And on you and on your people and on all your servants the frogs will come up.”’”

5 Later on Jehovah said to Moses: “Say to Aaron, ‘Stretch your hand with your rod out over the rivers, the Nile canals and the reedy pools and make the frogs come up over the land of Egypt.’” 6 At that Aaron stretched his hand out over the waters of Egypt, and the frogs began to come up and to cover the land of Egypt. 7 However, the magic-practicing priests did the same thing by their secret arts and made the frogs come up over the land of Egypt. 8 In time Phar′aoh called Moses and Aaron and said: “Entreat Jehovah that he may remove the frogs from me and my people, as I want to send the people away that they may sacrifice to Jehovah.” 9 Then Moses said to Phar′aoh: “You take the glory over me to say when I shall make entreaty for you and your servants and your people in order to cut the frogs off from you and your houses. Only in the Nile River will they be left.” 10 To this he said: “Tomorrow.” So he said: “It will be according to your word, in order that you may know that there is no one else like Jehovah our God, 11 in that the frogs will certainly turn away from you and your houses and your servants and your people. Only in the Nile River will they be left.”

12 Accordingly Moses and Aaron went out from Phar′aoh, and Moses cried out to Jehovah because of the frogs that He had put upon Phar′aoh. 13 Then Jehovah did according to Moses’ word, and the frogs began to die off from the houses, the courtyards and the fields. 14 And they went piling them up, heaps upon heaps, and the land began to stink. 15 When Phar′aoh got to see that relief had taken place, he made his heart unresponsive; and he did not listen to them, just as Jehovah had spoken.

16 Jehovah now said to Moses: “Say to Aaron, ‘Stretch your rod out and strike the dust of the earth, and it must become gnats in all the land of Egypt.’” 17 And they proceeded to do this. So Aaron stretched out his hand with his rod and struck the dust of the earth, and the gnats came to be on man and beast. All the dust of the earth became gnats in all the land of Egypt. 18 And the magic-practicing priests tried to do the same by their secret arts, in order to bring forth gnats, but they were unable. And the gnats came to be on man and beast. 19 Hence the magic-practicing priests said to Phar′aoh: “It is the finger of God!” But Phar′aoh’s heart continued to be obstinate, and he did not listen to them, just as Jehovah had spoken.

20 Then Jehovah said to Moses: “Get up early in the morning and take a position in front of Phar′aoh. Look! He is coming out to the water! And you must say to him, ‘This is what Jehovah has said: “Send my people away that they may serve me. 21 But if you are not sending my people away, here I am sending upon you and your servants and your people and into your houses the gadfly; and the houses of Egypt will simply be full of the gadfly, and also the ground upon which they are. 22 And on that day I shall certainly make the land of Go′shen upon which my people are standing distinct, that no gadfly may exist there; in order that you may know that I am Jehovah in the midst of the earth. 23 And I shall indeed set a demarcation between my people and your people. Tomorrow this sign will take place.”’”

24 And Jehovah proceeded to do so; and heavy swarms of gadflies began to invade the house of Phar′aoh and the houses of his servants and all the land of Egypt. The land came to ruin as a result of the gadflies. 25 Finally Phar′aoh called Moses and Aaron and said: “Go, sacrifice to YOUR God in the land.” 26 But Moses said: “It is not admissible to do so, because we would sacrifice to Jehovah our God a thing detestable to the Egyptians. Suppose we would sacrifice a thing detestable to the Egyptians before their eyes; would they not stone us? 27 We shall go a journey of three days into the wilderness and we shall definitely sacrifice to Jehovah our God just as he has said to us.”

28 Phar′aoh now said: “I—I shall send YOU away, and YOU will indeed sacrifice to Jehovah YOUR God in the wilderness. Only do not make it quite so far away that YOU are going. Make entreaty in my behalf.” 29 Then Moses said: “Here I am going forth from you, and I shall indeed make entreaty to Jehovah, and the gadflies will certainly turn away from Phar′aoh, his servants and his people tomorrow. Only let not Phar′aoh trifle again in not sending the people away to sacrifice to Jehovah.” 30 After that Moses went out from Phar′aoh and made entreaty to Jehovah. 31 So Jehovah did according to Moses’ word, and the gadflies turned away from Phar′aoh, his servants and his people. Not one was left. 32 However, Phar′aoh made his heart unresponsive this time also and did not send the people away.

Exodus

10 Then Jehovah said to Moses: “Go in to Phar′aoh, because I—I have let his heart and the hearts of his servants become unresponsive, in order that I may set these signs of mine right before him, 2 and in order that you may declare in the ears of your son and your son’s son how severely I have dealt with Egypt and my signs that I have established among them; and YOU will certainly know that I am Jehovah.”

3 So Moses and Aaron went in to Phar′aoh and said to him: “This is what Jehovah the God of the Hebrews has said, ‘How long must you refuse to submit yourself to me? Send my people away that they may serve me. 4 For if you continue refusing to send my people away, here I am bringing locusts within your boundaries tomorrow. 5 And they will actually cover the visible surface of the earth and it will not be possible to see the earth; and they will simply eat up the rest of what has escaped, what has been left to YOU people by the hail, and they will certainly eat every sprouting tree of YOURS out of the field. 6 And your houses and the houses of all your servants and the houses of all Egypt will be filled to an extent that your fathers and your fathers’ fathers have not seen it from the day of their existing upon the ground until this day.’” With that he turned and went out from Phar′aoh.

7 After that Phar′aoh’s servants said to him: “How long will this man prove to be as a snare to us? Send the men away that they may serve Jehovah their God. Do you not yet know that Egypt has perished?” 8 So Moses and Aaron were brought back to Phar′aoh, and he said to them: “Go, serve Jehovah YOUR God. Who in particular are the ones going?” 9 Then Moses said: “With our young people and our old people we shall go. With our sons and our daughters, with our sheep and our cattle we shall go, for we have a festival to Jehovah.” 10 In turn he said to them: “Let it prove to be so, that Jehovah is with YOU when I shall send YOU and YOUR little ones away! See, on the contrary, something evil is YOUR aim. 11 Not so! Go, please, YOU who are able-bodied men, and serve Jehovah, because that is what YOU are seeking to secure.” With that they were driven out from before Phar′aoh.

12 Jehovah now said to Moses: “Stretch your hand out over the land of Egypt for the locusts, that they may come up over the land of Egypt and eat up all the vegetation of the land, everything that the hail has let remain.” 13 At once Moses stretched his rod out over the land of Egypt, and Jehovah caused an east wind to blow upon the land all that day and all night. The morning came and the east wind carried the locusts. 14 And the locusts began to come up over all the land of Egypt and to settle down upon all the territory of Egypt. They were very burdensome. Before them there had never turned up in this way locusts like them, and there will never turn up any in this way after them. 15 And they went covering the visible surface of the entire land, and the land grew dark; and they went on eating up all the vegetation of the land and all the fruit of the trees that the hail had left; and there was left nothing green on the trees or on the vegetation of the field in all the land of Egypt.

16 So Phar′aoh hurriedly called Moses and Aaron and said: “I have sinned against Jehovah YOUR God and against YOU. 17 And now pardon, please, my sin just this once and ENTREAT Jehovah YOUR God that he may turn away just this deadly plague from upon me.” 18 So he went out from Phar′aoh and made entreaty to Jehovah. 19 Then Jehovah made a shift to a very stiff west wind, and it carried the locusts away and drove them into the Red Sea. Not a single locust was let remain in all the territory of Egypt. 20 However, Jehovah let Phar′aoh’s heart become obstinate, and he did not send the sons of Israel away.

21 Jehovah then said to Moses: “Stretch your hand out toward the heavens, that darkness may occur over the land of Egypt and the darkness may be felt.” 22 Moses immediately stretched his hand out toward the heavens, and a gloomy darkness began to occur in all the land of Egypt for three days. 23 They did not see one another, and none of them got up from his own place three days; but for all the sons of Israel there proved to be light in their dwellings. 24 After that Phar′aoh called Moses and said: “Go, SERVE Jehovah. Only YOUR sheep and YOUR cattle will be detained. YOUR little ones also may go with YOU.” 25 But Moses said: “You yourself will also give into our hands sacrifices and burnt offerings, as we must render them to Jehovah our God. 26 And our livestock will also go with us. Not a hoof will be allowed to remain, because it is from them that we shall take some to worship Jehovah our God, and we ourselves do not know what we shall render in worship to Jehovah until our arriving there.” 27 At this Jehovah let Phar′aoh’s heart become obstinate, and he did not consent to send them away. 28 So Phar′aoh said to him: “Get out from me! Watch yourself! Do not try to see my face again, because on the day of your seeing my face you will die.” 29 To this Moses said: “That is the way you have spoken. I shall not try to see your face anymore.”

Exodus

11 And Jehovah proceeded to say to Moses: “One plague more I am going to bring upon Phar′aoh and Egypt. After that he will send YOU away from here. At the time he sends YOU away altogether, he will literally drive YOU out from here. 2 Speak, now, in the ears of the people, that they should ask every man of his companion and every woman of her companion articles of silver and articles of gold.” 3 Accordingly Jehovah gave the people favor in the eyes of the Egyptians. The man Moses too was very great in the land of Egypt, in the eyes of Phar′aoh’s servants and in the eyes of the people.

4 And Moses went on to say: “This is what Jehovah has said, ‘About midnight I am going out into the midst of Egypt, 5 and every firstborn in the land of Egypt must die, from the firstborn of Phar′aoh who is sitting on his throne to the firstborn of the maidservant who is at the hand mill and every firstborn of beast. 6 And there will certainly occur a great outcry in all the land of Egypt, the like of which has never yet occurred, and the like of which will never be brought about again. 7 But against any of the sons of Israel will no dog move eagerly its tongue, from man to beast; in order that YOU people may know that Jehovah can make a distinction between the Egyptians and the sons of Israel.’ 8 And all these servants of yours will certainly come down to me and prostrate themselves to me, saying, ‘Go, you and all the people who follow your steps.’ And after that I shall go out.” With that he went out from Phar′aoh in the heat of anger.

9 Then Jehovah said to Moses: “Phar′aoh will not listen to YOU men, in order for my miracles to be increased in the land of Egypt.” 10 And Moses and Aaron performed all these miracles before Phar′aoh; but Jehovah would let Phar′aoh’s heart become obstinate, so that he did not send the sons of Israel away from his land.

Exodus

12 Jehovah now said to Moses and Aaron in the land of Egypt: 2 “This month will be the start of the months for YOU. It will be the first of the months of the year for YOU. 3 Speak to the entire assembly of Israel, saying, ‘On the tenth day of this month they are to take for themselves each one a sheep for the ancestral house, a sheep to a house. 4 But if the household proves to be too small for the sheep, then he and his neighbor close by must take it into his house according to the number of souls; YOU should compute each one proportionate to his eating as regards the sheep. 5 The sheep should prove to be sound, a male, a year old, for YOU. YOU may pick from the young rams or from the goats. 6 And it must continue under safeguard by YOU until the fourteenth day of this month, and the whole congregation of the assembly of Israel must slaughter it between the two evenings. 7 And they must take some of the blood and splash it upon the two doorposts and the upper part of the doorway belonging to the houses in which they will eat it.

8 “‘And they must eat the flesh on this night. They should eat it roasted with fire and with unfermented cakes along with bitter greens. 9 Do not eat any of it raw or boiled, cooked in water, but roast with fire, its head together with its shanks and its interior parts. 10 And YOU must not leave any of it over till morning, but what is left over of it till morning YOU should burn with fire. 11 And in this way YOU should eat it, with YOUR hips girded, sandals on YOUR feet and YOUR staff in YOUR hand; and YOU must eat it in haste. It is Jehovah’s passover. 12 And I must pass through the land of Egypt on this night and strike every firstborn in the land of Egypt, from man to beast; and on all the gods of Egypt I shall execute judgments. I am Jehovah. 13 And the blood must serve as YOUR sign upon the houses where YOU are; and I must see the blood and pass over YOU, and the plague will not come on YOU as a ruination when I strike at the land of Egypt.

14 “‘And this day must serve as a memorial for YOU, and YOU must celebrate it as a festival to Jehovah throughout YOUR generations. As a statute to time indefinite YOU should celebrate it. 15 Seven days YOU are to eat unfermented cakes. Yes, on the first day YOU are to take away sourdough from YOUR houses, because anyone eating what is leavened, from the first day down to the seventh, that soul must be cut off from Israel. 16 And on the first day there is to take place for YOU a holy convention, and on the seventh day a holy convention. No work is to be done on them. Only what every soul needs to eat, that alone may be done for YOU.

17 “‘And YOU must keep the festival of unfermented cakes, because on this very day I must bring YOUR armies out from the land of Egypt. And YOU must keep this day throughout YOUR generations as a statute to time indefinite. 18 In the first month, on the fourteenth day of the month, in the evening YOU are to eat unfermented cakes down till the twenty-first day of the month in the evening. 19 Seven days no sourdough is to be found in YOUR houses, because anyone tasting what is leavened, whether he is an alien resident or a native of the land, that soul must be cut off from the assembly of Israel. 20 Nothing leavened are YOU to eat. In all YOUR dwellings YOU are to eat unfermented cakes.’”

21 Promptly Moses called all the older men of Israel and said to them: “Draw out and take for yourselves small cattle according to YOUR families, and slaughter the passover victim. 22 And YOU must take a bunch of hyssop and dip it into the blood in a basin and strike upon the upper part of the doorway and upon the two doorposts some of the blood that is in the basin; and none of YOU should go out of the entrance of his house until morning. 23 Then when Jehovah does pass through to plague the Egyptians and does see the blood upon the upper part of the doorway and upon the two doorposts, Jehovah will certainly pass over the entrance, and he will not allow the ruination to enter into YOUR houses to plague YOU.

24 “And YOU must keep this thing as a regulation for you and your sons to time indefinite. 25 And it must occur that when YOU come into the land that Jehovah will give YOU, just as he has stated, then YOU must keep this service. 26 And it must occur that when YOUR sons say to YOU, ‘What does this service mean to YOU?’ 27 then YOU must say, ‘It is the sacrifice of the passover to Jehovah, who passed over the houses of the sons of Israel in Egypt when he plagued the Egyptians, but he delivered our houses.’”

Then the people bowed low and prostrated themselves. 28 Subsequently the sons of Israel went and did just as Jehovah had commanded Moses and Aaron. They did just so.

29 And it came about that at midnight Jehovah struck every firstborn in the land of Egypt, from the firstborn of Phar′aoh sitting on his throne to the firstborn of the captive who was in the prison hole, and every firstborn of beast. 30 Then Phar′aoh got up at night, he and all his servants and all other Egyptians; and there began arising a great outcry among the Egyptians, because there was not a house where there was not one dead. 31 At once he called Moses and Aaron by night and said: “Get up, get out from the midst of my people, both YOU and the other sons of Israel, and go, serve Jehovah, just as YOU have stated. 32 Take both YOUR flocks and YOUR herds, just as YOU have stated, and go. Also, YOU must bless me besides.”

33 And the Egyptians began to urge the people in order to send them away quickly out of the land, “because,” they said, “we are all as good as dead!” 34 Consequently the people carried their flour dough before it was leavened, with their kneading troughs wrapped up in their mantles upon their shoulder. 35 And the sons of Israel did according to the word of Moses in that they went asking from the Egyptians articles of silver and articles of gold and mantles. 36 And Jehovah gave the people favor in the eyes of the Egyptians, so that these granted them what was asked; and they stripped the Egyptians.

37 And the sons of Israel proceeded to depart from Ram′e·ses for Suc′coth, to the number of six hundred thousand able-bodied men on foot, besides little ones. 38 And a vast mixed company also went up with them, as well as flocks and herds, a very numerous stock of animals. 39 And they began to bake the flour dough that they had brought out from Egypt into round cakes, unfermented cakes, because it had not leavened, for they had been driven out of Egypt and had not been able to linger and too they had not prepared any provisions for themselves.

40 And the dwelling of the sons of Israel, who had dwelt in Egypt, was four hundred and thirty years. 41 And it came about at the end of the four hundred and thirty years, it even came about on this very day that all the armies of Jehovah went out of the land of Egypt. 42 It is a night for observance with regard to Jehovah for bringing them out of the land of Egypt. With regard to Jehovah this night is one for observance on the part of all the sons of Israel throughout their generations.

43 And Jehovah went on to say to Moses and Aaron: “This is the statute of the passover: No foreigner may eat of it. 44 But where there is any slave man purchased with money, you must circumcise him. Then first he may share in eating it. 45 A settler and a hired laborer may not eat of it. 46 In one house it is to be eaten. You must not take any of the flesh out of the house to some place outside. And YOU must not break a bone in it. 47 All the assembly of Israel are to celebrate it. 48 And in case an alien resident resides as an alien with you and he will actually celebrate the passover to Jehovah, let there be a circumcising of every male of his. First then he may come near to celebrate it; and he must become like a native of the land. But no uncircumcised man may eat of it. 49 One law is to exist for the native and for the alien resident who is residing as an alien in YOUR midst.”

50 So all the sons of Israel did just as Jehovah had commanded Moses and Aaron. They did just so. 51 And it came about on this very day that Jehovah brought the sons of Israel together with their armies out of the land of Egypt.

Exodus

18 Now Jeth′ro the priest of Mid′i·an, Moses’ father-in-law, got to hear about all that God had done for Moses and for Israel his people, how Jehovah had brought Israel out of Egypt. 2 So Jeth′ro, Moses’ father-in-law, took Zip·po′rah, Moses’ wife, after the sending of her away, 3 and her two sons, the name of one of whom was Ger′shom, “because,” he said, “an alien resident I have come to be in a foreign land”; 4 and the name of the other was E·li·e′zer, “because,” to quote him, “the God of my father is my helper in that he delivered me from Phar′aoh’s sword.”

5 So Jeth′ro, Moses’ father-in-law, and his sons and his wife came to Moses into the wilderness where he was camping, at the mountain of the true God. 6 Then he sent word to Moses: “I, your father-in-law, Jeth′ro, am come to you, and also your wife and her two sons with her.” 7 At once Moses went on out to meet his father-in-law, and he proceeded to prostrate himself and to kiss him; and they each one began asking how the other was getting along. After that they went into the tent.

8 And Moses went to relating to his father-in-law all that Jehovah had done to Phar′aoh and Egypt on account of Israel, and all the hardship that had befallen them in the way, and yet Jehovah was delivering them. 9 Then Jeth′ro felt glad over all the good that Jehovah had done for Israel in that he had delivered them from the hand of Egypt. 10 Consequently Jeth′ro said: “Blessed be Jehovah, who has delivered YOU from the hand of Egypt and from the hand of Phar′aoh, and who has delivered the people from under the hand of Egypt. 11 Now I do know that Jehovah is greater than all the other gods by reason of this affair in which they acted presumptuously against them.” 12 Then Jeth′ro, Moses’ father-in-law, took a burnt offering and sacrifices for God; and Aaron and all the older men of Israel came to eat bread with Moses’ father-in-law, before the true God.

13 And it came about on the next day that Moses sat down as usual to serve as judge for the people, and the people kept standing before Moses from the morning till the evening. 14 And Moses’ father-in-law got to see all that he was doing for the people. So he said: “What kind of business is this that you are doing for the people? Why do you alone continue sitting and all the people continue taking their stand before you from morning till evening?” 15 Then Moses said to his father-in-law: “Because the people keep coming to me to inquire of God. 16 In the event that they have a case arise, it must come to me and I must judge between the one party and the other, and I must make known the decisions of the true God and his laws.”

17 At this Moses’ father-in-law said to him: “It is not good the way you are doing. 18 You will surely wear out, both you and this people who are with you, because this business is too big a load for you. You are unable to do it by yourself. 19 Now listen to my voice. I shall advise you, and God will prove to be with you. You yourself serve as representative for the people before the true God, and you yourself must bring the cases to the true God. 20 And you must warn them of what the regulations and the laws are, and you must make known to them the way in which they should walk and the work that they should do. 21 But you yourself should select out of all the people capable men, fearing God, trustworthy men, hating unjust profit; and you must set these over them as chiefs over thousands, chiefs over hundreds, chiefs over fifties and chiefs over tens. 22 And they must judge the people on every proper occasion; and it must occur that every big case they will bring to you, but every small case they themselves will handle as judges. So make it lighter for yourself, and they must carry the load with you. 23 If you do this very thing, and God has commanded you, you will then certainly be able to stand it and, besides, this people will all come to their own place in peace.”

24 Immediately Moses listened to the voice of his father-in-law and did all that he had said. 25 And Moses proceeded to choose capable men out of all Israel and to give them positions as heads over the people, as chiefs of thousands, chiefs of hundreds, chiefs of fifties and chiefs of tens. 26 And they judged the people on every proper occasion. A hard case they would bring to Moses, but every small case they themselves would handle as judges. 27 After that Moses saw his father-in-law off, and he went his way to his land.

Exodus

19 In the third month after the sons of Israel came out of the land of Egypt, on the same day, they came into the wilderness of Si′nai. 2 And they proceeded to pull away from Reph′i·dim and to come into the wilderness of Si′nai and to encamp in the wilderness; and Israel went camping there in front of the mountain.

3 And Moses went up to the true God, and Jehovah began to call to him out of the mountain, saying: “This is what you are to say to the house of Jacob and to tell the sons of Israel, 4 ‘YOU yourselves have seen what I did to the Egyptians, that I might carry YOU on wings of eagles and bring YOU to myself. 5 And now if YOU will strictly obey my voice and will indeed keep my covenant, then YOU will certainly become my special property out of all other peoples, because the whole earth belongs to me. 6 And YOU yourselves will become to me a kingdom of priests and a holy nation.’ These are the words that you are to say to the sons of Israel.”

7 So Moses came and called the older men of the people and set before them all these words that Jehovah had commanded him. 8 After that all the people answered unanimously and said: “All that Jehovah has spoken we are willing to do.” Immediately Moses took back the words of the people to Jehovah. 9 At this Jehovah said to Moses: “Look! I am coming to you in a dark cloud, in order that the people may hear when I speak with you, and that in you also they may put faith to time indefinite.” Then Moses reported the words of the people to Jehovah.

10 And Jehovah went on to say to Moses: “Go to the people, and you must sanctify them today and tomorrow, and they must wash their mantles. 11 And they must prove ready for the third day, because on the third day Jehovah will come down before the eyes of all the people upon Mount Si′nai. 12 And you must set bounds for the people round about, saying, ‘Guard yourselves against going up into the mountain, and do not touch the edge of it. Anybody touching the mountain will positively be put to death. 13 No hand is to touch him, because he will positively be stoned or will positively be shot through. Whether beast or man, he will not live.’ At the blowing of the ram’s horn they themselves may come up to the mountain.”

14 Then Moses went down from the mountain to the people, and he set about sanctifying the people; and they engaged in washing their mantles. 15 Accordingly he said to the people: “Get ready during the three days. Do not YOU men come near a woman.”

16 And on the third day when it became morning it came about that thunders and lightnings began occurring, and a heavy cloud upon the mountain and a very loud sound of a horn, so that all the people who were in the camp began to tremble. 17 Moses now brought the people out of the camp to meet the true God, and they went taking their stand at the base of the mountain. 18 And Mount Si′nai smoked all over, due to the fact that Jehovah came down upon it in fire; and its smoke kept ascending like the smoke of a kiln, and the whole mountain was trembling very much. 19 When the sound of the horn became continually louder and louder, Moses began to speak, and the true God began to answer him with a voice.

20 So Jehovah came down upon Mount Si′nai to the top of the mountain. Then Jehovah called Moses to the top of the mountain, and Moses went on up. 21 Jehovah now said to Moses: “Go down, warn the people, that they do not try to break through to Jehovah to take a look and many of them have to fall. 22 And let the priests also who regularly come near to Jehovah sanctify themselves, that Jehovah may not break out upon them.” 23 At this Moses said to Jehovah: “The people are not able to come up to Mount Si′nai, because you yourself already warned us, saying, ‘Set bounds for the mountain and make it sacred.’” 24 However, Jehovah said to him: “Go, descend, and you must come up, you and Aaron with you; but let not the priests and the people break through to come up to Jehovah, that he may not break out upon them.” 25 Accordingly Moses descended to the people and told them.

Exodus

32 Meanwhile the people got to see that Moses was taking a long time about coming down from the mountain. So the people congregated themselves about Aaron and said to him: “Get up, make for us a god who will go ahead of us, because as regards this Moses, the man who led us up out of the land of Egypt, we certainly do not know what has happened to him.” 2 At this Aaron said to them: “Tear off the gold earrings that are in the ears of YOUR wives, of YOUR sons and of YOUR daughters and bring them to me.” 3 And all the people began tearing off the gold earrings that were in their ears and bringing them to Aaron. 4 Then he took the gold from their hands, and he formed it with a graving tool and proceeded to make it into a molten statue of a calf. And they began to say: “This is your God, O Israel, who led you up out of the land of Egypt.”

5 When Aaron got to see this, he went to building an altar before it. Finally Aaron called out and said: “There is a festival to Jehovah tomorrow.” 6 So on the next day they were early in rising, and they began offering up burnt offerings and presenting communion sacrifices. After that the people sat down to eat and drink. Then they got up to have a good time.

7 Jehovah now said to Moses: “Go, descend, because your people whom you led up out of the land of Egypt have acted ruinously. 8 They have turned aside in a hurry from the way I have commanded them to go. They have made a molten statue of a calf for themselves and keep bowing down to it and sacrificing to it and saying, ‘This is your God, O Israel, who led you up out of the land of Egypt.’” 9 And Jehovah went on to say to Moses: “I have looked at this people and here it is a stiff-necked people. 10 So now let me be, that my anger may blaze against them and I may exterminate them, and let me make you into a great nation.”

11 And Moses proceeded to soften the face of Jehovah his God and to say: “Why, O Jehovah, should your anger blaze against your people whom you brought out of the land of Egypt with great power and with a strong hand? 12 Why should the Egyptians say, ‘With evil intent he brought them out in order to kill them among the mountains and to exterminate them from the surface of the ground’? Turn from your burning anger and feel regret over the evil against your people. 13 Remember Abraham, Isaac and Israel your servants, to whom you swore by yourself, in that you said to them, ‘I shall multiply YOUR seed like the stars of the heavens, and all this land that I have designated I shall give to YOUR seed, that they may indeed take possession of it to time indefinite.’”

14 And Jehovah began to feel regret over the evil that he had spoken of doing to his people.

15 After that Moses turned and went down from the mountain with the two tablets of the Testimony in his hand, tablets written upon on both their sides. On this side and on that they were written upon. 16 And the tablets were the workmanship of God, and the writing was the writing of God engraved upon the tablets. 17 And Joshua began to hear the noise of the people because of their shouting, and he proceeded to say to Moses: “There is a noise of battle in the camp.” 18 But he said:

“It is not the sound of the singing over mighty performance,

And it is not the sound of the singing of defeat;

It is the sound of other singing that I am hearing.”

19 So it came about that as soon as he got near the camp and could see the calf and the dances, Moses’ anger began to blaze, and he at once threw the tablets from his hands and shattered them at the foot of the mountain. 20 Then he took the calf that they had made and he burnt it with fire and crushed it till it was fine, after which he scattered it upon the surface of the waters and made the sons of Israel drink it. 21 After that Moses said to Aaron: “What did this people do to you that you have brought a great sin upon it?” 22 To this Aaron said: “Do not let the anger of my lord blaze. You yourself well know the people, that they are evil-inclined. 23 So they said to me, ‘Make for us a god who will go ahead of us, because as regards this Moses, the man who led us up out of the land of Egypt, we certainly do not know what has happened to him.’ 24 Hence I said to them, ‘Who have any gold? They must tear it off themselves that they may give it to me.’ And I proceeded to throw it into the fire and this calf came on out.”

25 And Moses got to see that the people went unrestrained, because Aaron had let them go unrestrained for a disgrace among their opposers. 26 Then Moses took his stand in the gate of the camp and said: “Who is on Jehovah’s side? To me!” And all the sons of Le′vi began gathering themselves to him. 27 He now said to them: “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel has said, ‘Put each one of YOU his sword on his side. Pass through and return from gate to gate in the camp and kill each one his brother and each one his fellow and each one his intimate acquaintance.’” 28 And the sons of Le′vi proceeded to do as Moses had said, so that there fell of the people on that day about three thousand men. 29 And Moses went on to say: “Fill YOUR hand today with power for Jehovah, because each one of YOU is against his own son and his own brother, and that he may confer a blessing upon YOU today.”

30 And it came about on the very next day that Moses proceeded to say to the people: “YOU—YOU have sinned with a great sin, and now I shall go up to Jehovah. Perhaps I can make amends for YOUR sin.” 31 So Moses returned to Jehovah and said: “Ah, but this people has sinned with a great sin, in that they made a god of gold for themselves! 32 But now if you will pardon their sin,—and if not, wipe me out, please, from your book that you have written.” 33 However, Jehovah said to Moses: “Whoever has sinned against me, I shall wipe him out of my book. 34 And now, come, lead the people to where I have spoken to you of. Look! My angel will go ahead of you, and on the day of my bringing punishment I shall certainly bring punishment upon them for their sin.” 35 And Jehovah began plaguing the people because they had made the calf, which Aaron had made.

Exodus

39 And out of the blue thread and wool dyed reddish purple and coccus scarlet material they made garments of knitted work for ministering in the holy place. So they made the holy garments that were for Aaron, just as Jehovah had commanded Moses.

2 Accordingly he made the eph′od of gold, blue thread and wool dyed reddish purple and coccus scarlet material and fine twisted linen. 3 Then they beat plates of gold to thin sheets, and he cut out threads to work in among the blue thread and the wool dyed reddish purple and the coccus scarlet material and the fine linen, as the work of an embroiderer. 4 They made shoulder pieces for it that were joined. It was joined at its two extremities. 5 And the girdle, which was upon it for tying it close, was of the same material according to its workmanship, of gold, blue thread, and wool dyed reddish purple and coccus scarlet material and fine twisted linen, just as Jehovah had commanded Moses.

6 Then they made the onyx stones set with settings of gold, engraved with the engravings of a seal according to the names of the sons of Israel. 7 So he placed them upon the shoulder pieces of the eph′od as memorial stones for the sons of Israel, just as Jehovah had commanded Moses. 8 Then he made the breastpiece with the workmanship of an embroiderer, like the workmanship of the eph′od, out of gold, blue thread and wool dyed reddish purple and coccus scarlet material and fine twisted linen. 9 It proved to be foursquare when doubled. They made the breastpiece, when doubled, a span of the hand in its length and a span in its width. 10 Then they filled it with four rows of stones. A row of ruby, topaz and emerald was the first row. 11 And the second row was turquoise, sapphire and jasper. 12 And the third row was lesh′em stone, agate and amethyst. 13 And the fourth row was chrys′o·lite and onyx and jade. They were set with settings of gold in their fillings. 14 And the stones were according to the names of the sons of Israel. They were twelve according to their names, with the engravings of a seal, each according to its name for the twelve tribes.

15 And they proceeded to make upon the breastpiece wreathed chains, in ropework, of pure gold. 16 Then they made two settings of gold and two rings of gold and put the two rings upon the two extremities of the breastpiece. 17 After that they put the two ropes of gold through the two rings at the extremities of the breastpiece. 18 And they put the two ends of the two ropes through the two settings. Then they put them upon the shoulder pieces of the eph′od, at the forefront of it. 19 Next they made two rings of gold and set them at the two extremities of the breastpiece upon its edge that is on the side toward the eph′od inward. 20 Then they made two rings of gold and put them upon the two shoulder pieces of the eph′od from below, on its forefront, near its place of joining, above the girdle of the eph′od. 21 Finally they bound the breastpiece by its rings to the rings of the eph′od with a blue string, that it might continue above the girdle of the eph′od and the breastpiece might not get displaced from on top the eph′od, just as Jehovah had commanded Moses.

22 Then he made the sleeveless coat of the eph′od, the workmanship of a loom worker, all of blue thread. 23 And the opening of the sleeveless coat was in the middle of it, like the opening of a coat of mail. Its opening had a border round about that it might not be torn. 24 Then they made upon the hem of the sleeveless coat pomegranates of blue thread and wool dyed reddish purple and coccus scarlet material, twisted together. 25 Further, they made bells of pure gold and put the bells in between the pomegranates upon the hem of the sleeveless coat round about, in between the pomegranates; 26 a bell and a pomegranate, a bell and a pomegranate upon the hem of the sleeveless coat round about, for ministering, just as Jehovah had commanded Moses.

27 Next they made the robes of fine linen, the workmanship of a loom worker, for Aaron and his sons, 28 and the turban of fine linen and the ornamental headgears of fine linen and the linen drawers of fine twisted linen, 29 and the sash of fine twisted linen and blue thread and wool dyed reddish purple and coccus scarlet material, the work of a weaver, just as Jehovah had commanded Moses.

30 Finally they made the shining plate, the holy sign of dedication, out of pure gold and inscribed upon it an inscription with the engravings of a seal: “Holiness belongs to Jehovah.” 31 Then they put a string of blue thread to it in order to put it upon the turban up above, just as Jehovah had commanded Moses.

32 So the work for the tabernacle of the tent of meeting all came to its completion, in that the sons of Israel kept doing according to all that Jehovah had commanded Moses. They did just so.

33 And they proceeded to bring the tabernacle to Moses, the tent and all its utensils, its hooks, its panel frames, its bars and its pillars and its socket pedestals, 34 and its covering of ram skins dyed red and its covering of sealskins and the curtain of the screen, 35 and the ark of the testimony and its poles and the cover, 36 the table, all its utensils and the showbread, 37 the lampstand of pure gold, its lamps, the row of lamps, and all its utensils and the oil of illumination, 38 and the altar of gold and the anointing oil and the perfumed incense and the screen for the entrance of the tent, 39 the altar of copper and the grating of copper that belonged to it, its poles and all its utensils, the basin and its stand, 40 the hangings of the courtyard, its pillars and its socket pedestals and the screen for the gate of the courtyard, its tent cords and its tent pins and all the utensils for the service of the tabernacle, for the tent of meeting, 41 the garments of knitted work for ministering in the sanctuary, the holy garments for Aaron the priest and the garments of his sons for acting as priests.

42 According to all that Jehovah had commanded Moses, that was the way the sons of Israel did all the service. 43 And Moses got to see all the work, and, look! they had done it just as Jehovah had commanded. That was the way they had done. Consequently Moses blessed them.

Leviticus

7 “‘And this is the law of the guilt offering: It is something most holy. 2 In the place where they regularly slaughter the burnt offering they will slaughter the guilt offering, and its blood one will sprinkle round about upon the altar. 3 As for all its fat, he will present of it the fatty tail and the fat that covers the intestines, 4 and the two kidneys and the fat that is upon them the same as that upon the loins. And as for the appendage upon the liver, he will remove it along with the kidneys. 5 And the priest must make them smoke on the altar as an offering made by fire to Jehovah. It is a guilt offering. 6 Every male among the priests will eat it. In a holy place it will be eaten. It is something most holy. 7 Like the sin offering, so is the guilt offering. There is one law for them. The priest who will make atonement with it, his it will become.

8 “‘As for the priest who presents the burnt offering of any man, the skin of the burnt offering that he has presented to the priest will become his.

9 “‘And every grain offering that may be baked in the oven and every one made in the deep-fat kettle and upon the griddle belongs to the priest who presents it. It will become his. 10 But every grain offering that is moistened with oil or dry will come to be for all of Aaron’s sons, for the one the same as for the other.

11 “‘Now this is the law of the communion sacrifice that anyone will present to Jehovah: 12 If he would present it in expression of thanksgiving, then he must present along with the sacrifice of thanksgiving unfermented ring-shaped cakes moistened with oil and unfermented wafers smeared with oil and well-mixed fine flour as ring-shaped cakes moistened with oil. 13 Along with ring-shaped cakes of leavened bread he will present his offering together with the thanksgiving sacrifice of his communion sacrifices. 14 And out of it he must present one of each offering as a sacred portion to Jehovah; as for the priest who sprinkles the blood of the communion sacrifices, it will become his. 15 And the flesh of the thanksgiving sacrifice of his communion sacrifices is to be eaten on the day of his offering. He must not save up any of it until morning.

16 “‘And if the sacrifice of his offering is a vow or a voluntary offering, it is to be eaten on the day of his presenting his sacrifice, and on the next day what is left of it also may be eaten. 17 But what is left of the flesh of the sacrifice on the third day is to be burned with fire. 18 However, if any of the flesh of his communion sacrifice should at all be eaten on the third day, the one presenting it will not be accepted with approval. It will not be put to his account. It will become a foul thing, and the soul that eats some of it will answer for his error. 19 And the flesh that may touch anything unclean is not to be eaten. It is to be burned with fire. As for the flesh, everybody clean may eat the flesh.

20 “‘And the soul who eats the flesh of the communion sacrifice, which is for Jehovah, while his uncleanness is upon him, that soul must be cut off from his people. 21 And in case a soul touches anything unclean, the uncleanness of a man or an unclean beast or any unclean loathsome thing, and actually eats some of the flesh of the communion sacrifice, which is for Jehovah, that soul must be cut off from his people.’”

22 And Jehovah continued to speak to Moses, saying: 23 “Speak to the sons of Israel, saying, ‘YOU must not eat any fat of a bull or a young ram or a goat. 24 Now the fat of a body already dead and the fat of an animal torn to pieces may be used for anything else conceivable, but YOU must not eat it at all. 25 For anyone eating fat from the beast from which he presents it as an offering made by fire to Jehovah, the soul that eats must be cut off from his people.

26 “‘And YOU must not eat any blood in any places where YOU dwell, whether that of fowl or that of beast. 27 Any soul who eats any blood, that soul must be cut off from his people.’”

28 And Jehovah went on to speak to Moses, saying: 29 “Speak to the sons of Israel, saying, ‘He who presents his communion sacrifice to Jehovah will bring his offering to Jehovah from his communion sacrifice. 30 His hands will bring as Jehovah’s offerings made by fire the fat upon the breast. He will bring it with the breast to wave it to and fro as a wave offering before Jehovah. 31 And the priest must make the fat smoke upon the altar, but the breast must become Aaron’s and his sons’.

32 “‘And YOU will give the right leg as a sacred portion to the priest from YOUR communion sacrifices. 33 That one of Aaron’s sons who presents the blood of the communion sacrifices and the fat, the right leg will become his as a portion. 34 For the breast of the wave offering and the leg of the sacred portion I do take from the sons of Israel from their communion sacrifices, and I shall give them to Aaron the priest and his sons, as a regulation to time indefinite, from the sons of Israel.

35 “‘This was the priestly share of Aaron and the priestly share of his sons from Jehovah’s offerings made by fire, on the day that he presented them to act as priests to Jehovah, 36 just as Jehovah had commanded to give it to them on the day of his anointing them from among the sons of Israel. It is a statute to time indefinite for their generations.’”

37 This is the law concerning the burnt offering, the grain offering and the sin offering and the guilt offering and the installation sacrifice and the communion sacrifice, 38 just as Jehovah had commanded Moses in Mount Si′nai in the day of his commanding the sons of Israel to present their offerings to Jehovah in the wilderness of Si′nai.

Leviticus

10 Later on Aaron’s sons Na′dab and A·bi′hu took up and brought each one his fire holder and put fire in them and placed incense upon it, and they began offering before Jehovah illegitimate fire, which he had not prescribed for them. 2 At this a fire came out from before Jehovah and consumed them, so that they died before Jehovah. 3 Then Moses said to Aaron: “This is what Jehovah has spoken, saying, ‘Among those near to me let me be sanctified, and before the face of all the people let me be glorified.’” And Aaron kept silent.

4 So Moses called Mish′a·el and El·za′phan, the sons of Uz′zi·el, Aaron’s uncle, and said to them: “Come near, carry YOUR brothers from in front of the holy place to outside the camp.” 5 They accordingly came near and carried them in their robes to outside the camp, just as Moses had spoken.

6 Subsequently Moses said to Aaron and to El·e·a′zar and Ith′a·mar his other sons: “Do not let YOUR heads go ungroomed, and YOU must not tear YOUR garments, that YOU may not die and that he may not become indignant against all the assembly; but YOUR brothers of the whole house of Israel will do the weeping over the burning, which Jehovah has made burn. 7 And from the entrance of the tent of meeting YOU must not go out for fear YOU may die, because Jehovah’s anointing oil is upon YOU.” So they did according to Moses’ word.

8 And Jehovah proceeded to speak to Aaron, saying: 9 “Do not drink wine or intoxicating liquor, you and your sons with you, when YOU come into the tent of meeting, that YOU may not die. It is a statute to time indefinite for YOUR generations, 10 both in order to make a distinction between the holy thing and the profane and between the unclean thing and the clean, 11 and in order to teach the sons of Israel all the regulations that Jehovah has spoken to them by means of Moses.”

12 Then Moses spoke to Aaron and to El·e·a′zar and Ith′a·mar, his sons that were left: “Take the grain offering that was left over from Jehovah’s offerings made by fire and eat it unfermented near the altar, because it is something most holy. 13 And YOU must eat it in a holy place, because it is your allowance and the allowance of your sons from Jehovah’s offerings made by fire; for so I have been commanded. 14 And YOU will eat the breast of the wave offering and the leg of the sacred portion in a clean place, you and your sons and your daughters with you, because they have been given as your allowance and the allowance of your sons from the communion sacrifices of the sons of Israel. 15 They will bring the leg of the sacred portion and the breast of the wave offering along with the offerings made by fire, of the fatty pieces, in order to wave the wave offering to and fro before Jehovah; and it must serve as an allowance to time indefinite for you and your sons with you, just as Jehovah has commanded.”

16 And Moses searched thoroughly for the goat of the sin offering, and, look! it had been burned up. So he grew indignant at El·e·a′zar and Ith′a·mar, Aaron’s sons that were left, saying: 17 “Why did YOU not eat the sin offering in the place that is holy, since it is something most holy and he has given it to YOU that YOU may answer for the error of the assembly so as to make atonement for them before Jehovah? 18 Look! Its blood has not been brought into the holy place within. YOU should have eaten it without fail in the holy place, just as I had been commanded.” 19 At this Aaron spoke to Moses: “Look! Today they have presented their sin offering and their burnt offering before Jehovah, while such things as these began to befall me; and had I eaten the sin offering today, would it prove satisfactory in Jehovah’s eyes?” 20 When Moses got to hear that, then it proved satisfactory in his eyes.

Leviticus

13 And Jehovah proceeded to speak to Moses and Aaron, saying: 2 “In case a man develops in the skin of his flesh an eruption or a scab or a blotch and it does develop in the skin of his flesh into the plague of leprosy, he must then be brought to Aaron the priest or to one of his sons the priests. 3 And the priest must look at the plague in the skin of the flesh. When the hair in the plague has turned white and the appearance of the plague is deeper than the skin of his flesh, it is the plague of leprosy. And the priest must look at it, and he must declare him unclean. 4 But if the blotch is white in the skin of his flesh and its appearance is not deeper than the skin and its hair has not turned white, the priest must then quarantine the plague seven days. 5 And the priest must look at him on the seventh day, and if in the way it looks the plague has stopped, the plague has not spread in the skin, the priest must also quarantine him another seven days.

6 “And the priest must look at him on the seventh day the second time, and if the plague has grown dull and the plague has not spread in the skin, the priest must also pronounce him clean. It was a scab. And he must wash his garments and be clean. 7 But if the scab has unquestionably spread in the skin after his appearing before the priest for the establishment of his purification, he must then appear the second time before the priest, 8 and the priest must take a look; and if the scab has spread in the skin, the priest must then declare him unclean. It is leprosy.

9 “In case the plague of leprosy develops in a man, he must then be brought to the priest. 10 And the priest must take a look; and if there is a white eruption in the skin and it has turned the hair white and the raw of the living flesh is in the eruption, 11 it is chronic leprosy in the skin of his flesh; and the priest must declare him unclean. He should not quarantine him, for he is unclean. 12 Now if the leprosy unquestionably breaks out in the skin, and the leprosy does cover all the skin of the one with the plague from his head to his feet to the full sight of the priest’s eyes; 13 and the priest has looked and there the leprosy has covered all his flesh, he must then pronounce the plague clean. All of it has turned white. He is clean. 14 But on the day the living flesh appears in it, he will be unclean. 15 And the priest must see the living flesh, and he must declare him unclean. The living flesh is unclean. It is leprosy. 16 Or in case the living flesh goes back and it does change to white, he must then come to the priest. 17 And the priest must look at him, and if the plague has been changed to white, the priest must then pronounce the plague clean. He is clean.

18 “As for the flesh, in case a boil develops in its skin and it does get healed, 19 and in the place of the boil a white eruption has developed or a reddish-white blotch, he must then show himself to the priest. 20 And the priest must look, and if its appearance is lower than the skin and its hair has turned white, the priest must then declare him unclean. It is the plague of leprosy. It has broken out in the boil. 21 But if the priest looks at it, and, there now, there is no white hair in it and it is not deeper than the skin and it is dull, the priest must then quarantine him seven days. 22 And if it unmistakably spreads in the skin, the priest must then declare him unclean. It is a plague. 23 But if in its place the blotch should stand, it has not spread, it is the inflammation of the boil; and the priest must pronounce him clean.

24 “Or in case there comes to be a scar in the skin of the flesh from the fire, and the raw flesh of the scar does become a reddish-white blotch or a white one, 25 the priest must then look at it; and if the hair has been changed white in the blotch and its appearance is deeper than the skin, it is leprosy. It has broken out in the scar, and the priest must declare him unclean. It is the plague of leprosy. 26 But if the priest looks at it, and, there now, there is no white hair in the blotch and it is not lower than the skin and it is dull, the priest must then quarantine him seven days. 27 And the priest must look at him on the seventh day. If it unmistakably spreads in the skin, the priest must then declare him unclean. It is the plague of leprosy. 28 But if the blotch stands in its place, it has not spread in the skin and it is dull, it is an eruption of the scar; and the priest must pronounce him clean, because it is an inflammation of the scar.

29 “As for a man or a woman, in case a plague develops in such one on the head or on the chin, 30 the priest must then see the plague; and if its appearance is deeper than the skin, and the hair is yellow and scarce in it, the priest must then declare such one unclean. It is an abnormal falling off of hair. It is leprosy of the head or of the chin. 31 But in case the priest sees the plague of abnormal falling off of hair, and, look! its appearance is not deeper than the skin and there is no black hair in it, the priest must then quarantine the plague of abnormal falling off of hair seven days. 32 And the priest must look at the plague on the seventh day; and if the abnormal falling off of hair has not spread, and no yellow hair has developed in it and the appearance of the abnormal falling off of hair is not deeper than the skin, 33 he must then have himself shaved, but he will not have the abnormal falling off of hair shaved; and the priest must quarantine the abnormal falling off of hair seven days again.

34 “And the priest must look at the abnormal falling off of hair on the seventh day; and if the abnormal falling off of hair has not spread in the skin, and its appearance is not deeper than the skin, the priest must then pronounce him clean, and he must wash his garments and be clean. 35 But if the abnormal falling off of hair unmistakably spreads in the skin after the establishment of his purification, 36 the priest must then see him; and if the abnormal falling off of hair has spread in the skin, the priest need not make examination for yellow hair; he is unclean. 37 But if in its look the abnormal falling off of hair has stood and black hair has grown in it, the abnormal falling off of hair has been healed. He is clean, and the priest must pronounce him clean.

38 “As for a man or a woman, in case blotches develop in the skin of their flesh, white blotches, 39 the priest must then take a look; and if the blotches in the skin of their flesh are dull white, it is a harmless eruption. It has broken out in the skin. He is clean.

40 “As for a man, in case his head grows bald, it is baldness. He is clean. 41 And if his head grows bald up in front, it is forehead baldness. He is clean. 42 But in case a reddish-white plague develops in the baldness of the crown or of the forehead, it is leprosy breaking out in the baldness of his crown or of his forehead. 43 And the priest must look at him; and if there is an eruption of the reddish-white plague in the baldness of his crown or of his forehead like the appearance of leprosy in the skin of the flesh, 44 he is a leper. He is unclean. Unclean is what the priest should declare him. His plague is on his head. 45 As for the leprous one in whom the plague is, his garments should be torn, and his head should become ungroomed, and he should cover over the mustache and call out, ‘Unclean, unclean!’ 46 All the days that the plague is in him he will be unclean. He is unclean. He should dwell isolated. Outside the camp is his dwelling place.

47 “As for a garment, in case the plague of leprosy develops in it, whether in a woolen garment or in a linen garment, 48 or in the warp or in the woof of the linen and of the wool, or in a skin or in anything made of skin, 49 and the yellowish-green or reddish plague does develop in the garment or in the skin or in the warp or in the woof or in any article of skin, it is the plague of leprosy, and it must be shown to the priest. 50 And the priest must see the plague, and he must quarantine the plague seven days. 51 When he has seen the plague on the seventh day, that the plague has spread in the garment or in the warp or in the woof or in the skin for any use for which the skin may be made, the plague is malignant leprosy. It is unclean. 52 And he must burn the garment or the warp or the woof in the wool or in the linen, or any article of skin in which the plague may develop, because it is malignant leprosy. It should be burned in the fire.

53 “But if the priest takes a look, and, there now, the plague has not spread in the garment or in the warp or in the woof or in any article of skin, 54 the priest must also command that they should wash that in which the plague is, and he must quarantine it a second seven days. 55 And the priest must look at the plague after it has been washed out, and if the plague has not changed its look and yet the plague has not spread, it is unclean. You should burn it in the fire. It is a low spot in a threadbare patch on either its underside or its outside.

56 “But if the priest has taken a look, and, there now, the plague is dull after it has been washed out, he must then tear it out of the garment or the skin or the warp or the woof. 57 However, if it still appears in the garment or in the warp or in the woof or in any article of skin, it is breaking out. You should burn in the fire whatever it is in which the plague is. 58 As for the garment or the warp or the woof or any article of skin that you may wash, when the plague has disappeared from them, it must then be washed a second time; and it must be clean.

59 “This is the law of the plague of leprosy in a garment of wool or of linen, or in the warp or in the woof, or in any article of skin, in order to pronounce it clean or to declare it unclean.”

Leviticus

16 And Jehovah proceeded to speak to Moses after the death of Aaron’s two sons for their approaching before Jehovah so that they died. 2 And Jehovah proceeded to say to Moses: “Speak to Aaron your brother, that he should not at all times come into the holy place inside the curtain, in front of the cover which is upon the Ark, that he may not die; because in a cloud I shall appear over the cover.

3 “With the following Aaron should come into the holy place: with a young bull for a sin offering and a ram for a burnt offering. 4 He should put on the holy linen robe, and the linen drawers should come upon his flesh, and he should gird himself with the linen sash and wrap himself with the linen turban. They are holy garments. And he must bathe his flesh in water and put them on.

5 “And from the assembly of the sons of Israel he should take two male kids of the goats for a sin offering and one ram for a burnt offering.

6 “And Aaron must present the bull of the sin offering, which is for himself, and he must make atonement in behalf of himself and his house.

7 “And he must take the two goats and make them stand before Jehovah at the entrance of the tent of meeting. 8 And Aaron must draw lots over the two goats, the one lot for Jehovah and the other lot for A·za′zel. 9 And Aaron must present the goat over which the lot came up for Jehovah, and he must make it a sin offering. 10 But the goat over which the lot came up for A·za′zel should be stood alive before Jehovah to make atonement for it, so as to send it away for A·za′zel into the wilderness.

11 “And Aaron must present the bull of the sin offering, which is for himself, and make an atonement in behalf of himself and his house; and he must slaughter the bull of the sin offering, which is for himself.

12 “And he must take the fire holder full of burning coals of fire from off the altar before Jehovah, and the hollows of both his hands full of fine perfumed incense, and he must bring them inside the curtain. 13 He must also put the incense upon the fire before Jehovah, and the cloud of the incense must overspread the Ark cover, which is upon the Testimony, that he may not die.

14 “And he must take some of the bull’s blood and spatter it with his finger in front of the cover on the east side, and he will spatter some of the blood with his finger seven times before the cover.

15 “And he must slaughter the goat of the sin offering, which is for the people, and he must bring its blood inside the curtain and do with its blood the same as he did with the bull’s blood; and he must spatter it toward the cover and before the cover.

16 “And he must make atonement for the holy place concerning the uncleannesses of the sons of Israel and concerning their revolts in all their sins; and that is the way he should do for the tent of meeting, which is residing with them in the midst of their uncleannesses.

17 “And no other man should happen to be in the tent of meeting from when he goes in to make atonement in the holy place until he comes out; and he must make atonement in behalf of himself and in behalf of his house and in behalf of the entire congregation of Israel.

18 “And he must come out to the altar, which is before Jehovah, and make atonement for it, and he must take some of the bull’s blood and some of the goat’s blood and put it upon the horns of the altar round about. 19 He must also spatter some of the blood upon it with his finger seven times and cleanse it and sanctify it from the uncleannesses of the sons of Israel.

20 “When he has finished making atonement for the holy place and the tent of meeting and the altar, he must also present the live goat. 21 And Aaron must lay both his hands upon the head of the live goat and confess over it all the errors of the sons of Israel and all their revolts in all their sins, and he must put them upon the head of the goat and send it away by the hand of a ready man into the wilderness. 22 And the goat must carry upon itself all their errors into a desert land, and he must send the goat away into the wilderness.

23 “And Aaron must come into the tent of meeting and strip off the linen garments that he put on when he went into the holy place, and he must lay them down there. 24 And he must bathe his flesh in water in a holy place and put on his garments and come out and render up his burnt offering and the people’s burnt offering and make atonement in his own behalf and in behalf of the people. 25 And he will make the fat of the sin offering smoke upon the altar.

26 “As for the one who sent the goat away for A·za′zel, he should wash his garments, and he must bathe his flesh in water, and after that he may come into the camp.

27 “However, he will have the bull of the sin offering and the goat of the sin offering, the blood of both of which was brought in to make atonement in the holy place, taken forth outside the camp; and they must burn their skins and their flesh and their dung in the fire. 28 And the one who burned them should wash his garments, and he must bathe his flesh in water, and after that he may come into the camp.

29 “And it must serve as a statute to time indefinite for YOU people: In the seventh month on the tenth of the month YOU should afflict YOUR souls, and YOU must not do any work, either the native or the alien resident who is residing as an alien in YOUR midst. 30 For on this day atonement will be made for YOU to pronounce YOU clean. YOU will be clean from all YOUR sins before Jehovah. 31 It is a sabbath of complete rest for YOU, and YOU must afflict YOUR souls. It is a statute to time indefinite.

32 “And the priest who will be anointed and whose hand will be filled with power to act as priest as successor of his father must make an atonement and must put on the linen garments. They are holy garments. 33 And he must make atonement for the holy sanctuary, and for the tent of meeting and for the altar he will make atonement; and for the priests and for all the people of the congregation he will make atonement. 34 And this must serve as a statute to time indefinite for YOU, in order to make atonement for the sons of Israel concerning all their sins once in the year.”

Accordingly he did just as Jehovah had commanded Moses.

Leviticus

18 And Jehovah continued to speak to Moses, saying: 2 “Speak to the sons of Israel, and you must say to them, ‘I am Jehovah YOUR God. 3 The way the land of Egypt does, in which YOU dwelt, YOU must not do; and the way the land of Ca′naan does, into which I am bringing YOU, YOU must not do; and in their statutes YOU must not walk. 4 My judicial decisions YOU should carry out, and my statutes YOU should keep so as to walk in them. I am Jehovah YOUR God. 5 And YOU must keep my statutes and my judicial decisions, which if a man will do, he must also live by means of them. I am Jehovah.

6 “‘YOU people must not come near, any man of YOU, to any close fleshly relative of his to lay bare nakedness. I am Jehovah. 7 The nakedness of your father and the nakedness of your mother you must not lay bare. She is your mother. You must not lay bare her nakedness.

8 “‘The nakedness of your father’s wife you must not lay bare. It is your father’s nakedness.

9 “‘As for the nakedness of your sister, the daughter of your father or the daughter of your mother, whether born in the same household or born outside it, you must not lay bare their nakedness.

10 “‘As for the nakedness of the daughter of your son or the daughter of your daughter, you must not lay bare their nakedness, because they are your nakedness.

11 “‘As for the nakedness of the daughter of your father’s wife, the offspring of your father, she being your sister, you must not lay bare her nakedness.

12 “‘The nakedness of your father’s sister you must not lay bare. She is the blood relation of your father.

13 “‘The nakedness of your mother’s sister you must not lay bare, because she is a blood relation of your mother.

14 “‘The nakedness of your father’s brother you must not lay bare. You must not come near his wife. She is your aunt.

15 “‘The nakedness of your daughter-in-law you must not lay bare. She is your son’s wife. You must not lay her nakedness bare.

16 “‘The nakedness of your brother’s wife you must not lay bare. It is your brother’s nakedness.

17 “‘The nakedness of a woman and her daughter you must not lay bare. The daughter of her son and the daughter of her daughter you must not take in order to lay her nakedness bare. They are cases of blood relationship. It is loose conduct.

18 “‘And you must not take a woman in addition to her sister as a rival to uncover her nakedness, that is, besides her during her lifetime.

19 “‘And you must not come near a woman during the menstruation of her impurity to lay her nakedness bare.

20 “‘And you must not give your emission as semen to the wife of your associate to become unclean by it.

21 “‘And you must not allow the devoting of any of your offspring to Mo′lech. You must not profane the name of your God that way. I am Jehovah.

22 “‘And you must not lie down with a male the same as you lie down with a woman. It is a detestable thing.

23 “‘And you must not give your emission to any beast to become unclean by it, and a woman should not stand before a beast to have connection with it. It is a violation of what is natural.

24 “‘Do not make yourselves unclean by any of these things, because by all these things the nations whom I am sending out from before YOU have made themselves unclean. 25 Consequently the land is unclean, and I shall bring punishment for its error upon it, and the land will vomit its inhabitants out. 26 And YOU yourselves must keep my statutes and my judicial decisions, and YOU must not do any of all these detestable things, whether a native or an alien resident who is residing as an alien in YOUR midst. 27 For all these detestable things the men of the land who were before YOU have done, so that the land is unclean. 28 Then the land will not vomit YOU out for YOUR defiling it the same way as it will certainly vomit the nations out who were before YOU. 29 In case anyone does any of all these detestable things, then the souls doing them must be cut off from among their people. 30 And YOU must keep YOUR obligation to me not to carry on any of the detestable customs that have been carried on before YOU, that YOU may not make yourselves unclean by them. I am Jehovah YOUR God.’”

Leviticus

20 And Jehovah went on speaking to Moses, saying: 2 “You are to say to the sons of Israel, ‘Any man of the sons of Israel, and any alien resident who resides as an alien in Israel, who gives any of his offspring to Mo′lech, should be put to death without fail. The people of the land should pelt him to death with stones. 3 And as for me, I shall set my face against that man, and I will cut him off from among his people, because he has given some of his offspring to Mo′lech for the purpose of defiling my holy place and to profane my holy name. 4 And if the people of the land should deliberately hide their eyes from that man when he gives any of his offspring to Mo′lech by not putting him to death, 5 then I, for my part, shall certainly fix my face against that man and his family, and I shall indeed cut him and all those who have immoral intercourse along with him in having immoral intercourse with Mo′lech off from among their people.

6 “‘As for the soul who turns himself to the spirit mediums and the professional foretellers of events so as to have immoral intercourse with them, I shall certainly set my face against that soul and cut him off from among his people.

7 “‘And YOU must sanctify yourselves and prove yourselves holy, because I am Jehovah YOUR God. 8 And YOU must keep my statutes and do them. I am Jehovah who is sanctifying YOU.

9 “‘In case there should be any man who calls down evil upon his father and his mother, he should be put to death without fail. It is his father and his mother upon whom he has called down evil. His own blood is upon him.

10 “‘Now a man who commits adultery with another man’s wife is one who commits adultery with the wife of his fellowman. He should be put to death without fail, the adulterer and the adulteress as well. 11 And a man who lies down with his father’s wife has laid bare the nakedness of his father. Both of them should be put to death without fail. Their own blood is upon them. 12 And where a man lies down with his daughter-in-law, both of them should be put to death without fail. They have committed a violation of what is natural. Their own blood is upon them.

13 “‘And when a man lies down with a male the same as one lies down with a woman, both of them have done a detestable thing. They should be put to death without fail. Their own blood is upon them.

14 “‘And where a man takes a woman and her mother, it is loose conduct. They should burn him and them in the fire, in order that loose conduct may not continue in YOUR midst.

15 “‘And where a man gives his seminal emission to a beast, he should be put to death without fail, and YOU should kill the beast. 16 And where a woman approaches any beast to have a connection with it, you must kill the woman and the beast. They should be put to death without fail. Their own blood is upon them.

17 “‘And where a man takes his sister, the daughter of his father or the daughter of his mother, and he does see her nakedness, and she herself sees his nakedness, it is shame. So they must be cut off before the eyes of the sons of their people. It is the nakedness of his sister that he has laid bare. He should answer for his error.

18 “‘And where a man lies down with a menstruating woman and does lay bare her nakedness, he has exposed her source, and she herself has laid bare the source of her blood. So both of them must be cut off from among their people.

19 “‘And the nakedness of your mother’s sister and of your father’s sister you must not lay bare, because it is his blood relation that one has exposed. They should answer for their error. 20 And a man who lies down with his uncle’s wife has laid bare the nakedness of his uncle. They should answer for their sin. They should die childless. 21 And where a man takes his brother’s wife, it is something abhorrent. It is the nakedness of his brother that he has laid bare. They should become childless.

22 “‘And YOU people must keep all my statutes and all my judicial decisions and do them, that the land to which I am bringing YOU to dwell in it may not vomit YOU out. 23 And YOU must not walk in the statutes of the nations whom I am sending out from before YOU, because they have done all these things and I abhor them. 24 Hence I said to YOU: “YOU, for YOUR part, will take possession of their ground, and I, for my part, shall give it to YOU to take possession of it, a land flowing with milk and honey. Jehovah YOUR God I am, who have divided YOU off from the peoples.” 25 And YOU must make a distinction between the clean beast and the unclean and between the unclean fowl and the clean; and YOU must not make YOUR souls loathsome with the beast and the fowl and anything that moves on the ground that I have divided off for YOU in declaring them unclean. 26 And YOU must prove yourselves holy to me, because I Jehovah am holy; and I am proceeding to divide YOU off from the peoples to become mine.

27 “‘And as for a man or woman in whom there proves to be a mediumistic spirit or spirit of prediction, they should be put to death without fail. They should pelt them to death with stones. Their own blood is upon them.’”

Leviticus

25 And Jehovah spoke further to Moses in Mount Si′nai, saying: 2 “Speak to the sons of Israel, and you must say to them, ‘When YOU eventually come into the land that I am giving YOU, then the land must observe a sabbath to Jehovah. 3 Six years you should sow your field with seed, and six years you should prune your vineyard, and you must gather the land’s produce. 4 But in the seventh year there should occur a sabbath of complete rest for the land, a sabbath to Jehovah. Your field you must not sow with seed, and your vineyard you must not prune. 5 The growth from spilled kernels of your harvest you must not reap, and the grapes of your unpruned vine you must not gather. There should occur a year of complete rest for the land. 6 And the sabbath of the land must serve YOU people for food, for you and your slave man and your slave girl and your hired laborer and the settler with you, those who are residing as aliens with you, 7 and for your domestic animal and for the wild beast that is in your land. All its produce should serve for eating.

8 “‘And you must count for yourself seven sabbaths of years, seven times seven years, and the days of the seven sabbaths of years must amount to forty-nine years for you. 9 And you must cause the horn of loud tone to sound in the seventh month on the tenth of the month; on the day of atonement YOU people should cause the horn to sound in all YOUR land. 10 And YOU must sanctify the fiftieth year and proclaim liberty in the land to all its inhabitants. It will become a Jubilee for YOU, and YOU must return each one to his possession and YOU should return each one to his family. 11 A Jubilee is what that fiftieth year will become for YOU. YOU must not sow seed nor reap the land’s growth from spilled kernels nor gather the grapes of its unpruned vines. 12 For it is a Jubilee. It should become something holy to YOU. From the field YOU may eat what the land produces.

13 “‘In this year of the Jubilee YOU should return each one to his possession. 14 Now in case YOU should sell merchandise to your associate or be buying from your associate’s hand, do not YOU wrong one another. 15 By the number of the years after the Jubilee you should buy from your associate; by the number of the years of the crops he should sell to you. 16 In proportion to the great number of years he should increase its purchase value, and in proportion to the fewness of years he should reduce its purchase value, because the number of the crops is what he is selling to you. 17 And YOU must not wrong anyone his associate, and you must be in fear of your God, because I am Jehovah YOUR God. 18 So YOU must carry out my statutes and YOU should keep my judicial decisions and YOU must carry them out. Then YOU will certainly dwell on the land in security. 19 And the land will indeed give its fruitage, and YOU will certainly eat to satisfaction and dwell in security on it.

20 “‘But in case YOU should say: “What are we going to eat in the seventh year seeing that we may not sow seed or gather our crops?” 21 in that case I shall certainly command my blessing for YOU in the sixth year, and it must yield its crop for three years. 22 And YOU must sow seed the eighth year and YOU must eat from the old crop until the ninth year. Until the coming of its crop YOU will eat the old.

23 “‘So the land should not be sold in perpetuity, because the land is mine. For YOU are alien residents and settlers from my standpoint. 24 And in all the land of YOUR possession YOU should grant to the land the right of buying back.

25 “‘In case your brother grows poor and has to sell some of his possession, a repurchaser closely related to him must also come and buy back what his brother sold. 26 And in case anyone proves to have no repurchaser and his own hand does make gain and he does find enough for its repurchase, 27 he must also calculate the years from when he sold it and he must return what money remains over to the man to whom he made the sale, and he must return to his possession.

28 “‘But if his hand does not find enough to give back to him, what he sold must also continue in the hand of its purchaser until the Jubilee year; and it must go out in the Jubilee, and he must return to his possession.

29 “‘Now in case a man should sell a dwelling house in a walled city, his right of repurchase must also continue till the year from the time of his sale finishes out; his right of repurchase should continue a whole year. 30 But if it should not be bought back before the complete year has come to the full for him, the house that is in the city that has a wall must also stand in perpetuity as the property of its purchaser during his generations. It should not go out in the Jubilee. 31 However, the houses of settlements that have no wall about them should be accounted as part of the field of the country. Right of repurchase should continue for it, and in the Jubilee it should go out.

32 “‘As for cities of the Levites with the houses of the cities of their possession, the right of repurchase should continue to time indefinite for the Levites. 33 And where property of the Levites is not bought back, the house sold in the city of his possession must also go out in the Jubilee; because the houses of the cities of the Levites are their possession in the midst of the sons of Israel. 34 Moreover, the field of pasture ground of their cities may not be sold, because it is a possession to time indefinite for them.

35 “‘And in case your brother grows poor and so he is financially weak alongside you, you must also sustain him. As an alien resident and a settler, he must keep alive with you. 36 Do not take interest and usury from him, but you must be in fear of your God; and your brother must keep alive with you. 37 You must not give him your money on interest, and you must not give your food out on usury. 38 I am Jehovah YOUR God, who brought YOU out of the land of Egypt to give YOU the land of Ca′naan, to prove myself YOUR God.

39 “‘And in case your brother grows poor alongside you and he has to sell himself to you, you must not use him as a worker in slavish service. 40 He should prove to be with you like a hired laborer, like a settler. He should serve with you till the Jubilee year. 41 And he must go out from you, he and his sons with him, and he must return to his family, and he should return to the possession of his forefathers. 42 For they are my slaves whom I brought out of the land of Egypt. They must not sell themselves the way a slave is sold. 43 You must not tread down upon him with tyranny, and you must be in fear of your God. 44 As for your slave man and your slave girl who become yours from the nations that are round about YOU people, from them YOU may buy a slave man and a slave girl. 45 And also from the sons of the settlers who are residing as aliens with YOU, from them YOU may buy, and from their families that are with YOU whom they had born to them in YOUR land; and they must become YOUR possession. 46 And YOU must pass them on as an inheritance to YOUR sons after YOU to inherit as a possession to time indefinite. YOU may use them as workers, but upon YOUR brothers the sons of Israel, you must not tread, the one upon the other, with tyranny.

47 “‘But in case the hand of the alien resident or the settler with you becomes wealthy, and your brother has become poor alongside him and must sell himself to the alien resident or the settler with you, or to a member of the family of the alien resident, 48 after he has sold himself, the right of repurchase will continue in his case. One of his brothers may buy him back. 49 Or his uncle or the son of his uncle may buy him back, or any blood relative of his flesh, one of his family, may buy him back.

“‘Or if his own hand has become wealthy, he must also buy himself back. 50 And he must reckon with his purchaser from the year he sold himself to him till the Jubilee year, and the money of his sale must correspond with the number of years. The way workdays of a hired laborer are reckoned he should continue with him. 51 If there are yet many years, he should in proportion to them pay his repurchase price over from the money of his purchase. 52 But if only a few remain of the years until the Jubilee year, he must then make a calculation for himself. In proportion to the years of his he should pay over his repurchase price. 53 He should continue with him like a hired laborer from year to year. He may not tread him down with tyranny before your eyes. 54 However, if he cannot buy himself back on these terms, he must then go out in the year of Jubilee, he and his sons with him.

55 “‘For to me the sons of Israel are slaves. They are my slaves whom I brought out of the land of Egypt. I am Jehovah YOUR God.

Numbers

2 Jehovah now spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying: 2 “The sons of Israel should encamp, each man by his three-tribe division, by the signs for the house of their fathers. Round about in front of the tent of meeting they should encamp.

3 “And those camping eastward toward the sunrising will be the three-tribe division of the camp of Judah in their armies, and the chieftain for the sons of Judah is Nah′shon the son of Am·min′a·dab. 4 And his army and the ones registered of them are seventy-four thousand six hundred. 5 And those camping alongside him will be the tribe of Is′sa·char, and the chieftain for the sons of Is′sa·char is Ne·than′el the son of Zu′ar. 6 And his army and his registered ones are fifty-four thousand four hundred. 7 And the tribe of Zeb′u·lun; and the chieftain for the sons of Zeb′u·lun is E·li′ab the son of He′lon. 8 And his army and his registered ones are fifty-seven thousand four hundred.

9 “All the registered ones of the camp of Judah are one hundred eighty-six thousand four hundred in their armies. They should set out first.

10 “The three-tribe division of the camp of Reu′ben will be toward the south in their armies, and the chieftain for the sons of Reu′ben is E·li′zur the son of Shed′e·ur. 11 And his army and his registered ones are forty-six thousand five hundred. 12 And those camping alongside him will be the tribe of Sim′e·on, and the chieftain for the sons of Sim′e·on is She·lu′mi·el the son of Zu·ri·shad′dai. 13 And his army and the ones registered of them are fifty-nine thousand three hundred. 14 And the tribe of Gad; and the chieftain for the sons of Gad is E·li′a·saph the son of Reu′el. 15 And his army and the ones registered of them are forty-five thousand six hundred and fifty.

16 “All the registered ones of the camp of Reu′ben are one hundred and fifty-one thousand four hundred and fifty in their armies, and they should set out second.

17 “When the tent of meeting must set out, the camp of the Levites will be in the middle of the camps.

“Just as they should encamp, so they should set out, each one at his place, according to their three-tribe divisions.

18 “The three-tribe division of the camp of E′phra·im in their armies will be toward the west, and the chieftain for the sons of E′phra·im is E·lish′a·ma the son of Am·mi′hud. 19 And his army and the ones registered of them are forty thousand five hundred. 20 And alongside him will be the tribe of Ma·nas′seh, and the chieftain for the sons of Ma·nas′seh is Ga·ma′li·el the son of Pe·dah′zur. 21 And his army and the ones registered of them are thirty-two thousand two hundred. 22 And the tribe of Benjamin; and the chieftain for the sons of Benjamin is Ab′i·dan the son of Gid·e·o′ni. 23 And his army and the ones registered of them are thirty-five thousand four hundred.

24 “All the registered ones of the camp of E′phra·im are one hundred and eight thousand one hundred in their armies, and they should set out third.

25 “The three-tribe division of the camp of Dan will be toward the north in their armies, and the chieftain for the sons of Dan is A·hi·e′zer the son of Am·mi·shad′dai. 26 And his army and the ones registered of them are sixty-two thousand seven hundred. 27 And the ones camping alongside him will be the tribe of Ash′er, and the chieftain for the sons of Ash′er is Pa′gi·el the son of Och′ran. 28 And his army and the ones registered of them are forty-one thousand five hundred. 29 And the tribe of Naph′ta·li; and the chieftain for the sons of Naph′ta·li is A·hi′ra the son of E′nan. 30 And his army and the ones registered of them are fifty-three thousand four hundred.

31 “All the registered ones of the camp of Dan are one hundred fifty-seven thousand six hundred. They should set out last—according to their three-tribe divisions.”

32 These were the registered ones of the sons of Israel according to the house of their fathers; all the registered ones of the camps in their armies were six hundred and three thousand five hundred and fifty. 33 But the Levites did not get registered in among the sons of Israel, just as Jehovah had commanded Moses. 34 And the sons of Israel proceeded to do according to all that Jehovah had commanded Moses. That is the way they encamped in their three-tribe divisions, and that is the way they set out, each one in his families with regard to the house of his fathers.

Numbers

6 And Jehovah spoke further to Moses, saying: 2 “Speak to the sons of Israel and you must say to them, ‘In case a man or a woman takes a special vow to live as a Naz′i·rite to Jehovah, 3 he should keep away from wine and intoxicating liquor. He should not drink the vinegar of wine or the vinegar of intoxicating liquor, nor drink any liquid made from grapes, nor eat grapes either fresh or dried. 4 All the days of his Naziriteship he should not eat anything at all that is made from the wine vine, from the unripe grapes to the skins.

5 “‘All the days of the vow of his Naziriteship no razor should pass over his head; until the days that he should be separated to Jehovah come to the full, he should prove holy by letting the locks of the hair of his head grow. 6 All the days of his keeping separate to Jehovah he may not come toward any dead soul. 7 Not even for his father or his mother or his brother or his sister may he defile himself when they die, because the sign of his Naziriteship to his God is upon his head.

8 “‘All the days of his Naziriteship he is holy to Jehovah. 9 But in case anyone dying should die quite suddenly alongside him so that he has defiled the head of his Naziriteship, he must then shave his head in the day of establishing his purification. On the seventh day he should shave it. 10 And on the eighth day he should bring two turtledoves or two young pigeons to the priest to the entrance of the tent of meeting. 11 And the priest must handle one as a sin offering and the other as a burnt offering and make atonement for him, since he has sinned because of the dead soul. Then he must sanctify his head on that day. 12 And he must live as a Naz′i·rite to Jehovah for the days of his Naziriteship, and he must bring a young ram in its first year as a guilt offering; and the former days will go uncounted because he defiled his Naziriteship.

13 “‘Now this is the law about the Naz′i·rite: On the day that the days of his Naziriteship come to the full, he will be brought to the entrance of the tent of meeting. 14 And he must present as his offering to Jehovah one sound young ram in its first year as a burnt offering and one sound female lamb in its first year as a sin offering and one sound ram as a communion sacrifice, 15 and a basket of unfermented ring-shaped cakes of fine flour, moistened with oil, and unfermented wafers smeared with oil, and their grain offering and their drink offerings. 16 And the priest must present them before Jehovah and render up his sin offering and his burnt offering. 17 And he will render up the ram as a communion sacrifice to Jehovah along with the basket of unfermented cakes; and the priest must render up its grain offering and its drink offering.

18 “‘And the Naz′i·rite must shave the head of his Naziriteship at the entrance of the tent of meeting, and he must take the hair of the head of his Naziriteship and put it upon the fire that is under the communion sacrifice. 19 And the priest must take a boiled shoulder from the ram and one unfermented ring-shaped cake out of the basket, and one unfermented wafer, and put them upon the palms of the Naz′i·rite after he has had the sign of his Naziriteship shaved off. 20 And the priest must wave them to and fro as a wave offering before Jehovah. It is something holy for the priest, along with the breast of the wave offering and the leg of the contribution. And afterward the Naz′i·rite may drink wine.

21 “‘This is the law about the Naz′i·rite who vows—his offering to Jehovah over his Naziriteship, besides that which he can afford. According to his vow that he may make, so he should do because of the law of his Naziriteship.’”

22 Then Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying: 23 “Speak to Aaron and his sons, saying, ‘This is the way YOU should bless the sons of Israel, saying to them:

24 “May Jehovah bless you and keep you.

25 May Jehovah make his face shine toward you, and may he favor you.

26 May Jehovah lift up his face toward you and assign peace to you.”’

27 And they must place my name upon the sons of Israel, that I myself may bless them.”

Numbers

11 Now the people became as men having something evil to complain about in the ears of Jehovah. When Jehovah got to hear it, then his anger grew hot, and a fire of Jehovah began to blaze against them and to consume some in the extremity of the camp. 2 When the people began to cry out to Moses, then he made supplication to Jehovah, and the fire sank down. 3 And the name of that place got to be called Tab′e·rah, because a fire of Jehovah had blazed against them.

4 And the mixed crowd that was in the midst of them expressed selfish longing, and the sons of Israel too began to weep again and say: “Who will give us meat to eat? 5 How we remember the fish that we used to eat in Egypt for nothing, the cucumbers and the watermelons and the leeks and the onions and the garlic! 6 But now our soul is dried away. Our eyes are on nothing at all except the manna.”

7 Incidentally, the manna was like coriander seed, and its look was like the look of bdellium gum. 8 The people spread out and picked it up and ground it in hand mills or pounded it in a mortar, and they boiled it in cooking pots or made it into round cakes, and its taste proved to be like the taste of an oiled sweet cake. 9 And when the dew descended upon the camp by night, the manna would descend upon it.

10 And Moses got to hear the people weeping in their families, each man at the entrance of his tent. And Jehovah’s anger began growing very hot, and in the eyes of Moses it was bad. 11 Then Moses said to Jehovah: “Why have you caused evil to your servant, and why have I not found favor in your eyes, in placing the load of all this people upon me? 12 Have I myself conceived all this people? Is it I who have given them birth, so that you should say to me, ‘Carry them in your bosom, just as the male nurse carries the suckling,’ to the soil about which you swore to their forefathers? 13 From where do I have meat to give to all this people? For they keep weeping toward me, saying, ‘Do give us meat, and let us eat!’ 14 I am not able, I by myself, to carry all this people, because they are too heavy for me. 15 So if this is the way you are doing to me, please kill me off altogether, if I have found favor in your eyes, and let me not look upon my calamity.”

16 In turn Jehovah said to Moses: “Gather for me seventy men of the older men of Israel, whom you do know that they are older men of the people and officers of theirs, and you must take them to the tent of meeting, and they must station themselves there with you. 17 And I shall have to come down and speak with you there; and I shall have to take away some of the spirit that is upon you and place it upon them, and they will have to help you in carrying the load of the people that you may not carry it, just you alone. 18 And to the people you should say, ‘Sanctify yourselves for tomorrow, as YOU will certainly eat meat, because YOU have wept in the ears of Jehovah, saying: “Who will give us meat to eat, for it was well with us in Egypt?” And Jehovah will certainly give YOU meat, and YOU will indeed eat. 19 YOU will eat, not one day nor two days nor five days nor ten days nor twenty days, 20 but up to a month of days, until it comes out of YOUR nostrils and it has become a loathing to YOU, just because YOU rejected Jehovah, who is in YOUR midst, and YOU went weeping before him, saying: “Why is it that we have come out of Egypt?”’”

21 Then Moses said: “The people in the midst of whom I am are six hundred thousand men on foot, and yet you—you have said, ‘Meat I shall give them, and they will certainly eat for a month of days’! 22 Will flocks and herds be slaughtered for them, for it to be adequate for them? Or will all the fish of the sea be caught for them, for it to be adequate for them?”

23 At this Jehovah said to Moses: “The hand of Jehovah is cut short, is it? Now you will see whether what I say befalls you or not.”

24 After that Moses went out and spoke to the people the words of Jehovah. And he went gathering seventy men from the older men of the people and proceeded to have them stand round about the tent. 25 Then Jehovah came down in a cloud and spoke to him and took away some of the spirit that was upon him and put it upon each of the seventy older men. And it came about that as soon as the spirit settled down upon them, then they proceeded to act as prophets; but they did not do it again.

26 Now there were two of the men remaining in the camp. The name of the one was El′dad, and the name of the other was Me′dad. And the spirit began to settle down upon them, as they were among those written down, but they had not gone out to the tent. So they proceeded to act as prophets in the camp. 27 And a young man went running and reporting to Moses and saying: “El′dad and Me′dad are acting as prophets in the camp!” 28 Then Joshua the son of Nun, the minister of Moses from his young manhood on, responded and said: “My lord Moses, restrain them!” 29 However, Moses said to him: “Are you feeling jealous for me? No, I wish that all of Jehovah’s people were prophets, because Jehovah would put his spirit upon them!” 30 Later Moses withdrew to the camp, he and the older men of Israel.

31 And a wind burst forth from Jehovah and began driving quails from the sea and letting them fall above the camp about a day’s journey this way and about a day’s journey that way, all around the camp, and about two cubits above the surface of the earth. 32 Then the people got up all that day and all night and all the next day and kept gathering the quail. The one collecting least gathered ten ho′mers, and they kept spreading them extensively all around the camp for themselves. 33 The meat was yet between their teeth, before it could be chewed, when Jehovah’s anger blazed against the people, and Jehovah began striking at the people with a very great slaughter.

34 The name of that place came to be called Kib′roth-hat·ta′a·vah, because there they buried the people who showed selfish craving. 35 From Kib′roth-hat·ta′a·vah the people pulled away for Ha·ze′roth, and they continued in Ha·ze′roth.

Numbers

12 Now Mir′i·am and Aaron began to speak against Moses on account of the Cush′ite wife whom he had taken, because it was a Cush′ite wife he had taken. 2 And they kept saying: “Is it just by Moses alone that Jehovah has spoken? Is it not by us also that he has spoken?” And Jehovah was listening. 3 And the man Moses was by far the meekest of all the men who were upon the surface of the ground.

4 Then Jehovah suddenly said to Moses and Aaron and Mir′i·am: “Go out, the three of YOU, to the tent of meeting.” So the three of them went out. 5 After that Jehovah came down in the pillar of cloud and stood at the entrance of the tent and called Aaron and Mir′i·am. At this both of them went out. 6 And he went on to say: “Hear my words, please. If there came to be a prophet of YOURS for Jehovah, it would be in a vision I would make myself known to him. In a dream I would speak to him. 7 Not so my servant Moses! He is being entrusted with all my house. 8 Mouth to mouth I speak to him, thus showing him, and not by riddles; and the appearance of Jehovah is what he beholds. Why, then, did YOU not fear to speak against my servant, against Moses?”

9 And Jehovah’s anger got to be hot against them, and he went his way. 10 And the cloud turned away from over the tent, and, look! Mir′i·am was struck with leprosy as white as snow. Then Aaron turned toward Mir′i·am, and, look! she was struck with leprosy. 11 Immediately Aaron said to Moses: “Excuse me, my lord! Do not, please, attribute to us the sin in which we have acted foolishly and which we have committed! 12 Please, do not let her continue like someone dead, whose flesh at the time of his coming out of his mother’s womb is half eaten off!” 13 And Moses began to cry out to Jehovah, saying: “O God, please! Heal her, please!”

14 Then Jehovah said to Moses: “Were her father to spit directly in her face, would she not be humiliated seven days? Let her be quarantined seven days outside the camp, and afterward let her be received in.” 15 Accordingly Mir′i·am was quarantined outside the camp seven days, and the people did not pull away until Mir′i·am was received in. 16 And afterward the people pulled away from Ha·ze′roth and took up camping in the wilderness of Pa′ran.

Numbers

13 Jehovah now spoke to Moses, saying: 2 “Send out for yourself men that they may spy out the land of Ca′naan, which I am giving to the sons of Israel. YOU will send out one man for each tribe of his fathers, each one a chieftain among them.”

3 So Moses sent them out from the wilderness of Pa′ran at the order of Jehovah. All the men were heads of the sons of Israel. 4 And these are their names: Of the tribe of Reu′ben, Sham·mu′a the son of Zac′cur; 5 of the tribe of Sim′e·on, Sha′phat the son of Ho′ri; 6 of the tribe of Judah, Ca′leb the son of Je·phun′neh; 7 of the tribe of Is′sa·char, I′gal the son of Joseph; 8 of the tribe of E′phra·im, Ho·she′a the son of Nun; 9 of the tribe of Benjamin, Pal′ti the son of Ra′phu; 10 of the tribe of Zeb′u·lun, Gad′di·el the son of So′di; 11 of the tribe of Joseph, for the tribe of Ma·nas′seh, Gad′di the son of Su′si; 12 of the tribe of Dan, Am′mi·el the son of Ge·mal′li; 13 of the tribe of Ash′er, Se′thur the son of Mi′cha·el; 14 of the tribe of Naph′ta·li, Nah′bi the son of Voph′si; 15 of the tribe of Gad, Geu′el the son of Ma′chi. 16 These are the names of the men whom Moses sent to spy out the land. And Moses continued to call Ho·she′a the son of Nun Je·hosh′u·a.

17 When Moses was sending them to spy out the land of Ca′naan, he proceeded to say to them: “Go up here into the Neg′eb, and YOU must go up into the mountainous region. 18 And YOU must see what the land is and the people who are dwelling on it, whether they are strong or weak, whether they are few or many; 19 and what the land is in which they are dwelling, whether it is good or bad, and what the cities are in which they are dwelling, whether it is in encampments or in fortifications; 20 and what the land is, whether it is fat or lean, whether there are trees in it or not. And YOU must show yourselves courageous and take some of the fruitage of the land.” Now the days were the days of the first ripe fruits of the grapes.

21 So they went up and spied out the land from the wilderness of Zin to Re′hob to the entering in of Ha′math. 22 When they went up into the Neg′eb, they then came to He′bron. Now A·hi′man, She′shai and Tal′mai, those born of A′nak, were there. Incidentally, He′bron had been built seven years before Zo′an of Egypt. 23 When they came to the torrent valley of Esh′col, they then proceeded to cut down from there a shoot with one cluster of grapes. And they went carrying it with a bar on two of the men, and also some of the pomegranates and some of the figs. 24 They called that place the torrent valley of Esh′col, on account of the cluster that the sons of Israel cut down from there.

25 Finally at the end of forty days they returned from spying out the land. 26 So they walked and came to Moses and Aaron and all the assembly of the sons of Israel in the wilderness of Pa′ran, at Ka′desh. And they came bringing back word to them and all the assembly and showing them the fruitage of the land. 27 And they went on to report to him and say: “We entered into the land to which you sent us out, and it is indeed flowing with milk and honey, and this is its fruitage. 28 Nevertheless, the facts are that the people who dwell in the land are strong, and the fortified cities are very great; and, too, those born of A′nak we saw there. 29 The A·mal′ek·ites are dwelling in the land of the Neg′eb, and the Hit′tites and the Jeb′u·sites and the Am′or·ites are dwelling in the mountainous region, and the Ca′naan·ites are dwelling by the sea and by the side of the Jordan.”

30 Then Ca′leb tried to still the people toward Moses and went on to say: “Let us go up directly, and we are bound to take possession of it, because we can surely prevail over it.” 31 But the men who went up with him said: “We are not able to go up against the people, because they are stronger than we are.” 32 And they kept on bringing forth to the sons of Israel a bad report of the land that they had spied out, saying: “The land, which we passed through to spy it out, is a land that eats up its inhabitants; and all the people whom we saw in the midst of it are men of extraordinary size. 33 And there we saw the Neph′i·lim, the sons of A′nak, who are from the Neph′i·lim; so that we became in our own eyes like grasshoppers, and the same way we became in their eyes.”

Numbers

14 Then all the assembly raised their voice, and the people continued giving vent to their voice and weeping all through that night. 2 And all the sons of Israel began to murmur against Moses and Aaron, and all the assembly began to say against them: “If only we had died in the land of Egypt, or if only we had died in this wilderness! 3 And why is Jehovah bringing us to this land to fall by the sword? Our wives and our little ones will become plunder. Is it not better for us to return to Egypt?” 4 They even went to saying to one another: “Let us appoint a head, and let us return to Egypt!”

5 At this Moses and Aaron fell upon their faces before all the congregation of the assembly of the sons of Israel. 6 And Joshua the son of Nun and Ca′leb the son of Je·phun′neh, who were of those who spied out the land, ripped their garments apart, 7 and they proceeded to say this to all the assembly of the sons of Israel: “The land that we passed through to spy it out is a very, very good land. 8 If Jehovah has found delight in us, then he will certainly bring us into this land and give it to us, a land that is flowing with milk and honey. 9 Only against Jehovah do not rebel; and YOU, do not YOU fear the people of the land, for they are bread to us. Their shelter has turned away from over them, and Jehovah is with us. Do not fear them.”

10 However, all the assembly talked of pelting them with stones. And Jehovah’s glory appeared on the tent of meeting to all the sons of Israel.

11 Finally Jehovah said to Moses: “How long will this people treat me without respect, and how long will they not put faith in me for all the signs that I performed in among them? 12 Let me strike them with pestilence and drive them away, and let me make you a nation greater and mightier than they are.”

13 But Moses said to Jehovah: “Then the Egyptians will be bound to hear that you by your power have led this people up out of their midst. 14 And they will be bound to tell it to the inhabitants of this land. They have heard that you are Jehovah in among this people, who has appeared face to face. You are Jehovah, and your cloud is standing over them, and you are going before them in the pillar of cloud by day and in the pillar of fire by night. 15 Were you to put this people to death as one man, then the nations who have heard of your fame would certainly say this, 16 ‘Because of Jehovah’s not being able to bring this people into the land about which he swore to them he proceeded to slaughter them in the wilderness.’ 17 And now, please, let your power become great, O Jehovah, just as you have spoken, saying, 18 ‘Jehovah, slow to anger and abundant in loving-kindness, pardoning error and transgression, but by no means will he give exemption from punishment, bringing punishment for the error of the fathers upon sons, upon the third generation and upon the fourth generation.’ 19 Forgive, please, the error of this people according to the greatness of your loving-kindness, and just as you have pardoned this people from Egypt onward until now.”

20 Then Jehovah said: “I do forgive according to your word. 21 And, on the other hand, as I live, all the earth will be filled with the glory of Jehovah. 22 But all the men who have been seeing my glory and my signs that I have performed in Egypt and in the wilderness and yet kept testing me these ten times, and have not listened to my voice, 23 will never see the land about which I swore to their fathers, yes, all those treating me without respect will not see it. 24 As for my servant Ca′leb, because a different spirit has proved to be with him and he kept following wholly after me, I shall certainly bring him into the land where he has gone, and his offspring will take possession of it. 25 While the A·mal′ek·ites and the Ca′naan·ites are dwelling in the low plain, YOU people make a turn tomorrow and pull away to march to the wilderness by way of the Red Sea.”

26 And Jehovah went on to speak to Moses and Aaron, saying: 27 “How long will this evil assembly have this murmuring that they are carrying on against me? I have heard the murmurings of the sons of Israel that they are murmuring against me. 28 Say to them, ‘“As I live,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “if I shall not do to YOU just that way as YOU have spoken in my ears! 29 In this wilderness YOUR carcasses will fall, yes, all YOUR registered ones of all YOUR number from twenty years old upward, YOU who have murmured against me. 30 As for YOU, YOU will not enter into the land in which I lifted up my hand in oath to reside with YOU, except Ca′leb the son of Je·phun′neh and Joshua the son of Nun.

31 “‘“And YOUR little ones who YOU said would become plunder, these also I shall certainly bring in, and they will indeed know the land that YOU have rejected. 32 But the carcasses of YOU yourselves will fall in this wilderness. 33 And YOUR sons will become shepherds in the wilderness forty years, and they will have to answer for YOUR acts of fornication, until YOUR carcasses come to their end in the wilderness. 34 By the number of the days that YOU spied out the land, forty days, a day for a year, a day for a year, YOU will answer for YOUR errors forty years, as YOU must know what my being estranged means.

35 “‘“I Jehovah have spoken if this is not what I shall do to all this evil assembly, those who have gathered together against me: In this wilderness they will come to their end, and there they will die. 36 And the men whom Moses sent to spy out the land and who, when they returned, began making the whole assembly murmur against him, by bringing forth a bad report against the land, 37 yes, the men bringing forth the bad report about the land will die by the scourge before Jehovah. 38 But Joshua the son of Nun and Ca′leb the son of Je·phun′neh will certainly live on, of those men who went to spy out the land.”’”

39 When Moses proceeded to speak these words to all the sons of Israel, then the people began to mourn a great deal. 40 Moreover, they got up early in the morning and tried to go up to the top of the mountain, saying: “Here we are, and we have to go up to the place that Jehovah mentioned. For we have sinned.” 41 But Moses said: “Why is it that YOU are passing beyond the order of Jehovah? But that will not succeed. 42 Do not go up, because Jehovah is not in YOUR midst, that YOU may not be defeated before YOUR enemies. 43 For the A·mal′ek·ites and the Ca′naan·ites are there before YOU; and YOU are certain to fall by the sword, because, for the reason that YOU turned back from following Jehovah, Jehovah will not continue with YOU.”

44 However, they presumed to go up to the top of the mountain, but the ark of Jehovah’s covenant and Moses did not move away from the midst of the camp. 45 Then the A·mal′ek·ites and the Ca′naan·ites who were dwelling in that mountain came on down and began striking them and went scattering them as far as Hor′mah.

Numbers

16 And Ko′rah the son of Iz′har, the son of Ko′hath, the son of Le′vi, proceeded to get up, together with Da′than and A·bi′ram the sons of E·li′ab, and On the son of Pe′leth, the sons of Reu′ben. 2 And they proceeded to rise up before Moses, they and two hundred and fifty men of the sons of Israel, chieftains of the assembly, summoned ones of the meeting, men of fame. 3 So they congregated themselves against Moses and Aaron and said to them: “That is enough of YOU, because the whole assembly are all of them holy and Jehovah is in their midst. Why, then, should YOU lift yourselves up above the congregation of Jehovah?”

4 When Moses got to hear it he at once fell upon his face. 5 Then he spoke to Ko′rah and to his entire assembly, saying: “In the morning Jehovah will make known who belongs to him and who is holy and who must come near to him, and whoever he may choose will come near to him. 6 Do this: Take fire holders for yourselves, Ko′rah and his entire assembly, 7 and put fire in them and place incense upon them before Jehovah tomorrow, and it must occur that the man whom Jehovah will choose, he is the holy one. That is enough of YOU, YOU sons of Le′vi!”

8 And Moses went on to say to Ko′rah: “Listen, please, YOU sons of Le′vi. 9 Is it such a little thing for YOU men that the God of Israel has separated YOU men from the assembly of Israel to present YOU to himself to carry on the service of Jehovah’s tabernacle and to stand before the assembly to minister to them, 10 and that he should bring you and all your brothers the sons of Le′vi with you near? So must YOU men also try to secure the priesthood? 11 For that reason you and all your assembly who are gathering together are against Jehovah. As for Aaron, what is he that YOU men should murmur against him?”

12 Later Moses sent to call Da′than and A·bi′ram the sons of E·li′ab, but they said: “We are not going to come up! 13 Is it so little a thing that you have brought us up out of a land flowing with milk and honey to put us to death in the wilderness, that you should also try to play the prince over us to the limit? 14 As it is, you have not brought us into any land flowing with milk and honey, that you may give us an inheritance of field and vineyard. Is it the eyes of those men that you want to bore out? We are not going to come up!”

15 At this Moses became very angry and said to Jehovah: “Do not turn to look at their grain offering. Not one male ass have I taken away from them, nor have I harmed one of them.”

16 Then Moses said to Ko′rah: “You and all your assembly, be present before Jehovah, you and they and Aaron, tomorrow. 17 And take each one his fire holder, and YOU men must put incense upon them and present each one his fire holder before Jehovah, two hundred and fifty fire holders, and you and Aaron each his fire holder.” 18 So they took each one his fire holder and put fire upon them and placed incense upon them and stood at the entrance of the tent of meeting together with Moses and Aaron. 19 When Ko′rah got all the assembly together against them at the entrance of the tent of meeting, then Jehovah’s glory appeared to all the assembly.

20 Jehovah now spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying: 21 “Separate yourselves from the midst of this assembly, that I may exterminate them in an instant.” 22 At this they fell upon their faces and said: “O God, the God of the spirits of every sort of flesh, will just one man sin and you become indignant against the entire assembly?”

23 In turn Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying: 24 “Speak to the assembly, saying, ‘Get away from around the tabernacles of Ko′rah, Da′than and A·bi′ram!’”

25 After that Moses got up and went to Da′than and A·bi′ram, and the older men of Israel went with him. 26 Then he spoke to the assembly, saying: “Turn aside, please, from before the tents of these wicked men and do not touch anything that belongs to them, that YOU may not be swept away in all their sin.” 27 Immediately they got away from before the tabernacle of Ko′rah, Da′than and A·bi′ram, from every side, and Da′than and A·bi′ram came out, taking their stand at the entrance of their tents, together with their wives, and their sons and their little ones.

28 Then Moses said: “By this YOU will know that Jehovah has sent me to do all these deeds, that it is not of my own heart: 29 If it is according to the death of all mankind that these people will die and with the punishment of all mankind that punishment will be brought upon them, then it is not Jehovah that has sent me. 30 But if it is something created that Jehovah will create, and the ground has to open its mouth and swallow up them and everything that belongs to them and they have to go down alive into She′ol, YOU will then know for certain that these men have treated Jehovah disrespectfully.”

31 And it came about that as soon as he had finished speaking all these words, the ground that was under them began to be split apart. 32 And the earth proceeded to open its mouth and to swallow up them and their households and all humankind that belonged to Ko′rah and all the goods. 33 So down they went, and all who belonged to them, alive into She′ol, and the earth went covering them over, so that they perished from the midst of the congregation. 34 And all the Israelites who were round about them fled at the screaming of them, for they began to say: “We are afraid that the earth may swallow us up!” 35 And a fire came out from Jehovah and proceeded to consume the two hundred and fifty men offering the incense.

36 Jehovah now spoke to Moses, saying: 37 “Say to El·e·a′zar the son of Aaron the priest that he should take up the fire holders from within the conflagration, ‘And you scatter the fire over there; for they are holy, 38 even the fire holders of these men who sinned against their own souls. And they must make them into thin metal plates as an overlaying for the altar, because they presented them before Jehovah, so that they became holy; and they should serve as a sign to the sons of Israel.’” 39 Accordingly El·e·a′zar the priest took the copper fire holders, which those who had been burned up had presented, and they proceeded to beat them out into an overlaying for the altar, 40 as a memorial for the sons of Israel, to the end that no strange man who is not of the offspring of Aaron should come near to make incense smoke before Jehovah, and no one might become like Ko′rah and his assembly, just as Jehovah had spoken to him by means of Moses.

41 And directly the next day the whole assembly of the sons of Israel began to murmur against Moses and Aaron, saying: “YOU men, YOU have put Jehovah’s people to death.” 42 And it came about that when the assembly had congregated themselves together against Moses and Aaron, they then turned toward the tent of meeting; and, look! the cloud covered it, and Jehovah’s glory began to appear.

43 And Moses and Aaron proceeded to come before the tent of meeting. 44 Then Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying: 45 “YOU men, rise up from the midst of this assembly, that I may exterminate them in an instant.” At this they fell upon their faces. 46 After that Moses said to Aaron: “Take the fire holder and put fire from upon the altar in it and put on incense and go to the assembly in a hurry and make atonement for them, because the indignation has gone out from the face of Jehovah. The plague has started!” 47 Aaron at once took it, just as Moses had spoken, and went running into the midst of the congregation; and, look! the plague had started among the people. So he put the incense on and began making atonement for the people. 48 And he kept standing between the dead and the living. Eventually the scourge was stopped. 49 And those dead from the scourge amounted to fourteen thousand seven hundred, aside from those dead on account of Ko′rah. 50 When at last Aaron returned to Moses at the entrance of the tent of meeting, the scourge had been stopped.

Numbers

18 And Jehovah proceeded to say to Aaron: “You and your sons and the house of your father with you will answer for error against the sanctuary, and you and your sons with you will answer for error against YOUR priesthood. 2 And bring near, also, your brothers of the tribe of Le′vi, the clan of your father, with you, that they may be joined to you and may minister to you, to both you and your sons with you, before the tent of the Testimony. 3 And they must keep their obligation to you and their obligation to the entire tent. Only to the utensils of the holy place and to the altar they must not come near that they may not die, neither they nor YOU men. 4 And they must be joined to you and must keep their obligation to the tent of meeting as respects all the service of the tent, and no stranger may come near to YOU men. 5 And YOU must keep YOUR obligation to the holy place and YOUR obligation to the altar, that no further indignation may occur against the sons of Israel. 6 And I, look! I have taken YOUR brothers, the Levites, from among the sons of Israel, as a gift for YOU, as those given to Jehovah to carry on the service of the tent of meeting. 7 And you and your sons with you should safeguard YOUR priesthood as regards every concern of the altar and as regards what is inside the curtain; and YOU men must render service. As a service of gift I shall give YOUR priesthood, and the stranger drawing near should be put to death.”

8 And Jehovah spoke further to Aaron: “As for me, look! I have given you the custody of the contributions made to me. Of all the holy things of the sons of Israel I have given them to you and to your sons as a portion, as an allowance to time indefinite. 9 This should become yours out of the most holy things, out of the offering made by fire, every offering of theirs together with every grain offering of theirs and every sin offering of theirs and every guilt offering of theirs, which they will return to me. It is something most holy for you and for your sons. 10 In a most holy place you should eat it. Every male should eat it. It should become something holy to you. 11 And this belongs to you: the contribution of their gift together with all the wave offerings of the sons of Israel. I have given them to you and your sons and your daughters with you, as an allowance to time indefinite. Everyone clean in your house may eat it.

12 “All the best of the oil and all the best of the new wine and the grain, their firstfruits, which they will give to Jehovah, I have given them to you. 13 The first ripe fruits of all that is on their land, which they will bring to Jehovah, yours it should become. Everyone clean in your house may eat it.

14 “Every devoted thing in Israel should become yours.

15 “Everything opening the womb, of every sort of flesh, which they will present to Jehovah, among man and among beast, should become yours. However, you should without fail redeem the firstborn of mankind; and the firstborn of the unclean beast you should redeem. 16 And with a redemption price for it from a month old onward you should redeem it, by the estimated value, five silver shekels by the shekel of the holy place. It is twenty ge′rahs. 17 Only the firstborn bull or firstborn male lamb or firstborn goat you should not redeem. They are something holy. Their blood you should sprinkle upon the altar, and their fat you should make smoke as an offering made by fire for a restful odor to Jehovah. 18 And their flesh should become yours. Like the breast of the wave offering and like the right leg, it should become yours. 19 All the holy contributions, which the sons of Israel will contribute to Jehovah, I have given to you and your sons and your daughters with you, as an allowance to time indefinite. It is a covenant of salt to time indefinite before Jehovah for you and your offspring with you.”

20 And Jehovah went on to say to Aaron: “In their land you will not have an inheritance, and no share will become yours in their midst. I am your share and your inheritance in the midst of the sons of Israel.

21 “And to the sons of Le′vi, look! I have given every tenth part in Israel as an inheritance in return for their service that they are carrying on, the service of the tent of meeting. 22 And the sons of Israel should no more come near to the tent of meeting to incur sin so as to die. 23 And the Levites themselves must carry on the service of the tent of meeting, and they are the ones who should answer for their error. It is a statute to time indefinite during YOUR generations that in the midst of the sons of Israel they should not get possession of an inheritance. 24 For the tenth part of the sons of Israel, which they will contribute to Jehovah as a contribution, I have given to the Levites as an inheritance. That is why I have said to them, ‘In the midst of the sons of Israel they should not get possession of an inheritance.’”

25 Then Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying: 26 “And you should speak to the Levites, and you must say to them, ‘YOU will receive from the sons of Israel the tenth part that I have given to YOU from them for YOUR inheritance, and YOU must contribute from it as a contribution to Jehovah a tenth part of the tenth part. 27 And it must be reckoned to YOU as YOUR contribution, like the grain of the threshing floor and like the full produce of the wine or oil press. 28 In this way YOU yourselves also will contribute a contribution to Jehovah from all YOUR tenth parts that YOU will receive from the sons of Israel, and from them YOU must give the contribution to Jehovah to Aaron the priest. 29 From all the gifts to YOU, YOU will contribute every sort of contribution to Jehovah, of the very best of it, as some holy thing from them.’

30 “And you must say to them, ‘When YOU contribute the best of them, then it will certainly be reckoned to the Levites as the produce of the threshing floor and as the produce of the wine or oil press. 31 And YOU must eat it in every place, YOU and YOUR household, because it is YOUR wages in return for YOUR service in the tent of meeting. 32 And YOU must not incur sin for it when YOU contribute the best from them, and YOU must not profane the holy things of the sons of Israel, that YOU may not die.’”

Numbers

20 And the sons of Israel, the entire assembly, proceeded to come into the wilderness of Zin in the first month, and the people took up dwelling in Ka′desh. It was there that Mir′i·am died and there that she was buried.

2 Now there proved to be no water for the assembly, and they began to congregate themselves against Moses and Aaron. 3 And the people went quarreling with Moses and saying: “If only we had expired when our brothers expired before Jehovah! 4 And why have YOU men brought Jehovah’s congregation into this wilderness for us and our beasts of burden to die there? 5 And why have YOU conducted us up out of Egypt to bring us into this evil place? It is no place of seed and figs and vines and pomegranates, and there is no water to drink.” 6 Then Moses and Aaron came from before the congregation to the entrance of the tent of meeting and fell upon their faces, and Jehovah’s glory began to appear to them.

7 Then Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying: 8 “Take the rod and call the assembly together, you and Aaron your brother, and YOU must speak to the crag before their eyes that it may indeed give its water; and you must bring out water for them from the crag and give the assembly and their beasts of burden drink.”

9 So Moses took the rod from before Jehovah, just as he had commanded him. 10 After that Moses and Aaron called the congregation together before the crag, and he proceeded to say to them: “Hear, now, YOU rebels! Is it from this crag that we shall bring out water for YOU?” 11 With that Moses lifted his hand up and struck the crag with his rod twice; and much water began to come out, and the assembly and their beasts of burden began to drink.

12 Later Jehovah said to Moses and Aaron: “Because YOU did not show faith in me to sanctify me before the eyes of the sons of Israel, therefore YOU will not bring this congregation into the land that I shall certainly give them.” 13 These are the waters of Mer′i·bah, because the sons of Israel quarreled with Jehovah, so that he was sanctified among them.

14 Subsequently Moses sent messengers from Ka′desh to the king of E′dom: “This is what your brother Israel has said, ‘You yourself well know all the hardship that has overtaken us. 15 And our fathers proceeded to go down to Egypt, and we continued to dwell in Egypt many days; and the Egyptians began doing harm to us and our fathers. 16 Finally we cried out to Jehovah and he heard our voice and sent an angel and brought us out of Egypt; and here we are in Ka′desh, a city at the extremity of your territory. 17 Let us pass, please, through your land. We shall not pass through a field or a vineyard, and we shall not drink the water of a well. On the king’s road we shall march. We shall not bend toward the right or the left, until we shall pass through your territory.’”

18 However, E′dom said to him: “You must not pass through me, for fear I may come out with the sword to meet you.” 19 In turn the sons of Israel said to him: “By the highway we shall go up; and if I and my livestock should drink your water, I shall also certainly give the value of it. I want nothing more than to pass through on my feet.” 20 Still he said: “You must not pass through.” With that E′dom came on out to encounter him with a great many people and a strong hand. 21 So E′dom refused to grant Israel to pass through his territory. Hence Israel turned away from him.

22 And the sons of Israel, the entire assembly, proceeded to pull away from Ka′desh and come to Mount Hor. 23 Then Jehovah said this to Moses and Aaron in Mount Hor by the border of the land of E′dom: 24 “Aaron will be gathered to his people, for he will not enter into the land that I shall certainly give to the sons of Israel, on the ground that YOU men rebelled against my order respecting the waters of Mer′i·bah. 25 Take Aaron and El·e·a′zar his son and bring them up into Mount Hor. 26 And strip Aaron of his garments, and you must clothe with them El·e·a′zar his son; and Aaron will be gathered and must die there.”

27 So Moses did just as Jehovah had commanded; and before the eyes of all the assembly they went climbing Mount Hor. 28 Then Moses stripped Aaron of his garments and clothed El·e·a′zar his son with them, after which Aaron died there on the top of the mountain. And Moses and El·e·a′zar came on down from the mountain. 29 And all the assembly got to see that Aaron had expired, and all the house of Israel continued weeping for Aaron thirty days.

Numbers

22 Then the sons of Israel pulled away and encamped on the desert plains of Mo′ab across the Jordan from Jer′i·cho. 2 And Ba′lak the son of Zip′por got to see all that Israel had done to the Am′or·ites. 3 And Mo′ab became very frightened at the people, because they were many; and Mo′ab began to feel a sickening dread of the sons of Israel. 4 And Mo′ab proceeded to say to the older men of Mid′i·an: “Now this congregation will lick up all our surroundings like the bull licking up the green growth of the field.”

And Ba′lak the son of Zip′por was king of Mo′ab at that particular time. 5 He now sent messengers to Ba′laam the son of Be′or at Pe′thor, which is by the River of the land of the sons of his people, to call him, saying: “Look! A people has come out of Egypt. Look! They have covered the earth as far as one can see, and they are dwelling right in front of me. 6 And now do come, please; do curse this people for me, for they are mightier than I am. Perhaps I may be able to strike them and I may drive them out of the land; for I well know that the one whom you bless is a blessed one and the one whom you curse is cursed.”

7 So the older men of Mo′ab and the older men of Mid′i·an traveled with the payments for divination in their hands and went to Ba′laam and spoke to him Ba′lak’s words. 8 At that he said to them: “Lodge here tonight, and I shall certainly return YOU word just as Jehovah may speak to me.” Accordingly the princes of Mo′ab stayed with Ba′laam.

9 Then God came to Ba′laam and said: “Who are these men with you?” 10 So Ba′laam said to the true God: “Ba′lak the son of Zip′por, the king of Mo′ab, has sent to me, saying, 11 ‘Look! The people who are coming out of Egypt, and they go covering the earth as far as the eye can see. Now do come, do execrate them for me. Perhaps I may be able to fight against them and I shall actually drive them out.’” 12 But God said to Ba′laam: “You must not go with them. You must not curse the people, for they are blessed.”

13 After that Ba′laam got up in the morning and said to the princes of Ba′lak: “Go to YOUR country, because Jehovah has refused to let me go with YOU.” 14 So the princes of Mo′ab got up and came to Ba′lak and said: “Ba′laam has refused to come with us.”

15 However, Ba′lak sent again other princes in greater number and more honorable than the former. 16 In turn they came to Ba′laam and said to him: “This is what Ba′lak the son of Zip′por has said, ‘Do not be detained, please, from coming to me. 17 For I shall without fail honor you greatly, and everything you may say to me I shall do. So do come, please. Do execrate this people for me.’” 18 But Ba′laam answered and said to the servants of Ba′lak: “If Ba′lak were to give me his house full of silver and gold, I should not be able to pass beyond the order of Jehovah my God, so as to do something small or great. 19 And now YOU men also stay here, please, tonight that I may know what further Jehovah will speak with me.”

20 Then God came to Ba′laam by night and said to him: “If it is to call you that the men have come, get up, go with them. But only the word that I shall speak to you is what you may speak.” 21 After that Ba′laam got up in the morning and saddled his she-ass and went with the princes of Mo′ab.

22 And the anger of God began to blaze because he was going; and Jehovah’s angel proceeded to station himself in the road to resist him. And he was riding upon his she-ass, and two attendants of his were with him. 23 And the ass got to see Jehovah’s angel stationed in the road with his drawn sword in his hand; and the ass tried to turn aside from the road that she might go into the field, but Ba′laam began to strike the ass in order to turn her aside to the road. 24 And Jehovah’s angel kept standing in the narrow way between the vineyards, with a stone wall on this side and a stone wall on that side. 25 And the she-ass kept seeing Jehovah’s angel and began to squeeze herself against the wall and so to squeeze Ba′laam’s foot against the wall; and he went beating her some more.

26 Jehovah’s angel now passed by again and stood in a narrow place, where there was no way to turn aside to the right or the left. 27 When the ass got to see Jehovah’s angel she now lay down under Ba′laam; so that Ba′laam’s anger blazed, and he kept beating the ass with his staff. 28 Finally Jehovah opened the mouth of the ass and she said to Ba′laam: “What have I done to you so that you have beaten me these three times?” 29 At this Ba′laam said to the ass: “It is because you have dealt ruthlessly with me. If only there were a sword in my hand, for now I should have killed you!” 30 Then the she-ass said to Ba′laam: “Am I not your she-ass that you have ridden upon all your life long until this day? Have I ever been used to do to you this way?” To which he said: “No!” 31 And Jehovah proceeded to uncover Ba′laam’s eyes, so that he saw Jehovah’s angel stationed in the road with his drawn sword in his hand. At once he bowed low and prostrated himself on his face.

32 Then Jehovah’s angel said to him: “Why have you beaten your she-ass these three times? Look! I—I have come out to offer resistance, because your way has been headlong against my will. 33 And the she-ass got to see me and tried to turn aside before me these three times. Supposing she had not turned aside from before me! For by now even you I should have killed, but her I should have preserved alive.” 34 At this Ba′laam said to Jehovah’s angel: “I have sinned, because I did not know that it was you stationed in the road to meet me. And now, if it is bad in your eyes, let me go my way back.” 35 But Jehovah’s angel said to Ba′laam: “Go with the men; and nothing but the word that I shall speak to you is what you may speak.” And Ba′laam continued going with the princes of Ba′lak.

36 When Ba′lak got to hear that Ba′laam had come, he at once went out to meet him at the city of Mo′ab, which is on the bank of the Ar′non, which is on the extremity of the territory. 37 Then Ba′lak said to Ba′laam: “Have I not for a fact sent to you to call you? Why did you not come to me? Am I not really and truly able to honor you?” 38 At this Ba′laam said to Ba′lak: “Here I have come to you now. Shall I be able at all to speak something? The word that God will place in my mouth is what I shall speak.”

39 So Ba′laam went with Ba′lak and they came to Kir′i·ath-hu′zoth. 40 And Ba′lak proceeded to sacrifice cattle and sheep and to send some to Ba′laam and the princes who were with him. 41 And it came about in the morning that Ba′lak went taking Ba′laam and bringing him up to Ba′moth-ba′al, that he might see from there the whole of the people.

Numbers

23 Then Ba′laam said to Ba′lak: “Build for me on this spot seven altars and make ready for me on this spot seven bulls and seven rams.” 2 Ba′lak immediately did just as Ba′laam had spoken. After that Ba′lak and Ba′laam offered up a bull and a ram on each altar. 3 And Ba′laam went on to say to Ba′lak: “Station yourself by your burnt offering, and let me go. Perhaps Jehovah will get in touch and meet with me. In that case whatever he will show me, I shall certainly tell you.” So he went to a bare hill.

4 When God got in touch with Ba′laam, he then said to Him: “I set the seven altars in rows, and I proceeded to offer up a bull and a ram on each altar.” 5 Accordingly Jehovah put a word in the mouth of Ba′laam and said: “Return to Ba′lak, and this is what you will speak.” 6 So he returned to him, and, look! he and all the princes of Mo′ab were stationed by his burnt offering. 7 Then he took up his proverbial utterance and said:

“From A′ram Ba′lak the king of Mo′ab tried to conduct me,

From the mountains of the east:

‘Do come, do curse Jacob for me.

Yes, do come, do denounce Israel.’

8 How could I execrate those whom God has not execrated?

And how could I denounce those whom Jehovah has not denounced?

9 For from the top of the rocks I see them,

And from the hills I behold them.

There as a people they keep tabernacling isolated,

And among the nations they do not reckon themselves.

10 Who has numbered the dust particles of Jacob,

And who has counted the fourth part of Israel?

Let my soul die the death of the upright ones,

And let my end turn out afterward like theirs.”

11 At this Ba′lak said to Ba′laam: “What have you done to me? It was in order to execrate my enemies that I took you, and here you have blessed them to the limit.” 12 In turn he answered and said: “Is it not whatever Jehovah may put in my mouth that I should take care to speak?”

13 Then Ba′lak said to him: “Do come, please, with me to another place from which you can see them. Only the extremity of them you will see, and you will not see all of them. And execrate them for me from there.” 14 So he took him to the field of Zo′phim, to the top of Pis′gah, and proceeded to build seven altars and to offer up a bull and a ram on each altar. 15 After that he said to Ba′lak: “Station yourself here by your burnt offering, and, as for me, let me get in touch with him there.” 16 Subsequently Jehovah got in touch with Ba′laam and put a word in his mouth and said: “Return to Ba′lak, and this is what you will speak.” 17 So he came to him, and, look! he was stationed by his burnt offering, and the princes of Mo′ab with him. Then Ba′lak said to him: “What has Jehovah spoken?” 18 At this he took up his proverbial utterance and said:

“Get up, Ba′lak, and listen.

Do give ear to me, O son of Zip′por.

19 God is not a man that he should tell lies,

Neither a son of mankind that he should feel regret.

Has he himself said it and will he not do it,

And has he spoken and will he not carry it out?

20 Look! I have been taken to bless,

And He has blessed, and I shall not reverse it.

21 He has not looked upon any uncanny power against Jacob,

And no trouble has he seen against Israel.

Jehovah his God is with him,

And the loud hailing of a king is in his midst.

22 God is bringing them out of Egypt.

The swift course like that of a wild bull is his.

23 For there is no unlucky spell against Jacob,

Nor any divination against Israel.

At this time it may be said respecting Jacob and Israel,

‘What has God worked out!’

24 Behold, a people will get up like a lion,

And like the lion it will lift itself up.

It will not lie down until it may eat prey,

And the blood of slain ones it will drink.”

25 At this Ba′lak said to Ba′laam: “If, on the one hand, you cannot execrate him at all, then, on the other hand, you should not bless him at all.” 26 In turn Ba′laam answered and said to Ba′lak: “Did I not speak to you, saying, ‘All that Jehovah will speak is what I shall do’?”

27 Then Ba′lak said to Ba′laam: “O come, please. Let me take you to still another place. Perhaps it will be right in the eyes of the true God so that you will certainly execrate him for me from there.” 28 With that Ba′lak took Ba′laam to the top of Pe′or, which looks toward Je·shi′mon. 29 Then Ba′laam said to Ba′lak: “Build for me on this spot seven altars and make ready for me on this spot seven bulls and seven rams.” 30 So Ba′lak did just as Ba′laam had said, and he went offering up a bull and a ram on each altar.

Numbers

24 When Ba′laam got to see that it was good in the eyes of Jehovah to bless Israel, he did not go away as at the other times to come upon any unlucky omens, but he directed his face to the wilderness. 2 When Ba′laam raised his eyes and saw Israel tabernacling by his tribes, then the spirit of God came to be upon him. 3 Hence he took up his proverbial utterance and said:

“The utterance of Ba′laam the son of Be′or,

And the utterance of the able-bodied man with the eye unsealed,

4 The utterance of the one hearing the sayings of God,

Who got to see a vision of the Almighty

While falling down with the eyes uncovered:

5 How good-looking are your tents, O Jacob, your tabernacles, O Israel!

6 Like torrent valleys they have extended a long way,

Like gardens by the river.

Like aloe plants that Jehovah has planted,

Like cedars by the waters.

7 Water keeps trickling from his two leather buckets,

And his seed is by many waters.

His king also will be higher than A′gag,

And his kingdom will be lifted up.

8 God is bringing him out of Egypt;

The swift course of a wild bull is his.

He will consume the nations, his oppressors,

And their bones he will gnaw, and he will break them to pieces with his arrows.

9 He bowed down, he lay down like the lion,

And, like a lion, who dares rouse him?

Those blessing you are the ones blessed,

And those cursing you are the ones cursed.”

10 At that Ba′lak’s anger blazed against Ba′laam and he clapped his hands, and Ba′lak went on to say to Ba′laam: “It was to execrate my enemies that I called you, and, look! you have blessed them to the limit these three times. 11 And now run your way off to your place. I had said to myself I was without fail going to honor you, but, look! Jehovah has held you back from honor.”

12 In turn Ba′laam said to Ba′lak: “Was it not also to your messengers whom you sent to me that I spoke, saying, 13 ‘If Ba′lak were to give me his house full of silver and gold, I should not be able to pass beyond the order of Jehovah so as to do something good or bad out of my own heart. Whatever Jehovah may speak is what I shall speak’? 14 And now here I am going away to my people. Do come, let me advise you what this people will do to your people afterward in the end of the days.” 15 So he took up his proverbial utterance and said:

“The utterance of Ba′laam the son of Be′or,

And the utterance of the able-bodied man with the eye unsealed,

16 The utterance of the one hearing the sayings of God,

And the one knowing the knowledge of the Most High—

A vision of the Almighty he got to see

While falling down with the eyes uncovered:

17 I shall see him, but not now;

I shall behold him, but not near.

A star will certainly step forth out of Jacob,

And a scepter will indeed rise out of Israel.

And he will certainly break apart the temples of Mo′ab’s head

And the cranium of all the sons of tumult of war.

18 And E′dom must become a possession,

Yes, Se′ir must become the possession of his enemies,

While Israel is displaying his courage.

19 And out of Jacob one will go subduing,

And he must destroy any survivor from the city.”

20 When he got to see Am′a·lek, he carried further his proverbial utterance and went on to say:

“Am′a·lek was the first one of the nations,

But his end afterward will be even his perishing.”

21 When he got to see the Ken′ites, he carried further his proverbial utterance and went on to say:

“Durable is your dwelling, and set on the crag is your abode.

22 But there will come to be one to burn Ka′in down.

How long will it be till As·syr′i·a will carry you away captive?”

23 And he carried further his proverbial utterance and went on to say:

“Woe! Who will survive when God causes it?

24 And there will be ships from the coast of Kit′tim,

And they will certainly afflict As·syr′i·a,

And they will indeed afflict E′ber.

But he too will eventually perish.”

25 After that Ba′laam got up and went and returned to his place. And Ba′lak also went his own way.

Numbers

26 And it came about after the scourge, that Jehovah went on to say this to Moses and El·e·a′zar the son of Aaron the priest: 2 “TAKE the sum of the whole assembly of the sons of Israel from twenty years of age and upward, according to the house of their fathers, all those going out to the army in Israel.” 3 And Moses and El·e·a′zar the priest proceeded to speak with them in the desert plains of Mo′ab by the Jordan at Jer′i·cho, saying: 4 “Take the sum of them from the age of twenty years and upward, just as Jehovah had commanded Moses.”

Now the sons of Israel who went out of the land of Egypt were: 5 Reu′ben, Israel’s firstborn; Reu′ben’s sons: Of Ha′noch the family of the Ha′noch·ites; of Pal′lu the family of the Pal′lu·ites; 6 of Hez′ron the family of the Hez′ron·ites; of Car′mi the family of the Car′mites. 7 These were the families of the Reu′ben·ites, and their registered ones amounted to forty-three thousand seven hundred and thirty.

8 And the son of Pal′lu was E·li′ab. 9 And the sons of E·li′ab: Nem′u·el and Da′than and A·bi′ram. This Da′than and A·bi′ram were summoned ones of the assembly, who engaged in a struggle against Moses and Aaron in the assembly of Ko′rah, when they engaged in a struggle against Jehovah.

10 Then the earth opened its mouth and swallowed them up. As for Ko′rah, he died at the death of the assembly when the fire consumed two hundred and fifty men. And they came to be a symbol. 11 However, the sons of Ko′rah did not die.

12 The sons of Sim′e·on by their families: Of Nem′u·el the family of the Nem′u·el·ites; of Ja′min the family of the Ja′min·ites; of Ja′chin the family of the Ja′chin·ites; 13 of Ze′rah the family of the Ze′rah·ites; of Sha′ul the family of the Sha·u′lites. 14 These were the families of the Sim′e·on·ites: twenty-two thousand two hundred.

15 The sons of Gad by their families: Of Ze′phon the family of the Ze′phon·ites; of Hag′gi the family of the Hag′gites; of Shu′ni the family of the Shu′nites; 16 of Oz′ni the family of the Oz′nites; of E′ri the family of the E′rites; 17 of Ar′od the family of the Ar′od·ites; of A·re′li the family of the A·re′lites. 18 These were the families of the sons of Gad, of their registered ones: forty thousand five hundred.

19 The sons of Judah were Er and O′nan. However, Er and O′nan died in the land of Ca′naan. 20 And the sons of Judah came to be, by their families: Of She′lah the family of the She·la′nites; of Pe′rez the family of the Per′e·zites; of Ze′rah the family of the Ze′rah·ites. 21 And the sons of Pe′rez came to be: Of Hez′ron the family of the Hez′ron·ites; of Ha′mul the family of the Ha·mu′lites. 22 These were the families of Judah, of their registered ones: seventy-six thousand five hundred.

23 The sons of Is′sa·char by their families were: Of To′la the family of the To′la·ites; of Pu′vah the family of the Pu′nites; 24 of Ja′shub the family of the Jash′u·bites; of Shim′ron the family of the Shim′ron·ites. 25 These were the families of Is′sa·char, of their registered ones: sixty-four thousand three hundred.

26 The sons of Zeb′u·lun by their families were: Of Se′red the family of the Ser′e·dites; of E′lon the family of the E′lon·ites; of Jah′le·el the family of the Jah′le·el·ites. 27 These were the families of the Ze·bu′lu·nites, of their registered ones: sixty thousand five hundred.

28 The sons of Joseph by their families were Ma·nas′seh and E′phra·im. 29 The sons of Ma·nas′seh were: Of Ma′chir the family of the Ma′chir·ites. And Ma′chir became father to Gil′e·ad. Of Gil′e·ad the family of the Gil′e·ad·ites. 30 These were the sons of Gil′e·ad: Of Ie′zer the family of the Ie′zer·ites; of He′lek the family of the He′lek·ites; 31 of As′ri·el the family of the As′ri·el·ites; of She′chem the family of the She′chem·ites; 32 of She·mi′da the family of the She·mi′da·ites; of He′pher the family of the He′pher·ites. 33 Now Ze·lo′phe·had the son of He′pher proved to have no sons, but daughters, and the names of the daughters of Ze·lo′phe·had were Mah′lah and Noah, Hog′lah, Mil′cah and Tir′zah. 34 These were the families of Ma·nas′seh, and their registered ones were fifty-two thousand seven hundred.

35 These were the sons of E′phra·im by their families: Of Shu′the·lah the family of the Shu′thel·a′hites; of Be′cher the family of the Be′cher·ites; of Ta′han the family of the Ta′han·ites. 36 And these were the sons of Shu′the·lah: Of E′ran the family of the E′ran·ites. 37 These were the families of the sons of E′phra·im, of their registered ones: thirty-two thousand five hundred. These were the sons of Joseph by their families.

38 The sons of Benjamin by their families were: Of Be′la the family of the Be′la·ites; of Ash′bel the family of the Ash′bel·ites; of A·hi′ram the family of the A·hi′ram·ites; 39 of She·phu′pham the family of the Shu′pham·ites; of Hu′pham the family of the Hu′pham·ites. 40 The sons of Be′la came to be Ard and Na′a·man: Of Ard the family of the Ard′ites; of Na′a·man the family of the Na′a·mites. 41 These were the sons of Benjamin by their families, and their registered ones were forty-five thousand six hundred.

42 These were the sons of Dan by their families: Of Shu′ham the family of the Shu′ham·ites. These were the families of Dan by their families. 43 All the families of the Shu′ham·ites, of their registered ones, were sixty-four thousand four hundred.

44 The sons of Ash′er by their families were: Of Im′nah the family of the Im′nites; of Ish′vi the family of the Ish′vites; of Be·ri′ah the family of the Be·ri′ites; 45 of the sons of Be·ri′ah: Of He′ber the family of the He′ber·ites; of Mal′chi·el the family of the Mal′chi·el·ites. 46 And the name of Ash′er’s daughter was Se′rah. 47 These were the families of the sons of Ash′er, of their registered ones: fifty-three thousand four hundred.

48 The sons of Naph′ta·li by their families were: Of Jah′ze·el the family of the Jah′ze·el·ites; of Gu′ni the family of the Gu′nites; 49 of Je′zer the family of the Je′zer·ites; of Shil′lem the family of the Shil′lem·ites. 50 These were the families of Naph′ta·li by their families, and their registered ones were forty-five thousand four hundred.

51 These were the registered ones of the sons of Israel: six hundred and one thousand seven hundred and thirty.

52 After that Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying: 53 “To these the land should be apportioned for an inheritance by the number of the names. 54 According to the great number you should increase one’s inheritance, and according to the fewness you should reduce one’s inheritance. Each one’s inheritance should be given in proportion to his registered ones. 55 Only by the lot should the land be apportioned. According to the names of the tribes of their fathers they should get an inheritance. 56 By the determination of the lot one’s inheritance should be apportioned between the many and the few.”

57 Now these were the registered ones of the Levites by their families: Of Ger′shon the family of the Ger′shon·ites; of Ko′hath the family of the Ko′hath·ites; of Me·rar′i the family of the Me·rar′ites. 58 These were the families of the Levites: the family of the Lib′nites, the family of the He′bron·ites, the family of the Mah′lites, the family of the Mu′shites, the family of the Ko′rah·ites.

And Ko′hath became father to Am′ram. 59 And the name of Am′ram’s wife was Joch′e·bed, Le′vi’s daughter, whom his wife bore to Le′vi in Egypt. In time she bore to Am′ram Aaron and Moses and Mir′i·am their sister. 60 Then there were born to Aaron Na′dab and A·bi′hu, El·e·a′zar and Ith′a·mar. 61 But Na′dab and A·bi′hu died for their presenting illegitimate fire before Jehovah.

62 And their registered ones amounted to twenty-three thousand, all males from a month old and upward. For they did not get registered in among the sons of Israel, because no inheritance was to be given to them in among the sons of Israel.

63 These were the ones registered by Moses and El·e·a′zar the priest when they registered the sons of Israel in the desert plains of Mo′ab by the Jordan at Jer′i·cho. 64 But among these there did not prove to be a man of those registered by Moses and Aaron the priest when they registered the sons of Israel in the wilderness of Si′nai. 65 For Jehovah had said concerning them: “They will die without fail in the wilderness.” So there was not left of them a man except Ca′leb the son of Je·phun′neh and Joshua the son of Nun.

Numbers

27 Then the daughters of Ze·lo′phe·had the son of He′pher the son of Gil′e·ad the son of Ma′chir the son of Ma·nas′seh, of the families of Ma·nas′seh the son of Joseph, came near. And these were the names of his daughters: Mah′lah, Noah and Hog′lah and Mil′cah and Tir′zah. 2 And they proceeded to stand before Moses and before El·e·a′zar the priest and before the chieftains and all the assembly at the entrance of the tent of meeting, saying: 3 “Our father has died in the wilderness, and yet he did not prove to be in among the assembly, that is, those who ranged themselves against Jehovah in the assembly of Ko′rah, but for his own sin he has died; and he did not get to have any sons. 4 Why should the name of our father be taken away from the midst of his family because he had no son? O give us a possession in the midst of our father’s brothers.” 5 At that Moses presented their case before Jehovah.

6 Jehovah then said this to Moses: 7 “The daughters of Ze·lo′phe·had are speaking right. By all means you should give them the possession of an inheritance in the midst of their father’s brothers, and you must cause their father’s inheritance to pass to them. 8 And to the sons of Israel you should speak, saying, ‘In case any man should die without his having a son, YOU must then cause his inheritance to pass to his daughter. 9 And if he has no daughter, YOU must then give his inheritance to his brothers. 10 And if he has no brothers, YOU must then give his inheritance to his father’s brothers. 11 And if his father has no brothers, YOU must then give his inheritance to his blood relation who is closest to him of his family, and he must take possession of it. And it must serve as a statute by judicial decision for the sons of Israel, just as Jehovah has commanded Moses.’”

12 Subsequently Jehovah said to Moses: “Go up into this mountain of Ab′a·rim and see the land that I shall certainly give the sons of Israel. 13 When you have seen it, then you must be gathered to your people, yes, you, just as Aaron your brother was gathered, 14 inasmuch as YOU men rebelled against my order in the wilderness of Zin at the quarreling of the assembly, in relation to sanctifying me by the waters before their eyes. These are the waters of Mer′i·bah at Ka′desh in the wilderness of Zin.”

15 Then Moses spoke to Jehovah, saying: 16 “Let Jehovah the God of the spirits of all sorts of flesh appoint over the assembly a man 17 who will go out before them and who will come in before them and who will bring them out and who will bring them in, that Jehovah’s assembly may not become like sheep that have no shepherd.” 18 So Jehovah said to Moses: “Take for yourself Joshua the son of Nun, a man in whom there is spirit, and you must lay your hand upon him; 19 and you must stand him before El·e·a′zar the priest and before all the assembly, and you must commission him before their eyes. 20 And you must put some of your dignity upon him, in order that all the assembly of the sons of Israel may listen to him. 21 And it is before El·e·a′zar the priest that he will stand, and he must inquire in his behalf by the judgment of the U′rim before Jehovah. At his order they will go out and at his order they will come in, he and all the sons of Israel with him and all the assembly.”

22 And Moses proceeded to do just as Jehovah had commanded him. Accordingly he took Joshua and stood him before El·e·a′zar the priest and before all the assembly 23 and laid his hands upon him and commissioned him, just as Jehovah had spoken by means of Moses.

Numbers

31 Jehovah then spoke to Moses, saying: 2 “Take vengeance for the sons of Israel upon the Mid′i·an·ites. Afterward you will be gathered to your people.”

3 So Moses spoke to the people, saying: “Equip men from among YOU for the army, that they may serve against Mid′i·an to execute Jehovah’s vengeance upon Mid′i·an. 4 A thousand of each tribe of all the tribes of Israel YOU will send into the army.” 5 Accordingly from the thousands of Israel a thousand were assigned of a tribe, twelve thousand equipped for the army.

6 Then Moses sent them out, a thousand of each tribe, to the army, them and Phin′e·has the son of El·e·a′zar the priest to the army, and the holy utensils and the trumpets for blowing calls were in his hand. 7 And they went waging war against Mid′i·an, just as Jehovah had commanded Moses, and they proceeded to kill every male. 8 And they killed the kings of Mid′i·an along with the others slain, namely, E′vi and Re′kem and Zur and Hur and Re′ba, the five kings of Mid′i·an; and they killed Ba′laam the son of Be′or with the sword. 9 But the sons of Israel carried off the women of Mid′i·an and their little ones captive; and all their domestic animals and all their livestock and all their means of maintenance they plundered. 10 And all their cities in which they had settled and all their walled camps they burned with fire. 11 And they went taking all the spoil and all the booty in the way of humans and domestic animals. 12 And they came bringing to Moses and El·e·a′zar the priest and to the assembly of the sons of Israel the captives and the booty and the spoil, to the camp, to the desert plains of Mo′ab, which are by the Jordan at Jer′i·cho.

13 Then Moses and El·e·a′zar the priest and all the chieftains of the assembly went out to meet them outside the camp. 14 And Moses grew indignant at the appointed men of the combat forces, the chiefs of the thousands and the chiefs of the hundreds who were coming in from the military expedition. 15 So Moses said to them: “Have YOU preserved alive every female? 16 Look! They are the ones who, by Ba′laam’s word, served to induce the sons of Israel to commit unfaithfulness toward Jehovah over the affair of Pe′or, so that the scourge came upon the assembly of Jehovah. 17 And now kill every male among the little ones, and kill every woman who has had intercourse with man by lying with a male. 18 And preserve alive for yourselves all the little ones among the women who have not known the act of lying with a male. 19 As for YOU yourselves, camp outside the camp seven days. Everyone who has killed a soul and everyone who has touched someone slain, YOU should purify yourselves on the third day and on the seventh day, YOU and YOUR captives. 20 And every garment and every article of skin and everything made of goat’s hair and every article of wood YOU should purify for yourselves from sin.”

21 El·e·a′zar the priest then said to the men of the army who had gone into the battle: “This is the statute of the law that Jehovah commanded Moses, 22 ‘Only the gold and the silver, the copper, the iron, the tin and the lead, 23 everything that is processed with fire, YOU should pass through the fire, and it must be clean. Only it should be purified by the water for cleansing. And everything that is not processed with fire YOU should pass through the water. 24 And YOU must wash YOUR garments on the seventh day and be clean, and afterward YOU may come into the camp.’”

25 And Jehovah proceeded to say this to Moses: 26 “Take the sum of the booty, the captives both of humankind and of domestic animals, you and El·e·a′zar the priest and the heads of the fathers of the assembly. 27 And you must divide the booty in two between those taking part in the battle who went out on the expedition and all the rest of the assembly. 28 And as a tax for Jehovah you must take away from the men of war who went out on the expedition one soul out of five hundred, of humankind and of the herd and of the asses and of the flock. 29 From their half YOU should take it and you must give it to El·e·a′zar the priest as Jehovah’s contribution. 30 And from the half of the sons of Israel you should take one out of fifty, of humankind, of the herd, of the asses and of the flock, of every sort of domestic animal, and you must give them to the Levites, the keepers of the obligation of Jehovah’s tabernacle.”

31 And Moses and El·e·a′zar the priest went doing just as Jehovah had commanded Moses. 32 And the booty, the rest of the plunder that the people of the expedition had taken as plunder, amounted to six hundred and seventy-five thousand of the flock, 33 and seventy-two thousand of the herd, 34 and sixty-one thousand asses. 35 As for human souls from the women who had not known the act of lying with a male, all the souls were thirty-two thousand. 36 And the half that was the share of those who went out on the expedition amounted in number to three hundred and thirty-seven thousand five hundred of the flock. 37 And the tax for Jehovah from the flock amounted to six hundred and seventy-five. 38 And of the herd there were thirty-six thousand, and the tax on them for Jehovah was seventy-two. 39 And the asses were thirty thousand five hundred, and the tax on them for Jehovah was sixty-one. 40 And the human souls were sixteen thousand, and the tax on them for Jehovah was thirty-two souls. 41 Then Moses gave the tax as Jehovah’s contribution to El·e·a′zar the priest, just as Jehovah had commanded Moses.

42 And from the half belonging to the sons of Israel, which Moses divided from that belonging to the men who waged war: 43 Now the half of the assembly from the flock amounted to three hundred and thirty-seven thousand five hundred, 44 and of the herd, thirty-six thousand, 45 and the asses, thirty thousand five hundred, 46 and human souls, sixteen thousand. 47 Then Moses took from the half belonging to the sons of Israel the one to be taken out of fifty, of humankind and of domestic animals, and gave them to the Levites, the keepers of the obligation of Jehovah’s tabernacle, just as Jehovah had commanded Moses.

48 And the appointed men who were of the thousands of the army, the chiefs of the thousands and the chiefs of the hundreds, proceeded to approach Moses, 49 and to say to Moses: “Your servants have taken the sum of the men of war who are in our charge and not one has been reported missing from us. 50 So let us present each one what he has found as Jehovah’s offering, articles of gold, ankle chainlets, and bracelets, signet rings, earrings, and female ornaments, in order to make atonement for our souls before Jehovah.”

51 Accordingly Moses and El·e·a′zar the priest accepted the gold from them, all the jewelry. 52 And all the gold of the contribution that they contributed to Jehovah amounted to sixteen thousand seven hundred and fifty shekels, from the chiefs of the thousands and the chiefs of the hundreds. 53 The men of the army had taken plunder each for himself. 54 So Moses and El·e·a′zar the priest accepted the gold from the chiefs of the thousands and of the hundreds and brought it into the tent of meeting as a memorial for the sons of Israel before Jehovah.

Numbers

32 Now the sons of Reu′ben and the sons of Gad had come to have numerous livestock, very many, in fact. And they began to see the land of Ja′zer and the land of Gil′e·ad, and, look! the place was a place for livestock. 2 Hence the sons of Gad and the sons of Reu′ben came and said this to Moses and El·e·a′zar the priest and to the chieftains of the assembly: 3 “At′a·roth and Di′bon and Ja′zer and Nim′rah and Hesh′bon and E·le·a′leh and Se′bam and Ne′bo and Be′on, 4 the land that Jehovah defeated before the assembly of Israel, is a land for livestock, and your servants have livestock.” 5 And they went on to say: “If we have found favor in your eyes, let this land be given to your servants as a possession. Do not make us cross the Jordan.”

6 Then Moses said to the sons of Gad and the sons of Reu′ben: “Are YOUR brothers to go to war while YOU yourselves keep dwelling here? 7 And why should YOU dishearten the sons of Israel from crossing into the land that Jehovah will certainly give them? 8 That is the way YOUR fathers did when I sent them from Ka′desh-bar′ne·a to see the land. 9 When they went up to the torrent valley of Esh′col and saw the land, then they disheartened the sons of Israel, so as not to go into the land that Jehovah was certain to give them. 10 Consequently Jehovah’s anger blazed on that day so that he swore, saying, 11 ‘The men who came up out of Egypt from twenty years old upward will not see the soil of which I have sworn to Abraham, Isaac and Jacob, because they have not followed me wholly, 12 except Ca′leb the son of Je·phun′neh the Ken′iz·zite and Joshua the son of Nun, because they have followed Jehovah wholly.’ 13 So Jehovah’s anger blazed against Israel and he made them wander about in the wilderness forty years, until all the generation that was doing evil in the eyes of Jehovah came to their end. 14 And here YOU have risen in the place of YOUR fathers as the brood of sinful men in order to add further to the burning anger of Jehovah against Israel. 15 In case YOU should turn back from following him, he also would certainly once again let them stay longer in the wilderness, and YOU would have acted ruinously toward all this people.”

16 Later they approached him and said: “Let us build here stone flock pens for our livestock and cities for our little ones. 17 But we ourselves shall go equipped in battle formation before the sons of Israel until whenever we have brought them to their place, while our little ones must dwell in the cities with fortifications away from the face of the inhabitants of the land. 18 We shall not return to our houses until the sons of Israel have provided themselves with landed property, each with his own inheritance. 19 For we shall not get an inheritance with them from the side of the Jordan and beyond, because our inheritance has come to us from the side of the Jordan toward the sunrising.”

20 At this Moses said to them: “If YOU will do this thing, if YOU will equip yourselves before Jehovah for the war, 21 and every equipped one of YOURS will actually pass over the Jordan before Jehovah, until he drives away his enemies from before him, 22 and the land is actually subdued before Jehovah, and afterward YOU return, YOU also will indeed prove yourselves free from guilt against Jehovah and against Israel; and this land must become YOURS as a possession before Jehovah. 23 But if YOU will not do this way, YOU will also certainly sin against Jehovah. In that case know that YOUR sin will catch up with YOU. 24 Build for yourselves cities for YOUR little ones and stone pens for YOUR flocks, and what has gone forth from YOUR mouth YOU should do.”

25 Then the sons of Gad and the sons of Reu′ben said this to Moses: “Your servants will do just as my lord is commanding. 26 Our little ones, our wives, our livestock and all our domestic animals will stay there in the cities of Gil′e·ad, 27 but your servants will pass over, everyone equipped for the army, before Jehovah for the war, just as my lord is speaking.”

28 Accordingly Moses gave a command respecting them to El·e·a′zar the priest and to Joshua the son of Nun and to the heads of the fathers of the tribes of the sons of Israel. 29 So Moses said to them: “If the sons of Gad and the sons of Reu′ben pass with YOU over the Jordan, everyone equipped for the war, before Jehovah, and the land is actually subdued before YOU, YOU must then give them the land of Gil′e·ad as a possession. 30 But if they do not pass over equipped with YOU, they must then be settled in YOUR midst in the land of Ca′naan.”

31 To this the sons of Gad and the sons of Reu′ben answered, saying: “What Jehovah has spoken to your servants is the way we shall do. 32 We ourselves will pass over equipped before Jehovah to the land of Ca′naan, and the possession of our inheritance will be with us on this side of the Jordan.” 33 At this Moses gave to them, that is, to the sons of Gad and to the sons of Reu′ben and to half the tribe of Ma·nas′seh the son of Joseph, the kingdom of Si′hon the king of the Am′or·ites and the kingdom of Og the king of Ba′shan, the land belonging to its cities in the territories, and the cities of the land round about.

34 And the sons of Gad proceeded to build Di′bon and At′a·roth and A·ro′er, 35 and At′roth-sho′phan and Ja′zer and Jog′be·hah, 36 and Beth-nim′rah and Beth-ha′ran, cities with fortifications, and stone flock pens. 37 And the sons of Reu′ben built Hesh′bon and E·le·a′leh and Kir·i·a·tha′im, 38 and Ne′bo and Ba′al-me′on—their names being changed—and Sib′mah; and they began to call by their own names the names of the cities that they built.

39 And the sons of Ma′chir the son of Ma·nas′seh proceeded to march to Gil′e·ad and to capture it and to drive away the Am′or·ites who were in it. 40 So Moses gave Gil′e·ad to Ma′chir the son of Ma·nas′seh, and he took up dwelling in it. 41 And Ja′ir the son of Ma·nas′seh marched and went capturing their tent villages, and he began to call them Hav′voth-ja′ir. 42 And No′bah marched and went capturing Ke′nath and its dependent towns; and he began to call it No′bah by his own name.

Numbers

34 And Jehovah spoke further to Moses, saying: 2 “Command the sons of Israel, and you must say to them, ‘YOU are going into the land of Ca′naan. This is the land that will fall to YOU by inheritance, the land of Ca′naan according to its boundaries.

3 “‘And YOUR south side must prove to be from the wilderness of Zin alongside E′dom, and YOUR south boundary must prove to be from the extremity of the Salt Sea on the east. 4 And YOUR boundary must change direction from the south of the ascent of A·krab′bim and cross over to Zin, and its termination must prove to be on the south of Ka′desh-bar′ne·a; and it must go out to Ha′zar-ad′dar and pass over to Az′mon. 5 And the boundary must change direction at Az′mon to the torrent valley of Egypt, and its termination must prove to be at the Sea.

6 “‘As for a west boundary, it must prove to be for YOU the Great Sea and the shoreland. This will become YOUR west boundary.

7 “‘Now this will become YOUR north boundary: From the Great Sea YOU will mark out to Mount Hor as a boundary for yourselves. 8 From Mount Hor YOU will mark out the boundary to the entering in of Ha′math, and the termination of the boundary must prove to be at Ze′dad. 9 And the boundary must go out to Ziph′ron, and its termination must prove to be Ha′zar-e′nan. This will become YOUR north boundary.

10 “‘Then YOU must mark for yourselves as YOUR boundary on the east from Ha′zar-e′nan to She′pham. 11 And the boundary must go down from She′pham to Rib′lah on the east of A′in, and the border must go down and strike upon the eastern slope of the sea of Chin′ne·reth. 12 And the border must go down to the Jordan, and its termination must prove to be the Salt Sea. This will become YOUR land according to its boundaries all around.’”

13 So Moses commanded the sons of Israel, saying: “This is the land that YOU will apportion to yourselves as a possession by lot, just as Jehovah has commanded to give to the nine and a half tribes. 14 For the tribe of the sons of the Reu′ben·ites by the house of their fathers and the tribe of the sons of the Gad′ites by the house of their fathers have already taken, and the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh have already taken their inheritance. 15 The two and a half tribes have already taken their inheritance from the region of the Jordan by Jer′i·cho eastward toward the sunrising.”

16 And Jehovah spoke further to Moses, saying: 17 “These are the names of the men who will divide the land to YOU people for a possession, El·e·a′zar the priest and Joshua the son of Nun. 18 And YOU will take one chieftain out of each tribe to divide the land for a possession. 19 And these are the names of the men: Of the tribe of Judah, Ca′leb the son of Je·phun′neh; 20 and of the tribe of the sons of Sim′e·on, She·mu′el the son of Am·mi′hud; 21 of the tribe of Benjamin, E·li′dad the son of Chis′lon; 22 and of the tribe of the sons of Dan a chieftain, Buk′ki the son of Jog′li; 23 of the sons of Joseph, of the tribe of the sons of Ma·nas′seh a chieftain, Han′ni·el the son of E′phod; 24 and of the tribe of the sons of E′phra·im a chieftain, Kem·u′el the son of Shiph′tan; 25 and of the tribe of the sons of Zeb′u·lun a chieftain, E·li·za′phan the son of Par′nach; 26 and of the tribe of the sons of Is′sa·char a chieftain, Pal′ti·el the son of Az′zan; 27 and of the tribe of the sons of Ash′er a chieftain, A·hi′hud the son of She·lo′mi; 28 and of the tribe of the sons of Naph′ta·li a chieftain, Ped·ah′el the son of Am·mi′hud.” 29 These are the ones whom Jehovah commanded to make the sons of Israel landholders in the land of Ca′naan.

Deuteronomy

5 And Moses proceeded to call all Israel and to say to them: “Hear, O Israel, the regulations and the judicial decisions that I am speaking in YOUR ears today, and YOU must learn them and be careful to do them. 2 Jehovah our God concluded a covenant with us in Ho′reb. 3 It was not with our forefathers that Jehovah concluded this covenant, but with us, all those of us alive here today. 4 Face to face Jehovah spoke with YOU in the mountain out of the middle of the fire. 5 I was standing between Jehovah and YOU at that particular time to tell YOU the word of Jehovah, (for YOU were afraid because of the fire and did not go up into the mountain,) saying,

6 “‘I am Jehovah your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt, out of the house of slaves. 7 You must never have any other gods against my face.

8 “‘You must not make for yourself a carved image, any form like anything that is in the heavens above or that is on the earth underneath or that is in the waters under the earth. 9 You must not bow down to them or be led to serve them, because I Jehovah your God am a God exacting exclusive devotion, bringing punishment for the error of fathers upon sons and upon the third generation and upon the fourth generation, in the case of those who hate me; 10 but exercising loving-kindness toward the thousandth generation in the case of those who love me and keep my commandments.

11 “‘You must not take up the name of Jehovah your God in a worthless way, for Jehovah will not leave anyone unpunished who takes up his name in a worthless way.

12 “‘Keeping the sabbath day to hold it sacred, just as Jehovah your God commanded you, 13 you are to render service and you must do all your work six days. 14 But the seventh day is a sabbath to Jehovah your God. You must not do any work, you nor your son nor your daughter nor your slave man nor your slave girl nor your bull nor your ass nor any domestic animal of yours nor your alien resident who is inside your gates, in order that your slave man and your slave girl may rest the same as you. 15 And you must remember that you became a slave in the land of Egypt and Jehovah your God proceeded to bring you out from there with a strong hand and an outstretched arm. That is why Jehovah your God commanded you to carry on the sabbath day.

16 “‘Honor your father and your mother, just as Jehovah your God has commanded you; in order that your days may prove long and it may go well with you on the ground that Jehovah your God is giving you.

17 “‘You must not murder.

18 “‘Neither must you commit adultery.

19 “‘Neither must you steal.

20 “‘Neither must you testify to a falsehood against your fellowman.

21 “‘Neither must you desire your fellowman’s wife. Neither must you selfishly crave your fellowman’s house, his field or his slave man or his slave girl, his bull or his ass or anything that belongs to your fellowman.’

22 “These Words Jehovah spoke to all YOUR congregation in the mountain out of the middle of the fire, the cloud and the thick gloom, with a loud voice, and he added nothing; after which he wrote them upon two tablets of stone and gave me them.

23 “And it came about that as soon as YOU had heard the voice out of the middle of the darkness, while the mountain was burning with fire, YOU proceeded to come near to me, all the heads of YOUR tribes and YOUR older men. 24 Then YOU said, ‘Here Jehovah our God has shown us his glory and his greatness, and we have heard his voice out of the middle of the fire. This day we have seen that God may speak with man and he may actually keep living. 25 And now why should we die, for this great fire may consume us? If we are again hearing the voice of Jehovah our God any further, we are also certain to die. 26 For who is there of all flesh that has heard the voice of the living God speaking out of the middle of the fire as we did and yet goes on living? 27 You yourself go near and hear all that Jehovah our God will say; and you will be the one to speak to us all that Jehovah our God will speak to you, and we shall certainly listen and do.’

28 “So Jehovah heard the voice of YOUR words when YOU spoke to me, and Jehovah went on to say to me, ‘I have heard the voice of the words of this people, which they have spoken to you. They have done well in all they have spoken. 29 If only they would develop this heart of theirs to fear me and to keep all my commandments always, in order that it might go well with them and their sons to time indefinite! 30 Go say to them: “Return home to YOUR tents.” 31 And you stand here with me, and let me speak to you all the commandment and the regulations and the judicial decisions that you should teach to them and that they must do in the land that I am giving them to take possession of it.’ 32 And YOU people must take care to do just as Jehovah YOUR God has commanded YOU. YOU must not turn to the right or to the left. 33 In all the way that Jehovah YOUR God has commanded YOU, YOU should walk, in order that YOU may live and it may be well with YOU and YOU may indeed lengthen YOUR days in the land of which YOU will take possession.

Deuteronomy

6 “Now these are the commandment, the regulations and the judicial decisions that Jehovah YOUR God has commanded to teach YOU, so as to do them in the land to which YOU are passing over there to take possession of it; 2 in order that you may fear Jehovah your God so as to keep all his statutes and his commandments that I am commanding you, you and your son and your grandson, all the days of your life, and in order that your days may prove long. 3 And you must listen, O Israel, and take care to do them, that it may go well with you and that YOU may become very many, just as Jehovah the God of your forefathers has promised you, as respects the land flowing with milk and honey.

4 “Listen, O Israel: Jehovah our God is one Jehovah. 5 And you must love Jehovah your God with all your heart and all your soul and all your vital force. 6 And these words that I am commanding you today must prove to be on your heart; 7 and you must inculcate them in your son and speak of them when you sit in your house and when you walk on the road and when you lie down and when you get up. 8 And you must tie them as a sign upon your hand, and they must serve as a frontlet band between your eyes; 9 and you must write them upon the doorposts of your house and on your gates.

10 “And it must occur that when Jehovah your God will bring you into the land that he swore to your forefathers Abraham, Isaac and Jacob to give you, great and good-looking cities that you did not build, 11 and houses full of all good things and that you did not fill, and cisterns hewn out that you did not hew out, vineyards and olive trees that you did not plant, and you shall have eaten and become satisfied, 12 watch out for yourself that you may not forget Jehovah, who brought you out of the land of Egypt, out of the house of slaves. 13 Jehovah your God you should fear, and him you should serve, and by his name you should swear. 14 YOU must not walk after other gods, any gods of the peoples who are all around YOU, 15 (for Jehovah your God in your midst is a God exacting exclusive devotion,) for fear the anger of Jehovah your God may blaze against you and he must annihilate you from off the surface of the ground.

16 “YOU must not put Jehovah YOUR God to the test, the way YOU put him to the test at Mas′sah. 17 YOU should by all means keep the commandments of Jehovah YOUR God and his testimonies and his regulations that he has commanded you. 18 And you must do what is right and good in Jehovah’s eyes, in order that it may go well with you and you may indeed enter and take possession of the good land about which Jehovah has sworn to your forefathers, 19 by pushing away all your enemies from before you, just as Jehovah has promised.

20 “In case your son should ask you in a future day, saying, ‘What do the testimonies and the regulations and the judicial decisions mean that Jehovah our God has commanded YOU?’ 21 then you must say to your son, ‘We became slaves to Phar′aoh in Egypt, but Jehovah proceeded to bring us out of Egypt with a strong hand. 22 So Jehovah kept putting signs and miracles, great and calamitous, upon Egypt, upon Phar′aoh and upon all his household before our eyes. 23 And he brought us out from there in order that he might bring us here to give us the land about which he had sworn to our forefathers. 24 Hence Jehovah commanded us to carry out all these regulations, to fear Jehovah our God for our good always, that we might keep alive as at this day. 25 And it will mean righteousness for us, that we take care to do all this commandment before Jehovah our God, just as he has commanded us.’

Deuteronomy

15 “At the end of every seven years you should make a release. 2 And this is the manner of the release: there will be a releasing by every creditor of the debt that he may let his fellow incur. He should not press his fellow or his brother for payment, because a release to Jehovah must be called. 3 The foreigner you may press for payment; but whatever of yours may prove to be with your brother let your hand release. 4 However, no one should come to be poor among you, because Jehovah will without fail bless you in the land that Jehovah your God is giving you as an inheritance to take possession of it, 5 only if you will without fail listen to the voice of Jehovah your God so as to be careful to do all this commandment that I am commanding you today. 6 For Jehovah your God will indeed bless you just as he has promised you, and you will certainly lend on pledge to many nations, whereas you yourself will not borrow; and you must dominate over many nations, whereas over you they will not dominate.

7 “In case some one of your brothers becomes poor among you in one of your cities, in your land that Jehovah your God is giving you, you must not harden your heart or be closefisted toward your poor brother. 8 For you should generously open your hand to him and by all means lend him on pledge as much as he needs, which he is in want of. 9 Watch out for yourself for fear a base word should come to be in your heart, saying, ‘The seventh year, the year of the release, has come close,’ and your eye should indeed become ungenerous toward your poor brother, and you should give him nothing, and he has to call out to Jehovah against you, and it has become a sin on your part. 10 You should by all means give to him, and your heart should not be stingy in your giving to him, because on this account Jehovah your God will bless you in every deed of yours and in every undertaking of yours. 11 For someone poor will never cease to be in the midst of the land. That is why I am commanding you, saying, ‘You should generously open up your hand to your afflicted and poor brother in your land.’

12 “In case there should be sold to you your brother, a Hebrew or a Hebrewess, and he has served you six years, then in the seventh year you should send him out from you as one set free. 13 And in case you should send him out from you as one set free, you must not send him out empty-handed. 14 You should surely equip him with something from your flock and your threshing floor and your oil and winepress. Just as Jehovah your God has blessed you, you should give to him. 15 And you must remember that you became a slave in the land of Egypt and Jehovah your God proceeded to redeem you. That is why I am commanding you this thing today.

16 “And it must occur that in case he says to you, ‘I shall not go out from your company!’ because he does love you and your household, since it was well with him while with you, 17 you must also take an awl and put it through his ear and to the door, and he must become your slave to time indefinite. And to your slave girl you should also do this way. 18 It should not be something hard in your eyes when you send him out from your company as one set free; because for double the value of a hired laborer he served you six years, and Jehovah your God has blessed you in everything that you would do.

19 “Every male firstborn that will be born in your herd and in your flock you should sanctify to Jehovah your God. You must do no service with the firstborn of your bull, nor shear the firstborn of your flock. 20 Before Jehovah your God you should eat it year by year in the place that Jehovah will choose, you and your household. 21 And in case there should prove to be in it a defect, being lame or blind, any bad defect, you must not sacrifice it to Jehovah your God. 22 Inside your gates you should eat it, the unclean one and the clean one together, like the gazelle and like the stag. 23 Only its blood you must not eat. Upon the earth you should pour it out as water.

Deuteronomy

27 And Moses together with the older men of Israel went on to command the people, saying: “There should be an observing of every commandment that I am commanding YOU today. 2 And it must occur that in the day when YOU will cross the Jordan into the land that Jehovah your God is giving you, you must also set up for yourself great stones and whitewash them with lime. 3 And you must write upon them all the words of this law when you have crossed, in order that you may enter into the land that Jehovah your God is giving you, a land flowing with milk and honey, according to what Jehovah the God of your forefathers has spoken to you. 4 And it must occur that when YOU have crossed the Jordan, YOU should set up these stones, just as I am commanding YOU today, in Mount E′bal, and you must whitewash them with lime. 5 You must also build an altar there to Jehovah your God, an altar of stones. You must not wield an iron tool upon them. 6 With whole stones you should build the altar of Jehovah your God, and you must offer burnt offerings to Jehovah your God on it. 7 And you must sacrifice communion sacrifices and eat them there, and you must rejoice before Jehovah your God. 8 And you must write on the stones all the words of this law, making them quite clear.”

9 Then Moses and the priests, the Levites, spoke to all Israel, saying: “Keep silent and listen, O Israel. This day you have become the people of Jehovah your God. 10 And you must listen to the voice of Jehovah your God and carry out his commandments and his regulations, which I am commanding you today.”

11 And Moses went on to command the people on that day, saying: 12 “The following are the ones who will stand to bless the people on Mount Ger′i·zim when YOU have crossed the Jordan: Sim′e·on and Le′vi and Judah and Is′sa·char and Joseph and Benjamin. 13 And the following are the ones who will stand for the malediction on Mount E′bal: Reu′ben, Gad and Ash′er and Zeb′u·lun, Dan and Naph′ta·li. 14 And the Levites must answer and say with raised voice to every man of Israel:

15 “‘Cursed is the man who makes a carved image or a molten statue, a thing detestable to Jehovah, the manufacture of the hands of a wood-and-metal worker, and who has put it in a hiding place.’ (And all the people must answer and say, ‘Amen!’)

16 “‘Cursed is the one who treats his father or his mother with contempt.’ (And all the people must say, ‘Amen!’)

17 “‘Cursed is the one who moves back the boundary mark of his fellowman.’ (And all the people must say, ‘Amen!’)

18 “‘Cursed is the one who causes the blind to go astray in the way.’ (And all the people must say, ‘Amen!’)

19 “‘Cursed is the one who perverts the judgment of an alien resident, a fatherless boy and a widow.’ (And all the people must say, ‘Amen!’)

20 “‘Cursed is the one who lies down with his father’s wife, because he has uncovered the skirt of his father.’ (And all the people must say, ‘Amen!’)

21 “‘Cursed is the one who lies down with any beast.’ (And all the people must say, ‘Amen!’)

22 “‘Cursed is the one who lies down with his sister, the daughter of his father or the daughter of his mother.’ (And all the people must say, ‘Amen!’)

23 “‘Cursed is the one who lies down with his mother-in-law.’ (And all the people must say, ‘Amen!’)

24 “‘Cursed is the one who fatally strikes his fellowman from a hiding place.’ (And all the people must say, ‘Amen!’)

25 “‘Cursed is the one who accepts a bribe to strike a soul fatally, when it is innocent blood.’ (And all the people must say, ‘Amen!’)

26 “‘Cursed is the one who will not put the words of this law in force by doing them.’ (And all the people must say, ‘Amen!’)

Deuteronomy

33 Now this is the blessing with which Moses the man of the true God blessed the sons of Israel before his death. 2 And he proceeded to say:

“Jehovah—from Si′nai he came,

And he flashed forth from Se′ir upon them.

He beamed forth from the mountainous region of Pa′ran,

And with him were holy myriads,

At his right hand warriors belonging to them.

3 He was also cherishing his people;

All their holy ones are in your hand.

And they—they reclined at your feet;

They began to receive some of your words.

4 (Moses laid as a command upon us a law,

A possession of the congregation of Jacob.)

5 And he came to be king in Jesh′u·run,

When the heads of the people gathered themselves,

The entire number of the tribes of Israel.

6 Let Reu′ben live and not die off,

And let his men not become few.”

7 And this was Judah’s blessing, as he went on to say:

“Hear, O Jehovah, the voice of Judah,

And may you bring him to his people.

His arms have contended for what is his;

And may you prove yourself a helper from his adversaries.”

8 And as to Le′vi he said:

“Your Thum′mim and your U′rim belong to the man loyal to you,

Whom you put to the test at Mas′sah.

You began to contend with him by the waters of Mer′i·bah,

9 The man who said to his father and his mother, ‘I have not seen him.’

Even his brothers he did not acknowledge,

And his sons he did not know.

For they kept your saying,

And your covenant they continued to observe.

10 Let them instruct Jacob in your judicial decisions

And Israel in your law.

Let them render up incense before your nostrils

And a whole offering on your altar.

11 Bless, O Jehovah, his vital energy,

And may you show pleasure in the activity of his hands.

Wound severely in their hips those who rise up against him,

And those who intensely hate him, that they may not rise up.”

12 As to Benjamin he said:

“Let the beloved one of Jehovah reside in security by him,

While he shelters him the whole day,

And he must reside between his shoulders.”

13 And as to Joseph he said:

“May his land be continually blessed from Jehovah

With the choice things of heaven, with dew,

And with the watery deep lying down below,

14 And with the choice things, the products of the sun,

And with the choice things, the yield of the lunar months,

15 And with the choicest from the mountains of the east,

And with the choice things of the indefinitely lasting hills,

16 And with the choice things of the earth and its fullness,

And with the approval of the One residing in the thornbush.

May they come upon the head of Joseph

And upon the crown of the head of the one singled out from his brothers.

17 As the firstborn of a bull his splendor is,

And his horns are the horns of a wild bull.

With them he will push peoples

All together to the ends of the earth,

And they are the tens of thousands of E′phra·im,

And they are the thousands of Ma·nas′seh.”

18 And as to Zeb′u·lun he said:

“Rejoice, O Zeb′u·lun, in your going out,

And, Is′sa·char, in your tents.

19 Peoples to the mountain they will call.

There they will sacrifice the sacrifices of righteousness.

For they will suck the abounding wealth of the seas

And the hidden hoards of the sand.”

20 And as to Gad he said:

“Blessed is the one widening the borders of Gad.

As a lion he must reside,

And he must tear the arm, yes, the crown of the head.

21 And he will pick out the first part for himself,

For there the allotment of a statute-giver is reserved.

And the heads of the people will gather themselves together.

The righteousness of Jehovah will he certainly execute

And his judicial decisions with Israel.”

22 And as to Dan he said:

“Dan is a lion cub.

He will leap out from Ba′shan.”

23 And as to Naph′ta·li he said:

“Naph′ta·li is satisfied with the approval

And full of the blessing of Jehovah.

Do take possession of the west and south.”

24 And as to Ash′er he said:

“Blessed with sons is Ash′er.

Let him become one approved by his brothers,

And one dipping his foot in oil.

25 Iron and copper are your gate locks,

And in proportion to your days is your leisurely walk.

26 There is none like the true God of Jesh′u·run,

Who rides upon heaven in help of you

And upon cloudy skies in his eminence.

27 A hiding place is the God of ancient time,

And underneath are the indefinitely lasting arms.

And he will drive away from before you the enemy,

And he will say, ‘Annihilate them!’

28 And Israel will reside in security,

The fountain of Jacob by itself,

Upon a land of grain and new wine.

Yes, his heavens will let the dew drip down.

29 Happy you are, O Israel!

Who is there like you,

A people enjoying salvation in Jehovah,

The shield of your help,

And the One who is your eminent sword?

So your enemies will cringe before you,

And you—upon their high places you will tread.”

Joshua

3 Then Joshua got up early in the morning, and he and all the sons of Israel proceeded to pull away from Shit′tim and to come as far as the Jordan; and they went spending the night there before they would cross.

2 So it came about at the end of the three days that the officers proceeded to pass through the midst of the camp 3 and to command the people, saying: “As soon as YOU see the ark of the covenant of Jehovah YOUR God, and the priests, the Levites, carrying it, then YOU yourselves will pull away from YOUR place, and YOU must follow it, 4 —only let there prove to be a distance between YOU and it of about two thousand cubits by measure; do not get near to it—in order that YOU may know the way by which YOU should go, for YOU have not passed over on that way before.”

5 Joshua now said to the people: “Sanctify yourselves, for tomorrow Jehovah will do wonderful things in YOUR midst.”

6 Then Joshua said to the priests: “Take up the ark of the covenant and pass before the people.” So they took up the ark of the covenant and went before the people.

7 And Jehovah proceeded to say to Joshua: “This day I shall start to make you great in the eyes of all Israel, that they may know that just as I proved to be with Moses I shall prove to be with you. 8 And you—you should command the priests carrying the ark of the covenant, saying, ‘As soon as YOU have come as far as the edge of the waters of the Jordan, YOU should stand still in the Jordan.’”

9 And Joshua went on to say to the sons of Israel: “Approach here and listen to the words of Jehovah YOUR God.” 10 After that Joshua said: “By this YOU will know that a living God is in YOUR midst, and that he will without fail drive away from before YOU the Ca′naan·ites and the Hit′tites and the Hi′vites and the Per′iz·zites and the Gir′ga·shites and the Am′or·ites and the Jeb′u·sites. 11 Look! The ark of the covenant of the Lord of the whole earth is passing before YOU into the Jordan. 12 And now take for yourselves twelve men from the tribes of Israel, one man for each tribe. 13 And it must occur that at the instant that the soles of the feet of the priests carrying the ark of Jehovah, the Lord of the whole earth, rest in the waters of the Jordan, the waters of the Jordan will be cut off, the waters descending from above, and they will stand still as one dam.”

14 And it came about that when the people pulled away from their tents just before passing over the Jordan, with the priests carrying the ark of the covenant before the people, 15 and at the instant that the carriers of the Ark came as far as the Jordan and the feet of the priests carrying the Ark were dipped in the edge of the waters (now the Jordan overflows all its banks all the days of harvest), 16 then the waters descending from above began to stand still. They rose up as one dam very far away at Adam, the city at the side of Zar′e·than, while those descending toward the sea of the Ar′a·bah, the Salt Sea, were exhausted. They were cut off, and the people passed over in front of Jer′i·cho. 17 Meanwhile the priests carrying the ark of Jehovah’s covenant kept standing immovable on dry ground in the middle of the Jordan as all Israel were passing over on dry ground, until the whole nation had completed passing over the Jordan.

Joshua

4 And it came about that as soon as the whole nation had completed passing over the Jordan, Jehovah proceeded to say to Joshua: 2 “Take for yourselves twelve men from the people, one man from each tribe, 3 and command them, saying, ‘Take up for yourselves from the very middle of the Jordan, from the place where the priests’ feet stood motionless, twelve stones, and YOU must carry them over with YOU and deposit them in the lodging place in which YOU will lodge tonight.’”

4 So Joshua called twelve men whom he had appointed from the sons of Israel, one man from each tribe; 5 and Joshua went on to say to them: “Pass ahead of the ark of Jehovah YOUR God to the middle of the Jordan, and lift up for yourselves each one a stone upon his shoulder, according to the number of the tribes of the sons of Israel, 6 in order that this may serve as a sign in YOUR midst. In case YOUR sons should ask in time to come, saying, ‘Why do YOU have these stones?’ 7 YOU must also say to them, ‘Because the waters of the Jordan were cut off from before the ark of Jehovah’s covenant. When it passed through the Jordan the waters of the Jordan were cut off, and these stones must serve as a memorial to the sons of Israel to time indefinite.’”

8 Accordingly the sons of Israel did so, just as Joshua had commanded, and they took up twelve stones from the middle of the Jordan, just as Jehovah had stated to Joshua, to correspond with the number of the tribes of the sons of Israel; and they went taking them over with them to the lodging place and depositing them there.

9 There were also twelve stones that Joshua set up in the middle of the Jordan on the standing place of the feet of the priests carrying the ark of the covenant, and they continue there until this day.

10 And the priests carrying the Ark were standing in the middle of the Jordan until the whole matter had been completed that Jehovah had commanded Joshua to speak to the people, according to all that Moses had commanded Joshua. All the while the people hurried up and passed over. 11 And it came about that as soon as all the people had completed passing over, then the ark of Jehovah passed over, and the priests, before the people. 12 And the sons of Reu′ben and the sons of Gad and the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh proceeded to pass over in battle formation in the sight of the sons of Israel, just as Moses had stated to them. 13 About forty thousand equipped for the army passed over before Jehovah for the war onto the desert plains of Jer′i·cho.

14 On that day Jehovah made Joshua great in the eyes of all Israel, and they began to fear him just as they had feared Moses all the days of his life.

15 Then Jehovah said to Joshua: 16 “Command the priests carrying the ark of the testimony that they go up out of the Jordan.” 17 So Joshua commanded the priests, saying: “Go up out of the Jordan.” 18 And it came about that when the priests carrying the ark of the covenant of Jehovah came up out of the middle of the Jordan and the soles of the feet of the priests were drawn out onto the dry ground, then the waters of the Jordan began returning to their place and went overflowing all its banks as formerly.

19 And the people came up out of the Jordan on the tenth of the first month and took up camping at Gil′gal on the eastern border of Jer′i·cho.

20 As for the twelve stones that they had taken out of the Jordan, Joshua set these up at Gil′gal. 21 And he went on to say to the sons of Israel: “When YOUR sons ask their fathers in time to come, saying, ‘What do these stones mean?’ 22 YOU must then let YOUR sons know, saying, ‘On the dry land it was that Israel passed over this Jordan, 23 when Jehovah YOUR God dried up the waters of the Jordan from before them until they had passed over, just as Jehovah YOUR God had done to the Red Sea when he dried it up from before us until we had passed over; 24 in order that all the peoples of the earth may know Jehovah’s hand, that it is strong; in order that YOU may indeed fear Jehovah YOUR God always.’”

Joshua

7 And the sons of Israel went committing an act of unfaithfulness respecting the thing devoted to destruction in that A′chan the son of Car′mi, the son of Zab′di, the son of Ze′rah, of the tribe of Judah, took some of the thing devoted to destruction. At this Jehovah’s anger grew hot against the sons of Israel.

2 Then Joshua sent men out from Jer′i·cho to A′i, which is close by Beth-a′ven, to the east of Beth′el, and said to them: “Go up and spy on the land.” Accordingly the men went up and spied on A′i. 3 After that they returned to Joshua and said to him: “Let not all the people go up. Let about two thousand men or about three thousand men go up and strike A′i. Do not weary all the people with going there, for they are few.”

4 So about three thousand men of the people went up there, but they took to flight before the men of A′i. 5 And the men of A′i got to strike down about thirty-six men of them, and they went pursuing them from before the gate as far as Sheb′a·rim and continued striking them down on the descent. Consequently the heart of the people began to melt and became as water.

6 At this Joshua ripped his mantles and fell upon his face to the earth before the ark of Jehovah until the evening, he and the older men of Israel, and they kept putting dust upon their heads. 7 And Joshua went on to say: “Alas, Sovereign Lord Jehovah, why did you bring this people all the way across the Jordan, just to give us into the hand of the Am′or·ites for them to destroy us? And if only we had taken it upon ourselves and continued dwelling on the other side of the Jordan! 8 Excuse me, O Jehovah, but what can I say after Israel has turned his back before his enemies? 9 And the Ca′naan·ites and all the inhabitants of the land will hear of it, and they will certainly surround us and cut our name off from the earth; and what will you do for your great name?”

10 In turn Jehovah said to Joshua: “Get up, you! Why is it that you are falling upon your face? 11 Israel has sinned, and they have also overstepped my covenant that I laid as a command upon them; and they have also taken some of the thing devoted to destruction and have also stolen and also kept it secret and have also put it among their own articles. 12 And the sons of Israel will not be able to rise up against their enemies. The back is what they will turn before their enemies, because they have become a thing devoted to destruction. I shall not prove to be with YOU again unless YOU annihilate the thing devoted to destruction out of YOUR midst. 13 Get up! Sanctify the people, and you must say, ‘Sanctify yourselves tomorrow, for this is what Jehovah the God of Israel has said: “A thing devoted to destruction is in your midst, O Israel. You will not be able to rise up against your enemies until YOU people have removed the thing devoted to destruction from YOUR midst. 14 And YOU must present yourselves in the morning, tribe by tribe, and it must occur that the tribe that Jehovah will pick will come near, family by family, and the family that Jehovah will pick will come near, household by household, and the household that Jehovah will pick will come near, able-bodied man by able-bodied man. 15 And it must occur that the one picked with the thing devoted to destruction will be burned with fire, he and all that belongs to him, because he has overstepped the covenant of Jehovah and because he has committed a disgraceful folly in Israel.”’”

16 Then Joshua rose early in the morning and had Israel come near, tribe by tribe of it, and the tribe of Judah got to be picked. 17 Next he had the families of Judah come near and picked the family of the Ze′rah·ites, after which he had the family of the Ze′rah·ites come near, able-bodied man by able-bodied man, and Zab′di got to be picked. 18 Finally he had his household come near, able-bodied man by able-bodied man, and A′chan the son of Car′mi, the son of Zab′di, the son of Ze′rah, of the tribe of Judah, got to be picked. 19 Then Joshua said to A′chan: “My son, render, please, glory to Jehovah the God of Israel and make confession to him, and tell me, please, What have you done? Do not hide it from me.”

20 At this A′chan answered Joshua and said: “For a fact I—I have sinned against Jehovah the God of Israel, and this way and that way I have done. 21 When I got to see among the spoil an official garment from Shi′nar, a good-looking one, and two hundred shekels of silver and one gold bar, fifty shekels being its weight, then I wanted them, and I took them; and, look! they are hidden in the earth in the midst of my tent with the money underneath it.”

22 At once Joshua sent messengers, and they went running to the tent, and, look! it was hidden in his tent with the money underneath it. 23 So they took them from the midst of the tent and brought them to Joshua and all the sons of Israel and poured them out before Jehovah. 24 Joshua, and all Israel with him, now took A′chan the son of Ze′rah and the silver and the official garment and the bar of gold and his sons and his daughters and his bull and his ass and his flock and his tent and everything that was his and they brought them up to the low plain of A′chor. 25 Then Joshua said: “Why have you brought ostracism upon us? Jehovah will bring ostracism upon you on this day.” With that all Israel went pelting him with stones, after which they burned them with fire. Thus they stoned them with stones. 26 And they proceeded to raise up over him a big pile of stones, down to this day. At this Jehovah turned away from his hot anger. That is why the name of that place has been called Low Plain of A′chor, down to this day.

Joshua

8 Then Jehovah said to Joshua: “Do not be afraid or be terrified. Take with you all the people of war and get up, go up to A′i. See, I have given into your hand the king of A′i and his people and his city and his land. 2 And you must do to A′i and to its king just as you did to Jer′i·cho and its king. Only YOU people may plunder its spoil and its domestic animals for yourselves. Set an ambush of yours against the city at its rear.”

3 Accordingly Joshua and all the people of war rose to go up to A′i, and Joshua proceeded to choose thirty thousand men, valiant mighty ones, and to send them off by night. 4 And he went on to command them, saying: “See, YOU are lying in ambush against the city to the rear of the city. Do not go very far away from the city, and YOU must all of YOU hold yourselves in readiness. 5 As for me and all the people who are with me, we shall go close to the city. And it must occur that, in case they should come out to meet us just as at the first, we must then flee before them. 6 And they must come out after us until we have drawn them away from the city, for they will say, ‘They are fleeing before us just as at the first.’ And we must flee before them. 7 Then YOU—YOU will rise up from the ambush, and YOU must take possession of the city; and Jehovah YOUR God will certainly give it into YOUR hands. 8 And it must occur that as soon as YOU have seized the city, YOU should set the city on fire. According to Jehovah’s word YOU should do. See, I have commanded YOU.”

9 After that Joshua sent them out and they marched to the place of ambush and took up quarters between Beth′el and A′i to the west of A′i, while Joshua kept lodging on that night in the midst of the people.

10 Then Joshua rose up early in the morning and reviewed the people and went up, he and the older men of Israel, before the people to A′i. 11 And all the people of war who were with him went up, that they might approach and get in front of the city, and they proceeded to camp to the north of A′i, with the valley between them and A′i. 12 In the meantime he took about five thousand men and set them as an ambush between Beth′el and A′i, to the west of the city. 13 So the people set the main camp that was to the north of the city and the extreme rear of it that was to the west of the city, and Joshua proceeded to go during that night into the middle of the low plain.

14 And it came about that, as soon as the king of A′i saw it, then the men of the city got in a hurry and rose up early and went out to meet Israel in battle, he and all his people, at the appointed time, before the desert plain. As for him, he did not know that there was an ambush against him to the rear of the city. 15 When Joshua and all Israel suffered a blow before them, then they took to flight by the way of the wilderness. 16 At that all the people who were in the city were called out to chase after them, and they went chasing after Joshua and got to be drawn away from the city. 17 And there was not a man remaining in A′i and Beth′el that did not go out after Israel, so that they left the city wide open and went chasing after Israel.

18 Jehovah now said to Joshua: “Stretch out the javelin that is in your hand toward A′i, for into your hand I shall give it.” Accordingly Joshua stretched out the javelin that was in his hand toward the city. 19 And the ambush rose up quickly from its place, and they began to run at the instant that he stretched out his hand, and they proceeded to enter the city and capture it. Then they hurried and set the city on fire.

20 And the men of A′i began to turn back and look, and there the smoke of the city ascended to the heavens, and there proved to be no ability in them to flee this way or that. And the people that were fleeing to the wilderness turned upon the pursuers. 21 And Joshua and all Israel saw that the ambush had captured the city, and that the smoke of the city ascended, and so they turned around and went striking the men of A′i down. 22 And these others came out of the city to meet them, so that they got to be in between Israel, these on this side and those on that, and they went striking them down until there did not remain of them either a survivor or an escapee. 23 And the king of A′i they caught alive and proceeded to bring him near to Joshua.

24 And it came about that while Israel was finishing the killing of all the inhabitants of A′i in the field, in the wilderness in which they had pursued them, they kept falling, all of them, by the edge of the sword until they came to their end. After that all Israel returned to A′i and struck it with the edge of the sword. 25 And all those who fell on that day, from man to woman, amounted to twelve thousand, all the people of A′i. 26 And Joshua did not draw back his hand with which he stretched out the javelin until he had devoted all the inhabitants of A′i to destruction. 27 Only the domestic animals and the spoil of that city Israel plundered for themselves, according to Jehovah’s word that he had laid in command upon Joshua.

28 Then Joshua burned A′i and reduced it to an indefinitely lasting mound, as a desolation down to this day. 29 And he hanged the king of A′i upon a stake until the evening time; and as the sun was about to set Joshua gave the command, and then they took his dead body down from the stake and pitched it at the entrance of the gate of the city and raised up a great pile of stones over him, down to this day.

30 It was then that Joshua proceeded to build an altar to Jehovah the God of Israel, in Mount E′bal, 31 just as Moses the servant of Jehovah had commanded the sons of Israel, as it is written in the book of the law of Moses: “An altar of whole stones, upon which no iron tool has been wielded”; and they went offering up burnt offerings upon it to Jehovah and sacrificing communion sacrifices.

32 Then he wrote there upon the stones a copy of the law of Moses that he had written before the sons of Israel. 33 And all Israel and their older men and the officers and their judges were standing on this side and on that side of the Ark in front of the priests, the Levites, carrying the ark of the covenant of Jehovah, the alien resident as well as the native, one half of them in front of Mount Ger′i·zim and the other half of them in front of Mount E′bal, (just as Moses the servant of Jehovah had commanded,) to bless the people of Israel first of all. 34 And after this he read aloud all the words of the law, the blessing and the malediction, according to all that is written in the book of the law. 35 There proved to be not a word of all that Moses had commanded that Joshua did not read aloud in front of all the congregation of Israel, together with the women and the little ones and the alien residents who walked in their midst.

Joshua

9 And it came about that as soon as all the kings who were on the side of the Jordan in the mountainous region and in the She·phe′lah and along the whole coast of the Great Sea and in front of Leb′a·non, the Hit′tites and the Am′or·ites, the Ca′naan·ites, the Per′iz·zites, the Hi′vites and the Jeb′u·sites, heard of it, 2 they began to assemble themselves all together to make war against Joshua and Israel unanimously.

3 And the inhabitants of Gib′e·on heard what Joshua had done to Jer′i·cho and A′i. 4 So they, even of their own accord, acted with shrewdness and went and stocked themselves with provisions and took worn-out sacks for their asses, and wine skin-bottles worn out and burst and tied up, 5 and worn-out and patched sandals on their feet, and worn-out garments upon themselves, and all the bread of their provisions proved to be dry and crumby. 6 Then they went to Joshua at the camp at Gil′gal and said to him and the men of Israel: “It is from a distant land that we have come. And now CONCLUDE a covenant with us.” 7 At this the men of Israel said to the Hi′vites: “Perhaps it is in our vicinity that you are dwelling. So how could we conclude a covenant with you?” 8 In turn they said to Joshua: “We are your servants.”

Then Joshua said to them: “Who are YOU, and where do YOU come from?” 9 At this they said to him: “It is from a very distant land that your servants have come in regard to the name of Jehovah your God, because we have heard of his fame and of all that he did in Egypt, 10 and of all that he did to the two kings of the Am′or·ites who were on the other side of the Jordan, namely, Si′hon the king of Hesh′bon and Og the king of Ba′shan, who was in Ash′ta·roth. 11 Hence our older men and all the inhabitants of our land said this to us, ‘Take provisions in YOUR hands for the journey and go to meet them, and YOU must say to them: “We are YOUR servants. And now conclude a covenant with us.”’ 12 This bread of ours, it was hot when we took it as our provisions out of our houses on the day of our going out to come here to YOU, and now, look! it is dry and has become crumby. 13 And these are the wine skin-bottles that we filled new, and, look! they have burst, and these garments and sandals of ours, they have worn out because of the great length of the journey.”

14 Upon that the men took some of their provisions, and at the mouth of Jehovah they did not inquire. 15 And Joshua went making peace with them and concluding a covenant with them to let them live, and so the chieftains of the assembly swore to them.

16 And it came about that at the end of three days, after they had concluded a covenant with them, they got to hear that they were near to them and it was in their vicinity they were dwelling. 17 Then the sons of Israel pulled out and came to their cities on the third day, and their cities were Gib′e·on and Che·phi′rah and Be·er′oth and Kir′i·ath-je′a·rim. 18 And the sons of Israel did not strike them, because the chieftains of the assembly had sworn to them by Jehovah the God of Israel. And all the assembly began to murmur against the chieftains. 19 At this all the chieftains said to all the assembly: “We, for our part, have sworn to them by Jehovah the God of Israel, and now we are not allowed to hurt them. 20 This is what we shall do to them while letting them live, that no indignation may come upon us over the oath that we have sworn to them.” 21 So the chieftains said to them: “Let them live and let them become gatherers of wood and drawers of water for all the assembly, just as the chieftains have promised them.”

22 Joshua now called them and spoke to them, saying: “Why did YOU trick us, saying, ‘We are very far away from YOU,’ whereas YOU are dwelling in our very midst? 23 And now YOU are cursed people, and a slave’s position and being gatherers of wood and drawers of water for the house of my God will never be cut off from YOU.” 24 Then they answered Joshua and said: “It was because your servants were plainly told that Jehovah your God had commanded Moses his servant to give YOU all the land and to annihilate all the inhabitants of the land from before YOU, and we became very much afraid for our souls because of YOU. So we did this thing. 25 And now here we are, in your hand. Just as it is good and right in your eyes to do to us, do.” 26 And he proceeded to do so to them and to deliver them from the hand of the sons of Israel, and they did not kill them. 27 Accordingly Joshua constituted them on that day gatherers of wood and drawers of water for the assembly and for Jehovah’s altar, down to this day, at the place that he should choose.

Joshua

11 And it came about that as soon as Ja′bin the king of Ha′zor heard of it, he went sending to Jo′bab the king of Ma′don and to the king of Shim′ron and the king of Ach′shaph, 2 and to the kings that were to the north in the mountainous region and in the desert plains south of Chin′ne·reth and in the She·phe′lah and on the mountain ridges of Dor to the west, 3 the Ca′naan·ites to the east and the west, and the Am′or·ites and the Hit′tites and the Per′iz·zites and the Jeb′u·sites in the mountainous region and the Hi′vites at the base of Her′mon in the land of Miz′pah. 4 So they went out, they and all their camps with them, a people as numerous as the grains of sand that are on the seashore for multitude, and very many horses and war chariots. 5 Then all these kings met together by appointment and came and encamped together at the waters of Mer′om to fight against Israel.

6 At this Jehovah said to Joshua: “Do not be afraid because of them, for tomorrow about this time I am abandoning all of them slain to Israel. Their horses you will hamstring, and their chariots you will burn in the fire.” 7 And Joshua and all the people of war with him proceeded to come against them along the waters of Mer′om by surprise and to fall upon them. 8 Then Jehovah gave them into Israel’s hand, and they went striking them and pursuing them as far as populous Si′don and Mis′re·photh-ma′im and the valley plain of Miz′peh to the east; and they kept striking them until they had not let a survivor of theirs remain. 9 After that Joshua did to them just as Jehovah had said to him: their horses he hamstrung, and their chariots he burned in the fire.

10 More than that, Joshua turned about at that time and captured Ha′zor; and its king he struck down with the sword, because Ha′zor was before that the head of all these kingdoms. 11 And they went striking every soul that was in it with the edge of the sword, devoting them to destruction. No breathing thing at all was left over, and he burned Ha′zor in the fire. 12 And all the cities of these kings and all their kings Joshua captured and went striking them with the edge of the sword. He devoted them to destruction, just as Moses the servant of Jehovah had commanded. 13 It was only all the cities standing on their own mounds that Israel did not burn, except that Joshua did burn Ha′zor by itself. 14 And all the spoil of these cities and the domestic animals the sons of Israel plundered for themselves. It was only all humankind that they struck with the edge of the sword until they had annihilated them. They did not let anyone that breathed remain. 15 Just as Jehovah had commanded Moses his servant, so Moses commanded Joshua, and so Joshua did. He did not remove a word from all that Jehovah had commanded Moses.

16 And Joshua proceeded to take all this land, the mountainous region and all the Neg′eb and all the land of Go′shen and the She·phe′lah and the Ar′a·bah and the mountainous region of Israel and its She·phe′lah, 17 from Mount Ha′lak, which goes up to Se′ir, and as far as Ba′al-gad in the valley plain of Leb′a·non at the base of Mount Her′mon, and he captured all their kings and went striking them and putting them to death. 18 Many days it was that Joshua waged war with all these kings. 19 There proved to be no city that made peace with the sons of Israel but the Hi′vites inhabiting Gib′e·on. All the others they took by war. 20 For it proved to be Jehovah’s course to let their hearts become stubborn so as to declare war against Israel, in order that he might devote them to destruction, that they might come to have no favorable consideration, but in order that he might annihilate them, just as Jehovah had commanded Moses.

21 Furthermore, at that particular time Joshua went and cut off the An′a·kim from the mountainous region, from He′bron, from De′bir, from A′nab and from all the mountainous region of Judah and from all the mountainous region of Israel. Along with their cities Joshua devoted them to destruction. 22 No An′a·kim were left in the land of the sons of Israel. It was only in Ga′za, in Gath and in Ash′dod that they remained. 23 So Joshua took all the land, according to all that Jehovah had promised Moses, and Joshua then gave it as an inheritance to Israel by their shares, according to their tribes. And the land had no disturbance from war.

Joshua

14 Now this is what the sons of Israel took as a hereditary possession in the land of Ca′naan, which El·e·a′zar the priest and Joshua the son of Nun and the heads of the fathers of the tribes of the sons of Israel caused them to inherit. 2 Their inheritance was by lot, just as Jehovah had commanded by means of Moses for the nine tribes and the half tribe. 3 For Moses had given the inheritance of the two other tribes and the other half tribe on the other side of the Jordan; and to the Levites he did not give an inheritance in their midst. 4 For the sons of Joseph had become two tribes, Ma·nas′seh and E′phra·im; and they had not given a share in the land to the Levites, except cities to dwell in and their pasture grounds for their livestock and their property. 5 Just as Jehovah had commanded Moses, so the sons of Israel did; and they proceeded to apportion the land.

6 Then the sons of Judah approached Joshua in Gil′gal, and Ca′leb the son of Je·phun′neh the Ken′iz·zite said to him: “You yourself well know the word that Jehovah spoke to Moses the man of the true God with regard to me and with regard to you at Ka′desh-bar′ne·a. 7 Forty years old I was when Moses the servant of Jehovah sent me out of Ka′desh-bar′ne·a to spy out the land, and I came bringing him back word just as it was in my heart. 8 And my brothers who went up with me caused the heart of the people to melt; but as for me, I followed Jehovah my God fully. 9 Consequently Moses swore on that day, saying, ‘The land upon which your foot has trod will become yours and your sons’ as an inheritance to time indefinite, because you have followed Jehovah my God fully.’ 10 And now here Jehovah has preserved me alive, just as he promised, these forty-five years since Jehovah made this promise to Moses when Israel walked in the wilderness, and now here I am today eighty-five years old. 11 Yet I am today as strong as on the day of Moses’ sending me out. As my power was then, so my power is now for the war, both to go out and to come in. 12 And now do give me this mountainous region that Jehovah promised on that day, for you yourself heard on that day that there were An′a·kim there and great fortified cities. Likely Jehovah will be with me, and I shall certainly dispossess them, just as Jehovah promised.”

13 At that Joshua blessed him and gave He′bron to Ca′leb the son of Je·phun′neh as an inheritance. 14 That is why He′bron has come to belong to Ca′leb the son of Je·phun′neh the Ken′iz·zite as an inheritance down to this day, for the reason that he followed Jehovah the God of Israel fully. 15 The name of He′bron before that was Kir′i·ath-ar′ba (said Ar′ba was the great man among the An′a·kim). And the land had no disturbance from war.

Joshua

15 And the lot of the tribe of the sons of Judah by their families came to be to the boundary of E′dom, the wilderness of Zin, to the Neg′eb at its southern end. 2 And their southern boundary came to be from the extremity of the Salt Sea, from the bay that faces southward. 3 And it went out southward to the ascent of A·krab′bim and passed over to Zin and went up from the south to Ka′desh-bar′ne·a and passed over to Hez′ron and went up to Ad′dar and went around to Kar′ka. 4 And it passed on to Az′mon and went out to the torrent valley of Egypt; and the boundary’s termination proved to be at the sea. This came to be their southern boundary.

5 And the eastern boundary was the Salt Sea up to the end of the Jordan, and the boundary at the northern corner was at the bay of the sea, at the end of the Jordan. 6 And the boundary went up to Beth-hog′lah and passed over at the north of Beth-ar′a·bah, and the boundary went up to the stone of Bo′han the son of Reu′ben. 7 And the boundary went up to De′bir at the low plain of A′chor and turning northward to Gil′gal, which is in front of the ascent of A·dum′mim, which is south of the torrent valley; and the boundary passed over to the waters of En-she′mesh, and its termination proved to be En-ro′gel. 8 And the boundary went up to the valley of the son of Hin′nom to the slope of the Jeb′u·site at the south, that is to say, Jerusalem; and the boundary went up to the top of the mountain that faces the valley of Hin′nom to the west, which is at the extremity of the low plain of Reph′a·im to the north. 9 And the boundary was marked out from the top of the mountain to the spring of the waters of Neph·to′ah, and went out to the cities of Mount E′phron; and the boundary was marked out to Ba′al·ah, that is to say, Kir′i·ath-je′a·rim. 10 And the boundary went around from Ba′al·ah westward to Mount Se′ir and passed over to the slope of Mount Je′a·rim at the north, that is to say, Ches′a·lon; and it went down to Beth-she′mesh and passed over to Tim′nah. 11 And the boundary went out to the slope of Ek′ron to the north, and the boundary was marked out to Shik′ke·ron and passed over to Mount Ba′al·ah and went out to Jab′ne·el; and the boundary’s termination proved to be at the sea.

12 And the western boundary was at the Great Sea and its shoreland. This was the boundary all around, of the sons of Judah by their families.

13 And to Ca′leb the son of Je·phun′neh he gave a share in the midst of the sons of Judah at the order of Jehovah to Joshua, namely, Kir′i·ath-ar′ba (said Ar′ba being the father of A′nak), that is to say, He′bron. 14 So Ca′leb drove away from there the three sons of A′nak, namely, She′shai and A·hi′man and Tal′mai, those born of A′nak. 15 Then he went up from there to the inhabitants of De′bir. (Now the name of De′bir before that was Kir′i·ath-se′pher.) 16 And Ca′leb proceeded to say: “Whoever strikes Kir′i·ath-se′pher and does capture it, I shall certainly give him Ach′sah my daughter as a wife.” 17 At that Oth′ni·el the son of Ke′naz, Ca′leb’s brother, captured it. Accordingly he gave him Ach′sah his daughter as a wife. 18 And it came about that when she was going home, she kept inciting him to ask a field from her father. Then she clapped her hands while upon the ass. At this Ca′leb said to her: “What do you want?” 19 So she said: “Do give me a blessing, for it is a piece of land to the south you have given me, and you must give me Gul′loth-ma′im.” Accordingly he gave her Upper Gul′loth and Lower Gul′loth.

20 This was the inheritance of the tribe of the sons of Judah by their families.

21 And the cities at the extremity of the tribe of the sons of Judah toward the boundary of E′dom in the south came to be Kab′ze·el and E′der and Ja′gur, 22 and Ki′nah and Di·mo′nah and A·da′dah, 23 and Ke′desh and Ha′zor and Ith′nan, 24 Ziph and Te′lem and Be·a′loth, 25 and Ha′zor-ha·dat′tah and Ke′ri·oth-hez′ron, that is to say, Ha′zor, 26 A′mam and She′ma and Mo·la′dah, 27 and Ha′zar-gad′dah and Hesh′mon and Beth-pel′et, 28 and Ha′zar-shu′al and Be′er-she′ba and Biz·i·o·thi′ah, 29 Ba′al·ah and I′im and E′zem, 30 and El·to′lad and Che′sil and Hor′mah, 31 and Zik′lag and Mad·man′nah and San·san′nah, 32 and Le·ba′oth and Shil′him and A′in and Rim′mon; all the cities being twenty-nine, together with their settlements.

33 In the She·phe′lah there were Esh′ta·ol and Zo′rah and Ash′nah, 34 and Za·no′ah and En-gan′nim, Tap′pu·ah and E′nam, 35 Jar′muth and A·dul′lam, So′coh and A·ze′kah, 36 and Sha′a·ra′im and Ad·i·tha′im and Ge·de′rah and Ged·e·ro·tha′im; fourteen cities and their settlements.

37 Ze′nan and Ha·dash′ah and Mig′dal-gad, 38 and Di′le·an and Miz′peh and Jok′the·el, 39 La′chish and Boz′kath and Eg′lon, 40 and Cab′bon and Lah′mam and Chit′lish, 41 and Ge·de′roth, Beth-da′gon and Na′a·mah and Mak·ke′dah; sixteen cities and their settlements.

42 Lib′nah and E′ther and A′shan, 43 and Iph′tah and Ash′nah and Ne′zib, 44 and Kei′lah and Ach′zib and Ma·re′shah; nine cities and their settlements.

45 Ek′ron and its dependent towns and its settlements. 46 From Ek′ron westward all that is alongside Ash′dod and their settlements.

47 Ash′dod, its dependent towns and its settlements; Ga′za, its dependent towns and its settlements, down to the torrent valley of Egypt, and the Great Sea and the adjacent region.

48 And in the mountainous region Sha′mir and Jat′tir and So′coh, 49 and Dan′nah and Kir′i·ath-san′nah, that is to say, De′bir, 50 and A′nab and Esh′te·moh and A′nim, 51 and Go′shen and Ho′lon and Gi′loh; eleven cities and their settlements.

52 Arab and Du′mah and E′shan, 53 and Ja′nim and Beth-tap′pu·ah and A·phe′kah, 54 and Hum′tah and Kir′i·ath-ar′ba, that is to say, He′bron, and Zi′or; nine cities and their settlements.

55 Ma′on, Car′mel and Ziph and Jut′tah, 56 and Jez′re·el and Jok′de·am and Za·no′ah, 57 Ka′in, Gib′e·ah and Tim′nah; ten cities and their settlements.

58 Hal′hul, Beth-zur and Ge′dor, 59 and Ma′a·rath and Beth-a′noth and El′te·kon; six cities and their settlements.

60 Kir′i·ath-ba′al, that is to say, Kir′i·ath-je′a·rim, and Rab′bah; two cities and their settlements.

61 In the wilderness Beth-ar′a·bah, Mid′din and Se·ca′cah, 62 and Nib′shan and the City of Salt and En-ge′di; six cities and their settlements.

63 As for the Jeb′u·sites who were dwelling in Jerusalem, the sons of Judah were not able to drive them away; and the Jeb′u·sites continue dwelling with the sons of Judah in Jerusalem down to this day.

Joshua

18 Then all the assembly of the sons of Israel were congregated at Shi′loh, and they proceeded to locate the tent of meeting there, as the land was now subdued before them. 2 But there were still left among the sons of Israel those whose inheritance they had not apportioned out, namely, seven tribes. 3 So Joshua said to the sons of Israel: “How long are YOU going to be delinquent about going in to take possession of the land that Jehovah the God of YOUR forefathers has given YOU? 4 Furnish for yourselves three men of each tribe and let me send them out, that they may get up and walk about in the land and map it out in accord with their inheritance, and let them come to me. 5 And they must apportion it among themselves into seven shares. Judah will keep standing on his territory to the south, and the house of Joseph will keep standing on their territory to the north. 6 As for YOU people, YOU will map out the land into seven shares, and YOU must bring them here to me, and I must cast lots here for YOU before Jehovah our God. 7 For the Levites have no share in among YOU, because the priesthood of Jehovah is their inheritance; and Gad and Reu′ben and the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh have taken their inheritance on the side of the Jordan toward the east, which Moses the servant of Jehovah has given them.”

8 So the men got up that they might go, and Joshua proceeded to command those who were going to map out the land, saying: “Go and walk about in the land and map it out and return to me, and here is where I shall draw lots for YOU before Jehovah in Shi′loh.” 9 With that the men went and passed through the land and mapped it out by cities in seven shares, in a book. After that they came to Joshua at the camp in Shi′loh, 10 and Joshua went drawing lots for them in Shi′loh before Jehovah. Thus Joshua there apportioned the land to the sons of Israel in their shares.

11 Then the lot came up of the tribe of the sons of Benjamin by their families, and the territory of their lot went out between the sons of Judah and the sons of Joseph. 12 And their boundary came to be at the northern corner from the Jordan, and the boundary went up to the slope of Jer′i·cho on the north and went up on the mountain westward, and its termination proved to be at the wilderness of Beth-a′ven. 13 And the boundary passed over from there to Luz, at the southern slope of Luz, that is to say, Beth′el; and the boundary went down to At′a·roth-ad′dar upon the mountain that is on the south of Lower Beth-ho′ron. 14 And the boundary was marked out and went around at the western side to the south from the mountain that faces Beth-ho′ron to the south; and its termination proved to be at Kir′i·ath-ba′al, that is to say, Kir′i·ath-je′a·rim, a city of the sons of Judah. This is the western side.

15 And the side to the south was from the extremity of Kir′i·ath-je′a·rim, and the boundary went out westward and went out to the spring of the waters of Neph·to′ah. 16 And the boundary went down to the extremity of the mountain that faces the valley of the son of Hin′nom, which is in the low plain of Reph′a·im to the north, and it went down to the valley of Hin′nom, to the slope of the Jeb′u·site on the south, and went down to En-ro′gel. 17 And it was marked out northward and went out to En-she′mesh and went out to Gel·i′loth, which is in front of the ascent of A·dum′mim; and it went down to the stone of Bo′han the son of Reu′ben. 18 And it passed over to the northern slope in front of the Ar′a·bah and went down to the Ar′a·bah. 19 And the boundary passed over to the northern slope of Beth-hog′lah, and the termination of it (the border) proved to be at the northern bay of the Salt Sea at the southern end of the Jordan. This was the southern boundary. 20 And the Jordan served as its boundary on the eastern side. This was the inheritance of the sons of Benjamin by their families, by its boundaries all around.

21 And the cities of the tribe of the sons of Benjamin by their families proved to be Jer′i·cho and Beth-hog′lah and E′mek-ke′ziz, 22 and Beth-ar′a·bah and Zem·a·ra′im and Beth′el, 23 and Av′vim and Pa′rah and Oph′rah, 24 and Che′phar-am′mo·ni and Oph′ni and Ge′ba; twelve cities and their settlements.

25 Gib′e·on and Ra′mah and Be·er′oth, 26 and Miz′peh and Che·phi′rah and Mo′zah, 27 and Re′kem and Ir′pe·el and Tar′a·lah, 28 and Ze′lah, Ha-e′leph and Je·bu′si, that is to say, Jerusalem, Gib′e·ah and Kir′i·ath; fourteen cities and their settlements.

This was the inheritance of the sons of Benjamin by their families.

Judges

4 Then the sons of Israel again began to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes now that E′hud was dead. 2 So Jehovah sold them into the hand of Ja′bin the king of Ca′naan, who reigned in Ha′zor; and the chief of his army was Sis′e·ra, and he was dwelling in Ha·ro′sheth of the nations. 3 And the sons of Israel began to cry out to Jehovah, because he had nine hundred war chariots with iron scythes, and he himself oppressed the sons of Israel with harshness twenty years.

4 Now Deb′o·rah, a prophetess, the wife of Lap′pi·doth, was judging Israel at that particular time. 5 And she was dwelling under Deb′o·rah’s palm tree between Ra′mah and Beth′el in the mountainous region of E′phra·im; and the sons of Israel would go up to her for judgment. 6 And she proceeded to send and call Ba′rak the son of A·bin′o·am out of Ke′desh-naph′ta·li and to say to him: “Has not Jehovah the God of Israel given the command? ‘Go and you must spread yourself out on Mount Ta′bor, and you must take with you ten thousand men out of the sons of Naph′ta·li and out of the sons of Zeb′u·lun. 7 And I shall certainly draw to you at the torrent valley of Ki′shon Sis′e·ra the chief of Ja′bin’s army and his war chariots and his crowd, and I shall indeed give him into your hand.’”

8 At this Ba′rak said to her: “If you will go with me, I also shall certainly go; but if you will not go with me, I shall not go.” 9 To this she said: “Without fail I shall go with you. Just the same, the beautifying thing will not become yours on the way that you are going, for it will be into the hand of a woman that Jehovah will sell Sis′e·ra.” With that Deb′o·rah got up and went with Ba′rak to Ke′desh. 10 And Ba′rak began to call Zeb′u·lun and Naph′ta·li together to Ke′desh, and ten thousand men went on up following his steps; and Deb′o·rah went on up with him.

11 Incidentally He′ber the Ken′ite had separated from the Ken′ites, the sons of Ho′bab, whose son-in-law Moses was, and he had his tent pitched near the big tree in Za·a·nan′nim, which is at Ke′desh.

12 Then they reported to Sis′e·ra that Ba′rak the son of A·bin′o·am had gone up to Mount Ta′bor. 13 At once Sis′e·ra called together all his war chariots, the nine hundred war chariots with iron scythes, and all the people that were with him, out of Ha·ro′sheth of the nations to the torrent valley of Ki′shon. 14 Deb′o·rah now said to Ba′rak: “Get up, for this is the day that Jehovah will certainly give Sis′e·ra into your hand. Is it not Jehovah that has gone out before you?” And Ba′rak went descending from Mount Ta′bor with ten thousand men behind him. 15 And Jehovah began to throw Sis′e·ra and all his war chariots and all the camp into confusion by the edge of the sword before Ba′rak. Finally Sis′e·ra got down off the chariot and took to flight on foot. 16 And Ba′rak chased after the war chariots and the camp as far as Ha·ro′sheth of the nations, so that all the camp of Sis′e·ra fell by the edge of the sword. Not as much as one remained.

17 As for Sis′e·ra, he fled on foot to the tent of Ja′el the wife of He′ber the Ken′ite, for there was peace between Ja′bin the king of Ha′zor and the household of He′ber the Ken′ite. 18 Then Ja′el came on out to meet Sis′e·ra and said to him: “Turn this way, my lord, turn this way to me. Do not be afraid.” So he turned aside to her into the tent. Later she covered him with a blanket. 19 In time he said to her: “Give me, please, a little water to drink, for I am thirsty.” Accordingly she opened a skin bottle of milk and gave him a drink, after which she covered him. 20 And he went on to say to her: “Stand at the entrance of the tent, and it must occur that if anybody comes and does ask you and says, ‘Is there a man here?’ you must then say, ‘No!’”

21 And Ja′el the wife of He′ber proceeded to take a pin of the tent and to put the hammer into her hand. Then she went to him stealthily and drove the pin into his temples and beat it into the earth, while he was fast asleep and weary. So he died.

22 And, look! there was Ba′rak pursuing Sis′e·ra. Ja′el now came on out to meet him and said to him: “Come and I shall show you the man you are looking for.” So in he went to her, and, look! there was Sis′e·ra fallen dead, with the pin in his temples.

23 Thus God subdued Ja′bin the king of Ca′naan before the sons of Israel on that day. 24 And the hand of the sons of Israel went on getting harder and harder against Ja′bin the king of Ca′naan, until they had cut off Ja′bin the king of Ca′naan.

Judges

6 Then the sons of Israel began to do what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah. So Jehovah gave them into the hand of Mid′i·an for seven years. 2 And the hand of Mid′i·an came to prevail over Israel. Due to Mid′i·an the sons of Israel made for themselves the underground store places that were in the mountains, and the caves and the places difficult to approach. 3 And it occurred that, if Israel sowed seed, Mid′i·an and Am′a·lek and the Easterners came up, yes, they came up against them. 4 And they would camp against them and would ruin the yield of the earth all the way to Ga′za, and they would not let any sustenance or sheep or bull or ass remain in Israel. 5 For they and their livestock would come up with their tents. They would come as numerous as the locusts, and they and their camels were without number; and they would come into the land to ruin it. 6 And Israel became greatly impoverished due to Mid′i·an; and the sons of Israel began to call to Jehovah for aid.

7 And it came about that because the sons of Israel called to Jehovah for aid on account of Mid′i·an, 8 Jehovah proceeded to send a man, a prophet, to the sons of Israel and to say to them: “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel has said, ‘It was I who brought YOU up from Egypt and thus brought YOU out of the house of slaves. 9 So I delivered YOU out of the hand of Egypt and out of the hand of all YOUR oppressors and drove them out from before YOU and gave YOU their land. 10 Furthermore, I said to YOU: “I am Jehovah YOUR God. YOU must not fear the gods of the Am′or·ites in whose land YOU are dwelling.” And YOU did not listen to my voice.’”

11 Later Jehovah’s angel came and sat under the big tree that was in Oph′rah, which belonged to Jo′ash the Abi-ez′rite, while Gid′e·on his son was beating out wheat in the winepress so as to get it quickly out of the sight of Mid′i·an. 12 Then Jehovah’s angel appeared to him and said to him: “Jehovah is with you, you valiant, mighty one.” 13 At this Gid′e·on said to him: “Excuse me, my lord, but if Jehovah is with us, then why has all this come upon us, and where are all his wonderful acts that our fathers related to us, saying, ‘Was it not out of Egypt that Jehovah brought us up?’ And now Jehovah has deserted us, and he gives us into the palm of Mid′i·an.” 14 Upon that Jehovah faced him and said: “Go in this power of yours, and you will certainly save Israel out of Mid′i·an’s palm. Do I not send you?” 15 In turn he said to him: “Excuse me, Jehovah. With what shall I save Israel? Look! My thousand is the least in Ma·nas′seh, and I am the smallest in my father’s house.” 16 But Jehovah said to him: “Because I shall prove to be with you, and you will certainly strike down Mid′i·an as if one man.”

17 At this he said to him: “If, now, I have found favor in your eyes, you must also perform a sign for me that you are the one speaking with me. 18 Do not, please, move away from here until I come to you and I have brought out my gift and set it before you.” Accordingly he said: “I, for my part, shall keep sitting here until you return.” 19 And Gid′e·on went in and proceeded to make ready a kid of the goats and an e′phah of flour as unfermented cakes. The meat he put in the basket, and the broth he put in the cooking pot, after which he brought it out to him under the big tree and served it.

20 The angel of the true God now said to him: “Take the meat and the unfermented cakes and set them on the big rock there, and pour out the broth.” At that he did so. 21 Then Jehovah’s angel thrust out the tip of the staff that was in his hand and touched the meat and the unfermented cakes, and fire began to ascend out of the rock and to consume the meat and the unfermented cakes. As for Jehovah’s angel, he vanished from his sight. 22 Consequently Gid′e·on realized that it was Jehovah’s angel.

At once Gid′e·on said: “Alas, Sovereign Lord Jehovah, for the reason that I have seen Jehovah’s angel face to face!” 23 But Jehovah said to him: “Peace be yours. Do not fear. You will not die.” 24 So Gid′e·on built an altar there to Jehovah, and it continues to be called Je·ho′vah-sha′lom down to this day. It is yet in Oph′rah of the Abi-ez′rites.

25 And it came about during that night that Jehovah went on to say to him: “Take the young bull, the bull that belongs to your father, that is, the second young bull of seven years, and you must tear down the altar of Ba′al that is your father’s, and the sacred pole that is by it you should cut down. 26 And you must build an altar to Jehovah your God at the head of this stronghold, with the row of stones, and you must take the second young bull and offer it up as a burnt offering on the pieces of wood of the sacred pole that you will cut down.” 27 Accordingly Gid′e·on took ten men of his servants and went doing just as Jehovah had spoken to him; but it came about that, as he feared the household of his father and the men of the city too much to do it by day, he went doing it by night.

28 When the men of the city got up early in the morning as usual, why, look! the altar of Ba′al had been pulled down and the sacred pole that was beside it had been cut down, and the second young bull had been offered up on the altar that had been built. 29 And they began to say one to another: “Who has done this thing?” And they went inquiring and seeking. Finally they said: “Gid′e·on the son of Jo′ash is the one that has done this thing.” 30 So the men of the city said to Jo′ash: “Bring your son out that he may die, because he has pulled down the altar of Ba′al, and because he has cut down the sacred pole that was by it.” 31 At this Jo′ash said to all those who stood against him: “Will YOU be the ones to make a legal defense for Ba′al to see whether YOU yourselves may save him? Whoever makes a legal defense for him ought to be put to death even this morning. If he is God, let him make a legal defense for himself, because someone has pulled down his altar.” 32 And he began to call him Jer·ub·ba′al on that day, saying: “Let Ba′al make a legal defense in his own behalf, because someone has pulled down his altar.”

33 And all Mid′i·an and Am′a·lek and the Easterners gathered together as one and proceeded to cross over and camp in the low plain of Jez′re·el. 34 And Jehovah’s spirit enveloped Gid′e·on so that he went blowing the horn, and the Abi-ez′rites got to be called together after him. 35 And he sent out messengers through all of Ma·nas′seh, and they too got to be called together after him. He also sent out messengers through Ash′er and Zeb′u·lun and Naph′ta·li, and they came on up to meet him.

36 Then Gid′e·on said to the true God: “If you are saving Israel by means of me, just as you have promised, 37 here I am keeping a fleece of wool exposed on the threshing floor. If dew comes to be on the fleece alone but on all the earth there is dryness, then I must know that you will save Israel by means of me, just as you have promised.” 38 And it turned out to be that way. When he rose up early the next day and wrung the fleece, he got to drain off enough dew from the fleece to fill a large banquet bowl with water. 39 However, Gid′e·on said to the true God: “Do not let your anger blaze against me, but let me speak just once more. Let me, please, make a test only once more with the fleece. Let, please, dryness occur to the fleece alone, and upon all the earth let there come to be dew.” 40 So God did that way on that night; and dryness came to be on the fleece alone, and upon all the earth dew occurred.

Judges

7 Then Jer·ub·ba′al, that is to say, Gid′e·on, and all the people who were with him, rose early and took up camping at the well of Ha′rod; and the camp of Mid′i·an happened to be on the north of him, at the hill of Mo′reh, in the low plain. 2 Jehovah now said to Gid′e·on: “The people who are with you are too many for me to give Mid′i·an into their hand. Perhaps Israel would brag about itself against me, saying, ‘My hand it was that saved me.’ 3 And now call out, please, in the hearing of the people, saying, ‘Who is there afraid and trembling? Let him retire.’” So Gid′e·on put them to the proof. With that, twenty-two thousand of the people retired, and there were ten thousand that remained.

4 Still Jehovah said to Gid′e·on: “There are yet too many people. Have them go down to the water that I may put them to the proof for you there. And it must occur that of whomever I say to you, ‘This one will go with you,’ he is one that will go with you, but every one of whom I say to you, ‘This one will not go along with you,’ he is one that will not go along.” 5 So he had the people go down to the water.

Then Jehovah said to Gid′e·on: “Every one that laps up some of the water with his tongue just as a dog laps, you will set him by himself, also every one that bends down upon his knees to drink.” 6 And the number of those lapping with their hand to their mouth turned out to be three hundred men. As for all the rest of the people, they bent down upon their knees to drink water.

7 Jehovah now said to Gid′e·on: “By the three hundred men who did the lapping I shall save YOU people, and I will give Mid′i·an into your hand. As for all the other people, let them go each one to his place.” 8 So they took the provisions of the people in their hand, and their horns, and all the men of Israel he sent away each one to his home; and he kept hold of the three hundred men. As for the camp of Mid′i·an, it happened to be down below him in the low plain.

9 And it came about during that night that Jehovah proceeded to say to him: “Rise up, descend upon the camp, for I have given it into your hand. 10 But if you are afraid to descend, descend, you with Pu′rah your attendant, to the camp. 11 And you must listen to what they will speak, and afterward your hands will certainly grow strong, and you will be certain to descend upon the camp.” At that he and Pu′rah his attendant made their descent to the edge of those in battle formation who were in the camp.

12 Now Mid′i·an and Am′a·lek and all the Easterners were plumped in the low plain as numerous as locusts; and their camels were without number, as numerous as the grains of sand that are on the seashore. 13 Gid′e·on now came, and, look! there was a man relating a dream to his companion, and he went on to say: “Here is a dream that I have dreamed. And, look! there was a round cake of barley bread turning over and over into the camp of Mid′i·an. Then it came to a tent and struck it so that it fell, and it went turning it upside down, and the tent fell flat.” 14 At this his companion answered and said: “This is nothing else but the sword of Gid′e·on the son of Jo′ash, a man of Israel. The true God has given Mid′i·an and all the camp into his hand.”

15 And it came about that as soon as Gid′e·on heard the relating of the dream and its explanation, he began to worship. After that he returned to the camp of Israel and said: “Get up, for Jehovah has given the camp of Mid′i·an into YOUR hand.” 16 Then he divided the three hundred men up into three bands and put horns in the hands of all of them and large empty jars, and torches inside the large jars. 17 And he went on to say to them: “YOU should learn from watching me, and that is how YOU should do. And when I am come to the edge of the camp, it must also occur that just as I shall do, so YOU will do. 18 When I have blown the horn, I and all who are with me, YOU also must blow the horns, YOU too, round about all the camp, and YOU must say, ‘Jehovah’s and Gid′e·on’s!’”

19 In time Gid′e·on came with the hundred men who were with him to the edge of the camp at the start of the middle night watch. They had just got through posting the sentries. And they proceeded to blow the horns, and there was a dashing to pieces of the large water jars that were in their hands. 20 At that the three bands blew the horns and shattered the large jars and took fresh hold on the torches with their left hand and with their right hand on the horns to blow them, and they began calling out: “Jehovah’s sword and Gid′e·on’s!” 21 All the while they kept standing each one in his place all around the camp, and the whole camp got on the run and broke out into shouting and went fleeing. 22 And the three hundred continued to blow the horns, and Jehovah proceeded to set the sword of each one against the other in all the camp; and the camp kept up their flight as far as Beth-shit′tah, on to Zer′e·rah, as far as the outskirts of A′bel-me·ho′lah by Tab′bath.

23 Meantime the men of Israel were called together from Naph′ta·li and Ash′er and all of Ma·nas′seh, and they went chasing after Mid′i·an. 24 And Gid′e·on sent messengers into all the mountainous region of E′phra·im, saying: “Go down to meet Mid′i·an and capture ahead of them the waters as far as Beth-bar′ah and the Jordan.” So all the men of E′phra·im were called together, and they got to capture the waters as far as Beth-bar′ah and the Jordan. 25 They also got to capture the two princes of Mid′i·an, namely, O′reb and Ze′eb; and they proceeded to kill O′reb on the rock of O′reb, and they killed Ze′eb at the wine vat of Ze′eb. And they kept on pursuing Mid′i·an, and they brought the head of O′reb and that of Ze′eb to Gid′e·on in the region of the Jordan.

Judges

9 In time A·bim′e·lech the son of Jer·ub·ba′al went to She′chem to the brothers of his mother and began speaking to them and to all the family of the house of his mother’s father, saying: 2 “Speak, please, in the hearing of all the landowners of She′chem, ‘Which is better for YOU, for seventy men, all the sons of Jer·ub·ba′al, to rule over YOU or for one man to rule over YOU? And YOU must remember that YOUR bone and YOUR flesh I am.’”

3 So the brothers of his mother began speaking all these words about him in the hearing of all the landowners of She′chem so that their heart inclined toward A·bim′e·lech, for they said: “He is our own brother.” 4 Then they gave him seventy pieces of silver from the house of Ba′al-be′rith, and with them A·bim′e·lech proceeded to hire idle and insolent men, that they might accompany him. 5 After that he went to the house of his father at Oph′rah and killed his brothers, the sons of Jer·ub·ba′al, seventy men, upon one stone, but Jo′tham the youngest son of Jer·ub·ba′al was left over, because he had hid.

6 Subsequently all the landowners of She′chem and all the house of Mil′lo gathered together and went and made A·bim′e·lech reign as king, close by the big tree, the pillar that was in She′chem.

7 When they reported it to Jo′tham he at once went and stood on the top of Mount Ger′i·zim and raised his voice and called out and said to them: “Listen to me, YOU landowners of She′chem, and let God listen to YOU:

8 “Once upon a time the trees went to anoint a king over them. So they said to the olive tree, ‘Do be king over us.’ 9 But the olive tree said to them, ‘Must I give up my fatness with which they glorify God and men, and must I go to wave over the other trees?’ 10 Then the trees said to the fig tree, ‘You come, be queen over us.’ 11 But the fig tree said to them, ‘Must I give up my sweetness and my good produce, and must I go to wave over the other trees?’ 12 Next the trees said to the vine, ‘You come, be queen over us.’ 13 In turn the vine said to them, ‘Must I give up my new wine that makes God and men rejoice, and must I go to wave over the trees?’ 14 Finally all the other trees said to the bramble, ‘You come, be king over us.’ 15 At this the bramble said to the trees, ‘If it is in truth that YOU are anointing me as king over YOU, come, seek refuge under my shadow. But if not, let fire come out of the bramble and consume the cedars of Leb′a·non.’

16 “And now if it is in truth and in faultlessness that YOU have acted and that YOU went making A·bim′e·lech king, and if it is goodness that YOU have exercised toward Jer·ub·ba′al and his household, and if YOU have done to him as the doing of his hands deserved, 17 when my father fought for YOU and went risking his soul that he might deliver YOU out of Mid′i·an’s hand; 18 and YOU, for YOUR part, have risen up against the household of my father today that YOU might kill his sons, seventy men, upon one stone, and that YOU might make A·bim′e·lech, the son of his slave girl, king over the landowners of She′chem just because he is YOUR own brother; 19 yes, if it is in truth and in faultlessness that YOU have acted toward Jer·ub·ba′al and his household this day, rejoice over A·bim′e·lech and let him too rejoice over YOU. 20 But if not, let fire come out of A·bim′e·lech and consume the landowners of She′chem and the house of Mil′lo, and let fire come out of the landowners of She′chem and the house of Mil′lo and consume A·bim′e·lech.”

21 Then Jo′tham took to flight and went running off and made his way to Be′er, and he took up dwelling there because of A·bim′e·lech his brother.

22 And A·bim′e·lech kept playing the prince over Israel three years. 23 Then God let develop a bad spirit between A·bim′e·lech and the landowners of She′chem, and the landowners of She′chem proceeded to deal treacherously with A·bim′e·lech, 24 that the violence done to the seventy sons of Jer·ub·ba′al might come and that he might put their blood upon A·bim′e·lech their brother because he killed them, and upon the landowners of She′chem because they strengthened his hands to kill his brothers. 25 So the landowners of She′chem set ambush men for him upon the tops of the mountains, and they would rob everyone that would pass by them on the road. In time it was reported to A·bim′e·lech.

26 Then Ga′al the son of E′bed and his brothers came and crossed over into She′chem, and the landowners of She′chem began to trust in him. 27 And they went out as usual into the field and engaged in gathering the grapes of their vineyards and in treading them and in carrying on a festal exultation, after which they went into the house of their god and ate and drank and called down evil upon A·bim′e·lech. 28 And Ga′al the son of E′bed went on to say: “Who is A·bim′e·lech, and who is She′chem that we should serve him? Is he not the son of Jer·ub·ba′al, and is not Ze′bul a commissioner of his? Serve the men of Ha′mor, She′chem’s father, YOU others, but why should we ourselves serve him? 29 And if only this people were in my hand! Then I would remove A·bim′e·lech.” And he went on to say to A·bim′e·lech: “Make your army numerous and come on out.”

30 And Ze′bul the prince of the city got to hear the words of Ga′al the son of E′bed. Then his anger blazed. 31 So he sent messengers by subterfuge to A·bim′e·lech, saying: “Look! Ga′al the son of E′bed and his brothers are now come to She′chem, and here they are massing the city against you. 32 And now rise up by night, you and the people that are with you, and lie in wait in the field. 33 And it must occur in the morning that as soon as the sun shines forth you should get up early, and you must make a dash against the city; and when he and the people that are with him are going out against you, you must also do to him just as your hand finds it possible.”

34 Accordingly A·bim′e·lech and all the people that were with him rose up by night, and they began to lie in wait against She′chem in four bands. 35 Later Ga′al the son of E′bed went out and stood at the entrance of the city gate. Then A·bim′e·lech and the people that were with him rose up from the place of ambush. 36 When Ga′al caught sight of the people, he at once said to Ze′bul: “Look! People coming down from the tops of the mountains.” But Ze′bul said to him: “The shadows of the mountains are what you are seeing as though they were men.”

37 Later Ga′al spoke once more and said: “Look! People coming down out of the center of the land, and one band is coming by the way of the big tree of Me·on′e·nim.” 38 At this Ze′bul said to him: “Where now is that saying of yours that you mouthed, ‘Who is A·bim′e·lech that we should serve him?’ Is not this the people whom you rejected? Go out now, please, and fight against them.”

39 So Ga′al went on out at the head of the landowners of She′chem and took up the fight against A·bim′e·lech. 40 And A·bim′e·lech set out after him, and he went fleeing before him; and the slain kept falling in numbers as far as the entrance of the gate.

41 And A·bim′e·lech continued to dwell in A·ru′mah, and Ze′bul proceeded to drive Ga′al and his brothers out from dwelling in She′chem. 42 And it came about on the next day that the people began to go out into the field. So they told A·bim′e·lech. 43 Hence he took the people and divided them up into three bands and began to lie in wait in the field. Then he looked, and there the people were going out of the city. He now rose up against them and struck them down. 44 And A·bim′e·lech and the bands that were with him made a dash that they might stand at the entrance of the city gate, while two bands made a dash against all who were in the field, and they went striking them down. 45 And A·bim′e·lech fought against the city all that day and got to capture the city; and he killed the people that were in it, after which he pulled the city down and sowed it with salt.

46 When all the landowners of the tower of She′chem heard of it, they immediately went to the vault of the house of El-be′rith. 47 Then it was reported to A·bim′e·lech that all the landowners of the tower of She′chem had collected together. 48 At that A·bim′e·lech went up Mount Zal′mon, he and all the people that were with him. A·bim′e·lech now took an ax in his hand and cut down a branch of the trees and lifted it up and put it on his shoulder and said to the people that were with him: “What YOU have seen me do—hurry up, do like me!” 49 So all the people cut down also each one a branch for himself and went following A·bim′e·lech. Then they put them against the vault, and over them they set the vault on fire, so that all the men of the tower of She′chem died too, about a thousand men and women.

50 And A·bim′e·lech proceeded to go to The′bez and to camp against The′bez and capture it. 51 As a strong tower happened to be in the middle of the city, there was where all the men and women and all the landowners of the city went fleeing, after which they shut it behind them and climbed onto the roof of the tower. 52 And A·bim′e·lech made his way to the tower and began fighting against it, and he went on up close to the entrance of the tower to burn it with fire. 53 Then a certain woman pitched an upper millstone upon A·bim′e·lech’s head and broke his skull in pieces. 54 So he quickly called the attendant bearing his weapons and said to him: “Draw your sword and put me to death, for fear they should say about me, ‘It was a woman that killed him.’” Immediately his attendant ran him through, so that he died.

55 When the men of Israel got to see that A·bim′e·lech had died, they now went each one to his place. 56 Thus God made the evil of A·bim′e·lech that he had done to his father by killing his seventy brothers come back. 57 And all the evil of the men of She′chem God made come back upon their own heads, that the malediction of Jo′tham the son of Jer·ub·ba′al might come upon them.

Judges

11 Now Jeph′thah the Gil′e·ad·ite had become a mighty, valiant man, and he was the son of a prostitute woman, and Gil′e·ad came to be the father of Jeph′thah. 2 And Gil′e·ad’s wife kept bearing sons to him. When the sons of the wife got big, they proceeded to drive Jeph′thah out and to say to him: “You must have no inheritance in the household of our father, for you are the son of another woman.” 3 So Jeph′thah ran away because of his brothers and took up dwelling in the land of Tob. And idle men kept bringing themselves together to Jeph′thah, and they would go out with him.

4 And it came about after a while that the sons of Am′mon began to fight against Israel. 5 And it came about that when the sons of Am′mon did fight against Israel, the older men of Gil′e·ad immediately went to take Jeph′thah out of the land of Tob. 6 Then they said to Jeph′thah: “Do come and serve as our commander, and let us fight against the sons of Am′mon.” 7 But Jeph′thah said to the older men of Gil′e·ad: “Was it not YOU that hated me so that YOU drove me out of my father’s house? And why is it that YOU have come to me now just when YOU are in distress?” 8 At this the older men of Gil′e·ad said to Jeph′thah: “That is why now we have returned to you, and you must go with us and fight against the sons of Am′mon, and you must become for us the head of all the inhabitants of Gil′e·ad.” 9 So Jeph′thah said to the older men of Gil′e·ad: “If YOU are bringing me back to fight against the sons of Am′mon, and Jehovah does abandon them to me, I, for my part, shall become YOUR head!” 10 In turn the older men of Gil′e·ad said to Jeph′thah: “Let Jehovah prove to be the listener between us if the way we shall do is not according to your word.” 11 Consequently Jeph′thah went with the older men of Gil′e·ad and the people set him over them as head and commander. And Jeph′thah proceeded to speak all his words before Jehovah in Miz′pah.

12 Then Jeph′thah sent messengers to the king of the sons of Am′mon, saying: “What do I have to do with you, seeing that you have come against me to fight in my land?” 13 So the king of the sons of Am′mon said to the messengers of Jeph′thah: “It is because Israel took my land when they came up out of Egypt, from the Ar′non as far as the Jab′bok and as far as the Jordan. And now do return it peacefully.” 14 But Jeph′thah sent once more messengers to the king of the sons of Am′mon 15 and said to him:

“This is what Jeph′thah has said, ‘Israel did not take the land of Mo′ab and the land of the sons of Am′mon. 16 For when they came up out of Egypt Israel went walking through the wilderness as far as the Red Sea and got to come to Ka′desh. 17 Then Israel sent messengers to the king of E′dom, saying: “Let me pass, please, through your land,” and the king of E′dom did not listen. And also to the king of Mo′ab they sent, and he did not consent. And Israel kept dwelling in Ka′desh. 18 When they walked on through the wilderness, they went their way around the land of E′dom and the land of Mo′ab, so that they went toward the rising of the sun as respects the land of Mo′ab and took up camping in the region of the Ar′non; and they did not come within the boundary of Mo′ab, because Ar′non was the boundary of Mo′ab.

19 “‘After that Israel sent messengers to Si′hon the king of the Am′or·ites, the king of Hesh′bon, and Israel said to him: “Let us pass, please, through your land to my own place.” 20 And Si′hon did not feel sure about Israel’s crossing through his territory, and Si′hon went gathering all his people together and camping in Ja′haz and fighting against Israel. 21 At this Jehovah the God of Israel gave Si′hon and all his people into Israel’s hand, so that they struck them and Israel took possession of all the land of the Am′or·ites inhabiting that land. 22 Thus they took possession of all the territory of the Am′or·ites from the Ar′non as far as the Jab′bok and from the wilderness as far as the Jordan.

23 “‘And now Jehovah the God of Israel it was that dispossessed the Am′or·ites from before his people Israel, and you, for your part, would dispossess them. 24 Is it not whomever Che′mosh your god causes you to dispossess that you will dispossess? And every one whom Jehovah our God has dispossessed from before us is the one we shall dispossess. 25 And now are you any better than Ba′lak the son of Zip′por, the king of Mo′ab? Did he ever contend with Israel, or did he ever fight against them? 26 While Israel was dwelling in Hesh′bon and its dependent towns and in A·ro′er and its dependent towns and in all the cities that are by the banks of Ar′non for three hundred years, why, then, did YOU never snatch them away during that time? 27 As for me, I have not sinned against you, but you are dealing wrong with me by fighting against me. Let Jehovah the Judge judge today between the sons of Israel and the sons of Am′mon.’”

28 And the king of the sons of Am′mon did not listen to the words of Jeph′thah that he had sent to him.

29 Jehovah’s spirit now came upon Jeph′thah, and he proceeded to pass through Gil′e·ad and Ma·nas′seh and to pass through Miz′peh of Gil′e·ad, and from Miz′peh of Gil′e·ad he passed along to the sons of Am′mon.

30 Then Jeph′thah made a vow to Jehovah and said: “If you without fail give the sons of Am′mon into my hand, 31 it must also occur that the one coming out, who comes out of the doors of my house to meet me when I return in peace from the sons of Am′mon, must also become Jehovah’s, and I must offer that one up as a burnt offering.”

32 So Jeph′thah passed along to the sons of Am′mon to fight against them, and Jehovah proceeded to give them into his hand. 33 And he went striking them from A·ro′er all the way to Min′nith—twenty cities—and as far as A′bel-ker′a·mim with a very great slaughter. Thus the sons of Am′mon were subdued before the sons of Israel.

34 Finally Jeph′thah came to Miz′pah to his home, and, look! his daughter coming out to meet him with tambourine playing and dancing! Now she was absolutely the only child. Besides her he had neither son nor daughter. 35 And it came about that when he caught sight of her, he began to rip his garments and to say: “Alas, my daughter! You have indeed made me bend down, and you yourself have become the one I was ostracizing. And I—I have opened my mouth to Jehovah, and I am unable to turn back.”

36 But she said to him: “My father, if you have opened your mouth to Jehovah, do to me according to what has gone forth from your mouth, since Jehovah has executed acts of vengeance for you upon your enemies, the sons of Am′mon.” 37 And she went on to say to her father: “Let this thing be done to me: Let me alone for two months, and let me go, and I will descend upon the mountains, and let me weep over my virginity, I and my girl companions.”

38 At this he said: “Go!” So he sent her away for two months; and she kept going, she with her girl companions, and weeping over her virginity upon the mountains. 39 And it came about at the end of two months that she made her return to her father, after which he carried out his vow that he had made toward her. As for her, she never had relations with a man. And it came to be a regulation in Israel: 40 From year to year the daughters of Israel would go to give commendation to the daughter of Jeph′thah the Gil′e·ad·ite, four days in the year.

Judges

14 Then Samson went down to Tim′nah and saw a woman in Tim′nah of the daughters of the Phi·lis′tines. 2 So he went up and told his father and his mother and said: “There is a woman that I have seen in Tim′nah of the daughters of the Phi·lis′tines, and now get her for me as a wife.” 3 But his father and his mother said to him: “Is there not among the daughters of your brothers and among all my people a woman, so that you are going to take a wife from the uncircumcised Phi·lis′tines?” Still Samson said to his father: “Get just her for me, because she is the one just right in my eyes.” 4 As for his father and his mother, they did not know that that was from Jehovah, that he was looking for an opportunity against the Phi·lis′tines, as at that particular time the Phi·lis′tines were ruling over Israel.

5 Accordingly Samson went on down with his father and his mother to Tim′nah. When he got as far as the vineyards of Tim′nah, why, look! a maned young lion roaring upon meeting him. 6 Then Jehovah’s spirit became operative upon him, so that he tore it in two, just as someone tears a male kid in two, and there was nothing at all in his hand. And he did not tell his father or his mother what he had done. 7 And he continued on his way down and began to speak to the woman; and she was still right in Samson’s eyes.

8 Now after a while he went on back to take her home. Meantime he turned aside to look at the carcass of the lion, and there there was a swarm of bees in the lion’s corpse, and honey. 9 So he scraped it out into his palms and walked on, eating as he walked. When he rejoined his father and his mother, he at once gave them some, and they began to eat. And he did not tell them that it was out of the corpse of the lion that he had scraped the honey.

10 And his father continued on his way down to the woman, and Samson proceeded to hold a banquet there; for that was the way the young fellows used to do. 11 And it came about that, on their seeing him, they immediately took thirty groomsmen, that these should keep with him. 12 Then Samson said to them: “Let me, please, propound a riddle to YOU. If YOU will without fail tell it to me during the seven days of the banquet and YOU do solve it, I shall in that case have to give YOU thirty undergarments and thirty outfits of clothing. 13 But if YOU are unable to tell it to me, YOU yourselves also must give me thirty undergarments and thirty outfits of clothing.” At this they said to him: “Do propound your riddle, and let us hear it.” 14 So he said to them:

“Out of the eater something to eat came forth,

And out of the strong something sweet came forth.”

And they proved unable to tell the riddle for three days. 15 And it came about on the fourth day that they began to say to Samson’s wife: “Fool your husband that he may tell us the riddle. Otherwise we shall burn you and the house of your father with fire. Was it to take our possessions that YOU people invited us here?” 16 Consequently Samson’s wife began to weep over him and to say: “You only hate me, you do, and you do not love me. There was a riddle that you propounded to the sons of my people, but to me you have not told it.” At this he said to her: “Why, to my own father and my own mother I have not told it, and ought I to tell it to you?” 17 But she kept weeping over him the seven days that the banquet continued for them, and it came about on the seventh day that finally he told her, because she had pressured him. Then she told the riddle to the sons of her people. 18 So the men of the city said to him on the seventh day before ever he could go into the interior room:

“What is sweeter than honey,

And what is stronger than a lion?”

In turn he said to them:

“If YOU had not plowed with my young cow,

YOU would not have solved my riddle.”

19 And Jehovah’s spirit became operative upon him, so that he went down to Ash′ke·lon and struck down thirty men of theirs and took what he stripped off them and gave the outfits to the tellers of the riddle. And his anger continued hot, and he went his way up to his father’s house.

20 And Samson’s wife came to belong to a groomsman of his who had associated with him.

Judges

16 Once Samson went to Ga′za and saw a prostitute woman there and came in to her. 2 And report was made to the Ga′zites, saying: “Samson has come in here.” So they surrounded him and lay in wait for him all night long in the city gate. And they kept quiet the whole night, saying: “As soon as the morning gets light, we must also kill him.”

3 However, Samson kept lying till midnight and then rose at midnight and grabbed hold of the doors of the city gate and the two side posts and pulled them out along with the bar and put them upon his shoulders and went carrying them up to the top of the mountain that is in front of He′bron.

4 And it came about after that that he fell in love with a woman in the torrent valley of So′rek, and her name was De·li′lah. 5 And the axis lords of the Phi·lis′tines proceeded to come up to her and to say to her: “Fool him and see in what his great power is and with what we can prevail over him and with what we are certain to tie him so as to master him; and we, for our part, shall give you each one thousand one hundred silver pieces.”

6 Later De·li′lah said to Samson: “Do tell me, please, In what is your great power and with what can you be tied for one to master you?” 7 Then Samson said to her: “If they tie me with seven still-moist sinews that have not been dried out, I must also grow weak and become like an ordinary man.” 8 So the axis lords of the Phi·lis′tines brought up to her seven still-moist sinews that had not been dried out. Later she tied him with them. 9 Now the ambush was sitting in the interior room of hers, and she began to say to him: “The Phi·lis′tines are upon you, Samson!” At that he tore the sinews in two, just as a twisted thread of tow is torn in two when it smells fire. And his power did not become known.

10 Subsequently De·li′lah said to Samson: “Look! You have trifled with me that you might speak lies to me. Now tell me, do please, with what you can be tied.” 11 So he said to her: “If they tie me tight with new ropes with which no work has been done, I must also grow weak and become like an ordinary man.” 12 So De·li′lah took new ropes and tied him with them and said to him: “The Phi·lis′tines are upon you, Samson!” All the while the ambush was sitting in the interior room. At that he tore them in two from off his arms like a thread.

13 After that De·li′lah said to Samson: “Up till now you have trifled with me that you might speak lies to me. Do tell me with what you can be tied.” Then he said to her: “If you will weave the seven braids of my head with the warp thread.” 14 Accordingly she fixed them with the pin, after which she said to him: “The Phi·lis′tines are upon you, Samson!” So he awoke from his sleep and pulled out the loom pin and the warp thread.

15 She now said to him: “How dare you say, ‘I do love you,’ when your heart is not with me? These three times you have trifled with me and have not told me in what your great power is.” 16 And it came about that because she pressured him with her words all the time and kept urging him, his soul got to be impatient to the point of dying. 17 Finally he disclosed to her all his heart and said to her: “A razor has never come upon my head, because I am a Naz′i·rite of God from my mother’s belly. If I did get shaved, my power also would certainly depart from me, and I should indeed grow weak and become like all other men.”

18 When De·li′lah got to see that he had disclosed to her all his heart, she immediately sent and called the Phi·lis′tine axis lords, saying: “Come up this time, for he has disclosed to me all his heart.” And the Phi·lis′tine axis lords came up to her that they might bring up the money in their hand. 19 And she proceeded to make him sleep upon her knees. Then she called the man and had him shave off the seven braids of his head, after which she started to show the mastery of him, and his power kept departing from upon him. 20 Now she said: “The Phi·lis′tines are upon you, Samson!” At that he woke up from his sleep and said: “I shall go out as at other times and shake myself free.” And he himself did not know that it was Jehovah that had departed from him. 21 So the Phi·lis′tines grabbed hold of him and bored his eyes out and brought him down to Ga′za and bound him with two fetters of copper; and he came to be a grinder in the prison house. 22 Meanwhile the hair of his head started to grow luxuriantly as soon as he had been shaved.

23 As for the Phi·lis′tine axis lords, they gathered together to sacrifice a great sacrifice to Da′gon their god and for rejoicing, and they kept saying: “Our god has given into our hand Samson our enemy!” 24 When the people got to see him, they at once gave way to praising their god, “because,” said they, “our god has given into our hand our enemy and the devastator of our land and the one who multiplied our slain.”

25 And it came about that because their heart was merry, they began to say: “Call Samson that he may offer us some amusement.” So they called Samson out of the prison house that he might make sport before them; and they proceeded to stand him between the pillars. 26 Then Samson said to the boy that was holding him by his hand: “Do permit me to feel the pillars upon which the house is firmly established and let me lean against them.” 27 (Incidentally, the house was full of men and women and all the Phi·lis′tine axis lords were there; and upon the roof there were about three thousand men and women who were looking on while Samson offered some amusement.)

28 Samson now called to Jehovah and said: “Sovereign Lord Jehovah, remember me, please, and strengthen me, please, just this once, O you the true God, and let me avenge myself upon the Phi·lis′tines with vengeance for one of my two eyes.”

29 With that Samson braced himself against the two middle pillars upon which the house was firmly established, and got a grasp on them, one with his right and the other with his left hand. 30 And Samson proceeded to say: “Let my soul die with the Phi·lis′tines.” Then he bent himself with power, and the house went falling upon the axis lords and upon all the people that were in it, so that the dead that he put to death in his own death came to be more than those he had put to death during his lifetime.

31 Later his brothers and all the household of his father came on down and lifted him up and brought him up and buried him between Zo′rah and Esh′ta·ol in the burial place of Ma·no′ah his father. As for him, he had judged Israel twenty years.

Judges

17 Now there happened to be a man of the mountainous region of E′phra·im whose name was Mi′cah. 2 In time he said to his mother: “The thousand one hundred silver pieces that were taken from you and over which you pronounced a curse and also said it in my hearing—look! the silver is with me. It was I who took it.” At that his mother said: “Blessed may my son be of Jehovah.” 3 Accordingly he gave back the thousand one hundred pieces of silver to his mother; and his mother went on to say: “I must without fail sanctify the silver to Jehovah from my hand for my son, so as to make a carved image and a molten statue; and now I shall give it back to you.”

4 So he returned the silver to his mother, and his mother took two hundred silver pieces and gave them to the silversmith. And he went making a carved image and a molten statue; and it got to be in Mi′cah’s house. 5 As for the man Mi′cah, he had a house of gods, and he proceeded to make an eph′od and teraphim and to fill the hand of one of his sons with power, that he might serve as priest for him. 6 In those days there was no king in Israel. As for everybody, what was right in his own eyes he was accustomed to do.

7 Now there happened to be a young man of Beth′le·hem in Judah of the family of Judah, and he was a Levite. And he was residing there for a time. 8 And the man proceeded to go from the city of Beth′le·hem in Judah to reside for a time wherever he might find a place. At length while going his way he came into the mountainous region of E′phra·im as far as the house of Mi′cah. 9 Then Mi′cah said to him: “Where do you come from?” At that he said to him: “I am a Levite from Beth′le·hem in Judah, and I am on my way to reside for a time wherever I may find a place.” 10 So Mi′cah said to him: “Do dwell with me and serve as a father and priest for me, and I, for my part, shall give you ten silver pieces a year and the usual outfit of garments and your sustenance.” Accordingly the Levite went in. 11 Thus the Levite took it upon himself to dwell with the man, and the young man got to be as one of his sons to him. 12 Furthermore, Mi′cah filled the hand of the Levite with power, that the young man might serve as a priest for him and might continue in the house of Mi′cah. 13 Hence Mi′cah said: “Now I do know that Jehovah will do me good, because the Levite has become priest for me.”

Judges

21 Now the men of Israel had sworn in Miz′pah, saying: “Not a man of us will give his daughter to Benjamin as a wife.” 2 Consequently the people came to Beth′el and kept sitting there before the true God until the evening and continued to raise their voice and indulge in a great deal of weeping. 3 And they would say: “Why, O Jehovah the God of Israel, has this occurred in Israel, for one tribe to be missing today from Israel?” 4 And it came about the next day that the people proceeded to get up early and to build an altar there and to offer up burnt offerings and communion offerings.

5 Then the sons of Israel said: “Who is there out of all the tribes of Israel that has not come up in the congregation to Jehovah, for there is a great oath that has taken place respecting the one that has not come up to Jehovah at Miz′pah, saying, ‘Let him be put to death without fail.’” 6 And the sons of Israel began to feel regret over Benjamin their brother. So they said: “Today one tribe has been chopped off from Israel. 7 What shall we do to those who are left over as to wives, now that we ourselves have sworn by Jehovah not to give them any of our daughters as wives?”

8 And they went on to say: “Which one out of the tribes of Israel is it that has not come up to Jehovah at Miz′pah?” And, look! no one had come into the camp from Ja′besh-gil′e·ad to the congregation. 9 When the people were counted, well, look! there was not a man there from the inhabitants of Ja′besh-gil′e·ad. 10 Hence the assembly proceeded to send twelve thousand of the most valiant men there and to command them, saying: “Go, and YOU must strike the inhabitants of Ja′besh-gil′e·ad with the edge of the sword, even the women and the little ones. 11 And this is the thing that YOU should do: Every male and every woman that has experienced lying with a male YOU should devote to destruction.” 12 However, they found out of the inhabitants of Ja′besh-gil′e·ad four hundred girls, virgins, that had not had intercourse with a man by lying with a male. So they brought them to the camp at Shi′loh, which is in the land of Ca′naan.

13 And all the assembly now sent and spoke to the sons of Benjamin that were on the crag of Rim′mon and offered them peace. 14 Accordingly Benjamin came back at that time. Then they gave them the women that they had preserved alive from the women of Ja′besh-gil′e·ad; but they did not find enough for them. 15 And the people felt regret over Benjamin because Jehovah had made a rupture between the tribes of Israel. 16 Consequently the older men of the assembly said: “What shall we do to the men that are left over as to wives, for womankind has been annihilated out of Benjamin?” 17 Then they said: “There should be a possession for those who have escaped of Benjamin, that a tribe might not be wiped out of Israel. 18 As for us, we are not allowed to give them wives from our daughters, because the sons of Israel have sworn, saying, ‘Cursed is the one that gives a wife to Benjamin.’”

19 Finally they said: “Look! There is a festival of Jehovah from year to year in Shi′loh, which is to the north of Beth′el, toward the east of the highway that goes up from Beth′el to She′chem and toward the south of Le·bo′nah.” 20 So they commanded the sons of Benjamin, saying: “Go, and YOU must lie in wait in the vineyards. 21 And YOU must look, and, there now, when the daughters of Shi′loh come on out to dance in circle dances, YOU must also come out from the vineyards and carry off for yourselves by force each one his wife from the daughters of Shi′loh, and YOU must go to the land of Benjamin. 22 And it must occur that should their fathers or their brothers come to conduct a legal case against us, we also shall certainly say to them, ‘Do us a favor for their sakes, because we have not taken for each one his wife by war, for it was not YOU that did the giving to them at a time when YOU would become guilty.’”

23 Accordingly the sons of Benjamin did just that way, and they proceeded to carry off wives for their number from the women dancing around, whom they snatched away; after which they went off and returned to their inheritance and built the cities and took up dwelling in them.

24 And the sons of Israel began to disperse from there at that time, each one to his own tribe and his own family; and they went their way out from there, each one to his own inheritance.

25 In those days there was no king in Israel. What was right in his own eyes was what each one was accustomed to do.

Ruth

2 Now Na′o·mi had a kinsman of her husband, a man mighty in wealth, of the family of E·lim′e·lech, and his name was Bo′az.

2 In time Ruth the Mo′ab·ite woman said to Na′o·mi: “Let me go, please, to the field and glean among the ears of grain following after whoever it is in whose eyes I may find favor.” So she said to her: “Go, my daughter.” 3 At that she went off and entered and began to glean in the field behind the harvesters. Thus by chance she lighted on the tract of the field belonging to Bo′az, who was of the family of E·lim′e·lech. 4 And, look! Bo′az came from Beth′le·hem and proceeded to say to the harvesters: “Jehovah be with YOU.” In turn they would say to him: “Jehovah bless you.”

5 Subsequently Bo′az said to the young man who was set over the harvesters: “To whom does this young woman belong?” 6 So the young man set over the harvesters answered and said: “The young woman is a Mo′ab·i·tess, who returned with Na′o·mi from the field of Mo′ab. 7 Then she said, ‘Let me glean, please, and I shall certainly gather among the cut-off ears of grain behind the harvesters.’ So she entered and kept on her feet from that time in the morning until her sitting down just now in the house a little while.”

8 Later Bo′az said to Ruth: “You have heard, have you not, my daughter? Do not go away to glean in another field, and you must also not cross over from this place, and in that way you should keep close by my young women. 9 Let your eyes be on the field that they will harvest, and you must go with them. Have I not commanded the young men not to touch you? When you are thirsty, you must also go to the vessels and drink from what the young men will draw.”

10 At that she fell upon her face and bowed down to the earth and said to him: “How is it I have found favor in your eyes so that I am taken notice of, when I am a foreigner?” 11 Then Bo′az answered and said to her: “The report was fully made to me of all that you have done to your mother-in-law after the death of your husband, and how you proceeded to leave your father and your mother and the land of your relatives and to go to a people whom you had not known formerly. 12 May Jehovah reward the way you act, and may there come to be a perfect wage for you from Jehovah the God of Israel, under whose wings you have come to seek refuge.” 13 To this she said: “Let me find favor in your eyes, my lord, because you have comforted me and because you have spoken reassuringly to your maidservant, although I myself may not happen to be like one of your maidservants.”

14 And Bo′az proceeded to say to her at mealtime: “Approach here, and you must eat some of the bread and dip your piece in the vinegar.” So she sat down beside the harvesters, and he would hold out roasted grain to her and she would eat, so that she was satisfied and yet had something left over. 15 Then she got up to glean. Bo′az now commanded his young men, saying: “Let her glean also among the cut-off ears of grain, and YOU must not molest her. 16 And YOU should also be sure to pull out some from the bundles of ears for her, and YOU must leave them behind that she may glean them, and YOU must not rebuke her.”

17 And she continued to glean in the field until the evening, after which she beat out what she had gleaned, and it came to be about an e′phah of barley. 18 Then she took it up and went into the city, and her mother-in-law got to see what she had gleaned. After that she took out what food she had left over when she had satisfied herself and gave it to her.

19 Her mother-in-law now said to her: “Where did you glean today, and where did you work? May the one who took notice of you become blessed.” So she told her mother-in-law with whom she had worked; and she went on to say: “The name of the man with whom I worked today is Bo′az.” 20 At that Na′o·mi said to her daughter-in-law: “Blessed be he of Jehovah, who has not left his loving-kindness toward the living and the dead.” And Na′o·mi went on to say to her: “The man is related to us. He is one of our repurchasers.” 21 Then Ruth the Mo′ab·i·tess said: “He also said to me, ‘Close by the young people that are mine is where you should keep until they have finished the entire harvest that I have.’” 22 So Na′o·mi said to Ruth her daughter-in-law: “It is better, my daughter, that you should go out with his young women, that they may not annoy you in another field.”

23 And she continued to keep close by the young women of Bo′az to glean until the harvest of the barley and the harvest of the wheat came to an end. And she kept on dwelling with her mother-in-law.

Ruth

4 As for Bo′az, he went up to the gate and began to sit there. And, look! the repurchaser was passing by, whom Bo′az had mentioned. Then he said: “Do turn aside, do sit down here, So-and-so.” Hence he turned aside and sat down. 2 After that he took ten men of the older men of the city and said: “Sit down here.” So they sat down.

3 He now said to the repurchaser: “The tract of the field that belonged to our brother E·lim′e·lech, Na′o·mi, who has returned from the field of Mo′ab, must sell. 4 As for me, I thought that I should disclose it to you, saying, ‘Buy it in front of the inhabitants and the older men of my people. If you will repurchase it, repurchase it; but if you will not repurchase it, do tell me, that I may know, for there is no one else but you to do the repurchasing, and I am next to you.’” At that he said: “I shall be the one to repurchase it.” 5 Then Bo′az said: “On the day that you buy the field from Na′o·mi’s hand, it is also from Ruth the Mo′ab·i·tess, the wife of the dead man, that you must buy it so as to cause the name of the dead man to rise upon his inheritance.” 6 To this the repurchaser said: “I am unable to repurchase it for myself, for fear I may ruin my own inheritance. You repurchase it for yourself with my right of repurchase, because I am not able to do the repurchasing.”

7 Now this was the custom of former times in Israel concerning the right of repurchase and concerning the exchange, to establish every sort of thing: A man had to draw his sandal off and give it to his fellow, and this was the attestation in Israel. 8 So when the repurchaser said to Bo′az: “Buy it for yourself,” he proceeded to draw his sandal off. 9 Then Bo′az said to the older men and all the people: “YOU are witnesses today that I do buy all that belonged to E·lim′e·lech and all that belonged to Chil′i·on and Mah′lon from the hand of Na′o·mi. 10 And also Ruth the Mo′ab·i·tess, the wife of Mah′lon, I do buy for myself as a wife to cause the name of the dead man to rise upon his inheritance and that the name of the dead man may not be cut off from among his brothers and from the gate of his place. YOU are witnesses today.”

11 At this all the people that were in the gate and the older men said: “Witnesses! May Jehovah grant the wife who is coming into your house to be like Rachel and like Le′ah, both of whom built the house of Israel; and you prove your worth in Eph′ra·thah and make a notable name in Beth′le·hem. 12 And may your house become like the house of Pe′rez, whom Ta′mar bore to Judah, from the offspring that Jehovah will give you out of this young woman.”

13 Accordingly Bo′az took Ruth and she became his wife and he had relations with her. So Jehovah granted her conception and she bore a son. 14 And the women began to say to Na′o·mi: “Blessed be Jehovah, who has not let a repurchaser fail for you today; that his name may be proclaimed in Israel. 15 And he has become a restorer of your soul and one to nourish your old age, because your daughter-in-law who does love you, who is better to you than seven sons, has given birth to him.” 16 And Na′o·mi proceeded to take the child and to put it in her bosom, and she came to be its nurse. 17 Then the neighbor ladies gave it a name, saying: “A son has been born to Na′o·mi.” And they began to call his name O′bed. He is the father of Jes′se, David’s father.

18 Now these are the generations of Pe′rez: Pe′rez became father to Hez′ron; 19 and Hez′ron became father to Ram; and Ram became father to Am·min′a·dab; 20 and Am·min′a·dab became father to Nah′shon; and Nah′shon became father to Sal′mon; 21 and Sal′mon became father to Bo′az; and Bo′az became father to O′bed; 22 and O′bed became father to Jes′se; and Jes′se became father to David.

The First of Samuel

or, according to the Greek Septuagint, THE FIRST OF KINGS

1 Now there happened to be a certain man of Ra·math·a′im-zo′phim of the mountainous region of E′phra·im, and his name was El·ka′nah, the son of Je·ro′ham, the son of E·li′hu, the son of To′hu, the son of Zuph, an E′phra·im·ite. 2 And he had two wives, the name of the one being Han′nah, and the name of the other being Pe·nin′nah. And Pe·nin′nah came to have children, but Han′nah had no children. 3 And that man went up out of his city from year to year to prostrate himself and to sacrifice to Jehovah of armies in Shi′loh. And there is where the two sons of E′li, Hoph′ni and Phin′e·has, were priests to Jehovah.

4 And there came to be a day when El·ka′nah proceeded to sacrifice, and he gave to Pe·nin′nah his wife and to all her sons and her daughters portions; 5 but to Han′nah he gave one portion. Nonetheless it was Han′nah that he loved, and, as for Jehovah, he had closed up her womb. 6 And her rival wife also vexed her sorely for the sake of making her feel disconcerted because Jehovah had closed up her womb. 7 And that was the way she would do year by year, as often as she went up into the house of Jehovah. That was the way she would vex her, so that she would weep and not eat. 8 And El·ka′nah her husband proceeded to say to her: “Han′nah, why do you weep, and why do you not eat, and why does your heart feel bad? Am I not better to you than ten sons?”

9 Then Han′nah got up after they had eaten in Shi′loh and after the drinking, while E′li the priest was sitting upon the seat by the doorpost of the temple of Jehovah. 10 And she was bitter of soul, and she began to pray to Jehovah and to weep greatly. 11 And she went on to make a vow and say: “O Jehovah of armies, if you will without fail look upon the affliction of your slave girl and actually remember me, and you will not forget your slave girl and actually give to your slave girl a male offspring, I will give him to Jehovah all the days of his life, and no razor will come upon his head.”

12 And it occurred that while she prayed extendedly before Jehovah, E′li was watching her mouth. 13 As for Han′nah, she was speaking in her heart; only her lips were quivering, and her voice was not heard. But E′li took her for drunk. 14 So E′li said to her: “How long will you behave drunk? Put away your wine from upon you.” 15 At this Han′nah answered and said: “No, my lord! A woman hard pressed in spirit I am; and wine and intoxicating liquor I have not drunk, but I pour out my soul before Jehovah. 16 Do not make your slave girl like a good-for-nothing woman, for it is out of the abundance of my concern and my vexation that I have spoken until now.” 17 Then E′li answered and said: “Go in peace, and may the God of Israel grant your petition that you have asked of him.” 18 To this she said: “Let your maidservant find favor in your eyes.” And the woman proceeded to go on her way and to eat, and her face became self-concerned no more.

19 Then they got up early in the morning and prostrated themselves before Jehovah, after which they returned and came into their house at Ra′mah. El·ka′nah now had intercourse with Han′nah his wife, and Jehovah began remembering her. 20 So it came about at the rolling around of a year that Han′nah became pregnant and brought a son to birth and proceeded to call his name Samuel, because, said she, “it is from Jehovah that I have asked him.”

21 In time the man El·ka′nah went up with all his household to sacrifice to Jehovah the yearly sacrifice and his vow offering. 22 As for Han′nah, she did not go up, for she had said to her husband: “As soon as the boy is weaned, I must bring him, and he must appear before Jehovah and dwell there to time indefinite.” 23 At this El·ka′nah her husband said to her: “Do what is good in your eyes. Stay at home until you wean him. Only may Jehovah carry out his word.” So the woman stayed at home and kept nursing her son until she weaned him.

24 Accordingly just as soon as she had weaned him, she brought him up with her, along with a three-year-old bull and one e′phah of flour and a large jar of wine, and she proceeded to enter the house of Jehovah in Shi′loh. And the boy was with her. 25 Then they slaughtered the bull and brought the boy to E′li. 26 With that she said: “Excuse me, my lord! By the life of your soul, my lord, I am the woman that was standing with you in this place to pray to Jehovah. 27 It was with reference to this boy that I prayed that Jehovah should grant me my petition that I asked of him. 28 And I, in my turn, have lent him to Jehovah. All the days that he does happen to be, he is one requested for Jehovah.”

And he proceeded to bow down there to Jehovah.

1 Samuel

3 All the while the boy Samuel was ministering to Jehovah before E′li, and word from Jehovah had become rare in those days; there was no vision being spread abroad.

2 Now it came about on that day that E′li was lying in his place, and his eyes had begun to grow dim; he was not able to see. 3 And the lamp of God was not yet extinguished, and Samuel was lying in the temple of Jehovah, where the ark of God was. 4 And Jehovah proceeded to call Samuel. At this he said: “Here I am.” 5 And he went running to E′li and saying: “Here I am, for you called me.” But he said: “I did not call. Lie down again.” So he went and lay down. 6 And Jehovah went on to call yet again: “Samuel!” At this Samuel got up and went to E′li and said: “Here I am, for you did call me.” But he said: “I did not call, my son. Lie down again.” 7 (As regards Samuel, he had not yet come to know Jehovah, and the word of Jehovah had not yet begun to be revealed to him.) 8 So Jehovah called again for the third time: “Samuel!” At that he got up and went to E′li and said: “Here I am, for you must have called me.”

And E′li began to discern that it was Jehovah that was calling the boy. 9 Consequently E′li said to Samuel: “Go, lie down, and it must occur that, if he should call you, you must say, ‘Speak, Jehovah, for your servant is listening.’” So Samuel went and lay down in his place.

10 Then Jehovah came and took his position and called as at the other times: “Samuel, Samuel!” At this Samuel said: “Speak, for your servant is listening.” 11 And Jehovah went on to say to Samuel: “Look! I am doing something in Israel which if anyone hears about, both his ears will tingle. 12 On that day I shall carry out toward E′li all that I have said respecting his house, from beginning to end. 13 And you must tell him that I am judging his house to time indefinite for the error that he has known, because his sons are calling down evil upon God, and he has not rebuked them. 14 And that is why I have sworn to the house of E′li that the error of the house of E′li will not be brought to exemption from punishment by sacrifice or by offering to time indefinite.”

15 And Samuel continued lying down until the morning. Then he opened the doors of Jehovah’s house. And Samuel was afraid to tell E′li of the appearing. 16 But E′li called Samuel and said: “Samuel, my son!” At this he said: “Here I am.” 17 And he went on to say: “What is the word that he has spoken to you? Do not, please, hide it from me. May God do so to you and so may he add to it if you should hide from me a word of all the word that he has spoken to you.” 18 So Samuel told him all the words, and he did not hide anything from him. At that he said: “It is Jehovah. What is good in his eyes let him do.”

19 And Samuel continued growing up, and Jehovah himself proved to be with him and did not cause any of all his words to fall to the earth. 20 And all Israel from Dan to Be′er-she′ba became aware that Samuel was one accredited for the position of prophet to Jehovah. 21 And Jehovah proceeded to appear again in Shi′loh, because Jehovah revealed himself to Samuel in Shi′loh by the word of Jehovah.

1 Samuel

11 And Na′hash the Am′mon·ite proceeded to go up and camp against Ja′besh in Gil′e·ad. At that all the men of Ja′besh said to Na′hash: “Conclude a covenant with us that we may serve you.” 2 Then Na′hash the Am′mon·ite said to them: “On this condition I shall conclude it with YOU, on the condition of boring out every right eye of YOURS, and I must put it as a reproach upon all Israel.” 3 In turn the older men of Ja′besh said to him: “Give us seven days’ time, and we will send messengers into all the territory of Israel and, if there is no savior of us, we must then go out to you.” 4 In time the messengers came to Gib′e·ah of Saul and spoke the words in the ears of the people, and all the people began raising their voice and weeping.

5 But here is Saul coming after the herd from the field, and Saul proceeded to say: “What is the matter with the people, that they should weep?” And they began relating to him the words of the men of Ja′besh. 6 And the spirit of God became operative upon Saul on his hearing these words, and his anger got very hot. 7 So he took a pair of bulls and cut them in pieces and sent these into all the territory of Israel by the hand of the messengers, saying: “Whoever of us is not going out as a follower of Saul and of Samuel, this is the way it will be done to his cattle!” And the dread of Jehovah began to fall upon the people so that they came out as one man. 8 Then he took the sum of them in Be′zek, and the sons of Israel amounted to three hundred thousand, and the men of Judah thirty thousand. 9 They now said to the messengers that had come: “This is what YOU will say to the men of Ja′besh in Gil′e·ad, ‘Tomorrow salvation will take place for YOU when the sun gets hot.’” With that the messengers came and told the men of Ja′besh, and they gave way to rejoicing. 10 Accordingly the men of Ja′besh said: “Tomorrow we shall come out to YOU people, and YOU must do to us in harmony with all that is good in YOUR eyes.”

11 And it came about on the next day that Saul proceeded to put the people into three bands; and they made their way into the middle of the camp during the morning watch and went striking down the Am′mon·ites till the day grew hot. When there proved to be some that were left over, then they were sent scattering and there were not left over among them two together. 12 And the people began to say to Samuel: “Who is it saying, ‘Saul—is he to be king over us?’ GIVE the men over, that we may put them to death.” 13 However, Saul said: “Not a man should be put to death on this day, because today Jehovah has performed salvation in Israel.”

14 Later Samuel said to the people: “Come and let us go to Gil′gal that we may there make the kingship anew.” 15 So all the people went to Gil′gal, and there they proceeded to make Saul king before Jehovah in Gil′gal. Then they rendered up communion sacrifices there before Jehovah, and there Saul and all the men of Israel continued rejoicing to a great degree.

1 Samuel

13 Saul was [?] years old when he began to reign, and for two years he reigned over Israel. 2 And Saul proceeded to choose for himself three thousand men out of Israel; and two thousand came to be with Saul at Mich′mash and in the mountainous region of Beth′el, and a thousand proved to be with Jon′a·than at Gib′e·ah of Benjamin, and the rest of the people he sent away, each one to his tent. 3 Then Jon′a·than struck down the garrison of the Phi·lis′tines that was in Ge′ba; and the Phi·lis′tines got to hear of it. As for Saul, he had the horn blown throughout all the land, saying: “Let the Hebrews hear!” 4 And all Israel itself heard tell: “Saul has struck down a garrison of the Phi·lis′tines, and now Israel has become foul-smelling among the Phi·lis′tines.” So the people were called together to follow Saul to Gil′gal.

5 And the Phi·lis′tines, for their part, collected themselves together to fight against Israel, thirty thousand war chariots and six thousand horsemen and people like the grains of sand that are upon the seashore for multitude; and they went their way up and began camping in Mich′mash to the east of Beth-a′ven. 6 And the men of Israel themselves saw that they were in sore straits, because the people were hard pressed; and the people went hiding themselves in the caves and the hollows and the crags and the vaults and the waterpits. 7 Hebrews even crossed the Jordan to the land of Gad and Gil′e·ad. But Saul himself was yet in Gil′gal, and all the people trembled while following him. 8 And he continued waiting for seven days to the appointed time that Samuel had said; and Samuel did not come to Gil′gal, and the people were scattering from him. 9 Finally Saul said: “BRING near to me the burnt sacrifice and the communion sacrifices.” With that he went offering up the burnt sacrifice.

10 And it came about that as soon as he had finished offering up the burnt sacrifice, why, there was Samuel coming in. So Saul went out to meet him and bless him. 11 Then Samuel said: “What is it you have done?” To this Saul said: “I saw that the people had been dispersed from me, and you—you did not come within the appointed days, and the Phi·lis′tines were being collected together at Mich′mash, 12 so I said to myself, ‘Now the Phi·lis′tines will come down against me at Gil′gal, and the face of Jehovah I have not softened.’ So I compelled myself and went offering up the burnt sacrifice.”

13 At this Samuel said to Saul: “You have acted foolishly. You have not kept the commandment of Jehovah your God that he commanded you, because, if you had, Jehovah would have made your kingdom firm over Israel to time indefinite. 14 And now your kingdom will not last. Jehovah will certainly find for himself a man agreeable to his heart; and Jehovah will commission him as a leader over his people, because you did not keep what Jehovah commanded you.”

15 Then Samuel rose and went his way up from Gil′gal to Gib′e·ah of Benjamin, and Saul proceeded to take the count of the people, those yet found with him, about six hundred men. 16 And Saul and Jon′a·than his son and the people yet found with them were dwelling in Ge′ba of Benjamin. As for the Phi·lis′tines, they had encamped in Mich′mash. 17 And the force of pillagers would sally forth from the camp of the Phi·lis′tines in three bands. The one band would turn to the road to Oph′rah, to the land of Shu′al, 18 and the other band would turn to the road of Beth-ho′ron, and the third band would turn to the road to the boundary that looks toward the valley of Ze·bo′im, toward the wilderness.

19 Now there was not a smith to be found in all the land of Israel, because the Phi·lis′tines had said: “That the Hebrews may not make a sword or a spear.” 20 And all the Israelites would go down to the Phi·lis′tines to get each one his plowshare or his mattock or his ax or his sickle sharpened. 21 And the price for sharpening proved to be a pim for the plowshares and for the mattocks and for the three-toothed instruments and for the axes and for fixing fast the oxgoad. 22 And it happened on the day of battle that not a sword or a spear was found in the hand of any of the people that were with Saul and Jon′a·than; but there could be found one belonging to Saul and to Jon′a·than his son.

23 Now an outpost of the Phi·lis′tines would sally forth to the ravine pass of Mich′mash.

1 Samuel

14 And it came about one day that Jon′a·than the son of Saul proceeded to say to the attendant carrying his weapons: “Do come and let us cross over to the outpost of the Phi·lis′tines who are across over there.” But to his father he did not tell it. 2 And Saul was dwelling at the outskirts of Gib′e·ah under the pomegranate tree that is in Mig′ron; and the people that were with him were about six hundred men. 3 (And A·hi′jah the son of A·hi′tub, the brother of Ich′a·bod, the son of Phin′e·has, the son of E′li, the priest of Jehovah in Shi′loh, was carrying the eph′od.) And the people themselves did not know that Jon′a·than had gone. 4 Now between the passages that Jon′a·than looked for to cross over against the outpost of the Phi·lis′tines there was a toothlike crag here on this side and a toothlike crag there on that side, and the name of the one was Bo′zez and the name of the other was Se′neh. 5 The one tooth was a pillar on the north facing Mich′mash, and the other was on the south facing Ge′ba.

6 So Jon′a·than said to the attendant, his armor-bearer: “Do come and let us cross over to the outpost of these uncircumcised men. Perhaps Jehovah will work for us, for there is no hindrance to Jehovah to save by many or by few.” 7 At this his armor-bearer said to him: “Do whatever is in your heart. Turn where you wish to. Here I am with you in accord with your heart.” 8 Then Jon′a·than said: “Here we are crossing over to the men, and let us expose ourselves to them. 9 If this is the way they should say to us, ‘Stand still until we make contact with YOU!’ we must then stand where we are, and we should not go on up to them. 10 But if this is the way they should say, ‘Come up against us!’ we must then go up, because Jehovah will certainly give them into our hand, and this is for us the sign.”

11 With that the two of them exposed themselves to the outpost of the Phi·lis′tines. And the Phi·lis′tines proceeded to say: “Here are the Hebrews coming out from the holes where they have hidden themselves.” 12 So the men of the outpost answered Jon′a·than and his armor-bearer and said: “Come on up to us, and we will let YOU know a thing!” At once Jon′a·than said to his armor-bearer: “Come up after me, because Jehovah will certainly give them into the hand of Israel.” 13 And Jon′a·than kept going up on his hands and his feet, and his armor-bearer after him; and they began to fall before Jon′a·than, and his armor-bearer was putting them to death behind him. 14 And the first slaughter with which Jon′a·than and his armor-bearer struck them down amounted to about twenty men within about half the plowing line in an acre of field.

15 Then a trembling occurred in the camp in the field and among all the people of the outpost; and the force of pillagers trembled, even they, and the earth began quaking, and it developed into a trembling from God. 16 And the watchmen belonging to Saul in Gib′e·ah of Benjamin got to see it, and, look! the turmoil swayed this way and that.

17 And Saul proceeded to say to the people that were with him: “Take the count, please, and see who has gone out from us.” When they took the count, why, look! Jon′a·than and his armor-bearer were not there. 18 Saul now said to A·hi′jah: “Do bring the ark of the true God near!” (For the ark of the true God proved to be on that day with the sons of Israel.) 19 And it came about that while Saul was speaking to the priest, the turmoil that was in the camp of the Phi·lis′tines continued to go on, getting greater and greater. Then Saul said to the priest: “Withdraw your hand.” 20 Thus Saul and all the people that were with him were called out. So they came as far as the battle, and there the sword of each one had come to be against his fellowman; the rout was very great. 21 And the Hebrews that had come to belong to the Phi·lis′tines as formerly and that had gone up with them into the camp round about, even they too were for proving themselves to be with Israel who was with Saul and Jon′a·than. 22 All the men of Israel also that were hidden in the mountainous region of E′phra·im heard that the Phi·lis′tines had taken to flight, and they too went pursuing closely after them into the battle. 23 And Jehovah proceeded on that day to save Israel, and the battle itself passed over to Beth-a′ven.

24 And the men of Israel themselves were hard pressed on that day, and yet Saul put the people under the pledge of an oath, saying: “Cursed is the man that eats bread before the evening and until I have taken vengeance upon my enemies!” And none of the people tasted bread.

25 And all those of the land came into the woods, when honey happened to be over the surface of the field. 26 When the people came into the woods, why, look! there was a dripping of honey, but there was no one putting his hand to his mouth, because the people were afraid of the oath. 27 As for Jon′a·than, he had not been listening when his father put the people under an oath, so he stretched out the tip of the rod that was in his hand and dipped it into the honeycomb and drew his hand back to his mouth, and his eyes began to beam. 28 At this one of the people answered and said: “Your father solemnly put the people under oath, saying, ‘Cursed is the man that eats bread today!’” (And the people began to get tired.) 29 However, Jon′a·than said: “My father has brought ostracism upon the land. SEE, please, how my eyes have beamed because I tasted this little bit of honey. 30 How much more so if the people had but eaten today from the spoil of their enemies that they found! For now the slaughter upon the Phi·lis′tines has not been great.”

31 And on that day they kept striking down the Phi·lis′tines from Mich′mash to Ai′ja·lon, and the people got to be very tired. 32 And the people began darting greedily at the spoil and taking sheep and cattle and calves and slaughtering them on the earth, and the people fell to eating along with the blood. 33 So they told Saul, saying: “Look! The people are sinning against Jehovah by eating along with the blood.” At this he said: “YOU have dealt treacherously. First of all, roll a great stone to me.” 34 After that Saul said: “Scatter among the people, and YOU must say to them, ‘Bring near to me, each one of YOU, his bull and, each one, his sheep, and YOU must do the slaughtering in this place and the eating, and YOU must not sin against Jehovah by eating along with the blood.’” Accordingly all the people brought near each one his bull that was in his hand that night and did the slaughtering there. 35 And Saul proceeded to build an altar to Jehovah. With it he started altar building to Jehovah.

36 Later Saul said: “Let us go down after the Phi·lis′tines by night and plunder them until the morning lightens up, and let us not leave a single one among them.” To this they said: “Anything that is good in your eyes do.” Then the priest said: “Let us approach here to the true God.” 37 And Saul began to inquire of God: “Shall I go down after the Phi·lis′tines? Will you give them into the hand of Israel?” And he did not answer him on that day. 38 So Saul said: “Come near here, all YOU keymen of the people, and ascertain and see in what way this sin has come to be today. 39 For as Jehovah, who is the Deliverer of Israel, is alive, even if it is in Jon′a·than my son, yet he will positively die.” But there was no one answering him out of all the people. 40 And he went on to say to all Israel: “YOU yourselves will come to be on the one side, and I and Jon′a·than my son—we will come to be on the other side.” At this the people said to Saul: “What is good in your eyes do.”

41 And Saul proceeded to say to Jehovah: “O God of Israel, do give Thum′mim!” Then Jon′a·than and Saul were taken, and the people themselves went out. 42 Saul now said: “CAST lots to decide between me and Jon′a·than my son.” And Jon′a·than got to be taken. 43 Then Saul said to Jon′a·than: “Do tell me, What have you done?” So Jon′a·than told him and said: “I did for a fact taste a little honey on the tip of the rod that is in my hand. Here I am! Let me die!”

44 At this Saul said: “Thus may God do and thus may he add to it, if you do not positively die, Jon′a·than.” 45 But the people said to Saul: “Is Jon′a·than to die, who has performed this great salvation in Israel? It is unthinkable! As Jehovah is alive, not as much as a single hair of his head will fall to the earth; for it was with God that he worked this day.” With that the people redeemed Jon′a·than, and he did not die.

46 So Saul withdrew from following the Phi·lis′tines, and the Phi·lis′tines themselves went to their place.

47 And Saul himself took the kingship over Israel and went warring round about against all his enemies, against Mo′ab and against the sons of Am′mon and against E′dom and against the kings of Zo′bah and against the Phi·lis′tines; and wherever he would turn he administered condemnation. 48 And he went on acting valiantly and proceeded to strike down Am′a·lek and to deliver Israel out of the hand of their pillager.

49 And the sons of Saul came to be Jon′a·than and Ish′vi and Mal′chi-shu′a, and, as for the names of his two daughters, the name of the one born first was Me′rab and the name of the younger one Mi′chal. 50 And the name of Saul’s wife was A·hin′o·am the daughter of A·him′a·az, and the name of the chief of his army was Ab′ner the son of Ner, the uncle of Saul. 51 And Kish was the father of Saul, and Ner the father of Ab′ner was the son of A·bi′el.

52 And the warfare continued heavy against the Phi·lis′tines all the days of Saul. When Saul saw any mighty man or any valiant person, he would gather him to himself.

1 Samuel

15 Then Samuel said to Saul: “It was I whom Jehovah sent to anoint you as king over his people Israel, and now listen to the voice of the words of Jehovah. 2 This is what Jehovah of armies has said, ‘I must call to account what Am′a·lek did to Israel when he set himself against him in the way while he was coming up out of Egypt. 3 Now go, and you must strike down Am′a·lek and devote him to destruction with all that he has, and you must not have compassion upon him, and you must put them to death, man as well as woman, child as well as suckling, bull as well as sheep, camel as well as ass.’” 4 Accordingly Saul summoned the people and took the count of them in Te·la′im, two hundred thousand men on foot and ten thousand men of Judah.

5 And Saul proceeded to come as far as the city of Am′a·lek and to lie in ambush by the torrent valley. 6 Meanwhile Saul said to the Ken′ites: “GO, DEPART, GO DOWN from the midst of the A·mal′ek·ites, that I may not sweep you away with them. As for you, you exercised loving-kindness with all the sons of Israel at the time of their coming up out of Egypt.” So the Ken′ites departed from the midst of Am′a·lek. 7 After that Saul went striking down Am′a·lek from Hav′i·lah as far as Shur, which is in front of Egypt. 8 And he got to catch A′gag the king of Am′a·lek alive, and all the other people he devoted to destruction with the edge of the sword. 9 But Saul and the people had compassion upon A′gag and upon the best of the flock and the herd and the fat ones and upon the rams and upon all that was good, and they did not wish to devote them to destruction. As for all the goods that were despicable and rejected, these they devoted to destruction.

10 The word of Jehovah now came to Samuel, saying: 11 “I do regret that I have caused Saul to reign as king, because he has turned back from following me, and my words he has not carried out.” And it was distressing to Samuel, and he kept crying out to Jehovah all night long. 12 Then Samuel got up early to meet Saul in the morning. But report was made to Samuel, saying: “Saul came to Car′mel, and, look! he was erecting a monument for himself, and he then turned around and went across and descended to Gil′gal.” 13 At length Samuel came to Saul, and Saul began to say to him: “Blessed are you of Jehovah. I have carried out the word of Jehovah.” 14 But Samuel said: “Then what does this sound of the flock in my ears mean, and the sound of the herd that I am hearing?” 15 To this Saul said: “From the A·mal′ek·ites they have brought them, because the people had compassion upon the best of the flock and of the herd, for the purpose of sacrificing to Jehovah your God; but what was left over we have devoted to destruction.” 16 At this Samuel said to Saul: “Stop! And I will tell you what Jehovah spoke to me last night.” So he said to him: “Speak!”

17 And Samuel went on to say: “Was it not when you were little in your own eyes that you were head of the tribes of Israel, and Jehovah proceeded to anoint you as king over Israel? 18 Later Jehovah sent you on a mission and said, ‘Go, and you must devote the sinners, the A·mal′ek·ites, to destruction, and you must fight against them until you will have exterminated them.’ 19 So why is it you did not obey the voice of Jehovah but went darting greedily at the spoil and doing what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah?”

20 However, Saul said to Samuel: “But I have obeyed the voice of Jehovah in that I went on the mission on which Jehovah had sent me and I brought A′gag the king of Am′a·lek, but Am′a·lek I have devoted to destruction. 21 And the people went taking from the spoil sheep and cattle, the choicest of them as something devoted to destruction, to sacrifice to Jehovah your God in Gil′gal.”

22 In turn Samuel said: “Does Jehovah have as much delight in burnt offerings and sacrifices as in obeying the voice of Jehovah? Look! To obey is better than a sacrifice, to pay attention than the fat of rams; 23 for rebelliousness is the same as the sin of divination, and pushing ahead presumptuously the same as using uncanny power and teraphim. Since you have rejected the word of Jehovah, he accordingly rejects you from being king.”

24 Then Saul said to Samuel: “I have sinned; for I have overstepped the order of Jehovah and your words, because I feared the people and so obeyed their voice. 25 And now, please, pardon my sin and return with me that I may prostrate myself to Jehovah.” 26 But Samuel said to Saul: “I shall not return with you, for you have rejected the word of Jehovah, and Jehovah rejects you from continuing as king over Israel.” 27 As Samuel was turning about to go, he immediately grabbed hold of the skirt of his sleeveless coat, but it ripped away. 28 At this Samuel said to him: “Jehovah has ripped away the royal rule of Israel from off you today, and he will certainly give it to a fellowman of yours who is better than you. 29 And, besides, the Excellency of Israel will not prove false, and He will not feel regrets, for He is not an earthling man so as to feel regrets.”

30 At this he said: “I have sinned. Now honor me, please, in front of the older men of my people and in front of Israel and return with me, and I shall certainly prostrate myself to Jehovah your God.” 31 So Samuel returned behind Saul, and Saul proceeded to prostrate himself to Jehovah. 32 After that Samuel said: “BRING A′gag the king of Am′a·lek near to me.” Then A′gag went to him reluctantly, and A′gag began to say to himself: “Truly the bitter experience of death has departed.” 33 However, Samuel said: “Just as your sword has bereaved women of children, in that way your mother will be most bereaved of children among women.” With that Samuel went hacking A′gag to pieces before Jehovah in Gil′gal.

34 Samuel now went his way to Ra′mah, and Saul, for his part, went up to his own house at Gib′e·ah of Saul. 35 And Samuel did not see Saul again until the day of his death, because Samuel had gone into mourning for Saul. As for Jehovah, he regretted that he had made Saul king over Israel.

1 Samuel

18 And it came about that, as soon as he had finished speaking to Saul, Jon′a·than’s very soul became bound up with the soul of David, and Jon′a·than began to love him as his own soul. 2 Then Saul took him on that day, and he did not allow him to return to his father’s house. 3 And Jon′a·than and David proceeded to conclude a covenant, because of his loving him as his own soul. 4 Further, Jon′a·than stripped himself of the sleeveless coat that was on him and gave it to David, and also his garments, and even his sword and his bow and his belt. 5 And David began going out. Wherever Saul would send him he would act prudently, so that Saul placed him over the men of war; and it seemed good in the eyes of all the people and also in the eyes of the servants of Saul.

6 And it came about that at their coming in, when David returned from striking the Phi·lis′tines down, the women began coming out from all the cities of Israel with song and dances to meet Saul the king, with tambourines, with rejoicing and with lutes. 7 And the women that were celebrating kept responding and saying:

“Saul has struck down his thousands,

And David his tens of thousands.”

8 And Saul began to be very angry, and this saying was bad from his viewpoint, so that he said: “They have given David tens of thousands, but to me they have given the thousands, and there is yet only the kingship to give him!” 9 And Saul was continually looking suspiciously at David from that day forward.

10 And it came about the next day that God’s bad spirit became operative upon Saul, so that he behaved like a prophet within the house, while David was playing music with his hand, as in former days; and the spear was in Saul’s hand. 11 And Saul proceeded to hurl the spear and say: “I will pin David even to the wall!” but David turned aside from before him, twice. 12 And Saul grew afraid of David because Jehovah proved to be with him, but from Saul he had departed. 13 Consequently Saul removed him from his company and appointed him as chief of a thousand for him; and he regularly went out and came in before the people. 14 And David was continually acting prudently in all his ways, and Jehovah was with him. 15 And Saul kept seeing that he was acting very prudently, so that he was scared of him. 16 And all Israel and Judah were lovers of David, because he was going out and coming in before them.

17 Finally Saul said to David: “Here is my oldest daughter Me′rab. She is the one that I shall give you as a wife. Only prove yourself a valiant person to me and fight the wars of Jehovah.” But as for Saul, he said to himself: “Do not let my hand come to be upon him, but let the hand of the Phi·lis′tines come to be upon him.” 18 At this David said to Saul: “Who am I and who are my kinsfolk, my father’s family, in Israel, so that I should become son-in-law to the king?” 19 However, it came about that at the time for giving Me′rab, Saul’s daughter, to David, she herself had already been given to A′dri·el the Me·hol′ath·ite as a wife.

20 Now Mi′chal, Saul’s daughter, was in love with David, and they went reporting it to Saul, and the matter was to his liking. 21 So Saul said: “I shall give her to him that she may serve as a snare to him, and that the hand of the Phi·lis′tines may come to be upon him.” Accordingly Saul said to David: “By one of the two women you will form a marriage alliance with me today.” 22 Further, Saul commanded his servants: “Speak to David secretly, saying, ‘Look! The king has found delight in you, and all his servants themselves have fallen in love with you. So now form a marriage alliance with the king.’” 23 And the servants of Saul began to speak these words in the ears of David, but David said: “Is it an easy thing in YOUR eyes to form a marriage alliance with the king, when I am a man of little means and lightly esteemed?” 24 Then the servants of Saul reported to him, saying: “It was with words like these that David spoke.”

25 At that Saul said: “This is what YOU men will say to David, ‘The king has delight, not in marriage money, but in a hundred foreskins of the Phi·lis′tines, to avenge himself on the enemies of the king.’” But as for Saul, he had schemed to have David fall by the hand of the Phi·lis′tines. 26 So his servants reported these words to David, and the matter was to David’s liking, to form a marriage alliance with the king, and the days had not yet expired. 27 So David rose and he and his men went and struck down among the Phi·lis′tines two hundred men, and David came bringing their foreskins and giving them in full number to the king, to form a marriage alliance with the king. In turn Saul gave him Mi′chal his daughter as a wife. 28 And Saul got to see and know that Jehovah was with David. As for Mi′chal, Saul’s daughter, she loved him. 29 And again Saul felt still more fear because of David, and Saul came to be an enemy of David always.

30 And the princes of the Phi·lis′tines would go out, and it would happen that as often as they went out David acted most prudently of all the servants of Saul; and his name came to be very precious.

1 Samuel

20 And David went running away from Nai′oth in Ra′mah. However, he came and said in front of Jon′a·than: “What have I done? What is my error, and what sin have I committed before your father, for he is seeking for my soul?” 2 At this he said to him: “It is unthinkable! You will not die. Look! My father will not do a big thing or a little thing and not disclose it to my ear; and for what reason should my father conceal this matter from me? This does not happen.” 3 But David swore in addition and said: “Your father must surely know that I have found favor in your eyes, and so would say, ‘Do not let Jon′a·than know this for fear he may feel hurt.’ But, in fact, as Jehovah is living and as your soul is living, there is just about a step between me and death!”

4 And Jon′a·than went on to say to David: “Whatever your soul may say I shall do for you.” 5 At this David said to Jon′a·than: “Look! Tomorrow is new moon, and I myself ought, without fail, to be sitting with the king to eat; and you must send me away, and I must conceal myself in the field until the evening on the third day. 6 If your father should miss me at all, then you must say, ‘David earnestly asked leave of absence of me to run to Beth′le·hem his city, because there is a yearly sacrifice there for all the family.’ 7 If the way he should say is, ‘It is all right!’ it means peace to your servant. But if he should at all become angry, know that what is bad has been determined upon by him. 8 And you must render loving-kindness toward your servant, for it is into a covenant of Jehovah that you have brought your servant with you. But if there is error in me, put me to death yourself, since why should it be to your father that you should bring me?”

9 To this Jon′a·than said: “That is unthinkable respecting you! But if I should at all get to know that evil has been determined upon by my father to come upon you, shall I not tell it to you?” 10 Then David said to Jon′a·than: “Who will tell me whether what your father may answer you is harsh?” 11 In turn Jon′a·than said to David: “Just come, and let us go out into the field.” So both of them went out into the field. 12 And Jon′a·than went on to say to David: “Jehovah the God of Israel be a witness that I shall sound out my father about this time tomorrow, or the third day, and if he is well-disposed toward David, shall I not then send to you and certainly disclose it to your ear? 13 So may Jehovah do to Jon′a·than and so may he add to it, if, in case it should seem good to my father to do evil against you, I do not indeed disclose it to your ear and send you away, and you do not certainly go in peace. And may Jehovah prove to be with you, just as he proved to be with my father. 14 And will you not, if I shall be still alive, yes, will you not exercise the loving-kindness of Jehovah toward me, that I may not die? 15 And you will not cut off your own loving-kindness from being with my household to time indefinite. Nor, when Jehovah cuts off the enemies of David, every one from the surface of the ground, 16 will the name of Jon′a·than be cut off from the house of David. And Jehovah must require it at the hand of David’s enemies.” 17 So Jon′a·than swore again to David because of his love for him; for as he loved his own soul he loved him.

18 And Jon′a·than went on to say to him: “Tomorrow is new moon, and you will certainly be missed, because your seat will be vacant. 19 And certainly on the third day you will be missed very much; and you must come to the place where you concealed yourself on the working day, and you must dwell near this stone here. 20 And as for me, I shall shoot three arrows to one side of it, to send them where I will to a target. 21 And, look! I shall send the attendant, saying, ‘Go, find the arrows.’ If I should specifically say to the attendant, ‘Look! The arrows are on this side of you, take them,’ then you come, for it means peace for you and there is nothing the matter, as Jehovah is living. 22 But if this is the way I should say to the lad, ‘Look! The arrows are farther away from you,’ go, for Jehovah has sent you away. 23 And as for the word that we have spoken, I and you, why, may Jehovah be between me and you to time indefinite.”

24 And David proceeded to conceal himself in the field. And it came to be new moon, and the king took his seat at the meal to eat. 25 And the king was sitting in his seat as at other times, in the seat by the wall; and Jon′a·than was facing him, and Ab′ner was sitting at Saul’s side, but David’s place was vacant. 26 And Saul did not say anything at all on that day, for he said to himself: “Something has happened so that he is not clean, for he has not been cleansed.” 27 And it came about the day after the new moon, on the second day, that David’s place continued vacant. At this Saul said to Jon′a·than his son: “Why has not the son of Jes′se come to the meal either yesterday or today?” 28 So Jon′a·than answered Saul: “David earnestly asked leave of absence from me to go to Beth′le·hem. 29 And he went on to say, ‘Send me away, please, because we have a family sacrifice in the city, and it was my own brother that commanded me. So now, if I have found favor in your eyes, let me slip away, please, that I may see my brothers.’ That is why he has not come to the king’s table.” 30 Then Saul’s anger grew hot against Jon′a·than and he said to him: “You son of a rebellious maid, do I not well know that you are choosing the son of Jes′se to your own shame and to the shame of the secret parts of your mother? 31 For all the days that the son of Jes′se is alive on the ground, you and your kingship will not be firmly established. So now send and fetch him to me, for he is destined for death.”

32 However, Jon′a·than answered Saul his father and said to him: “Why should he be put to death? What has he done?” 33 At that Saul went hurling the spear at him to strike him; and Jon′a·than came to know that it had been determined upon by his father to put David to death. 34 Immediately Jon′a·than rose up from the table in the heat of anger, and he did not eat bread on the second day after the new moon, for he had been hurt respecting David, because his own father had humiliated him.

35 And it came about in the morning that Jon′a·than made his way out to the field of David’s appointed place, and a young attendant was with him. 36 And he proceeded to say to his attendant: “Run, please, find the arrows that I am shooting.” The attendant ran, and he himself shot the arrow to make it pass beyond him. 37 When the attendant came as far as the place of the arrow that Jon′a·than had shot, Jon′a·than began to call from behind the attendant and say: “Is not the arrow farther away from you?” 38 And Jon′a·than went on calling from behind the attendant: “In haste! Act quickly! Do not stand still!” And the attendant of Jon′a·than went picking up the arrows and then came to his master. 39 As for the attendant, he did not know anything; only Jon′a·than and David themselves knew about the matter. 40 After that Jon′a·than gave his weapons to the attendant that belonged to him and he said to him: “Go, take them to the city.”

41 The attendant went. As for David, he rose up from nearby to the south. Then he fell on his face to the earth and bowed three times; and they began kissing each other and weeping for each other, until David had done it the most. 42 And Jon′a·than went on to say to David: “Go in peace, since we have sworn, both of us, in the name of Jehovah, saying, ‘May Jehovah himself prove to be between me and you and between my offspring and your offspring to time indefinite.’”

Accordingly David rose up and went his way, and Jon′a·than himself came into the city.

1 Samuel

21 Later David came into Nob to A·him′e·lech the priest; and A·him′e·lech began to tremble at meeting David and then said to him: “Why is it you are by yourself, and no one is with you?” 2 At this David said to A·him′e·lech the priest: “The king himself commanded me as to a matter, and he went on to say to me, ‘Let no one know anything at all of the matter concerning which I am sending you and concerning which I have commanded you.’ And I have made an appointment with the young men for such and such a place. 3 And now, if there are five loaves of bread at your disposal, just give them into my hand, or whatever may be found.” 4 But the priest answered David and said: “There is no ordinary bread under my hand, but there is holy bread; provided that the young men have at least kept themselves from womankind.” 5 So David answered the priest and said to him: “But womankind has been kept away from us the same as formerly when I went out, and the organisms of the young men continue holy, although the mission itself is ordinary. And how much more so today, when one becomes holy in his organism?” 6 At that the priest gave him what was holy, because there happened to be no bread there but the showbread that had been removed from before Jehovah so as to place fresh bread there on the day of its being taken away.

7 Now one of Saul’s servants was there on that day, detained before Jehovah, and his name was Do′eg the E′dom·ite, the principal one of the shepherds that belonged to Saul.

8 And David went on to say to A·him′e·lech: “And is there nothing here at your disposal, a spear or a sword? For neither my own sword nor my weapons did I take in my hand, because the king’s matter proved to be urgent.” 9 To this the priest said: “The sword of Go·li′ath the Phi·lis′tine, whom you struck down in the low plain of E′lah—here it is, wrapped up in a mantle, behind the eph′od. If it is what you would take for yourself, take it, because there is no other here except it.” And David went on to say: “There is none like it. Give it to me.”

10 Then David rose up and continued running away on account of Saul on that day, and at length came to A′chish the king of Gath. 11 And the servants of A′chish began to say to him: “Is not this David the king of the land? Was it not to this one that they kept responding with dances, saying,

‘Saul has struck down his thousands,

And David his tens of thousands’?”

12 And David began to take these words to his heart, and he became very much afraid on account of A′chish the king of Gath. 13 So he disguised his sanity under their eyes and began acting insane in their hand and kept making cross marks on the doors of the gate and let his saliva run down upon his beard. 14 Finally A′chish said to his servants: “Here YOU see a man behaving crazy. Why should YOU bring him to me? 15 Am I in need of people driven crazy, so that YOU have brought this one to behave crazy by me? Should this one come into my home?”

1 Samuel

22 So David proceeded to go from there and escape to the cave of A·dul′lam; and his brothers and the entire house of his father got to hear of it and made their way down there to him. 2 And all men in distress and all men who had a creditor and all men bitter in soul began to collect together to him, and he came to be a chief over them; and there came to be with him about four hundred men.

3 Later David went from there to Miz′peh in Mo′ab and said to the king of Mo′ab: “Let my father and my mother, please, dwell with YOU people until I know what God will do to me.” 4 Accordingly he settled them before the king of Mo′ab, and they continued dwelling with him all the days that David happened to be in the inaccessible place.

5 In time Gad the prophet said to David: “You must not keep dwelling in the inaccessible place. Go away, and you must come yourself into the land of Judah.” Hence David went away and came into the forest of He′reth.

6 And Saul got to hear that David and the men that were with him had been discovered, while Saul was sitting in Gib′e·ah under the tamarisk tree on the high place with his spear in his hand and all his servants stationed about him. 7 Then Saul said to his servants stationed about him: “Listen, please, YOU Ben′ja·min·ites. Will the son of Jes′se also give to all of YOU fields and vineyards? Will he appoint all of YOU chiefs of thousands and chiefs of hundreds? 8 For YOU have conspired, all of YOU, against me; and there is no one disclosing it to my ear when my own son concludes a covenant with the son of Jes′se, and there is no one of YOU having sympathy for me and disclosing to my ear that my own son has raised up my own servant against me as a lier in ambush the way it is this day.”

9 At this Do′eg the E′dom·ite, being stationed as he was over the servants of Saul, answered and said: “I saw the son of Jes′se come to Nob to A·him′e·lech the son of A·hi′tub. 10 And he proceeded to inquire of Jehovah for him; and provisions he gave him, and the sword of Go·li′ath the Phi·lis′tine he gave him.” 11 At once the king sent to call A·him′e·lech the son of A·hi′tub the priest and all the house of his father, the priests that were in Nob. So all of them came to the king.

12 Saul now said: “Listen, please, you son of A·hi′tub!” to which he said: “Here I am, my lord.” 13 And Saul went on to say to him: “Why have YOU men conspired against me, you and the son of Jes′se, by your giving him bread and a sword, and there being an inquiry of God for him, to rise up against me as a lier in ambush the way it is this day?” 14 At this A·him′e·lech answered the king and said: “And who among all your servants is like David, faithful, and the son-in-law of the king and a chief over your bodyguard and honored in your house? 15 Is it today that I have started to inquire of God for him? It is unthinkable on my part! Do not let the king lay anything against his servant and against the entire house of my father, for in all this your servant did not know a thing small or great.”

16 But the king said: “You will positively die, A·him′e·lech, you with all the house of your father.” 17 With that the king said to the runners stationed about him: “Turn and put to death the priests of Jehovah, because their hand also is with David and because they knew that he was a runaway and they did not disclose it to my ear!” And the servants of the king did not want to thrust out their hand to assault the priests of Jehovah. 18 Finally the king said to Do′eg: “You turn and assault the priests!” Immediately Do′eg the E′dom·ite turned and himself assaulted the priests and put to death on that day eighty-five men bearing an eph′od of linen. 19 Even Nob the city of the priests he struck with the edge of the sword, man as well as woman, child as well as suckling and bull and ass and sheep with the edge of the sword.

20 However, one son of A·him′e·lech the son of A·hi′tub, whose name was A·bi′a·thar, made his escape and went running away to follow David. 21 Then A·bi′a·thar told David: “Saul has killed the priests of Jehovah.” 22 At this David said to A·bi′a·thar: “I well knew on that day, because Do′eg the E′dom·ite was there, that he would without fail tell Saul. I personally have wronged every soul of the house of your father. 23 Just dwell with me. Do not be afraid, for whoever looks for my soul looks for your soul, for you are one needing protection with me.”

1 Samuel

25 In time Samuel died; and all Israel proceeded to collect together and bewail him and bury him at his house in Ra′mah. Then David rose up and went down to the wilderness of Pa′ran.

2 Now there was a man in Ma′on, and his work was in Car′mel. And the man was very great, and he had three thousand sheep and a thousand goats; and he came to be engaged in shearing his sheep at Car′mel. 3 And the man’s name was Na′bal, and his wife’s name was Ab′i·gail. And the wife was good in discretion and beautiful in form, but the husband was harsh and bad in his practices; and he was a Ca′leb·ite. 4 And David got to hear in the wilderness that Na′bal was shearing his sheep. 5 So David sent ten young men and David said to the young men: “Go up to Car′mel, and YOU must come to Na′bal and ask him in my name about his welfare. 6 And this is what YOU must say to my brother, ‘May you be well and also your household be well and all that you have be well. 7 And now I have heard that you have shearers. Now the shepherds that belong to you happened themselves to be with us. We did not molest them, and nothing at all showed up missing of theirs all the days they happened to be in Car′mel. 8 Ask your own young men, and they will tell you, that my young men may find favor in your eyes, because it was upon a good day that we came. Just give, please, whatever your hand may find to your servants and to your son David.’”

9 Accordingly David’s young men came and spoke to Na′bal in accord with all these words in the name of David and then waited. 10 At this Na′bal answered David’s servants and said: “Who is David, and who is the son of Jes′se? Nowadays the servants that are breaking away, each one from before his master, have become many. 11 And do I have to take my bread and my water and my slaughtered meat that I have butchered for my shearers and give it to men of whom I do not even know from where they are?”

12 Upon that David’s young men turned around on their way and went back and came and reported to him in accord with all these words. 13 Immediately David said to his men: “Gird on every one his sword!” So they girded on every one his sword and David also girded on his own sword; and they began to go up after David, about four hundred men, while two hundred sat by the baggage.

14 Meanwhile, to Ab′i·gail, Na′bal’s wife, one of the young men reported, saying: “Look! David sent messengers from the wilderness to wish our master well, but he screamed rebukes at them. 15 And the men were very good to us, and they did not molest us, and we did not miss a single thing all the days of our walking about with them while we happened to be in the field. 16 A wall was what they proved to be around us both by night and by day, all the days that we happened to be with them, shepherding the flock. 17 And now know and see what you are going to do, for calamity has been determined against our master and against all his house, as he is too much of a good-for-nothing fellow to speak to him.”

18 At once Ab′i·gail hastened and took two hundred loaves of bread and two large jars of wine and five sheep dressed and five seah measures of roasted grain and a hundred cakes of raisins and two hundred cakes of pressed figs and put them upon the asses. 19 Then she said to her young men: “Pass on ahead of me. Look! I am coming after YOU.” But to her husband Na′bal she told nothing.

20 And it occurred that while she was riding on the ass and secretly going down the mountain, why, there were David and his men coming down to meet her. So she encountered them. 21 As for David, he had said: “It was altogether for disappointment that I guarded everything that belongs to this fellow in the wilderness and not a single thing of all that belongs to him showed up missing, and yet he repays me evil in return for good. 22 So may God do to the enemies of David and so may he add to it if I shall let anyone of all who are his that urinates against the wall remain until the morning.”

23 When Ab′i·gail caught sight of David, she at once hastened and got down off the ass and fell upon her face before David and bowed to the earth. 24 She then fell at his feet and said: “Upon me myself, O my lord, be the error; and, please, let your slave girl speak in your ears, and listen to the words of your slave girl. 25 Please, do not let my lord set his heart upon this good-for-nothing man Na′bal, for, as his name is, so is he. Na′bal is his name, and senselessness is with him. As for me your slave girl, I did not see my lord’s young men that you had sent. 26 And now, my lord, as Jehovah is living and as your soul is living, Jehovah has held you back from entering into bloodguilt and having your own hand come to your salvation. And now let your enemies and those seeking injury to my lord become like Na′bal. 27 And now as regards this gift blessing that your maidservant has brought to my lord, it must be given to the young men that are walking about in the steps of my lord. 28 Pardon, please, the transgression of your slave girl, because Jehovah will without fail make for my lord a lasting house, because the wars of Jehovah are what my lord is fighting; and as for badness, it will not be found in you throughout your days. 29 When man rises up to pursue you and look for your soul, the soul of my lord will certainly prove to be wrapped up in the bag of life with Jehovah your God; but, as for the soul of your enemies, he will sling it forth as from inside the hollow of the sling. 30 And it must occur that, because Jehovah will do to my lord the good toward you according to all that he has spoken, he certainly will commission you as leader over Israel. 31 And let this not become to you a cause for staggering or a stumbling block to the heart of my lord, both by the shedding of blood without cause and by having the hand of my lord itself come to his salvation. And Jehovah will certainly do good to my lord, and you must remember your slave girl.”

32 At this David said to Ab′i·gail: “Blessed be Jehovah the God of Israel, who has sent you this day to meet me! 33 And blessed be your sensibleness, and blessed be you who have restrained me this day from entering into bloodguilt and having my own hand come to my salvation. 34 And, on the other hand, as Jehovah the God of Israel is living, who has held me back from doing injury to you, if you had not hastened that you might come to meet me, there would certainly not have remained to Na′bal until the morning light anyone urinating against a wall.” 35 With that David accepted from her hand what she had brought him, and to her he said: “Go up in peace to your house. See, I have listened to your voice that I may have consideration for your person.”

36 Later Ab′i·gail came in to Na′bal, and there he was having a feast in his house like the feast of the king; and Na′bal’s heart was feeling good within him, and he was as drunk as could be; and she did not tell him a thing, small or great, until the morning light. 37 And it came about in the morning, when the wine had gone out of Na′bal, that his wife went telling him these things. And his heart came to be dead inside him, and he himself became as a stone. 38 After that about ten days elapsed and then Jehovah struck Na′bal, so that he died.

39 And David got to hear that Na′bal had died, and so he said: “Blessed be Jehovah, who has conducted the legal case of my reproach to free me from Na′bal’s hand and has kept his servant back from badness, and the badness of Na′bal Jehovah has turned back upon his own head!” And David proceeded to send and propose to Ab′i·gail to take her as his wife. 40 So David’s servants came to Ab′i·gail at Car′mel and spoke to her, saying: “David himself has sent us to you to take you as his wife.” 41 Immediately she rose up and bowed with her face to the earth and said: “Here is your slave girl as a maidservant to wash the feet of the servants of my lord.” 42 Then Ab′i·gail hastened and rose up and went riding on the ass with five maids of hers walking behind her; and she went accompanying the messengers of David and then became his wife.

43 David had also taken A·hin′o·am from Jez′re·el; and the women came to be, even both of them, his wives.

44 As for Saul, he had given Mi′chal his daughter, David’s wife, to Pal′ti the son of La′ish, who was from Gal′lim.

1 Samuel

26 In time the men of Ziph came to Saul at Gib′e·ah, saying: “Is not David concealing himself on the hill of Hach·i′lah, facing Je·shi′mon?” 2 And Saul proceeded to rise up and go down to the wilderness of Ziph, and with him three thousand men, the chosen ones of Israel, to look for David in the wilderness of Ziph. 3 And Saul took up camping on the hill of Hach·i′lah, which faces Je·shi′mon, by the road, while David was dwelling in the wilderness. And he got to see that Saul had come after him into the wilderness. 4 So David sent spies that he might know that Saul had for a fact come. 5 Later David rose up and went to the place where Saul had encamped, and David got to see the place where Saul had lain down, and also Ab′ner the son of Ner the chief of his army; and Saul was lying in the camp enclosure with the people camping all around him. 6 Then David answered and said to A·him′e·lech the Hit′tite and A·bish′ai the son of Ze·ru′iah, the brother of Jo′ab: “Who will go down with me to Saul into the camp?” To this A·bish′ai said: “I myself shall go down with you.” 7 And David made his way with A·bish′ai to the people by night; and, look! Saul was lying asleep in the camp enclosure with his spear stuck into the earth at his head, and Ab′ner and the people were lying all around him.

8 A·bish′ai now said to David: “God has today surrendered your enemy into your hand. And now let me, please, pin him to the earth with the spear just once, and I shall not do it to him twice.” 9 However, David said to A·bish′ai: “Do not bring him to ruin, for who is it that has thrust his hand out against the anointed of Jehovah and has remained innocent?” 10 And David went on to say: “As Jehovah is living, Jehovah himself will deal him a blow; or his day will come and he will have to die, or down into battle he will go, and he will certainly be swept away. 11 It is unthinkable, on my part, from Jehovah’s standpoint, to thrust my hand out against the anointed of Jehovah! So now take, please, the spear that is at his head and the water jug, and let us get on our way.” 12 Accordingly David took the spear and the water jug from the place at Saul’s head, and then they got on their way; and there was no one seeing nor anyone taking note nor anyone waking up, for all of them were asleep, because it was a deep sleep from Jehovah that had fallen upon them. 13 Then David passed on to the other side and stood upon the top of the mountain at a distance, the space between them being vast.

14 And David began to call out to the people and to Ab′ner the son of Ner, saying: “Will you not answer, Ab′ner?” And Ab′ner began to answer and say: “Who are you that have called out to the king?” 15 And David went on to say to Ab′ner: “Are you not a man? And who is like you in Israel? Why, then, did you not watch over your lord the king? For one of the people came in to bring the king your lord to ruin. 16 This thing that you have done is not good. As Jehovah is living, YOU men deserve to die, because YOU have not watched over YOUR lord, over the anointed of Jehovah. And now see where the king’s spear and the water jug are that were at his head.”

17 And Saul began to recognize the voice of David and to say: “Is this your voice, my son David?” To this David said: “It is my voice, my lord the king.” 18 And he added: “Why is this that my lord is chasing after his servant, for what have I done, and what badness is there in my hand? 19 And now let my lord the king, please, listen to the words of his servant: If it is Jehovah that has incited you against me, let him smell a grain offering. But if it is the sons of man, they are cursed before Jehovah, because they have driven me out today from feeling myself attached to the inheritance of Jehovah, saying, ‘Go, serve other gods!’ 20 And now do not let my blood fall to the earth before the face of Jehovah; for the king of Israel has gone out to look for a single flea, just as one chases a partridge upon the mountains.”

21 In turn Saul said: “I have sinned. Come back, my son David, for I shall no more do you injury, in view of the fact that my soul has been precious in your eyes this day. Look! I have acted foolishly and am very much mistaken.” 22 Then David answered and said: “Here is the spear of the king, and let one of the young men come on over and fetch it. 23 And Jehovah it is who will repay to each one his own righteousness and his own faithfulness, in that Jehovah today gave you into my hand, and I was unwilling to thrust my hand out against the anointed of Jehovah. 24 And, look! just as your soul was great this day in my eyes, so may my soul be great in the eyes of Jehovah, that he may deliver me out of all distress.” 25 At this Saul said to David: “Blessed may you be, my son David. Not only will you without fail work but you will also without fail come off the winner.” And David proceeded to go on his way; and as for Saul, he returned to his place.

1 Samuel

27 However, David said in his heart: “Now I shall be swept away one day by Saul’s hand. There is nothing better for me than that I should escape without fail to the land of the Phi·lis′tines; and Saul must despair of me in looking for me any longer in all the territory of Israel, and I shall certainly escape from his hand.” 2 So David rose up and he and six hundred men that were with him passed over to A′chish the son of Ma′och, the king of Gath. 3 And David continued to dwell with A′chish in Gath, he and his men, each one with his household, David and his two wives, A·hin′o·am the Jez′re·el·i·tess and Ab′i·gail, Na′bal’s wife, the Car′mel·it·ess. 4 In time report was made to Saul that David had run away to Gath, and so he did not go looking for him still another time.

5 Then David said to A′chish: “If, now, I have found favor in your eyes, let them give me a place in one of the cities of the countryside, that I may dwell there; for why should your servant dwell in the royal city with you?” 6 Accordingly A′chish gave him Zik′lag on that day. That is why Zik′lag has come to belong to the kings of Judah down to this day.

7 And the number of the days that David dwelt in the countryside of the Phi·lis′tines came to be a year and four months. 8 And David proceeded to go up with his men that they might raid the Gesh′ur·ites and the Gir′zites and the A·mal′ek·ites; for they were inhabiting the land that extended from Te′lam as far as Shur and down to the land of Egypt. 9 And David struck the land, but he preserved neither man nor woman alive; and he took flocks and herds and asses and camels and garments, after which he returned and came to A′chish. 10 Then A′chish said: “Where did YOU men make a raid today?” To this David said: “Upon the south of Judah and upon the south of the Je·rah′me·el·ites and upon the south of the Ken′ites.” 11 As for man and woman, David was not preserving any alive to bring them to Gath, saying: “That they may not tell on us, saying, ‘This is the way David did.’” (And this way has been his procedure all the days that he dwelt in the countryside of the Phi·lis′tines.) 12 Consequently A′chish believed David, saying to himself: “He has unquestionably become a stench among his people Israel; and he will have to become my servant to time indefinite.”

1 Samuel

28 And it came about in those days that the Phi·lis′tines began to collect their camps for the army to make war against Israel. So A′chish said to David: “You undoubtedly know that it is with me that you should go out into the camp, you and your men.” 2 At that David said to A′chish: “That is why you yourself know what your servant is to do.” Accordingly A′chish said to David: “That is why guardian of my head I shall appoint you always.”

3 Now Samuel himself had died, and all Israel had proceeded to bewail him and bury him in Ra′mah his own city. As for Saul, he had removed the spirit mediums and the professional foretellers of events from the land.

4 Subsequently the Phi·lis′tines collected together and came and pitched camp in Shu′nem. So Saul collected all Israel together and they pitched camp in Gil·bo′a. 5 When Saul got to see the camp of the Phi·lis′tines he became afraid, and his heart began to tremble very much. 6 Although Saul would inquire of Jehovah, Jehovah never answered him, either by dreams or by the U′rim or by the prophets. 7 Finally Saul said to his servants: “Seek for me a woman who is a mistress of spirit mediumship, and I will go to her and consult her.” Then his servants said to him: “Look! There is a woman who is a mistress of spirit mediumship in En-dor.”

8 So Saul disguised himself and clothed himself with other garments and went, he and two men with him; and they came to the woman by night. He now said: “Employ divination, please, for me by spirit mediumship and bring up for me the one whom I shall designate to you.” 9 However, the woman said to him: “Here you yourself well know what Saul did, how he cut off the spirit mediums and the professional foretellers of events from the land. Why, then, are you acting like a trapper against my soul to have me put to death?” 10 Immediately Saul swore to her by Jehovah, saying: “As Jehovah is alive, guilt for error will not befall you in this matter!” 11 At this the woman said: “Whom shall I bring up for you?” To this he said: “Bring up Samuel for me.” 12 When the woman saw “Samuel” she began crying out at the top of her voice; and the woman went on to say to Saul: “Why did you trick me, when you yourself are Saul?” 13 But the king said to her: “Do not be afraid, but what did you see?” And the woman went on to say to Saul: “A god I saw coming up out of the earth.” 14 At once he said to her: “What is his form?” to which she said: “It is an old man coming up, and he has himself covered with a sleeveless coat.” At that Saul recognized that it was “Samuel,” and he proceeded to bow low with his face to the earth and to prostrate himself.

15 And “Samuel” began to say to Saul: “Why have you disturbed me by having me brought up?” To this Saul said: “I am in very sore straits, as the Phi·lis′tines are fighting against me, and God himself has departed from me and has answered me no more, either by means of the prophets or by dreams; so that I am calling you to let me know what I shall do.”

16 And “Samuel” went on to say: “Why, then, do you inquire of me, when Jehovah himself has departed from you and proves to be your adversary? 17 And Jehovah will do for himself just as he spoke by means of me, and Jehovah will rip the kingdom away from your hand and give it to your fellowman David. 18 As you did not obey the voice of Jehovah, and you did not execute his burning anger against Am′a·lek, that is why this is the thing that Jehovah will certainly do to you this day. 19 And Jehovah will also give Israel with you into the hand of the Phi·lis′tines, and tomorrow you and your sons will be with me. Even the camp of Israel Jehovah will give into the hand of the Phi·lis′tines.”

20 At that Saul quickly fell down his full length to the earth and became very much afraid because of “Samuel’s” words. Also, there happened to be no power in him, because he had not eaten food the whole day and the whole night. 21 The woman now came to Saul and saw that he had been greatly disturbed. So she said to him: “Here your maidservant has obeyed your voice, and I proceeded to put my soul in my palm and obey the words that you spoke to me. 22 And now, please, you, in turn, obey the voice of your maidservant; and let me set before you a piece of bread, and you eat, that power may come to be in you, because you will go on your way.” 23 But he refused and said: “I am not going to eat.” However, his servants and also the woman kept urging him. Finally he obeyed their voice and rose up from the earth and sat on the couch. 24 Now the woman had a fattened calf in the house. So she quickly sacrificed it and took flour and kneaded dough and baked it into unfermented cakes. 25 Then she served them to Saul and his servants, and they ate. After that they rose up and went away during that night.

1 Samuel

30 And it came about while David and his men were coming to Zik′lag on the third day, that the A·mal′ek·ites made a raid on the south and on Zik′lag; and they proceeded to strike Zik′lag and burn it with fire, 2 and to carry off captive the women and all that were in it, from the smallest to the greatest. They did not put anyone to death, but they drove them along and went on their way. 3 When David came with his men to the city, why, there it was burned with fire, and, as for their wives and their sons and their daughters, they had been carried off captive. 4 And David and the people that were with him began to raise their voice and weep, until there was in them no power to weep anymore. 5 And David’s two wives had been carried off captive, A·hin′o·am the Jez′re·el·i·tess and Ab′i·gail the wife of Na′bal the Car′mel·ite. 6 And it became very distressing to David, because the people said to stone him; for the soul of all the people had become bitter, each one because of his sons and his daughters. So David took to strengthening himself by Jehovah his God.

7 Hence David said to A·bi′a·thar the priest, the son of A·him′e·lech: “Do, please, bring the eph′od near to me.” And A·bi′a·thar came bringing the eph′od near to David. 8 And David began to inquire of Jehovah, saying: “Shall I chase after this marauder band? Shall I overtake them?” At this he said to him: “Go in chase, for you will without fail overtake them, and you will without fail make a deliverance.”

9 Promptly David got on his way, he and the six hundred men that were with him, and they went on as far as the torrent valley of Be′sor, and the men that were to be left behind stood still. 10 And David kept up the chase, he and four hundred men, but two hundred men that were too tired to pass over the torrent valley of Be′sor stood still.

11 And they got to find a man, an Egyptian, in the field. So they took him to David and gave him bread that he might eat and gave him water to drink. 12 Further, they gave him a slice of a cake of pressed figs and two cakes of raisins. Then he ate and his spirit returned to him; for he had not eaten bread or drunk water for three days and three nights. 13 David now said to him: “To whom do you belong, and where are you from?” to which he said: “I am an Egyptian attendant, a slave of an A·mal′ek·ite man, but my master left me because I took sick three days ago. 14 We were the ones that made a raid on the south of the Cher′e·thites and upon that which belongs to Judah and upon the south of Ca′leb; and Zik′lag we burned with fire.” 15 At this David said to him: “Will you lead me down to this marauder band?” To this he said: “Do swear to me by God that you will not put me to death, and that you will not surrender me into the hand of my master, and I shall lead you down to this marauder band.”

16 Accordingly he led him down, and there they were spread disorderly over the surface of all the land eating and drinking and having a feast on account of all the great spoil that they had taken from the land of the Phi·lis′tines and the land of Judah. 17 And David went striking them down from the morning darkness until the evening, that he might devote them to destruction; and not a man of them escaped except four hundred young men that rode upon camels and took to flight. 18 And David got to deliver all that the A·mal′ek·ites had taken, and his two wives David delivered. 19 And there was nothing of theirs lacking, from the smallest to the greatest and to sons and daughters and from the spoil, even to anything that they had taken for themselves. Everything David recovered. 20 So David took all the flocks and the herds, which they drove before that other livestock. Then they said: “This is David’s spoil.”

21 At length David came to the two hundred men who had been too tired to go along with David, and whom they had kept sitting by the torrent valley of Be′sor; and they came out to meet David and to meet the people that were with him. When David came near to the people he began to ask them how they were. 22 However, every bad and good-for-nothing man out of the men that had gone with David answered and kept saying: “For the reason that they did not go with us, we will give them none of the spoil that we delivered, except to each one his wife and his sons, and let them lead them and go.” 23 But David said: “YOU must not do that way, my brothers, with what Jehovah has given us, in that he safeguarded us and gave the marauder band that came against us into our hand. 24 And who will listen to YOU as to this saying? For as the share of the one that went down into the battle even so will the share of the one that sat by the baggage be. All will have a share together.” 25 And it came about from that day forward that he kept it set as a regulation and a judicial decision for Israel down to this day.

26 When David came to Zik′lag he proceeded to send some of the spoil to the older men of Judah, his friends, saying: “Here is a gift blessing for YOU from the spoil of Jehovah’s enemies.” 27 To those who were in Beth′el, and to those in Ra′moth of the south, and to those in Jat′tir, 28 and to those in A·ro′er, and to those in Siph′moth, and to those in Esh·te·mo′a, 29 and to those in Ra′cal, and to those in the cities of the Je·rah′me·el·ites, and to those in the cities of the Ken′ites, 30 and to those in Hor′mah, and to those in Bor′a·shan, and to those in A′thach, 31 and to those in He′bron, and to all the places where David had walked about, he and his men.

The Second of Samuel

or, according to the Greek Septuagint, THE SECOND OF KINGS

1 And it came about after Saul’s death, and when David himself had returned from striking down the A·mal′ek·ites, that David continued to dwell at Zik′lag two days. 2 And it came about on the third day that, look! a man was coming from the camp, from Saul, with his garments ripped apart and dirt upon his head; and it came about that when he came to David, he at once fell down to the earth and prostrated himself.

3 And David proceeded to say to him: “Where do you come from?” at which he said to him: “From the camp of Israel I have escaped.” 4 And David went on to say to him: “How did the matter turn out? Tell me, please.” To this he said: “The people have fled from the battle and also many of the people have fallen so that they died, and even Saul and Jon′a·than his son have died.” 5 Then David said to the young man that was telling him: “How do you really know that Saul has died and also Jon′a·than his son?” 6 At this the young man that was telling him said: “I unexpectedly chanced to be on Mount Gil·bo′a, and there was Saul supporting himself upon his spear; and, look! the charioteers and the mounted men had caught up with him. 7 When he turned back and saw me, then he called me, and I said, ‘Here I am!’ 8 And he went on to say to me, ‘Who are you?’ at which I said to him, ‘I am an A·mal′ek·ite.’ 9 Then he said, ‘Stand, please, over me and definitely put me to death, for the cramp has seized me, because all my soul is yet in me.’ 10 So I stood over him and definitely put him to death, for I knew that he could not live after he had fallen. Then I took the diadem that was upon his head and the bracelet that was upon his arm, that I might bring them to my lord here.”

11 At this David took hold of his garments and ripped them apart, and so did all the men also that were with him. 12 And they began to wail and weep and fast until the evening over Saul and over Jon′a·than his son and over the people of Jehovah and over the house of Israel, because they had fallen by the sword.

13 David now said to the young man that was telling him: “Where are you from?” to which he said: “I am the son of an alien resident, an A·mal′ek·ite.” 14 Then David said to him: “How was it that you did not fear to thrust your hand out to bring the anointed of Jehovah to ruin?” 15 With that David called one of the young men and said: “Go near. Smite him.” Accordingly he struck him down so that he died. 16 David then said to him: “The bloodguilt for you be upon your own head, because your own mouth has testified against you, saying, ‘I myself definitely put the anointed of Jehovah to death.’”

17 And David proceeded to chant this dirge over Saul and Jon′a·than his son 18 and to say that the sons of Judah should be taught “The Bow.” Look! It is written in the book of Ja′shar:

19 “The beauty, O Israel, is slain upon your high places.

How have the mighty men fallen!

20 Do not, YOU people, tell it in Gath;

Do not announce it in the streets of Ash′ke·lon,

For fear that the daughters of the Phi·lis′tines may rejoice,

For fear that the daughters of the uncircumcised men may exult.

21 YOU mountains of Gil·bo′a, let no dew, let no rain be upon YOU, nor let there be fields of holy contributions;

Because there the shield of mighty ones was befouled,

The shield of Saul, so that there was none anointed with oil.

22 From the blood of the slain, from the fat of mighty ones,

The bow of Jon′a·than did not turn back,

And the sword of Saul would not return without success.

23 Saul and Jon′a·than, the lovable ones and the pleasant ones during their life,

And in their death they were not separated.

Swifter than the eagles they were,

Mightier than the lions they were.

24 YOU daughters of Israel, weep over Saul,

Who clothed YOU in scarlet with finery,

Who put ornaments of gold upon YOUR clothing.

25 How have the mighty ones fallen in the midst of the battle!

Jon′a·than slain upon your high places!

26 I am distressed over you, my brother Jon′a·than,

Very pleasant you were to me.

More wonderful was your love to me than the love from women.

27 How have the mighty ones fallen

And the weapons of war perished!”

2 Samuel

3 And the war between the house of Saul and the house of David came to be long drawn out; and David kept getting stronger, and the house of Saul kept declining more and more.

2 Meantime, sons were born to David in He′bron, and his firstborn came to be Am′non by A·hin′o·am the Jez′re·el·i·tess. 3 And his second was Chil′e·ab by Ab′i·gail the wife of Na′bal the Car′mel·ite, and the third was Ab′sa·lom the son of Ma′a·cah the daughter of Tal′mai the king of Gesh′ur. 4 And the fourth was Ad·o·ni′jah the son of Hag′gith, and the fifth was Sheph·a·ti′ah the son of A·bi′tal. 5 And the sixth was Ith′re·am by Eg′lah, David’s wife. These were the ones born to David in He′bron.

6 And it came about that while the war between the house of Saul and the house of David kept up, Ab′ner himself was continually strengthening his position in the house of Saul. 7 Now Saul had had a concubine whose name was Riz′pah, the daughter of A′iah. Later Ish-bo′sheth said to Ab′ner: “Why was it that you had relations with the concubine of my father?” 8 And Ab′ner got very angry at the words of Ish-bo′sheth and went on to say: “Am I a dog’s head that belongs to Judah? Today I keep exercising loving-kindness toward the house of Saul your father, to his brothers and his personal friends, and I have not let you find yourself in the hand of David; and yet you call me to account for an error concerning a woman today. 9 So may God do to Ab′ner and so may he add to it, if, just as Jehovah swore to David, that is not the way that I shall do to him, 10 so as to transfer the kingdom from the house of Saul and to establish the throne of David over Israel and over Judah from Dan to Be′er-she′ba.” 11 And he was not able to say one word more in reply to Ab′ner because of being afraid of him.

12 Accordingly Ab′ner sent messengers to David on the spot, saying: “To whom does the land belong?” adding: “Do conclude your covenant with me, and, look! my hand will be with you to turn to your side the whole of Israel.” 13 To this he said: “Good! I myself shall conclude a covenant with you. Only one thing there is that I am asking of you, saying, ‘You may not see my face except first you bring Mi′chal, Saul’s daughter, when you come to see my face.’” 14 Further, David sent messengers to Ish-bo′sheth, Saul’s son, saying: “Do give over my wife Mi′chal, whom I engaged to myself for a hundred foreskins of the Phi·lis′tines.” 15 So Ish-bo′sheth sent and took her from her husband, Pal′ti·el the son of La′ish. 16 But her husband kept walking with her, weeping as he walked after her as far as Ba·hu′rim. Then Ab′ner said to him: “Go, return!” At that he returned.

17 Meanwhile there had come to be communication by Ab′ner with the older men of Israel, saying: “Both yesterday and previously YOU proved yourselves seeking David as king over YOU. 18 And now act, for Jehovah himself said to David, ‘By the hand of David my servant I shall save my people Israel from the hand of the Phi·lis′tines and from the hand of all their enemies.’” 19 Then Ab′ner also spoke in the ears of Benjamin, after which Ab′ner also went to speak in the ears of David at He′bron all that was good in the eyes of Israel and in the eyes of the whole house of Benjamin.

20 When Ab′ner came to David at He′bron, and with him twenty men, David proceeded to make a feast for Ab′ner and for the men that were with him. 21 Then Ab′ner said to David: “Let me rise up and go and collect all Israel together to my lord the king, that they may conclude a covenant with you, and you will certainly become king over all that your soul craves.” So David sent Ab′ner off, and he got on his way in peace.

22 And here David’s servants and Jo′ab were coming from a raid, and the spoil that they brought with them was abundant. As for Ab′ner, he was not with David in He′bron, for he had sent him off, and he was on his way in peace. 23 And Jo′ab and all the army that was with him came in, and they now reported to Jo′ab, saying: “Ab′ner the son of Ner came to the king, and he proceeded to send him off, and he is on his way in peace.” 24 So Jo′ab went in to the king and said: “What have you done? Look! Ab′ner has come to you. Why was it that you sent him off so that he successfully went away? 25 You well know Ab′ner the son of Ner, that it was to fool you that he came and to get to know your going out and your coming in and to get to know everything that you are doing.”

26 With that Jo′ab went out from David and sent messengers after Ab′ner, and they then had him return from the cistern of Si′rah; and David himself did not know of it. 27 When Ab′ner returned to He′bron, Jo′ab now led him aside inside the gate to speak with him quietly. However, there he struck him in the abdomen, so that he died because of the blood of As′a·hel his brother. 28 When David heard of it afterward, he at once said: “I and my kingdom, from the standpoint of Jehovah, are innocent for time indefinite of bloodguilt for Ab′ner the son of Ner. 29 May it whirl back upon the head of Jo′ab and upon the entire house of his father, and let there not be cut off from Jo′ab’s house a man with a running discharge or a leper or a man taking hold of the twirling spindle or one falling by the sword or one in need of bread!” 30 As for Jo′ab and A·bish′ai his brother, they killed Ab′ner over the fact that he had put As′a·hel their brother to death at Gib′e·on in the battle.

31 Then David said to Jo′ab and all the people that were with him: “Rip YOUR garments apart and tie on sackcloth and wail before Ab′ner.” Even King David was walking behind the couch. 32 And they had the burial of Ab′ner in He′bron; and the king began to raise his voice and weep at Ab′ner’s burial place, and all the people gave way to weeping. 33 And the king went on to chant over Ab′ner and say:

“As with the death of a senseless person should Ab′ner die?

34 Your hands had not been bound ones,

And your feet had not been put into fetters of copper.

As one falling before the sons of unrighteousness you have fallen.”

At that all the people wept over him again.

35 Later all the people came to give David bread for consolation while it was yet that day, but David swore, saying: “So may God do to me and so may he add to it, if before the sun sets I shall taste bread or anything at all!” 36 And all the people themselves took notice, and it was good in their eyes. Like everything that the king did, it was in the eyes of all the people good. 37 And all the people and all Israel got to know on that day that it had not originated with the king to have Ab′ner the son of Ner put to death. 38 And the king went on to say to his servants: “Do YOU not know that it is a prince and a great man that has fallen this day in Israel? 39 And I today am weak although anointed as king, and these men, the sons of Ze·ru′iah, are too severe for me. May Jehovah repay the doer of what is bad according to his own badness.”

2 Samuel

6 And David proceeded again to gather all the choice men in Israel, thirty thousand. 2 Then David and all the people that were with him rose up and went to Ba′al·e-ju′dah to bring up from there the ark of the true God, where a name is called on, the name of Jehovah of armies, sitting on the cherubs. 3 However, they had the ark of the true God ride upon a new wagon, that they might carry it from the house of A·bin′a·dab, which was on the hill; and Uz′zah and A·hi′o, the sons of A·bin′a·dab, were leading the new wagon.

4 So they carried it from A·bin′a·dab’s house, which was on the hill—with the ark of the true God; and A·hi′o was walking ahead of the Ark. 5 And David and all the house of Israel were celebrating before Jehovah with all sorts of instruments of juniper wood and with harps and with stringed instruments and with tambourines and with sistrums and with cymbals. 6 And they came gradually as far as the threshing floor of Na′con, and Uz′zah now thrust his hand out to the ark of the true God and grabbed hold of it, for the cattle nearly caused an upset. 7 At that Jehovah’s anger blazed against Uz′zah and the true God struck him down there for the irreverent act, so that he died there close by the ark of the true God. 8 And David became angry over the fact that Jehovah had broken through in a rupture against Uz′zah, and that place came to be called Pe′rez-uz′zah down to this day. 9 And David became afraid of Jehovah on that day and began to say: “How will the ark of Jehovah come to me?” 10 And David was not willing to remove the ark of Jehovah to him at the City of David. So David had it carried aside to the house of O′bed-e′dom the Git′tite.

11 And the ark of Jehovah kept dwelling at the house of O′bed-e′dom the Git′tite three months; and Jehovah kept blessing O′bed-e′dom and all his household. 12 Finally the report was made to King David, saying: “Jehovah has blessed the house of O′bed-e′dom and all that is his on account of the ark of the true God.” At that David proceeded to go and bring the ark of the true God out of the house of O′bed-e′dom up to the City of David with rejoicing. 13 And it came about that when the carriers of the ark of Jehovah had marched six steps, he immediately sacrificed a bull and a fatling.

14 And David was dancing around before Jehovah with all his power, all the while David being girded with an eph′od of linen. 15 And David and all the house of Israel were bringing up the ark of Jehovah with joyful shouting and sound of horn. 16 And it occurred that when the ark of Jehovah came into the City of David, Mi′chal, Saul’s daughter, herself looked down through the window and got to see King David leaping and dancing around before Jehovah; and she began to despise him in her heart. 17 So they brought the ark of Jehovah in and set it in its place inside the tent that David had pitched for it; after which David offered up burnt sacrifices and communion sacrifices before Jehovah. 18 When David was finished with offering up the burnt sacrifices and the communion sacrifices, he then blessed the people in the name of Jehovah of armies. 19 Further, he apportioned to all the people, to the whole crowd of Israel, man as well as woman, to each one a ring-shaped cake of bread and a date cake and a raisin cake, after which all the people went each to his own house.

20 David now returned to bless his own household, and Mi′chal, Saul’s daughter, came on out to meet David and then said: “How glorious the king of Israel made himself today when he uncovered himself today to the eyes of the slave girls of his servants, just as one of the empty-headed men uncovers himself outright!” 21 At this David said to Mi′chal: “It was before Jehovah, who chose me rather than your father and all his household to put me in command as leader over Jehovah’s people Israel, and I will celebrate before Jehovah. 22 And I will make myself even more lightly esteemed than this, and I will become low in my eyes; and with the slave girls whom you mentioned, with them I am determined to glorify myself.” 23 So, as regards Mi′chal, Saul’s daughter, she came to have no child down to the day of her death.

2 Samuel

7 And it came about that, when the king dwelt in his own house and Jehovah himself had given him rest from all his enemies round about, 2 then the king said to Nathan the prophet: “See, now, I am dwelling in a house of cedars while the ark of the true God is dwelling in the middle of tent cloths.” 3 Upon that Nathan said to the king: “Everything that is in your heart—go, do, because Jehovah is with you.”

4 And it came about on that night that the word of Jehovah came to Nathan, saying: 5 “Go, and you must say to my servant David, ‘This is what Jehovah has said: “Should you yourself build me a house for me to dwell in? 6 For I have not dwelt in a house from the day of my bringing the sons of Israel up out of Egypt to this day, but I was continually walking about in a tent and in a tabernacle. 7 During all the time that I have walked about among all the sons of Israel, was there a word that I spoke with one of the tribes of Israel that I commanded to shepherd my people Israel, saying, ‘Why did YOU people not build me a house of cedars?’”’ 8 And now this is what you will say to my servant David, ‘This is what Jehovah of armies has said: “I myself took you from the pasture ground from following the flock to become a leader over my people Israel. 9 And I shall prove to be with you wherever you do go, and I will cut off all your enemies from before you; and I shall certainly make for you a great name, like the name of the great ones that are in the earth. 10 And I shall certainly appoint a place for my people Israel and plant them, and they will indeed reside where they are, and no more will they be disturbed; and the sons of unrighteousness will not afflict them again as they did at the first, 11 even from the day that I put judges in command over my people Israel; and I will give you rest from all your enemies.

“‘“And Jehovah has told you that a house is what Jehovah will make for you. 12 When your days come to the full, and you must lie down with your forefathers, then I shall certainly raise up your seed after you, which will come out of your inward parts; and I shall indeed firmly establish his kingdom. 13 He is the one that will build a house for my name, and I shall certainly establish the throne of his kingdom firmly to time indefinite. 14 I myself shall become his father, and he himself will become my son. When he does wrong, I will also reprove him with the rod of men and with the strokes of the sons of Adam. 15 As for my loving-kindness, it will not depart from him the way I removed it from Saul, whom I removed on account of you. 16 And your house and your kingdom will certainly be steadfast to time indefinite before you; your very throne will become one firmly established to time indefinite.”’”

17 According to all these words and according to all this vision was the way that Nathan spoke to David.

18 At that King David came in and sat down before Jehovah and said: “Who am I, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah? And what is my house that you have brought me thus far? 19 As though this should even be something little in your eyes, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah, yet you also speak respecting the house of your servant down to a distant future time; and this is the law given for mankind, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah. 20 And what more can David add and speak to you, when you yourself know your servant well, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah? 21 For the sake of your word and in agreement with your own heart you have done all these great things to cause your servant to know them. 22 That is why you are indeed great, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah; for there is no other like you, and there is no God except you among all of whom we have heard with our ears. 23 And what one nation in the earth is like your people Israel, whom God went to redeem to himself as a people and to assign himself a name and to do for them great and fear-inspiring things—to drive out because of your people, whom you have redeemed to yourself from Egypt, the nations and their gods? 24 And you proceeded to establish your people Israel firmly for yourself as your people to time indefinite; and you yourself, O Jehovah, have become their God.

25 “And now, Jehovah God, the word that you have spoken concerning your servant and concerning his house carry out to time indefinite and do just as you have spoken. 26 And let your own name become great to time indefinite, saying, ‘Jehovah of armies is God over Israel,’ and let the very house of your servant David become firmly established before you. 27 For you, Jehovah of armies the God of Israel, have made a revelation to your servant’s ear, saying, ‘A house I shall build for you.’ That is why your servant has taken heart to pray to you with this prayer. 28 And now, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah, you are the true God; and as for your words, let them prove to be truth, since you promise to your servant this goodness. 29 And now take it upon yourself and bless the house of your servant for it to continue to time indefinite before you; for you yourself, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah, have promised, and due to your blessing let the house of your servant be blessed to time indefinite.”

2 Samuel

9 And David proceeded to say: “Is there yet anyone that is left over of the house of Saul, that I may exercise loving-kindness toward him for the sake of Jon′a·than?” 2 Now the house of Saul had a servant whose name was Zi′ba. So they called him to David, and the king then said to him: “Are you Zi′ba?” to which he said: “I am your servant.” 3 And the king went on to say: “Is there nobody of the house of Saul anymore, that I may exercise toward him the loving-kindness of God?” At this Zi′ba said to the king: “There is yet a son of Jon′a·than, lame in the feet.” 4 Then the king said to him: “Where is he?” So Zi′ba said to the king: “Look! He is in the house of Ma′chir the son of Am′mi·el at Lo-de′bar.”

5 Immediately King David sent and took him from the house of Ma′chir the son of Am′mi·el at Lo-de′bar. 6 When Me·phib′o·sheth the son of Jon′a·than the son of Saul came in to David, he at once fell upon his face and prostrated himself. Then David said: “Me·phib′o·sheth!” to which he said: “Here is your servant.” 7 And David went on to say to him: “Do not be afraid, for without fail I shall exercise loving-kindness toward you for the sake of Jon′a·than your father; and I must return to you all the field of Saul your grandfather, and you yourself will eat bread at my table constantly.”

8 At that he prostrated himself and said: “What is your servant, that you have turned your face to the dead dog such as I am?” 9 The king now called Zi′ba, Saul’s attendant, and said to him: “Everything that had come to belong to Saul and to all his house I do give to the grandson of your master. 10 And you must cultivate the ground for him, you and your sons and your servants, and you must do the gathering in, and it must serve as food for those belonging to the grandson of your master, and they must eat; but Me·phib′o·sheth himself, the grandson of your master, will eat bread at my table constantly.”

Now Zi′ba had fifteen sons and twenty servants. 11 So Zi′ba said to the king: “In accord with all that my lord the king commands for his servant is the way that your servant will do; but Me·phib′o·sheth is eating at my table like one of the sons of the king.” 12 Now Me·phib′o·sheth had a young son whose name was Mi′ca, and all those dwelling in the house of Zi′ba were servants to Me·phib′o·sheth. 13 And Me·phib′o·sheth himself was dwelling in Jerusalem, for it was constantly at the table of the king that he was eating; and he was lame in both of his feet.

2 Samuel

10 And it came about afterward that the king of the sons of Am′mon came to die, and Ha′nun his son began to reign instead of him. 2 At this David said: “I shall exercise loving-kindness toward Ha′nun the son of Na′hash, just as his father exercised loving-kindness toward me.” Accordingly David sent by means of his servants to comfort him over his father, and the servants of David proceeded to come into the land of the sons of Am′mon. 3 However, the princes of the sons of Am′mon said to Ha′nun their lord: “Is David honoring your father in your eyes in that he has sent to you comforters? Is it not for the sake of searching through the city and to spy it out and to overthrow it that David has sent his servants to you?” 4 So Ha′nun took the servants of David and shaved off half their beards and cut their garments in half to their buttocks and sent them away. 5 Later people reported it to David, and he at once sent to meet them, because the men had come to feeling very humiliated; and the king went on to say: “Dwell in Jer′i·cho until YOUR beards grow abundantly. Then YOU must return.”

6 In time the sons of Am′mon saw that they had become foul-smelling to David, and the sons of Am′mon proceeded to send and hire Syrians of Beth-re′hob and Syrians of Zo′bah, twenty thousand men on foot, and the king of Ma′a·cah, a thousand men, and Ish′tob, twelve thousand men. 7 When David heard of it, then he sent Jo′ab and all the army and the mighty men. 8 And the sons of Am′mon began to go out and draw up in battle formation at the entrance of the gate, also the Syrians of Zo′bah and of Re′hob, and Ish′tob and Ma′a·cah by themselves in the open field.

9 When Jo′ab saw that the battle charges had come to be against him from the front and from the rear, he at once chose some of all the choice men in Israel and drew them up in formation to meet the Syrians. 10 And the rest of the people he gave into the hand of A·bish′ai his brother, that he might draw them up in formation to meet the sons of Am′mon. 11 And he went on to say: “If the Syrians become too strong for me, then you must serve as a salvation for me; but if the sons of Am′mon themselves become too strong for you, I must also come to save you. 12 Be strong, that we may show ourselves courageous in behalf of our people and in behalf of the cities of our God; and as for Jehovah, he will do what is good in his own eyes.”

13 Then Jo′ab and the people that were with him advanced to the battle against the Syrians, and they went fleeing from before him. 14 As for the sons of Am′mon, they saw that the Syrians had fled, and they took to flight from before A·bish′ai and hence came into the city. After that Jo′ab returned from the sons of Am′mon and came to Jerusalem.

15 When the Syrians saw that they had been defeated before Israel, they proceeded to gather themselves together. 16 So Had·ad·e′zer sent and brought out the Syrians that were in the region of the River; and then they came to He′lam, with Sho′bach the chief of the army of Had·ad·e′zer before them.

17 When the report was made to David, he immediately gathered all Israel and crossed the Jordan and came to He′lam. The Syrians now drew up in formation to meet David and began to fight against him. 18 And the Syrians took to flight from before Israel; and David got to kill of the Syrians seven hundred charioteers and forty thousand horsemen, and Sho′bach the chief of their army he struck down so that he died there. 19 When all the kings, the servants of Had·ad·e′zer, saw that they had been defeated before Israel, they promptly made peace with Israel and began to serve them; and the Syrians were afraid to try saving the sons of Am′mon anymore.

2 Samuel

14 Now Jo′ab the son of Ze·ru′iah came to know that the king’s heart was toward Ab′sa·lom. 2 Accordingly Jo′ab sent to Te·ko′a and took from there a wise woman and said to her: “Go in mourning, please, and dress yourself, please, with garments of mourning, and do not rub yourself with oil; and you must become like a woman here who has been mourning many days over someone dead. 3 And you must come in to the king and speak to him a word like this.” With that Jo′ab put the words in her mouth.

4 And the Te·ko′ite woman proceeded to come in to the king and fall upon her face to the earth and prostrate herself and say: “Do save, O king!” 5 At this the king said to her: “What is the matter with you?” To this she said: “For a fact I am a widowed woman, now that my husband is dead. 6 And your maidservant had two sons, and the two of them began to struggle with each other in the field while there was no deliverer to part them. Finally the one struck the other down and put him to death. 7 And here all the family have risen up against your maidservant and keep saying, ‘Give over the striker of his brother, that we may put him to death for the soul of his brother whom he killed, and let us even annihilate the heir!’ And they will certainly extinguish the glow of my charcoals that has remained, so as to assign to my husband neither a name nor a remnant on the surface of the ground.”

8 Then the king said to the woman: “Go to your house, and I myself shall give command regarding you.” 9 At this the Te·ko′ite woman said to the king: “Upon me, O my lord the king, be the error, and also upon the house of my father, while the king and his throne are innocent.” 10 And the king went on to say: “If there is anyone speaking to you, you must also bring him to me, and he will never hurt you again.” 11 But she said: “Let the king, please, remember Jehovah your God, that the avenger of blood may not be continually causing ruin and that they may not annihilate my son.” To this he said: “As Jehovah is living, not a single hair of your son will fall to the earth.” 12 The woman now said: “Let your maidservant, please, speak a word to my lord the king.” So he said: “Speak!”

13 And the woman went on to say: “Why, then, have you reasoned like this against the people of God? As the king is speaking this word he is like one that is guilty, in that the king does not bring back his own banished one. 14 For we shall die without fail and be like waters that are being poured down to the earth, which cannot be gathered. But God will not take away a soul, and he has thought out reasons why the one banished should not be banished from him. 15 And now that I have come in to speak this word to the king my lord, it is because the people made me afraid. So your maidservant said, ‘Let me speak, please, to the king. Perhaps the king will act on the word of his slave girl. 16 Because the king proceeded to listen so as to deliver his slave girl out of the palm of the man seeking to annihilate me and my lone son from the inheritance given by God,’ 17 then your maidservant said, ‘Let the word of my lord the king serve, please, to give rest.’ For just like an angel of the true God is the way my lord the king is, to distinguish what is good and what is bad, and may Jehovah your God himself prove to be with you.”

18 The king now answered and said to the woman: “Do not, please, hide from me a thing about which I am asking you.” To this the woman said: “Let my lord the king speak, please.” 19 And the king went on to say: “Is the hand of Jo′ab with you in all this?” Then the woman answered and said: “As your soul is living, O my lord the king, no man can go to the right or go to the left from all that my lord the king has spoken; for it was your servant Jo′ab that commanded me, and he it was that put in the mouth of your maidservant all these words. 20 For the sake of altering the face of the matter your servant Jo′ab has done this thing, but my lord is wise as with the wisdom of the angel of the true God so as to know all that is in the earth.”

21 Subsequently the king said to Jo′ab: “Here, now, I shall certainly do this thing. So go, bring the young man Ab′sa·lom back.” 22 At this Jo′ab fell upon his face to the earth and prostrated himself and blessed the king; and Jo′ab went on to say: “Today your servant does know that I have found favor in your eyes, O my lord the king, because the king has acted on the word of his servant.” 23 With that Jo′ab rose up and went to Gesh′ur and brought Ab′sa·lom to Jerusalem. 24 However, the king said: “Let him turn toward his own house, but my face he may not see.” So Ab′sa·lom turned toward his own house, and the face of the king he did not see.

25 Now compared with Ab′sa·lom there proved to be no man so beautiful in all Israel as to be praised so much. From the sole of his foot to the crown of his head there proved to be no defect in him. 26 And when he shaved his head—and it occurred at the end of every year that he would shave it; because it was so heavy upon him, he shaved it—he weighed the hair of his head, two hundred shekels by the royal stone weight. 27 And there came to be born to Ab′sa·lom three sons and one daughter whose name was Ta′mar. She proved to be a woman most beautiful in appearance.

28 And Ab′sa·lom continued dwelling in Jerusalem for two full years, and the face of the king he did not see. 29 So Ab′sa·lom sent for Jo′ab to send him to the king, and he did not consent to come to him. Then he sent again, a second time, and he did not consent to come. 30 Finally he said to his servants: “See Jo′ab’s tract of land beside mine, and there he has barley. Go and set it ablaze with fire.” Accordingly the servants of Ab′sa·lom set the tract of land ablaze with fire. 31 At this Jo′ab rose up and came to Ab′sa·lom at the house and said to him: “Why did your servants set the tract of land that is mine ablaze with fire?” 32 So Ab′sa·lom said to Jo′ab: “Look! I sent to you, saying, ‘Come here and let me send you to the king, saying: “Why have I come from Gesh′ur? It would be better for me that I should still be there. And now let me see the face of the king and, if there is any error in me, he must then put me to death.”’”

33 Subsequently Jo′ab came in to the king and told him. Then he called Ab′sa·lom, who now came in to the king and prostrated himself to him, falling upon his face to the earth before the king; after which the king kissed Ab′sa·lom.

2 Samuel

19 Later it was reported to Jo′ab: “Look! The king is weeping, and he carries on mourning over Ab′sa·lom.” 2 So the salvation on that day came to be an occasion of mourning on the part of all the people, because the people heard say on that day: “The king has felt hurt over his son.” 3 And the people began to steal away on that day to come into the city, just as the people would steal away when they felt disgraced because they fled in the battle. 4 And the king himself covered up his face, and the king continued crying out with a loud voice: “My son Ab′sa·lom! Ab′sa·lom my son, my son!”

5 Finally Jo′ab came in to the king at the house and said: “You have today put to shame the face of all your servants, the ones providing escape for your soul today and for the soul of your sons and your daughters and the soul of your wives and the soul of your concubines, 6 by loving those hating you and by hating those loving you; for you have reported today that chiefs and servants are nothing to you, because I well know today that if only Ab′sa·lom were alive and all of us others were today dead, why, in that case it would be right in your eyes. 7 And now rise up, go out and speak straight to the heart of your servants, because, by Jehovah, I do swear that, in case you are not going out, not a man will lodge with you tonight; and this will certainly be worse for you than all the injury that has come upon you from your youth until now.” 8 Accordingly the king rose up and seated himself in the gate, and to all the people they made the report, saying: “There is the king sitting in the gate.” And all the people began to come before the king.

As for Israel, they had fled each one to his home. 9 And all the people came to be involved in dispute in all the tribes of Israel, saying: “It was the king that delivered us out of the palm of our enemies, and he it was that provided escape for us out of the palm of the Phi·lis′tines; and now he has run away out of the land from Ab′sa·lom. 10 As for Ab′sa·lom, whom we anointed over us, he has died in the battle. So now why are YOU doing nothing to bring the king back?”

11 As for King David, he sent to Za′dok and A·bi′a·thar the priests, saying: “SPEAK to the older men of Judah, saying, ‘Why should YOU become the last ones to bring the king back to his house, when the word of all Israel itself has come to the king at his house? 12 My brothers YOU are; my bone and my flesh YOU are. So why should YOU become the last ones to bring the king back?’ 13 And to A·ma′sa YOU should say, ‘Are you not my bone and my flesh? So may God do to me and so may he add to it if you will not become the army chief before me always instead of Jo′ab.’”

14 And he proceeded to bend the heart of all the men of Judah as one man, so that they sent word to the king: “Come back, you and all your servants.”

15 And the king began to go back and got to come as far as the Jordan. As for Judah, they came to Gil′gal to go and meet the king, to conduct the king across the Jordan. 16 Then Shim′e·i the son of Ge′ra the Ben′ja·min·ite, who was from Ba·hu′rim, hurried and went down with the men of Judah to meet King David. 17 And there were with him a thousand men from Benjamin. (And also Zi′ba the attendant of the house of Saul and his fifteen sons and twenty servants of his were with him, and they made it successfully to the Jordan before the king. 18 And he crossed the ford to conduct the household of the king across and to do what was good in his eyes.) As for Shim′e·i the son of Ge′ra, he fell down before the king when he was about to cross the Jordan. 19 He now said to the king: “Do not let my lord attribute error to me, and do not remember the wrong that your servant did on the day that my lord the king went out of Jerusalem, so that the king should lay it to his heart. 20 For your servant well knows that I am the one that sinned; and so here I have today come the first of all the house of Joseph to go down to meet my lord the king.”

21 At once A·bish′ai the son of Ze·ru′iah answered and said: “In return for this should not Shim′e·i be put to death, in that he called evil down upon the anointed of Jehovah?” 22 But David said: “What do I have to do with YOU men, YOU sons of Ze·ru′iah, that YOU should become today a resister of me? Will anyone today be put to death in Israel? For do I not well know that today I am king over Israel?” 23 Then the king said to Shim′e·i: “You will not die.” And the king went on to swear to him.

24 As for Me·phib′o·sheth the grandson of Saul, he came down to meet the king; and he had not attended to his feet nor had he attended to his mustache nor had he washed his garments from the day that the king went away until the day that he came in peace. 25 And it came about that, when he came to Jerusalem to meet the king, then the king said to him: “Why did you not go with me, Me·phib′o·sheth?” 26 To this he said: “My lord the king, it was my servant that tricked me. For your servant had said, ‘Let me saddle the female ass for me that I may ride upon it and go with the king,’ for your servant is lame. 27 So he slandered your servant to my lord the king. But my lord the king is as an angel of the true God, and so do what is good in your eyes. 28 For all the household of my father would have become nothing but doomed to death to my lord the king, and yet you placed your servant among those eating at your table. So what do I still have as a just claim even for crying out further to the king?”

29 However, the king said to him: “Why do you yet keep speaking your words? I do say, You and Zi′ba should share in the field.” 30 At this Me·phib′o·sheth said to the king: “Let him even take the whole, now that my lord the king has come in peace to his house.”

31 And Bar·zil′lai the Gil′e·ad·ite himself came down from Ro·ge′lim that he might pass on to the Jordan with the king so as to escort him to the Jordan. 32 And Bar·zil′lai was very old, being eighty years of age; and he himself supplied the king with food while he was dwelling in Ma·ha·na′im, for he was a very great man. 33 So the king said to Bar·zil′lai: “You yourself cross over with me, and I shall certainly supply you with food with me in Jerusalem.” 34 But Bar·zil′lai said to the king: “What are the days of the years of my life like, that I should go up with the king to Jerusalem? 35 I am eighty years old today. Could I discern between good and bad, or could your servant taste what I ate and what I drank, or could I listen anymore to the voice of male and female singers? So why should your servant become a burden anymore to my lord the king? 36 For it is just a little way that your servant could bring the king along to the Jordan, and why should the king repay me with this reward? 37 Let your servant return, please, and let me die in my city close by the burial place of my father and my mother. But here is your servant Chim′ham. Let him cross over with my lord the king; and you do to him what is good in your eyes.”

38 Accordingly the king said: “With me Chim′ham will go across, and I myself shall do to him what is good in your eyes; and all that you may choose to lay upon me I shall do for you.” 39 All the people now began to cross the Jordan, and the king himself crossed; but the king kissed Bar·zil′lai and blessed him, after which he returned to his place. 40 When the king went across to Gil′gal, Chim′ham himself crossed with him, and also all the people of Judah, and also half the people of Israel, that they might bring the king across.

41 And, look! all the men of Israel were coming to the king, and they proceeded to say to the king: “Why did our brothers the men of Judah steal you that they might bring the king and his household and all the men of David with him over the Jordan?” 42 At this all the men of Judah answered the men of Israel: “Because the king is closely related to us; and why is it that you have become angry over this thing? Have we eaten at all at the king’s expense, or has a gift been carried to us?”

43 However, the men of Israel answered the men of Judah and said: “We have ten parts in the king, so that even in David we are more than you. Why, then, have you treated us with contempt, and why did not our matter become first for us to bring our king back?” But the word of the men of Judah was more severe than the word of the men of Israel.

2 Samuel

21 Now there came to be a famine in the days of David for three years, year after year; and David proceeded to consult the face of Jehovah. Then Jehovah said: “Upon Saul and upon his house there is bloodguilt, because he put the Gib′e·on·ites to death.” 2 So the king called the Gib′e·on·ites and talked to them. (Incidentally, the Gib′e·on·ites were not of the sons of Israel, but of the remainder of the Am′or·ites; and the sons of Israel themselves had sworn to them, but Saul sought to strike them down in his feeling jealous for the sons of Israel and Judah.) 3 And David went on to say to the Gib′e·on·ites: “What shall I do to YOU, and with what shall I make atonement, that YOU may certainly bless the inheritance of Jehovah?” 4 So the Gib′e·on·ites said to him: “It is not a matter of silver or gold for us in connection with Saul and his household, neither is it ours to put a man to death in Israel.” At that he said: “Whatever YOU are saying I shall do for YOU.” 5 At this they said to the king: “The man that exterminated us and that schemed to annihilate us from subsisting in any of the territory of Israel, 6 let there be given to us seven men of his sons; and we must expose them to Jehovah in Gib′e·ah of Saul, the chosen one of Jehovah.” Accordingly the king said: “I myself shall give them.”

7 However, the king felt compassion upon Me·phib′o·sheth the son of Jon′a·than the son of Saul on account of the oath of Jehovah that was between them, between David and Jon′a·than the son of Saul. 8 Consequently the king took the two sons of Riz′pah the daughter of A′iah whom she bore to Saul, Ar·mo′ni and Me·phib′o·sheth, and the five sons of Mi′chal the daughter of Saul whom she bore to A′dri·el the son of Bar·zil′lai the Me·hol′ath·ite. 9 Then he gave them into the hand of the Gib′e·on·ites and they proceeded to expose them on the mountain before Jehovah, so that the seven of them fell together; and they themselves were put to death in the first days of harvest, at the start of the barley harvest. 10 However, Riz′pah the daughter of A′iah took sackcloth and spread it for herself upon the rock from the start of harvest until water poured down upon them from the heavens; and she did not allow the fowls of the heavens to rest upon them by day nor the wild beasts of the field by night.

11 At length it was reported to David what Riz′pah the daughter of A′iah, Saul’s concubine, had done. 12 So David went and took the bones of Saul and the bones of Jon′a·than his son from the landowners of Ja′besh-gil′e·ad, who had stolen them from the public square of Beth-shan, where the Phi·lis′tines had hanged them on the day that the Phi·lis′tines struck down Saul on Gil·bo′a. 13 And he proceeded to bring up from there the bones of Saul and the bones of Jon′a·than his son; furthermore, they gathered the bones of the men being exposed. 14 Then they buried the bones of Saul and of Jon′a·than his son in the land of Benjamin in Ze′la in the burial place of Kish his father, that they might do everything that the king had commanded. So God let himself be entreated for the land after this.

15 And the Phi·lis′tines came to have war again with Israel. Accordingly David and his servants with him went down and fought the Phi·lis′tines; and David grew tired. 16 And Ish′bi-be′nob, who was among those born of the Reph′a·im, the weight of whose spear was three hundred shekels of copper and who was girded with a new sword, got to think of striking David down. 17 At once A·bish′ai the son of Ze·ru′iah came to his help and struck the Phi·lis′tine down and put him to death. At that time the men of David swore to him, saying: “You must not go out with us to the battle anymore, that you may not extinguish the lamp of Israel!”

18 And it came about after this that war arose once more with the Phi·lis′tines at Gob. Then it was that Sib′be·cai the Hu′shath·ite struck down Saph, who was among those born of the Reph′a·im.

19 And war arose once again with the Phi·lis′tines at Gob, and El·ha′nan the son of Ja′a·re-or′e·gim the Beth′le·hem·ite got to strike down Go·li′ath the Git′tite, the shaft of whose spear was like the beam of loom workers.

20 And war arose yet again at Gath, when there happened to be a man of extraordinary size, with six fingers on each of his hands and six toes on each of his feet, twenty-four in number; and he too had been born to the Reph′a·im. 21 And he kept taunting Israel. Finally Jon′a·than the son of Shim′e·i, David’s brother, struck him down.

22 These four had been born to the Reph′a·im in Gath; and they came to fall by the hand of David and by the hand of his servants.

2 Samuel

22 And David proceeded to speak to Jehovah the words of this song in the day that Jehovah had delivered him out of the palm of all his enemies and out of Saul’s palm; 2 and he went on to say:

“Jehovah is my crag and my stronghold and the Provider of escape for me.

3 My God is my rock. I shall take refuge in him,

My shield and my horn of salvation, my secure height,

And my place for flight, my Savior; from violence you save me.

4 On the One to be praised, Jehovah, I shall call,

And from my enemies I shall be saved.

5 For deadly breaking waves encircled me;

There were flash floods of good-for-nothing men that kept terrifying me.

6 The ropes of She′ol themselves surrounded me;

The snares of death confronted me.

7 In my distress I kept calling upon Jehovah,

And to my God I kept calling.

Then out of his temple he heard my voice,

With my cry for help in his ears.

8 And back and forth the earth began to shake and to rock;

The foundations of the heavens themselves became agitated,

And they kept shaking back and forth because he had been angered.

9 Smoke went up at his nostrils, and fire itself from his mouth kept devouring;

Coals themselves blazed up from him.

10 And he proceeded to bend the heavens down and to descend;

And thick gloom was beneath his feet.

11 And he came riding upon a cherub and came flying;

And he was visible upon the wings of a spirit.

12 Then he put a darkness around him as booths,

Dark waters, thick clouds.

13 From the brightness in front of him burning coals of fire blazed up.

14 From heaven Jehovah began to thunder,

And the Most High himself began to give forth his voice.

15 And he kept sending out arrows, that he might scatter them;

Lightning, that he might throw them into confusion.

16 And the streambeds of the sea became visible,

The foundations of the productive land became uncovered,

At the rebuke of Jehovah, from the blast of the breath of his nostrils.

17 He was sending from on high, he was taking me,

He was drawing me out of great waters.

18 He was delivering me from my strong enemy,

From those hating me; because they were stronger than I was.

19 They kept confronting me in the day of my disaster,

But Jehovah became my support.

20 And he proceeded to bring me out into a roomy place;

He was rescuing me, because he had found delight in me.

21 Jehovah rewards me according to my righteousness;

According to the cleanness of my hands he repays me.

22 For I have kept the ways of Jehovah,

And I have not wickedly departed from my God.

23 For all his judicial decisions are in front of me;

And as for his statutes, I shall not turn aside from them.

24 And I shall prove myself faultless toward him,

And I will keep myself from error on my part.

25 And let Jehovah repay me according to my righteousness,

According to my cleanness in front of his eyes.

26 With someone loyal you will act in loyalty;

With the faultless, mighty one you will deal faultlessly;

27 With the one keeping clean you will show yourself clean,

And with the crooked one you will act as silly.

28 And the humble people you will save;

But your eyes are against the haughty ones, that you may bring them low.

29 For you are my lamp, O Jehovah,

And it is Jehovah that makes my darkness shine.

30 For by you I can run against a marauder band;

By my God I can climb a wall.

31 As for the true God, perfect is his way;

The saying of Jehovah is a refined one.

A shield he is to all those taking refuge in him.

32 For who is a God besides Jehovah,

And who is a rock besides our God?

33 The true God is my strong fortress,

And he will cause my way to be perfect,

34 Making my feet like those of the hinds;

And upon places high for me he keeps me standing.

35 He is teaching my hands for warfare;

And my arms have pressed down a bow of copper.

36 And you will give me your shield of salvation,

And it is your humility that makes me great.

37 You will make room large enough for my steps under me;

And my ankles will certainly not wobble.

38 I will pursue my enemies, that I may annihilate them,

And I shall not return until they are exterminated.

39 And I shall exterminate them and break them in pieces, that they may not rise up;

And they will fall under my feet.

40 And you will gird me with vital energy for the battle;

You will make those rising against me collapse under me.

41 And as for my enemies, you will certainly give me the back of their neck;

Those hating me intensely—I shall also silence them.

42 They cry for help, but there is no savior;

To Jehovah, but he actually does not answer them.

43 And I shall pound them fine like the dust of the earth;

Like the mire of the streets I shall pulverize them;

I shall beat them flat.

44 And you will provide me escape from the faultfinding of my people.

You will safeguard me to be the head of nations;

A people that I have not known—they will serve me.

45 Foreigners themselves will come cringing to me;

Ears will be obedient to hear me.

46 Foreigners themselves will fade away,

And they will come quaking out from their bulwarks.

47 Jehovah is living; and blessed be my Rock;

And let the God of the rock of my salvation be exalted.

48 The true God is the Giver of acts of vengeance to me

And the One bringing the peoples down under me,

49 And the One bringing me out from my enemies.

And above those who rise up against me you will lift me up;

From the man of violent deeds you will deliver me.

50 That is why I shall thank you, O Jehovah, among the nations;

And to your name I shall make melody:

51 The One doing great acts of salvation for his king

And exercising loving-kindness to his anointed one,

To David and to his seed for time indefinite.”

2 Samuel

23 And these are the last words of David:

“The utterance of David the son of Jes′se,

And the utterance of the able-bodied man that was raised up on high,

The anointed of the God of Jacob,

And the pleasant one of the melodies of Israel.

2 The spirit of Jehovah it was that spoke by me,

And his word was upon my tongue.

3 The God of Israel said,

To me the Rock of Israel spoke,

‘When one ruling over mankind is righteous,

Ruling in the fear of God,

4 Then it is as the light of morning, when the sun shines forth,

A morning without clouds.

From brightness, from rain, there is grass out of the earth.’

5 For is not my household like that with God?

Because it is an indefinitely lasting covenant that he has assigned to me,

Nicely put in order in everything and secured.

Because it is all my salvation and all my delight,

Is that not why he will make it grow?

6 But good-for-nothing persons are chased away, like thornbushes, all of them;

For it is not by the hand that they should be taken.

7 When a man touches them

He should be fully armed with iron and the shaft of a spear,

And with fire they will thoroughly be burned up.”

8 These are the names of the mighty men that belonged to David: Jo′sheb-bas·she′beth a Tah·che′mo·nite, the head of the three. He was brandishing his spear over eight hundred slain at one time. 9 Next to him El·e·a′zar the son of Do′do the son of A·ho′hi was among the three mighty men with David when they taunted the Phi·lis′tines. They had gathered themselves there for the battle, and so the men of Israel retreated. 10 He it was that rose up and kept striking down the Phi·lis′tines until his hand wearied and his hand kept cleaving to the sword, so that Jehovah performed a great salvation on that day; and as for the people, they returned behind him only to strip those struck down.

11 And next to him was Sham′mah the son of A′gee the Har′a·rite. And the Phi·lis′tines proceeded to gather themselves to Le′hi, where there then happened to be a tract of the field full of lentils; and the people themselves fled because of the Phi·lis′tines. 12 But he took his stand in the middle of the tract and delivered it and kept striking down the Phi·lis′tines, so that Jehovah performed a great salvation.

13 And three of the thirty head ones proceeded to go down and come at the harvest, to David at the cave of A·dul′lam; and a tent village of the Phi·lis′tines was encamped in the low plain of the Reph′a·im. 14 And David was then in the place hard to approach; and an outpost of the Phi·lis′tines was then in Beth′le·hem. 15 After a while David expressed his craving and said: “O that I might have a drink of the water from the cistern of Beth′le·hem that is at the gate!” 16 At that the three mighty men forced their way into the camp of the Phi·lis′tines and drew water from the cistern of Beth′le·hem that is at the gate and came carrying and bringing it to David; and he did not consent to drink it, but poured it out to Jehovah. 17 And he went on to say: “It is unthinkable on my part, O Jehovah, that I should do this! Shall I drink the blood of the men going at the risk of their souls?” And he did not consent to drink it.

These are the things the three mighty men did.

18 As for A·bish′ai the brother of Jo′ab the son of Ze·ru′iah, he was the head of the thirty, and he was brandishing his spear over three hundred slain ones, and he had a reputation like the three. 19 Although he was distinguished even more than the rest of the thirty, and he came to be their chief, to the rank of the first three he did not come.

20 As for Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da the son of a valiant man, who did many deeds in Kab′ze·el, he himself struck down the two sons of Ar′i·el of Mo′ab; and he himself descended and struck down a lion inside a waterpit on a day of snowfall. 21 And he it was that struck down the Egyptian man that was of extraordinary size. Though there was a spear in the hand of the Egyptian, yet he went on down to him with a rod and snatched the spear away from the Egyptian’s hand and killed him with his own spear. 22 These things Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da did; and he had a reputation like the three mighty men. 23 Although he was distinguished even more than the thirty, to the rank of the three he did not come; but David appointed him to his own bodyguard.

24 As′a·hel the brother of Jo′ab was among the thirty; El·ha′nan the son of Do′do of Beth′le·hem, 25 Sham′mah the Ha′rod·ite, E·li′ka the Ha′rod·ite, 26 He′lez the Pal′tite, I′ra the son of Ik′kesh the Te·ko′ite, 27 Abi-e′zer the An′a·thoth·ite, Me·bun′nai the Hu′shath·ite, 28 Zal′mon the A·ho′hite, Ma′ha·rai the Ne·toph′a·thite, 29 He′leb the son of Ba′a·nah the Ne·toph′a·thite, It′tai the son of Ri′bai of Gib′e·ah of the sons of Benjamin, 30 Be·nai′ah a Pir′a·thon·ite, Hid′dai of the torrent valleys of Ga′ash, 31 A′bi-al′bon the Ar′bath·ite, Az′ma·veth the Bar-hu′mite, 32 E·li′ah·ba the Sha·al′bo·nite, the sons of Ja′shen, Jon′a·than, 33 Sham′mah the Har′a·rite, A·hi′am the son of Sha′rar the Har′a·rite, 34 E·liph′e·let the son of A·has′bai the son of the Ma·ac′a·thite, E·li′am the son of A·hith′o·phel the Gi′lon·ite, 35 Hez′ro the Car′mel·ite, Pa′a·rai the Ar′bite, 36 I′gal the son of Nathan of Zo′bah, Ba′ni the Gad′ite, 37 Ze′lek the Am′mon·ite, Na′ha·rai the Be·er′oth·ite, armor-bearers of Jo′ab the son of Ze·ru′iah, 38 I′ra the Ith′rite, Ga′reb the Ith′rite, 39 U·ri′ah the Hit′tite—thirty-seven in all.

2 Samuel

24 And again the anger of Jehovah came to be hot against Israel, when one incited David against them, saying: “Go, take a count of Israel and Judah.” 2 So the king said to Jo′ab the chief of the military forces who was with him: “Move about, please, through all the tribes of Israel, from Dan to Be′er-she′ba, and YOU men register the people, and I shall certainly know the number of the people.” 3 But Jo′ab said to the king: “May Jehovah your God even add to the people a hundred times as many as they are while the very eyes of my lord the king are seeing it. But as for my lord the king, why has he found delight in this thing?”

4 Finally the king’s word prevailed upon Jo′ab and the chiefs of the military forces. So Jo′ab and the chiefs of the military forces went out from before the king to register the people Israel. 5 Then they crossed the Jordan and took up camping at A·ro′er to the right of the city that is in the middle of the torrent valley, toward the Gad′ites, and to Ja′zer. 6 After that they came on to Gil′e·ad and the land of Tah′tim-hod′shi and continued on to Dan-ja′an and went around to Si′don. 7 Then they came to the fortress of Tyre and all the cities of the Hi′vites and of the Ca′naan·ites and came to the terminating point in the Neg′eb of Judah at Be′er-she′ba. 8 Thus they went moving about through all the land and came to Jerusalem at the end of nine months and twenty days. 9 Jo′ab now gave the number of the registration of the people to the king; and Israel amounted to eight hundred thousand valiant men drawing sword, and the men of Judah were five hundred thousand men.

10 And David’s heart began to beat him after he had so numbered the people. Consequently David said to Jehovah: “I have sinned very much in what I have done. And now, Jehovah, let your servant’s error pass by, please; for I have acted very foolishly.” 11 When David proceeded to rise up in the morning, Jehovah’s word itself came to Gad the prophet, David’s visionary, saying: 12 “Go, and you must say to David, ‘This is what Jehovah has said: “Three things I am laying upon you. Choose for yourself one of them that I may do it to you.”’” 13 Accordingly Gad came in to David and told him and said to him: “Should there come to you seven years of famine in your land, or three months of your fleeing before your adversaries, with them pursuing you, or the occurring of three days of pestilence in your land? Now know and see what I shall reply to the One sending me.” 14 So David said to Gad: “It is very distressing to me. Let us fall, please, into the hand of Jehovah, for many are his mercies; but into the hand of man do not let me fall.”

15 Then Jehovah gave a pestilence in Israel from the morning until the time appointed, so that out of the people from Dan to Be′er-she′ba seventy thousand persons died. 16 And the angel kept his hand thrust out toward Jerusalem to bring it to ruin; and Jehovah began to feel regret over the calamity, and so he said to the angel that was bringing ruin among the people: “It is enough! Now let your hand drop.” And Jehovah’s angel himself happened to be close by the threshing floor of A·rau′nah the Jeb′u·site.

17 And David proceeded to say to Jehovah, when he saw the angel that was striking the people down, yes, he proceeded to say: “Here it is I that have sinned and it is I that have done wrong; but these sheep—what have they done? Let your hand, please, come upon me and upon the house of my father.”

18 Later Gad came in to David on that day and said to him: “Go up, set up for Jehovah an altar on the threshing floor of A·rau′nah the Jeb′u·site.” 19 And David began to go up in accord with the word of Gad, according to what Jehovah had commanded. 20 When A·rau′nah looked down and saw the king and his servants passing along toward him, A·rau′nah at once went out and bowed down to the king with his face to the earth. 21 Then A·rau′nah said: “Why has my lord the king come to his servant?” At that David said: “To buy from you the threshing floor for building an altar to Jehovah, that the scourge may be halted from upon the people.” 22 But A·rau′nah said to David: “Let my lord the king take it and offer up what is good in his eyes. See the cattle for the burnt offering and the threshing sledge and the implements of the cattle for the wood. 23 Everything A·rau′nah, O king, does give to the king.” And A·rau′nah went on to say to the king: “May Jehovah your God show pleasure in you.”

24 However, the king said to A·rau′nah: “No, but without fail I shall buy it from you for a price; and I shall not offer up to Jehovah my God burnt sacrifices without cost.” Accordingly David bought the threshing floor and the cattle for fifty silver shekels. 25 And David proceeded to build there an altar to Jehovah and offer up burnt sacrifices and communion sacrifices, and Jehovah began letting himself be entreated for the land, so that the scourge was halted from upon Israel.

1 Kings

5 And Hi′ram the king of Tyre proceeded to send his servants to Sol′o·mon, for he had heard that it was he that they had anointed as king in place of his father; for a lover of David Hi′ram had always proved to be. 2 In turn Sol′o·mon sent to Hi′ram, saying: 3 “You yourself well know that David my father was not able to build a house to the name of Jehovah his God because of the warfare with which they surrounded him, until Jehovah put them under the soles of his feet. 4 And now Jehovah my God has given me rest all around. There is no resister, and there is nothing bad happening. 5 And here I am thinking of building a house to the name of Jehovah my God, just as Jehovah promised to David my father, saying, ‘Your son whom I shall put upon your throne in place of you, he is the one that will build the house to my name.’ 6 And now command that they cut for me cedars from Leb′a·non; and my servants themselves will prove to be with your servants, and the wages of your servants I shall give to you according to all that you may say, for you yourself well know that there is among us no one knowing how to cut trees like the Si·do′ni·ans.”

7 And it came about that as soon as Hi′ram heard the words of Sol′o·mon, he began to rejoice greatly, and he went on to say: “Blessed is Jehovah today in that he has given David a wise son over this numerous people!” 8 Accordingly Hi′ram sent to Sol′o·mon, saying: “I have heard what you sent to me. For my part, I shall do all your delight in the matter of timbers of cedar trees and timbers of juniper trees. 9 My servants themselves will bring them down out of Leb′a·non to the sea; and I, for my part, shall put them in log rafts to go by sea clear to the place that you will send me notice of; and I shall certainly have them broken up there, and you, for your part, will carry them; and you, for your part, will do my delight by giving the food for my household.”

10 So Hi′ram became a giver of timbers of cedar trees and timbers of juniper trees to Sol′o·mon according to all his delight. 11 And Sol′o·mon, for his part, gave Hi′ram twenty thousand cor measures of wheat as food supplies for his household and twenty cor measures of beaten-out oil. That was what Sol′o·mon kept giving Hi′ram year by year. 12 And Jehovah, for his part, gave Sol′o·mon wisdom, just as he had promised him; and there came to be peace between Hi′ram and Sol′o·mon, and both of them proceeded to conclude a covenant.

13 And King Sol′o·mon kept bringing up those conscripted for forced labor out of all Israel; and those conscripted for forced labor amounted to thirty thousand men. 14 And he would send them to Leb′a·non in shifts of ten thousand a month. For a month they would continue in Leb′a·non, for two months at their homes; and Ad·o·ni′ram was over those conscripted for forced labor. 15 And Sol′o·mon came to have seventy thousand burden bearers and eighty thousand cutters in the mountain, 16 besides Sol′o·mon’s princely deputies who were over the work, three thousand three hundred foremen over the people who were active in the work. 17 Accordingly the king commanded that they should quarry great stones, expensive stones, to lay the foundation of the house with hewn stones. 18 So Sol′o·mon’s builders and Hi′ram’s builders and the Ge′bal·ites did the cutting, and they kept preparing the timbers and the stones to build the house.

1 Kings

7 And his own house Sol′o·mon built in thirteen years, so that he finished all his own house.

2 And he proceeded to build the House of the Forest of Leb′a·non a hundred cubits in its length, and fifty cubits in its width, and thirty cubits in its height, upon four rows of pillars of cedarwood; and there were beams of cedarwood upon the pillars. 3 And it was paneled in with cedarwood above upon the girders that were upon the forty-five pillars. There were fifteen to a row. 4 As for framed windows, there were three rows, and there was an illumination opening opposite an illumination opening in three tiers. 5 And all the entrances and the doorposts were squared with the frame, and also the forefront of the illumination opening opposite an illumination opening in three tiers.

6 And the Porch of Pillars he made fifty cubits in its length, and thirty cubits in its width; and another porch was in front of them with pillars and a canopy in front of them.

7 As for the Porch of the Throne where he would do judging, he made the porch of judgment; and they covered it in with cedarwood from the floor to the rafters.

8 As regards the house of his where he was to dwell, at the other courtyard, it was away from the house belonging to the Porch. It proved to be like this in workmanship. And there was a house like this Porch that he proceeded to build for Phar′aoh’s daughter, whom Sol′o·mon had taken.

9 All these were of expensive stones according to measures, hewn, sawed with stone-saws, inside and outside, and from the foundation up to the coping, and outside as far as the great courtyard. 10 And the expensive stones laid as a foundation were great stones, stones of ten cubits, and stones of eight cubits. 11 And up above there were expensive stones according to measures, hewn, and also cedarwood. 12 As for the great courtyard, round about were three rows of hewn stone and a row of beams of cedarwood; and this also for the inner courtyard of the house of Jehovah, and for the porch of the house.

13 And King Sol′o·mon proceeded to send and fetch Hi′ram out of Tyre. 14 He was the son of a widowed woman from the tribe of Naph′ta·li, and his father was a Tyr′i·an man, a worker in copper; and he was full of the wisdom and the understanding and the knowledge for doing every sort of work in copper. Accordingly he came to King Sol′o·mon and began to do all his work.

15 Then he cast the two pillars of copper, eighteen cubits being the height of each pillar, and a string of twelve cubits would measure around each of the two pillars. 16 And two capitals he made to put upon the tops of the pillars, cast in copper. Five cubits was the height of the one capital, and five cubits was the height of the other capital. 17 There were nets in network, twisted ornaments in chainwork, for the capitals that were upon the top of the pillars; seven for the one capital, and seven for the other capital. 18 And he went on to make the pomegranates and two rows round about upon the one network to cover the capitals that were upon the top of the pillars; and that was what he did for the other capital. 19 And the capitals that were upon the top of the pillars at the porch were of lily work, of four cubits. 20 And the capitals were upon the two pillars, also up close beside the belly that was adjoining the network; and there were two hundred pomegranates in rows all around upon each capital.

21 And he proceeded to set up the pillars belonging to the porch of the temple. So he set up the right-hand pillar and called its name Ja′chin, and then set up the left-hand pillar and called its name Bo′az. 22 And upon the top of the pillars there was lily work. And the work of the pillars was gradually completed.

23 And he proceeded to make the molten sea ten cubits from its one brim to its other brim, circular all around; and its height was five cubits, and it took a line of thirty cubits to circle all around it. 24 And there were gourd-shaped ornaments down below its brim all around, encircling it, ten in a cubit, enclosing the sea all around, with two rows of the gourd-shaped ornaments cast in its casting. 25 It was standing upon twelve bulls, three facing north, and three facing west, and three facing south, and three facing east; and the sea was above upon them, and all their hind parts were toward the center. 26 And its thickness was a handbreadth; and its brim was like the workmanship of the brim of a cup, a lily blossom. Two thousand bath measures were what it would contain.

27 And he went on to make the ten carriages of copper, four cubits being the length of each carriage, and four cubits its width, and three cubits its height. 28 And this was the workmanship of the carriages: they had sidewalls, and the sidewalls were between the crossbars. 29 And upon the sidewalls that were between the crossbars there were lions, bulls and cherubs, and over the crossbars it was like that. Up above and beneath the lions and the bulls there were wreaths in hanging work. 30 And there were four wheels of copper to each carriage, with axles of copper; and its four cornerpieces were supports for them. Beneath the basin were the supports, cast with wreaths across from each. 31 And its mouth from inside to the supports and upward was [?] cubits; and its mouth was round, the workmanship of a stand of one and a half cubits, and also upon its mouth there were carvings. And their sidewalls were squared, not round. 32 And the four wheels were down below the sidewalls, and the supports of the wheels were by the carriage; and the height of each wheel was one and a half cubits. 33 And the workmanship of the wheels was like the workmanship of a chariot wheel. Their supports and their felloes and their spokes and their hubs, they were all cast. 34 And there were four supports upon the four corners of each carriage; its supports were of one piece with the carriage. 35 And on top of the carriage there was a stand a half a cubit in height, circular all around; and upon the top of the carriage its sides and its sidewalls were of one piece with it. 36 Further, he engraved upon the plates of its sides and upon its sidewalls cherubs, lions and palm-tree figures according to the clear space of each, and wreaths all around. 37 It was like this that he made the ten carriages; they all had one cast, one measure, one shape.

38 And he proceeded to make ten basins of copper. Forty bath measures were what each basin would contain. Each basin was four cubits. There was one basin upon each carriage for the ten carriages. 39 Then he put five carriages on the right side of the house, and five on the left side of the house; and the sea itself he put to the right side of the house eastward, toward the south.

40 And Hi′ram gradually made the basins and the shovels and the bowls. At length Hi′ram finished doing all the work that he did for King Sol′o·mon as respects the house of Jehovah: 41 The two pillars and the bowl-shaped capitals that were upon the top of the two pillars, and the two networks to cover the two round capitals that were upon the top of the pillars, 42 and the four hundred pomegranates for the two networks, two rows of pomegranates to each network, to cover the two bowl-shaped capitals that were upon the two pillars; 43 and the ten carriages and the ten basins upon the carriages, 44 and the one sea and the twelve bulls beneath the sea; 45 and the cans and the shovels and the bowls and all these utensils, which Hi′ram made of polished copper for King Sol′o·mon for the house of Jehovah. 46 In the District of the Jordan it was that the king cast them in the clay mold, between Suc′coth and Zar′e·than.

47 And Sol′o·mon left all the utensils unweighed because of so extraordinarily great a quantity. The weight of the copper was not ascertained. 48 And Sol′o·mon gradually made all the utensils that pertained to the house of Jehovah, the altar of gold and the table on which was the showbread, of gold, 49 and the lampstands, five to the right and five to the left before the innermost room, of pure gold, and the blossoms and the lamps and the snuffers, of gold, 50 and the basins and the extinguishers and the bowls and the cups and the fire holders, of pure gold, and the sockets for the doors of the inner house, that is, the Most Holy, and for the doors of the house of the temple, of gold.

51 Finally all the work that King Sol′o·mon had to do as regards the house of Jehovah was at its completion; and Sol′o·mon began to bring in the things made holy by David his father; the silver and the gold and the articles he put in the treasures of the house of Jehovah.

1 Kings

10 Now the queen of She′ba was hearing the report about Sol′o·mon in connection with the name of Jehovah. So she came to test him with perplexing questions. 2 Finally she arrived at Jerusalem with a very impressive train, camels carrying balsam oil and very much gold and precious stones; and she came on in to Sol′o·mon and began to speak to him all that happened to be close to her heart. 3 Sol′o·mon, in turn, went on to tell her all her matters. There proved to be no matter hidden from the king that he did not tell her.

4 When the queen of She′ba got to see all the wisdom of Sol′o·mon and the house that he had built, 5 and the food of his table and the sitting of his servants and the table service of his waiters and their attire and his drinks and his burnt sacrifices that he regularly offered up at the house of Jehovah, then there proved to be no more spirit in her. 6 So she said to the king: “True has the word proved to be that I heard in my own land about your matters and about your wisdom. 7 And I did not put faith in the words until I had come that my own eyes might see; and, look! I had not been told the half. You have surpassed in wisdom and prosperity the things heard to which I listened. 8 Happy are your men; happy are these servants of yours who are standing before you constantly, listening to your wisdom! 9 May Jehovah your God come to be blessed, who has taken delight in you by putting you upon the throne of Israel; because Jehovah loves Israel to time indefinite, so that he appointed you as king to render judicial decision and righteousness.”

10 Then she gave the king a hundred and twenty talents of gold and a very great deal of balsam oil and precious stones. There never came anymore the like of that balsam oil for quantity such as the queen of She′ba gave to King Sol′o·mon.

11 And Hi′ram’s fleet of ships that carried gold from O′phir also brought from O′phir timbers of algum trees in very great amount and precious stones. 12 And the king proceeded to make out of the timbers of the algum trees supports for the house of Jehovah and for the house of the king, and also harps and stringed instruments for the singers. Timbers of algum trees like this have not come in nor have they been seen down to this day.

13 And King Sol′o·mon himself gave the queen of She′ba all her delight for which she asked, apart from what he gave her according to the openhandedness of King Sol′o·mon. After that she turned about and went to her own land, she together with her servants.

14 And the weight of the gold that came to Sol′o·mon in one year amounted up to six hundred and sixty-six talents of gold, 15 apart from the men of travel and the profit from the traders and all the kings of the Arabs and the governors of the land.

16 And King Sol′o·mon went on to make two hundred large shields of alloyed gold (six hundred shekels of gold he proceeded to lay upon each large shield), 17 and three hundred bucklers of alloyed gold (three mi′nas of gold he proceeded to lay upon each buckler). Then the king put them in the House of the Forest of Leb′a·non.

18 Further, the king made a great ivory throne and overlaid it with refined gold. 19 There were six steps to the throne, and the throne had a round canopy behind it, and there were armrests on this side and on that side by the place of sitting, and two lions were standing beside the armrests. 20 And there were twelve lions standing there upon the six steps, on this side and on that side. No other kingdom had any made just like it.

21 And all the drinking vessels of King Sol′o·mon were of gold, and all the vessels of the House of the Forest of Leb′a·non were of pure gold. There was nothing of silver; it was considered in the days of Sol′o·mon as nothing at all. 22 For the king had a fleet of ships of Tar′shish on the sea along with Hi′ram’s fleet of ships. Once every three years the fleet of ships of Tar′shish would come carrying gold and silver, ivory, and apes and peacocks.

23 So King Sol′o·mon was greater in riches and wisdom than all the other kings of the earth. 24 And all the people of the earth were seeking the face of Sol′o·mon to hear his wisdom that God had put in his heart. 25 And they were bringing each his gift, articles of silver and articles of gold and garments and armor and balsam oil, horses and mules, as a yearly matter of course.

26 And Sol′o·mon kept gathering more chariots and steeds; and he came to have a thousand four hundred chariots and twelve thousand steeds, and he kept them stationed in the chariot cities and close by the king in Jerusalem.

27 And the king came to make the silver in Jerusalem like the stones, and cedarwood he made like the sycamore trees that are in the She·phe′lah for great quantity.

28 And there was the export of the horses that Sol′o·mon had from Egypt, and the company of the king’s merchants would themselves take the horse drove for a price. 29 And a chariot customarily came up and was exported from Egypt for six hundred silver pieces, and a horse for a hundred and fifty; and that was the way it was for all the kings of the Hit′tites and the kings of Syria. It was by means of them that they did the exporting.

1 Kings

12 And Re·ho·bo′am proceeded to go to She′chem, for it was to She′chem that all Israel came to make him king. 2 And it came about that as soon as Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat heard of it while he was yet in Egypt (because he had run off on account of King Sol′o·mon, that Jer·o·bo′am might dwell in Egypt), 3 then they sent and called him. After that Jer·o·bo′am and all the congregation of Israel came and began to speak to Re·ho·bo′am, saying: 4 “Your father, for his part, made our yoke hard, and, as for you, now make the hard service of your father and his heavy yoke that he put upon us lighter, and we shall serve you.”

5 At this he said to them: “Go away for three days and return to me.” So the people went away. 6 And King Re·ho·bo′am began to take counsel with the older men who had continued attending upon Sol′o·mon his father while he continued alive, saying: “How are YOU advising to reply to this people?” 7 Accordingly they spoke to him, saying: “If today you would prove yourself a servant to this people and actually serve them, you must also answer them and speak to them with good words; and they will be bound to become your servants always.”

8 However, he left the counsel of the older men with which they had advised him, and he began to take counsel with the young men that had grown up with him, who were the ones attending upon him. 9 And he went on to say to them: “What is it that YOU are offering in counsel that we may reply to this people who have spoken to me, saying, ‘Make the yoke that your father put upon us lighter’?” 10 In turn the young men that had grown up with him spoke to him, saying: “This is what you should say to this people who have spoken to you, saying, ‘Your father, for his part, made our yoke heavy, but, as for you, make it lighter upon us’; this is what you should speak to them, ‘My little finger itself will certainly be thicker than my father’s hips. 11 And now my father, for his part, loaded upon YOU a heavy yoke; but I, for my part, shall add to YOUR yoke. My father, for his part, chastised YOU with whips, but I, for my part, shall chastise YOU with scourges.’”

12 And Jer·o·bo′am and all the people proceeded to come to Re·ho·bo′am on the third day, just as the king had spoken, saying: “Return to me on the third day.” 13 And the king began to answer the people harshly, and to leave the counsel of the older men who had counseled him. 14 And he went on to speak to them according to the counsel of the young men, saying: “My father, for his part, made YOUR yoke heavy, but I, for my part, shall add to YOUR yoke. My father, for his part, chastised YOU with whips, but I, for my part, shall chastise YOU with scourges.” 15 And the king did not listen to the people, because the turn of affairs took place at the instance of Jehovah, in order that he might indeed carry out his word that Jehovah had spoken by means of A·hi′jah the Shi′lo·nite to Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat.

16 When all Israel got to see that the king had not listened to them, then the people replied to the king, saying: “What share do we have in David? And there is no inheritance in the son of Jes′se. To your gods, O Israel. Now see to your own house, O David!” With that Israel began to go to their tents. 17 As for the sons of Israel that were dwelling in the cities of Judah, Re·ho·bo′am continued to reign over them.

18 Subsequently King Re·ho·bo′am sent A·do′ram, who was over those conscripted for forced labor, but all Israel pelted him with stones, so that he died. And King Re·ho·bo′am himself managed to get up into the chariot to flee to Jerusalem. 19 And the Israelites kept up their revolt against the house of David down to this day.

20 And it came about that as soon as all Israel heard that Jer·o·bo′am had returned, they at once sent and called him to the assembly and made him king over all Israel. None became a follower of the house of David except the tribe of Judah by itself.

21 When Re·ho·bo′am arrived at Jerusalem, he immediately congregated all the house of Judah and the tribe of Benjamin, a hundred and eighty thousand choice men able-bodied for war, to fight against the house of Israel, so as to bring the kingship back to Re·ho·bo′am the son of Sol′o·mon. 22 Then the word of the true God came to She·mai′ah the man of the true God, saying: 23 “Say to Re·ho·bo′am the son of Sol′o·mon the king of Judah and to all the house of Judah and Benjamin and the rest of the people, 24 ‘This is what Jehovah has said: “YOU must not go up and fight against YOUR brothers the sons of Israel. Go back each one to his house, for it is at the instance of myself that this thing has been brought about.”’” So they obeyed the word of Jehovah, and went back home according to the word of Jehovah.

25 And Jer·o·bo′am proceeded to build She′chem in the mountainous region of E′phra·im and to dwell in it. Then he went forth from there and built Pe·nu′el. 26 And Jer·o·bo′am began to say in his heart: “Now the kingdom will return to the house of David. 27 If this people continues going up to render sacrifices in the house of Jehovah in Jerusalem, the heart of this people will also be bound to return to their lord, Re·ho·bo′am the king of Judah; and they will certainly kill me and return to Re·ho·bo′am the king of Judah.” 28 Consequently the king took counsel and made two golden calves and said to the people: “It is too much for YOU to go up to Jerusalem. Here is your God, O Israel, that brought you up out of the land of Egypt.” 29 Then he placed the one in Beth′el, and the other he put in Dan. 30 And this thing came to be a cause for sin, and the people began to go before the one as far as Dan.

31 And he began to make a house of high places and to make priests from the people in general, who did not happen to be of the sons of Le′vi. 32 And Jer·o·bo′am went on to make a festival in the eighth month on the fifteenth day of the month, like the festival that was in Judah, that he might make offerings upon the altar that he had made in Beth′el, to sacrifice to the calves that he had made; and he put in attendance at Beth′el the priests of the high places that he had made. 33 And he began to make offerings upon the altar that he had made in Beth′el on the fifteenth day in the eighth month, in the month that he had invented by himself; and he proceeded to make a festival for the sons of Israel and to make offerings upon the altar to make sacrificial smoke.

1 Kings

14 At that particular time A·bi′jah the son of Jer·o·bo′am fell sick. 2 So Jer·o·bo′am said to his wife: “Rise up, please, and you must disguise yourself that they may not know that you are the wife of Jer·o·bo′am, and you must go to Shi′loh. Look! There is where A·hi′jah the prophet is. He is the one that spoke with reference to me as to becoming king over this people. 3 And you must take in your hand ten loaves of bread and sprinkled cakes and a flask of honey, and you must come in to him. He it is that will certainly tell you what is going to happen to the boy.”

4 And the wife of Jer·o·bo′am proceeded to do so. Consequently she rose up and went to Shi′loh and came to the house of A·hi′jah. Now A·hi′jah himself was unable to see, for his eyes had set because of his age.

5 And Jehovah himself had said to A·hi′jah: “Here is the wife of Jer·o·bo′am coming to apply for a word from you regarding her son; for he is sick. This way and that is how you should speak to her. And it will occur that as soon as she arrives, she will be making herself unrecognizable.”

6 And it came about that as soon as A·hi′jah heard the sound of her feet as she was coming into the entrance, he began to say: “Come in, you wife of Jer·o·bo′am. Why is it that you are making yourself unrecognizable while I am being sent to you with a severe message? 7 Go, say to Jer·o·bo′am, ‘This is what Jehovah the God of Israel has said: “For the reason that I raised you up out of the middle of your people, that I might constitute you a leader over my people Israel, 8 and I went on to rip the kingdom away from the house of David and give it to you, and you have not become like my servant David, who kept my commandments and who walked after me with all his heart by doing only what was right in my eyes, 9 but you began to act worse than all those who happened to be prior to you, and you went and made for yourself another god and molten images to offend me, and it is I whom you have cast behind your back; 10 for that reason here I am bringing calamity upon the house of Jer·o·bo′am, and I shall certainly cut off from Jer·o·bo′am anyone urinating against a wall, a helpless and worthless one in Israel; and I shall indeed make a clean sweep behind the house of Jer·o·bo′am, just as one clears away the dung until it is disposed of. 11 The one dying of Jer·o·bo′am’s in the city, the dogs will eat; and the one dying in the field, the fowls of the heavens will eat, because Jehovah himself has spoken it.”’

12 “And you yourself, rise up, go to your house. When your feet come into the city the child will certainly die. 13 And all Israel will indeed bewail him and bury him, because this one alone of Jer·o·bo′am’s will come into a burial place; for the reason that something good toward Jehovah the God of Israel has been found in him in the house of Jer·o·bo′am. 14 And Jehovah will certainly raise up to himself a king over Israel who will cut off the house of Jer·o·bo′am the said day, and what if right now? 15 And Jehovah will indeed strike Israel down, just as the reed sways in the water; and he will certainly uproot Israel off this good ground that he gave to their forefathers, and he will indeed scatter them beyond the River, for the reason that they made their sacred poles, so offending Jehovah. 16 And he will give Israel up on account of the sins of Jer·o·bo′am with which he sinned and with which he caused Israel to sin.”

17 At that Jer·o·bo′am’s wife rose up and went her way and came to Tir′zah. As she was arriving at the threshold of the house, the boy himself died. 18 So they buried him, and all Israel went wailing for him, according to Jehovah’s word that he had spoken by means of his servant A·hi′jah the prophet.

19 And the rest of the affairs of Jer·o·bo′am, how he warred and how he reigned, there they are written in the book of the affairs of the days of the kings of Israel. 20 And the days that Jer·o·bo′am reigned were twenty-two years, after which he lay down with his forefathers; and Na′dab his son began to reign in place of him.

21 As for Re·ho·bo′am the son of Sol′o·mon, he had become king in Judah. Forty-one years old Re·ho·bo′am was when he began to reign, and seventeen years he reigned in Jerusalem, the city that Jehovah had chosen out of all the tribes of Israel to put his name there. And his mother’s name was Na′a·mah the Am′mon·it·ess. 22 And Judah went on doing what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah, so that they incited him to jealousy more than all that their forefathers had done by their sins with which they sinned. 23 And they too kept building for themselves high places and sacred pillars and sacred poles upon every high hill and under every luxuriant tree. 24 And even the male temple prostitute proved to be in the land. They acted according to all the detestable things of the nations whom Jehovah had driven out from before the sons of Israel.

25 And it came about in the fifth year of King Re·ho·bo′am that Shi′shak the king of Egypt came up against Jerusalem. 26 And he got to take the treasures of the house of Jehovah and the treasures of the house of the king; and everything he took. And he went on to take all the gold shields that Sol′o·mon had made. 27 Consequently King Re·ho·bo′am made in place of them copper shields, and he committed them to the control of the chiefs of the runners, the guards of the entrance of the king’s house. 28 And it would occur that as often as the king came to the house of Jehovah, the runners would carry them, and they returned them to the guard chamber of the runners.

29 And the rest of the affairs of Re·ho·bo′am and all that he did, are they not written in the book of the affairs of the times of the kings of Judah? 30 And warfare itself took place between Re·ho·bo′am and Jer·o·bo′am always. 31 Finally Re·ho·bo′am lay down with his forefathers and was buried with his forefathers in the City of David. And his mother’s name was Na′a·mah the Am′mon·it·ess. And A·bi′jam his son began to reign in place of him.

1 Kings

15 And in the eighteenth year of King Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat, A·bi′jam became king over Judah. 2 Three years he reigned in Jerusalem; and his mother’s name was Ma′a·cah the granddaughter of A·bish′a·lom. 3 And he went on walking in all the sins of his father that he did prior to him; and his heart did not prove to be complete with Jehovah his God, like the heart of David his forefather. 4 For, on account of David, Jehovah his God gave him a lamp in Jerusalem by raising his son up after him and keeping Jerusalem in existence, 5 because David did what was right in the eyes of Jehovah, and he did not turn aside from anything that He had commanded him all the days of his life, only in the matter of U·ri′ah the Hit′tite. 6 And warfare itself took place between Re·ho·bo′am and Jer·o·bo′am all the days of his life.

7 As for the rest of the affairs of A·bi′jam and all that he did, are they not written in the book of the affairs of the days of the kings of Judah? There was warfare also that took place between A·bi′jam and Jer·o·bo′am. 8 Finally A·bi′jam lay down with his forefathers and they buried him in the City of David; and A′sa his son began to reign in place of him.

9 In the twentieth year of Jer·o·bo′am the king of Israel, A′sa reigned as king of Judah. 10 And forty-one years he reigned in Jerusalem; and his grandmother’s name was Ma′a·cah the granddaughter of A·bish′a·lom. 11 And A′sa proceeded to do what was right in the eyes of Jehovah, like David his forefather. 12 Accordingly he had the male temple prostitutes pass out of the land and removed all the dungy idols that his forefathers had made. 13 As for even Ma′a·cah his grandmother, he went on to remove her from being lady, because she had made a horrible idol to the sacred pole; after which A′sa cut down her horrible idol and burned it at the torrent valley of Kid′ron. 14 And the high places he did not remove. Nevertheless, A′sa’s heart itself proved to be complete with Jehovah all his days. 15 And he began to bring in the things made holy by his father and the things made holy by himself into the house of Jehovah, silver and gold and articles.

16 And warfare itself took place between A′sa and Ba′a·sha the king of Israel all their days. 17 So Ba′a·sha the king of Israel came up against Judah and began to build Ra′mah, to allow no one to go out or come in to A′sa the king of Judah. 18 At that A′sa took all the silver and the gold that were left in the treasures of the house of Jehovah and the treasures of the house of the king and put them in the hand of his servants; and King A′sa now sent them to Ben-ha′dad the son of Tab·rim′mon the son of He′zi·on, the king of Syria, who was dwelling in Damascus, saying: 19 “There is a covenant between me and you, between my father and your father. Here I have sent you a present of silver and gold. Come, do break your covenant with Ba′a·sha the king of Israel, that he may withdraw from me.” 20 Accordingly Ben-ha′dad listened to King A′sa and sent the chiefs of the military forces that were his against the cities of Israel and went striking down I′jon and Dan and A′bel-beth-ma′a·cah and all Chin′ne·reth, as far as all the land of Naph′ta·li. 21 And it came about that as soon as Ba′a·sha heard of it, he immediately quit building Ra′mah and continued dwelling in Tir′zah. 22 And King A′sa, for his part, summoned all Judah—there was none exempt—and they proceeded to carry the stones of Ra′mah and the timbers of it, with which Ba′a·sha had been building; and King A′sa began to build with them Ge′ba in Benjamin, and Miz′pah.

23 As for the rest of all the affairs of A′sa and all his mightiness and all that he did and the cities that he built, are they not written in the book of the affairs of the days of the kings of Judah? Only at the time of his growing old he got diseased in his feet. 24 Finally A′sa lay down with his forefathers and was buried with his forefathers in the City of David his forefather; and Je·hosh′a·phat his son began to reign in place of him.

25 As for Na′dab the son of Jer·o·bo′am, he became king over Israel in the second year of A′sa the king of Judah; and he continued to reign over Israel two years. 26 And he kept doing what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah and went on walking in the way of his father and in his sin with which he caused Israel to sin. 27 And Ba′a·sha the son of A·hi′jah of the house of Is′sa·char began to conspire against him; and Ba′a·sha got to strike him down at Gib′be·thon, which belonged to the Phi·lis′tines, while Na′dab and all Israel were besieging Gib′be·thon. 28 So Ba′a·sha put him to death in the third year of A′sa the king of Judah and began to reign in place of him. 29 And it came about that as soon as he became king, he struck down all the house of Jer·o·bo′am. He did not let anyone breathing remain of Jer·o·bo′am’s until he had annihilated them, according to Jehovah’s word that he had spoken by means of his servant A·hi′jah the Shi′lo·nite, 30 on account of the sins of Jer·o·bo′am with which he sinned and with which he caused Israel to sin and by his offensiveness with which he offended Jehovah the God of Israel. 31 As for the rest of the affairs of Na′dab and all that he did, are they not written in the book of the affairs of the days of the kings of Israel? 32 And warfare itself took place between A′sa and Ba′a·sha the king of Israel all their days.

33 In the third year of A′sa the king of Judah, Ba′a·sha the son of A·hi′jah became king over all Israel in Tir′zah for twenty-four years. 34 And he kept doing what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah and went walking in the way of Jer·o·bo′am and in his sin with which he caused Israel to sin.

1 Kings

16 The word of Jehovah now came to Je′hu the son of Ha·na′ni against Ba′a·sha, saying: 2 “Inasmuch as I raised you up out of the dust that I might constitute you leader over my people Israel, but you went walking in the way of Jer·o·bo′am and so caused my people Israel to sin by offending me with their sins, 3 here I am making a clean sweep after Ba′a·sha and after his house, and I shall certainly constitute his house like the house of Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat. 4 Anyone of Ba′a·sha that is dying in the city the dogs will eat; and anyone of his that is dying in the field the fowls of the heavens will eat.”

5 As for the rest of the affairs of Ba′a·sha and what he did and his mightiness, are they not written in the book of the affairs of the days of the kings of Israel? 6 Finally Ba′a·sha lay down with his forefathers and was buried in Tir′zah; and E′lah his son began to reign in place of him. 7 And also by means of Je′hu the son of Ha·na′ni the prophet, Jehovah’s word itself had come against Ba′a·sha and his house, both because of all the badness that he committed in the eyes of Jehovah by offending him with the work of his hands, that it might become like the house of Jer·o·bo′am, and because he struck him down.

8 In the twenty-sixth year of A′sa the king of Judah, E′lah the son of Ba′a·sha became king over Israel in Tir′zah for two years. 9 And his servant Zim′ri the chief of half the chariots began to conspire against him, while he was in Tir′zah drinking himself drunk at the house of Ar′za, who was over the household in Tir′zah. 10 And Zim′ri proceeded to come in and strike him down and put him to death in the twenty-seventh year of A′sa the king of Judah, and he began to reign in place of him. 11 And it came about that when he began to reign, as soon as he sat down upon his throne, he struck down all the house of Ba′a·sha. He did not let anyone of his remain that urinates against a wall or his avengers of blood or his friends. 12 Thus Zim′ri annihilated the whole house of Ba′a·sha, according to the word of Jehovah that he had spoken against Ba′a·sha by means of Je′hu the prophet, 13 on account of all the sins of Ba′a·sha and the sins of E′lah his son with which they sinned and with which they caused Israel to sin by offending Jehovah the God of Israel with their vain idols. 14 As for the rest of the affairs of E′lah and all that he did, are they not written in the book of the affairs of the days of the kings of Israel?

15 In the twenty-seventh year of A′sa the king of Judah, Zim′ri became king for seven days in Tir′zah, while the people were encamping against Gib′be·thon, which belonged to the Phi·lis′tines. 16 In time the people that were encamped heard it said: “Zim′ri has conspired and also struck down the king.” So all Israel made Om′ri, the chief of the army, king over Israel on that day in the camp. 17 Om′ri and all Israel with him now went on up from Gib′be·thon and began to lay siege to Tir′zah. 18 And it came about that as soon as Zim′ri saw that the city had been captured, he then came into the dwelling tower of the king’s house and burned the king’s house over himself with fire, so that he died, 19 for the sins of his with which he had sinned by doing what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah by walking in the way of Jer·o·bo′am and in his sin which he did by causing Israel to sin. 20 As for the rest of the affairs of Zim′ri and his conspiracy with which he conspired, are they not written in the book of the affairs of the days of the kings of Israel?

21 It was then that the people of Israel began to divide themselves into two parts. There was one part of the people that became followers of Tib′ni the son of Gi′nath, to make him king, and the other part followers of Om′ri. 22 Finally the people that were following Om′ri overcame the people that were following Tib′ni the son of Gi′nath; so that Tib′ni met death, and Om′ri began to reign.

23 In the thirty-first year of A′sa the king of Judah, Om′ri became king over Israel for twelve years. In Tir′zah he reigned six years. 24 And he proceeded to buy the mountain of Sa·mar′i·a from She′mer for two talents of silver, and began to build on the mountain and call the name of the city that he built by the name of She′mer the master of the mountain, Sa·mar′i·a. 25 And Om′ri kept doing what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah and came to do worse than all who were prior to him. 26 And he went walking in all the way of Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat and in his sin with which he caused Israel to sin by offending Jehovah the God of Israel with their vain idols. 27 As for the rest of the affairs of Om′ri, what he did and his mightiness with which he acted, are they not written in the book of the affairs of the days of the kings of Israel? 28 Finally Om′ri lay down with his forefathers and was buried in Sa·mar′i·a; and A′hab his son began to reign in place of him.

29 And as for A′hab the son of Om′ri, he became king over Israel in the thirty-eighth year of A′sa the king of Judah; and A′hab the son of Om′ri continued to reign over Israel in Sa·mar′i·a twenty-two years. 30 And A′hab the son of Om′ri proceeded to do worse in the eyes of Jehovah than all those who were prior to him. 31 And it came about that, as if it were the most trivial thing for him to walk in the sins of Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat, he now took as wife Jez′e·bel the daughter of Eth·ba′al the king of the Si·do′ni·ans and began to go and serve Ba′al and to bow down to him. 32 Further, he set up an altar to Ba′al at the house of Ba′al that he built in Sa·mar′i·a. 33 And A′hab went on to make the sacred pole; and A′hab came to do more to offend Jehovah the God of Israel than all the kings of Israel that happened to be prior to him.

34 In his days Hi′el the Beth′el·ite built Jer′i·cho. At the forfeit of A·bi′ram his firstborn he laid the foundation of it, and at the forfeit of Se′gub his youngest he put up its doors, according to Jehovah’s word that he spoke by means of Joshua the son of Nun.

1 Kings

18 And it came about after many days that Jehovah’s own word came to E·li′jah in the third year, saying: “Go, show yourself to A′hab, as I am determined to give rain upon the surface of the ground.” 2 Accordingly E·li′jah went to show himself to A′hab, while the famine was severe in Sa·mar′i·a.

3 Meantime, A′hab called O·ba·di′ah, who was over the household. (Now O·ba·di′ah himself had proved to be one greatly fearing Jehovah. 4 Hence it came about that when Jez′e·bel cut off Jehovah’s prophets, O·ba·di′ah proceeded to take a hundred prophets and keep them hid by fifties in a cave, and he supplied them bread and water.) 5 And A′hab went on to say to O·ba·di′ah: “Go through the land to all the springs of water and to all the torrent valleys. Perhaps we may find green grass, that we may preserve the horses and mules alive and may not have any more of the beasts cut off.” 6 So they divided between themselves the land through which to pass. A′hab himself went alone by one way, and O·ba·di′ah himself went alone by another way.

7 As O·ba·di′ah continued on the way, why, there was E·li′jah to meet him. At once he recognized him and fell upon his face and said: “Is this you, my lord E·li′jah?” 8 At this he said to him: “It is I. Go, say to your lord, ‘Here is E·li′jah.’” 9 But he said: “What sin have I committed that you should be putting your servant into the hand of A′hab to put me to death? 10 As Jehovah your God is living, there is not a nation or kingdom where my lord has not sent to look for you. After they had said, ‘He is not here,’ he made the kingdom and the nation swear that they could not find you. 11 And now you are saying, ‘Go, say to your lord: “Here is E·li′jah.”’ 12 And it is bound to occur that, when I myself go from you, then the spirit of Jehovah itself will carry you away to where I shall not know; and I shall have come to tell A′hab, and he will not find you, and he will be bound to kill me, as your servant himself has feared Jehovah from his youth. 13 Has not my lord been told what I did when Jez′e·bel killed the prophets of Jehovah, how I kept some of the prophets of Jehovah hid, a hundred men by fifties in a cave, and kept supplying them bread and water? 14 And now you are saying, ‘Go, say to your lord: “Here is E·li′jah.”’ And he will be bound to kill me.” 15 However, E·li′jah said: “As Jehovah of armies before whom I do stand is living, today I shall show myself to him.”

16 Accordingly O·ba·di′ah went off to meet A′hab and told him; and so A′hab went to meet E·li′jah.

17 And it came about that, as soon as A′hab saw E·li′jah, A′hab immediately said to him: “Is this you, the bringer of ostracism upon Israel?”

18 To this he said: “I have not brought ostracism upon Israel, but you and the house of your father have, because YOU men have left the commandments of Jehovah, and you went following the Ba′als. 19 And now send, collect together all Israel to me at Mount Car′mel and also the four hundred and fifty prophets of Ba′al and the four hundred prophets of the sacred pole, who are eating at the table of Jez′e·bel.” 20 And A′hab proceeded to send among all the sons of Israel and collect the prophets together at Mount Car′mel.

21 Then E·li′jah approached all the people and said: “How long will YOU be limping upon two different opinions? If Jehovah is the true God, go following him; but if Ba′al is, go following him.” And the people did not say a word in answer to him. 22 And E·li′jah went on to say to the people: “I myself have been left as a prophet of Jehovah, I alone, while the prophets of Ba′al are four hundred and fifty men. 23 Now let them give us two young bulls, and let them choose for themselves one young bull and cut it in pieces and put it upon the wood, but they should not put fire to it. And I myself shall dress the other young bull, and I must place it upon the wood, but I shall not put fire to it. 24 And YOU must call upon the name of YOUR god, and I, for my part, shall call upon the name of Jehovah; and it must occur that the true God that answers by fire is the true God.” To this all the people answered and said: “The thing is good.”

25 E·li′jah now said to the prophets of Ba′al: “Choose for yourselves one young bull and dress it first, because YOU are the majority; and call upon the name of YOUR god, but YOU must not put fire to it.” 26 Accordingly they took the young bull that he gave them. Then they dressed it, and they kept calling upon the name of Ba′al from morning till noon, saying: “O Ba′al, answer us!” But there was no voice, and there was no one answering. And they kept limping around the altar that they had made. 27 And it came about at noon that E·li′jah began to mock them and say: “Call at the top of YOUR voice, for he is a god; for he must be concerned with a matter, and he has excrement and has to go to the privy. Or maybe he is asleep and ought to wake up!” 28 And they began calling at the top of their voice and cutting themselves according to their custom with daggers and with lances, until they caused blood to flow out upon them. 29 And it came about that, as soon as noon was past and they continued behaving as prophets until the going up of the grain offering, there was no voice, and there was no one answering, and there was no paying of attention.

30 At length E·li′jah said to all the people: “Approach me.” So all the people approached him. Then he proceeded to mend the altar of Jehovah that was torn down. 31 So E·li′jah took twelve stones, according to the number of the tribes of the sons of Jacob, to whom Jehovah’s word had come, saying: “Israel is what your name will become.” 32 And he went on to build the stones into an altar in the name of Jehovah and to make a trench, of about the area sowed with two seah measures of seed, all around the altar. 33 After that he put the pieces of wood in order and cut the young bull in pieces and placed it upon the pieces of wood. He now said: “FILL four large jars with water and pour it upon the burnt offering and upon the pieces of wood.” 34 Then he said: “Do it again.” So they did it again. But he said: “Do it a third time.” So they did it a third time. 35 Thus the water went all around the altar, and the trench also he filled with water.

36 And it came about at the time that the grain offering goes up that E·li′jah the prophet began to approach and say: “O Jehovah, the God of Abraham, Isaac and Israel, today let it be known that you are God in Israel and I am your servant and it is by your word that I have done all these things. 37 Answer me, O Jehovah, answer me, that this people may know that you, Jehovah, are the true God and you yourself have turned their heart back.”

38 At that the fire of Jehovah came falling and went eating up the burnt offering and the pieces of wood and the stones and the dust, and the water that was in the trench it licked up. 39 When all the people saw it, they immediately fell upon their faces and said: “Jehovah is the true God! Jehovah is the true God!” 40 Then E·li′jah said to them: “Seize the prophets of Ba′al! Do not let a single one of them escape!” At once they seized them, and E·li′jah then brought them down to the torrent valley of Ki′shon and slaughtered them there.

41 E·li′jah now said to A′hab: “Go up, eat and drink; for there is the sound of the turmoil of a downpour.” 42 And A′hab proceeded to go up to eat and drink. As for E·li′jah, he went up to the top of Car′mel and began crouching to the earth and keeping his face put between his knees. 43 Then he said to his attendant: “Go up, please. Look in the direction of the sea.” So he went up and looked and then said: “There is nothing at all.” And he went on to say, “Go back,” for seven times. 44 And it came about at the seventh time that he got to say: “Look! There is a small cloud like a man’s palm ascending out of the sea.” He now said: “Go up, say to A′hab, ‘Hitch up! And go down that the downpour may not detain you!’” 45 And it came about in the meantime that the heavens themselves darkened up with clouds and wind and a great downpour began to occur. And A′hab kept riding and made his way to Jez′re·el. 46 And the very hand of Jehovah proved to be upon E·li′jah, so that he girded up his hips and went running ahead of A′hab all the way to Jez′re·el.

1 Kings

20 As for Ben-ha′dad the king of Syria, he collected all his military forces together and also thirty-two kings with him and horses and chariots, and he proceeded to go up and lay siege to Sa·mar′i·a and fight against it. 2 Then he sent messengers to A′hab the king of Israel at the city. And he went on to say to him: “This is what Ben-ha′dad has said, 3 ‘Your silver and your gold are mine, and your wives and your sons, the best looking, are mine.’” 4 To this the king of Israel answered and said: “According to your word, my lord the king, yours I am with all that belongs to me.”

5 Later the messengers came back and said: “This is what Ben-ha′dad has said, ‘I sent to you, saying: “Your silver and your gold and your wives and your sons you will give me. 6 But about this time tomorrow I shall send my servants to you, and they must carefully search your house and the houses of your servants; and it must occur that everything desirable to your eyes they will put in their hand, and they must take it away.”’”

7 At that the king of Israel called all the older men of the land and said: “Take note, please, and see that it is calamity that this one is seeking; for he sent to me for my wives and my sons and my silver and my gold, and I did not hold them back from him.” 8 Then all the older men and all the people said to him: “Do not obey, and you should not consent.” 9 So he said to the messengers of Ben-ha′dad: “Say to my lord the king, ‘All that you sent to your servant at first I shall do; but this thing I am not able to do.’” With that the messengers went off and brought word back to him.

10 Ben-ha′dad now sent to him and said: “So may the gods do to me, and so may they add to it, if the dust of Sa·mar′i·a will be sufficient for handfuls for all the people that follow me!” 11 In turn the king of Israel answered and said: “YOU men, speak to him, ‘Do not let one girding on boast about himself like one unfastening.’” 12 And it came about that as soon as he heard this word, while he himself and the kings were drinking in the booths, he immediately said to his servants: “Get set!” And they began to get set against the city.

13 And, look! a certain prophet approached A′hab the king of Israel and then said: “This is what Jehovah has said, ‘Have you seen all this great crowd? Here I am giving it into your hand today, and you will certainly know that I am Jehovah.’” 14 Then A′hab said: “By whom?” to which he said: “This is what Jehovah has said, ‘By the young men of the princes of the jurisdictional districts.’” Finally he said: “Who will open the battle engagement?” to which he said: “You!”

15 And he proceeded to take the count of the young men of the princes of the jurisdictional districts, and they came to be two hundred and thirty-two; and after them he took the count of all the people, all the sons of Israel, seven thousand. 16 And they began to go out at noon while Ben-ha′dad was drinking himself drunk in the booths, he together with the kings, the thirty-two kings that were helping him. 17 When the young men of the princes of the jurisdictional districts came out first, Ben-ha′dad at once sent out; and they came telling him, saying: “There are men that have come out from Sa·mar′i·a.” 18 At that he said: “Whether it is for peace that they have come out, YOU should seize them alive; or whether it is for battle that they have come out, alive is how YOU should seize them.” 19 And these were the ones that came out from the city, the young men of the princes of the jurisdictional districts and the military forces that were behind them. 20 And they began to strike down each one his man; and the Syrians took to flight, and Israel went in pursuit of them, but Ben-ha′dad the king of Syria got to escape upon a horse together with the horsemen. 21 But the king of Israel went out and kept striking down the horses and the chariots, and he struck down the Syrians with a great slaughter.

22 Later the prophet approached the king of Israel and said to him: “Go, strengthen yourself and take note and see what you are going to do; for at the return of the year the king of Syria is coming up against you.”

23 As for the servants of the king of Syria, they said to him: “Their God is a God of mountains. That is why they proved stronger than we were. So, on the other hand, let us fight against them on the level land and see whether we shall not prove stronger than they are. 24 And do this thing: Remove the kings each one from his place and put in governors instead of them. 25 As for you, you should number a military force for yourself equal to the military force that fell from your side, with horse for horse and chariot for chariot; and let us fight against them on the level land and see whether we shall not prove stronger than they are.” Accordingly he listened to their voice and did just that way.

26 And it came about at the return of the year that Ben-ha′dad proceeded to muster the Syrians and to go up to A′phek for battle against Israel. 27 As for the sons of Israel, they were mustered and supplied and began to go out to meet them; and the sons of Israel went into camp in front of them like two tiny flocks of goats, while the Syrians, for their part, filled the earth. 28 Then the man of the true God approached and said to the king of Israel, yes, he went on to say: “This is what Jehovah has said, ‘For the reason that the Syrians have said: “Jehovah is a God of mountains, and he is not a God of low plains,” I shall have to give all this great crowd into your hand, and YOU men will certainly know that I am Jehovah.’”

29 And they continued encamped for seven days, these in front of those. And it came about on the seventh day that the engagement in battle began; and the sons of Israel went striking down the Syrians, a hundred thousand men on foot in one day. 30 And those that were left went fleeing to A′phek, to the city; and the wall came falling down upon twenty-seven thousand men that were left. As for Ben-ha′dad, he fled and finally came into the city into the innermost chamber.

31 So his servants said to him: “Here, now, we have heard that the kings of the house of Israel are kings of loving-kindness. Please, let us carry sackcloth upon our loins and ropes upon our heads, and let us go out to the king of Israel. Perhaps he will preserve your soul alive.” 32 Accordingly they girded sackcloth about their loins, with ropes upon their heads, and came in to the king of Israel and said: “Your servant Ben-ha′dad has said, ‘Please, let my soul live.’” To this he said: “Is he still alive? He is my brother.” 33 So the men themselves took it as an omen and quickly took it as a decision of his own accord, and they went on to say: “Ben-ha′dad is your brother.” At that he said: “Come, fetch him.” Then Ben-ha′dad went out to him; and he at once had him get up into the chariot.

34 Ben-ha′dad now said to him: “The cities that my father took from your father I shall return; and streets you will assign to yourself in Damascus the same as my father assigned in Sa·mar′i·a.”

“And as for me, in a covenant I shall send you away.”

With that he concluded a covenant with him and sent him away.

35 And a certain man of the sons of the prophets said to his friend by the word of Jehovah: “Strike me, please.” But the man refused to strike him. 36 Therefore he said to him: “For the reason that you did not listen to the voice of Jehovah, here you are going away from me, and a lion will certainly strike you down.” After that he went away from beside him, and the lion got to find him and strike him down.

37 And he went on to find another man and to say: “Strike me, please.” So the man struck him, striking and wounding.

38 Then the prophet went and stood still for the king by the road, and he kept himself disguised with a bandage over his eyes. 39 And it came about that as the king was passing by, he cried out to the king and proceeded to say: “Your servant himself went out into the thick of the battle; and, look! a man was leaving the line, and he came bringing a man to me and then said, ‘Guard this man. If he should in any way be missing, your soul will also have to take the place of his soul, or else a talent of silver you will weigh out.’ 40 And it came about that as your servant was active here and there, why, he himself was gone.” At this the king of Israel said to him: “Thus your own judgment is. You yourself have decided.” 41 Upon that he hurriedly removed the bandage from over his eyes, and the king of Israel got to recognize him, that he was from the prophets. 42 He now said to him: “This is what Jehovah has said, ‘For the reason that you have let go out of your hand the man devoted to me for destruction, your soul must take the place of his soul, and your people the place of his people.’” 43 At that the king of Israel went on his way toward his house, sullen and dejected, and came to Sa·mar′i·a.

1 Kings

21 And it came about after these things that there was a vineyard that happened to belong to Na′both the Jez′re·el·ite, which was in Jez′re·el, beside the palace of A′hab the king of Sa·mar′i·a. 2 So A′hab spoke to Na′both, saying: “Do give me your vineyard, that it may serve as a garden of vegetables to me, for it is close by my house; and let me give you in place of it a vineyard better than it. Or if it is good in your eyes, I will give you money as the price of this.” 3 But Na′both said to A′hab: “It is unthinkable on my part, from Jehovah’s standpoint, for me to give the hereditary possession of my forefathers to you.” 4 Consequently A′hab came into his house, sullen and dejected over the word that Na′both the Jez′re·el·ite had spoken to him, when he said: “I shall not give you the hereditary possession of my forefathers.” Then he lay down upon his couch and kept his face turned, and he did not eat bread.

5 Finally Jez′e·bel his wife came in to him and spoke to him: “Why is it that your spirit is sad and you are not eating bread?” 6 At that he spoke to her: “Because I proceeded to speak to Na′both the Jez′re·el·ite and say to him, ‘Do give me your vineyard for money. Or, if you prefer, let me give you another vineyard in place of it.’ But he said, ‘I shall not give you my vineyard.’” 7 Then Jez′e·bel his wife said to him: “Is it you that now exercise the kingship over Israel? Rise up, eat bread and let your heart be merry. I myself shall give you the vineyard of Na′both the Jez′re·el·ite.” 8 Accordingly she wrote letters in A′hab’s name and sealed them with his seal, and sent the letters to the older men and the nobles that were in his city dwelling with Na′both. 9 But she wrote in the letters, saying: “Proclaim a fast, and HAVE Na′both sit at the head of the people. 10 And MAKE two men, good-for-nothing fellows, sit in front of him, and let them bear witness against him, saying, ‘You have cursed God and the king!’ And BRING him out and stone him that he may die.”

11 So the men of his city, the older men and the nobles that were dwelling in his city, did just as Jez′e·bel had sent to them, just as it was written in the letters that she had sent to them. 12 They proclaimed a fast and had Na′both sit at the head of the people. 13 Then two of the men, good-for-nothing fellows, came in and sat down in front of him; and the good-for-nothing men began to bear witness against him, that is, Na′both, in front of the people, saying: “Na′both has cursed God and the king!” After that they brought him out to the outskirts of the city and stoned him with stones, so that he died. 14 They now sent to Jez′e·bel, saying: “Na′both has been stoned so that he is dead.”

15 And it came about that, as soon as Jez′e·bel heard that Na′both had been stoned so that he died, Jez′e·bel immediately said to A′hab: “Rise up, take possession of the vineyard of Na′both the Jez′re·el·ite, which he refused to give you for money; for Na′both is no longer alive, but dead.” 16 And it came about that, as soon as A′hab heard that Na′both was dead, A′hab at once rose up to go down to the vineyard of Na′both the Jez′re·el·ite, to take possession of it.

17 And Jehovah’s word came to E·li′jah the Tish′bite, saying: 18 “Rise up, go down to meet A′hab the king of Israel, who is in Sa·mar′i·a. There he is in the vineyard of Na′both, where he has gone down to take possession of it. 19 And you must speak to him, saying, ‘This is what Jehovah has said: “Have you murdered and also taken possession?”’ And you must speak to him, saying, ‘This is what Jehovah has said: “In the place where the dogs licked up the blood of Na′both, the dogs will lick up your blood, even yours.”’”

20 And A′hab proceeded to say to E·li′jah: “Have you found me, O enemy of mine?” to which he said: “I have found you. ‘For the reason that you have sold yourself to do what is bad in the eyes of Jehovah, 21 here I am bringing calamity upon you; and I shall certainly make a clean sweep after you and cut off from A′hab anyone urinating against a wall and the helpless and worthless one in Israel. 22 And I shall certainly constitute your house like the house of Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat and like the house of Ba′a·sha the son of A·hi′jah, for the offense with which you have offended and then caused Israel to sin.’ 23 And also as regards Jez′e·bel Jehovah has spoken, saying, ‘The very dogs will eat up Jez′e·bel in the plot of land of Jez′re·el. 24 Anyone of A′hab’s that is dying in the city the dogs will eat up; and anyone dying in the field the fowls of the heavens will eat up. 25 Without exception no one has proved to be like A′hab, who sold himself to do what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah, whom Jez′e·bel his wife egged on. 26 And he went acting very detestably by going after the dungy idols, the same as all that the Am′or·ites had done, whom Jehovah drove out from before the sons of Israel.’”

27 And it came about that as soon as A′hab heard these words, he proceeded to rip his garments apart and to put sackcloth upon his flesh; and he went on a fast and kept lying down in sackcloth and walking despondently. 28 And Jehovah’s word came to E·li′jah the Tish′bite, saying: 29 “Have you seen how A′hab has humbled himself on my account? For the reason that he has humbled himself because of me, I shall not bring the calamity in his own days. In the days of his son I shall bring the calamity upon his house.”

1 Kings

22 And for three years they continued dwelling without war between Syria and Israel. 2 And it came about in the third year that Je·hosh′a·phat the king of Judah proceeded to go down to the king of Israel. 3 Then the king of Israel said to his servants: “Do YOU really know that Ra′moth-gil′e·ad belongs to us? Yet we are hesitating to take it out of the hand of the king of Syria.” 4 And he went on to say to Je·hosh′a·phat: “Will you go with me to the fight at Ra′moth-gil′e·ad?” At this Je·hosh′a·phat said to the king of Israel: “I am the same as you. My people are the same as your people. My horses are the same as your horses.”

5 However, Je·hosh′a·phat went on to say to the king of Israel: “Inquire, please, first of all for the word of Jehovah.” 6 So the king of Israel collected the prophets together, about four hundred men, and said to them: “Shall I go against Ra′moth-gil′e·ad in war, or shall I refrain?” And they began to say: “Go up, and Jehovah will give it into the king’s hand.”

7 But Je·hosh′a·phat said: “Is there not here a prophet of Jehovah still? Then let us inquire through him.” 8 At that the king of Israel said to Je·hosh′a·phat: “There is still one man through whom to inquire of Jehovah; but I myself certainly hate him, for he does not prophesy good things concerning me but bad—Mi·cai′ah the son of Im′lah.” However, Je·hosh′a·phat said: “Do not let the king say a thing like that.”

9 Accordingly the king of Israel called a certain court official and said: “Do bring Mi·cai′ah the son of Im′lah quickly.” 10 Now the king of Israel and Je·hosh′a·phat the king of Judah were sitting each one on his throne, clothed in garments, in the threshing floor at the entrance of the gate of Sa·mar′i·a; and all the prophets were acting as prophets before them. 11 Then Zed·e·ki′ah the son of Che·na′a·nah made for himself horns of iron and said: “This is what Jehovah has said, ‘With these you will push the Syrians until you exterminate them.’” 12 And all the other prophets were prophesying the same as that, saying: “Go up to Ra′moth-gil′e·ad and prove successful; and Jehovah will certainly give it into the king’s hand.”

13 And the messenger that had gone to call Mi·cai′ah spoke to him, saying: “Look, now! The words of the prophets are unanimously of good to the king. Let your word, please, become like the word of one of them, and you must speak good.” 14 But Mi·cai′ah said: “As Jehovah is living, what Jehovah will say to me, that is what I shall speak.” 15 Then he came in to the king, and the king proceeded to say to him: “Mi·cai′ah, shall we go to Ra′moth-gil′e·ad in war, or shall we refrain?” At once he said to him: “Go up and prove successful; and Jehovah will certainly give it into the king’s hand.” 16 At that the king said to him: “For how many times am I putting you under oath that you should not speak to me anything but truth in the name of Jehovah?” 17 So he said: “I certainly see all the Israelites scattered on the mountains, like sheep that have no shepherd. And Jehovah went on to say: ‘These have no masters. Let them go back each one to his house in peace.’”

18 Then the king of Israel said to Je·hosh′a·phat: “Did I not say to you, ‘He will prophesy concerning me, not good things, but bad’?”

19 And he went on to say: “Therefore hear the word of Jehovah: I certainly see Jehovah sitting upon his throne and all the army of the heavens standing by him, to his right and to his left. 20 And Jehovah proceeded to say, ‘Who will fool A′hab, that he may go up and fall at Ra′moth-gil′e·ad?’ And this one began to say something like this, while that one was saying something like that. 21 Finally a spirit came out and stood before Jehovah and said, ‘I myself shall fool him.’ At that Jehovah said to him, ‘By what means?’ 22 To this he said, ‘I shall go forth, and I shall certainly become a deceptive spirit in the mouth of all his prophets.’ So he said, ‘You will fool him, and, what is more, you will come off the winner. Go out and do that way.’ 23 And now here Jehovah has put a deceptive spirit into the mouth of all these prophets of yours; but Jehovah himself has spoken calamity concerning you.”

24 Zed·e·ki′ah the son of Che·na′a·nah now approached and struck Mi·cai′ah upon the cheek and said: “In just which way did the spirit of Jehovah pass along from me to speak with you?” 25 At that Mi·cai′ah said: “Look! You are seeing which way on that day when you will enter the innermost chamber to hide yourself.” 26 Then the king of Israel said: “Take Mi·cai′ah and turn him back to A′mon the chief of the city and to Jo′ash the king’s son. 27 And you must say, ‘This is what the king has said: “PUT this fellow in the house of detention and feed him with a reduced allowance of bread and a reduced allowance of water until I come in peace.”’” 28 Upon that Mi·cai′ah said: “If you return at all in peace, Jehovah has not spoken with me.” And he added: “Hear, all YOU peoples.”

29 And the king of Israel and Je·hosh′a·phat the king of Judah proceeded to go up to Ra′moth-gil′e·ad. 30 The king of Israel now said to Je·hosh′a·phat: “There will be a disguising and entering into the battle for me, but you, for your part, put on your garments.” Accordingly, the king of Israel disguised himself and entered into the battle. 31 As for the king of Syria, he had commanded the thirty-two chiefs of the chariots that were his, saying: “YOU must fight, neither with the small nor the great, but with the king of Israel alone.” 32 And it came about that, as soon as the chiefs of the chariots saw Je·hosh′a·phat, they, for their part, said to themselves: “Surely it is the king of Israel.” So they turned aside against him to fight; and Je·hosh′a·phat began to cry for aid. 33 And it came about that, as soon as the chiefs of the chariots saw that it was not the king of Israel, they immediately came back from following him.

34 And there was a man that bent the bow in his innocence, but he got to strike the king of Israel between the appendages and the coat of mail, so that he said to his charioteer: “Turn your hand around, and take me out from the camp, because I have been badly wounded.” 35 And the battle kept rising in intensity on that day, and the king himself had to be kept in a standing position in the chariot facing the Syrians, and gradually he died in the evening; and the blood of the wound kept pouring out upon the interior of the war chariot. 36 And the ringing cry began to pass through the camp about the setting of the sun, saying: “Everyone to his city, and everyone to his land!” 37 Thus the king died. When he was brought to Sa·mar′i·a, then they buried the king in Sa·mar′i·a. 38 And they began to wash off the war chariot by the pool of Sa·mar′i·a, and the dogs went licking up his blood (and the prostitutes themselves bathed there), according to Jehovah’s word that he had spoken.

39 As for the rest of the affairs of A′hab and all that he did and the house of ivory that he built and all the cities that he built, are they not written in the book of the affairs of the days of the kings of Israel? 40 Finally A′hab lay down with his forefathers; and A·ha·zi′ah his son began to reign in place of him.

41 As for Je·hosh′a·phat the son of A′sa, he had become king over Judah in the fourth year of A′hab the king of Israel. 42 Je·hosh′a·phat was thirty-five years old when he began to reign, and for twenty-five years he reigned in Jerusalem; and his mother’s name was A·zu′bah the daughter of Shil′hi. 43 And he kept walking in all the way of A′sa his father. He did not turn aside from it, by doing what was right in the eyes of Jehovah. Only the high places themselves did not disappear. The people were still sacrificing and making sacrificial smoke on the high places. 44 And Je·hosh′a·phat kept peaceful relations with the king of Israel. 45 As for the rest of the affairs of Je·hosh′a·phat and the mightiness with which he acted and how he warred, are they not written in the book of the affairs of the days of the kings of Judah? 46 And the rest of the male temple prostitutes that had been left over in the days of A′sa his father he cleared out from the land.

47 As regards a king, there was none in E′dom; a deputy was king.

48 Je·hosh′a·phat, for his part, made Tar′shish ships to go to O′phir for gold; but they did not go, because the ships were wrecked at E′zi·on-ge′ber. 49 It was then that A·ha·zi′ah the son of A′hab said to Je·hosh′a·phat: “Let my servants go with your servants in the ships,” but Je·hosh′a·phat did not consent.

50 Finally Je·hosh′a·phat lay down with his forefathers and was buried with his forefathers in the City of David his forefather; and Je·ho′ram his son began to reign in place of him.

51 As for A·ha·zi′ah the son of A′hab, he became king over Israel in Sa·mar′i·a in the seventeenth year of Je·hosh′a·phat the king of Judah, and he continued to reign over Israel for two years. 52 And he kept doing what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes and went walking in the way of his father and in the way of his mother and in the way of Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat, who had caused Israel to sin. 53 And he continued serving Ba′al and bowing down to him and kept offending Jehovah the God of Israel according to all that his father had done.

The Second of Kings

or, according to the Greek Septuagint, THE FOURTH OF KINGS

1 And Mo′ab began to revolt against Israel after the death of A′hab.

2 Then A·ha·zi′ah fell down through the grating in his roof chamber that was in Sa·mar′i·a and got sick. So he sent messengers and said to them: “Go, inquire of Ba′al-ze′bub the god of Ek′ron whether I shall revive from this sickness.” 3 As for the angel of Jehovah, he spoke to E·li′jah the Tish′bite: “Rise up, go up to meet the messengers of the king of Sa·mar′i·a and say to them, ‘Is it because there is no God at all in Israel that YOU are going to inquire of Ba′al-ze′bub the god of Ek′ron? 4 So therefore this is what Jehovah has said: “As regards the couch upon which you have gone up, you will not come down off it, because you will positively die.”’” With that E·li′jah went off.

5 When the messengers came back to him, he immediately said to them: “Why is it that YOU have come back?” 6 So they said to him: “There was a man that came up to meet us, and he proceeded to say to us, ‘Go, return to the king who sent YOU, and YOU must speak to him: “This is what Jehovah has said, ‘Is it because there is no God at all in Israel that you are sending to inquire of Ba′al-ze′bub the god of Ek′ron? Therefore, as regards the couch upon which you have gone up, you will not come down off it, because you will positively die.’”’” 7 At this he spoke to them: “What was the appearance of the man that came up to meet YOU and then spoke these words to YOU?” 8 So they said to him: “A man possessing a hair garment, with a leather belt girded about his loins.” Immediately he said: “It was E·li′jah the Tish′bite.”

9 And he proceeded to send to him a chief of fifty with his fifty. When he went up to him, there he was sitting upon the top of the mountain. He now spoke to him: “Man of the true God, the king himself has spoken, ‘Do come down.’” 10 But E·li′jah answered and spoke to the chief of the fifty: “Well, if I am a man of God, let fire come down from the heavens and eat up you and your fifty.” And fire came descending from the heavens and went eating up him and his fifty.

11 So he sent again to him another chief of fifty with his fifty. In turn he answered and spoke to him: “Man of the true God, this is what the king has said, ‘Do come down quickly.’” 12 But E·li′jah answered and spoke to them: “If I am a man of the true God, let fire come down from the heavens and eat up you and your fifty.” And fire of God came descending from the heavens and went eating up him and his fifty.

13 And he went sending again a third chief of fifty and his fifty. But the third chief of fifty went up and came and bent down upon his knees in front of E·li′jah and began to implore favor of him and speak to him: “Man of the true God, please let my soul and the soul of these fifty servants of yours be precious in your eyes. 14 Here fire came down from the heavens and went eating up the two former chiefs of fifty and their fifties, but now let my soul be precious in your eyes.”

15 At that the angel of Jehovah spoke to E·li′jah: “Go down with him. Do not be afraid because of him.” So he rose and went down with him to the king. 16 Then he spoke to him: “This is what Jehovah has said, ‘For the reason that you have sent messengers to inquire of Ba′al-ze′bub the god of Ek′ron, is it because there is no God at all in Israel of whose word to inquire? Therefore as regards the couch upon which you have gone up, you will not come down off it, because you will positively die.’” 17 And he gradually died, according to the word of Jehovah that E·li′jah had spoken; and Je·ho′ram began to reign in place of him, in the second year of Je·ho′ram the son of Je·hosh′a·phat the king of Judah, because he had not come to have a son.

18 As for the rest of A·ha·zi′ah’s things that he did, are they not written in the book of the affairs of the days of the kings of Israel?

2 Kings

5 Now a certain Na′a·man, the chief of the army of the king of Syria, had become a great man before his lord and held in esteem, because it was by him that Jehovah had given salvation to Syria; and the man himself had proved to be a valiant, mighty man, though a leper. 2 And the Syrians, for their part, had gone out as marauder bands, and they got to take captive from the land of Israel a little girl, and she came to be before Na′a·man’s wife. 3 In time she said to her mistress: “If only my lord were before the prophet that is in Sa·mar′i·a! In that case he would recover him from his leprosy.” 4 Subsequently someone came and reported to his lord, saying: “It was like this and that that the girl spoke who is from the land of Israel.”

5 Then the king of Syria said: “Get going! Come, and let me send a letter to the king of Israel.” So he proceeded to go and take in his hand ten talents of silver and six thousand pieces of gold and ten changes of garments. 6 And he came bringing the letter to the king of Israel, saying: “And now at the same time that this letter comes to you, here I do send to you Na′a·man my servant, that you may recover him from his leprosy.” 7 And it came about that as soon as the king of Israel read the letter, he immediately ripped his garments apart and said: “Am I God, to put to death and to preserve alive? For this person is sending to me to recover a man from his leprosy; for just take note, please, YOU men, and see how he is seeking a quarrel with me.”

8 And it came about that, as soon as E·li′sha the man of the true God heard that the king of Israel had ripped his garments apart, he at once sent to the king, saying: “Why did you rip your garments apart? Let him come, please, to me that he may know that there exists a prophet in Israel.” 9 So Na′a·man came with his horses and his war chariots and stood at the entrance of the house of E·li′sha. 10 However, E·li′sha sent a messenger to him, saying: “Going there, you must bathe seven times in the Jordan that your flesh may come back to you; and be clean.” 11 At this Na′a·man grew indignant and began to go away and say: “Here I had said to myself, ‘To me he will come out all the way and will certainly stand and call upon the name of Jehovah his God and move his hand to and fro over the place and actually give the leper recovery.’ 12 Are not the A·ba′nah and the Phar′par, the rivers of Damascus, better than all the waters of Israel? Can I not bathe in them and certainly be clean?” With that he turned and went away in a rage.

13 His servants now approached and spoke to him and said: “My father, had it been a great thing that the prophet himself had spoken to you, would you not do it? How much more, then, since he said to you, ‘Bathe and be clean’?” 14 At that he went down and began to plunge into the Jordan seven times according to the word of the man of the true God; after which his flesh came back like the flesh of a little boy and he became clean.

15 Then he went back to the man of the true God, he with all his camp, and came and stood before him and said: “Here, now, I certainly know that there is no God anywhere in the earth but in Israel. And now accept, please, a blessing gift from your servant.” 16 However, he said: “As Jehovah before whom I do stand is living, I will not accept it.” And he began to urge him to accept it, but he kept refusing. 17 Finally Na′a·man said: “If not, please, let there be given to your servant some ground, the load of a pair of mules; because your servant will no more render up a burnt offering or a sacrifice to any other gods but to Jehovah. 18 In this thing may Jehovah forgive your servant: When my lord comes into the house of Rim′mon to bow down there, and he is supporting himself upon my hand, and I have to bow down at the house of Rim′mon, when I bow down at the house of Rim′mon may Jehovah, please, forgive your servant in this respect.” 19 At this he said to him: “Go in peace.” Accordingly he went away from him for a good stretch of the land.

20 Then Ge·ha′zi the attendant of E·li′sha the man of the true God said: “Here my master has spared Na′a·man this Syrian by not accepting from his hand what he brought. As Jehovah is living, I will run after him and take something from him.” 21 And Ge·ha′zi went chasing after Na′a·man. When Na′a·man saw someone running after him, he at once got down from his chariot to meet him and then said: “Is all well?” 22 To this he said: “All is well. My master himself has sent me, saying, ‘Look! Just now there have come to me two young men from the mountainous region of E′phra·im from the sons of the prophets. Do give them, please, a talent of silver and two changes of garments.’” 23 At that Na′a·man said: “Go on, take two talents.” And he kept urging him and finally bound up two talents of silver in two bags, with two changes of garments, and gave them to two of his attendants, that they might carry them before him.

24 When he came to O′phel, he immediately took them from their hand and deposited them in the house and sent the men away. So off they went. 25 And he himself came in and then stood by his master. E·li′sha now said to him: “Where did you come from, Ge·ha′zi?” But he said: “Your servant did not go anywhere at all.” 26 At that he said to him: “Did not my heart itself go along just as the man turned to get down off his chariot to meet you? Is it a time to accept silver or to accept garments or olive groves or vineyards or sheep or cattle or menservants or maidservants? 27 So the leprosy of Na′a·man will stick to you and your offspring to time indefinite.” Immediately he went out from before him, a leper white as snow.

2 Kings

6 And the sons of the prophets began to say to E·li′sha: “Look, now! The place where we are dwelling before you is too cramped for us. 2 Let us go, please, as far as the Jordan and take from there each one a beam and make for ourselves there a place in which to dwell.” So he said: “Go.” 3 And a certain one went on to say: “Come on, please, and go with your servants.” At that he said: “I myself shall go.” 4 Accordingly he went with them, and they finally came to the Jordan and began to cut down the trees. 5 And it came about that a certain one was felling his beam, and the axhead itself fell into the water. And he began to cry out and say: “Alas, my master, for it was borrowed!” 6 Then the man of the true God said: “Where did it fall?” So he showed him the place. Immediately he cut off a piece of wood and threw it there and made the axhead float. 7 He now said: “Lift it up for yourself.” At once he thrust his hand out and took it.

8 And the king of Syria, for his part, became involved in war against Israel. Accordingly he took counsel with his servants, saying: “At such and such a place YOU will encamp with me.” 9 Then the man of the true God sent to the king of Israel, saying: “Guard yourself against passing by this place, because there is where the Syrians are coming down.” 10 So the king of Israel sent to the place that the man of the true God had said to him. And he warned him, and he kept away from there, not once or twice.

11 Consequently the heart of the king of Syria became enraged over this matter, so that he called his servants and said to them: “Will YOU not tell me who from those who belong to us is for the king of Israel?” 12 Then one of his servants said: “None, my lord the king, but it is E·li′sha the prophet who is in Israel that tells the king of Israel the things that you speak in your inner bedroom.” 13 So he said: “YOU men go and see where he is, that I may send and take him.” Later the report was made to him, saying: “There he is in Do′than.” 14 Immediately he sent horses and war chariots and a heavy military force there; and they proceeded to come by night and close in upon the city.

15 When the minister of the man of the true God rose early to get up, and went out, why, there a military force was surrounding the city with horses and war chariots. At once his attendant said to him: “Alas, my master! What shall we do?” 16 But he said: “Do not be afraid, for there are more who are with us than those who are with them.” 17 And E·li′sha began to pray and say: “O Jehovah, open his eyes, please, that he may see.” Immediately Jehovah opened the attendant’s eyes, so that he saw; and, look! the mountainous region was full of horses and war chariots of fire all around E·li′sha.

18 When they began to come down to him, E·li′sha went on to pray to Jehovah and say: “Please, strike this nation with blindness.” So he struck them with blindness according to the word of E·li′sha. 19 E·li′sha now said to them: “This is not the way, and this is not the city. Follow me, and let me conduct YOU to the man YOU look for.” However, he conducted them to Sa·mar′i·a.

20 And it came about that as soon as they arrived at Sa·mar′i·a, E·li′sha then said: “O Jehovah, open the eyes of these that they may see.” Immediately Jehovah opened their eyes, and they got to see; and here they were in the middle of Sa·mar′i·a. 21 The king of Israel now said to E·li′sha as soon as he saw them: “Shall I strike them down, shall I strike them down, my father?” 22 But he said: “You must not strike them down. Are those whom you have taken captive with your sword and with your bow the ones that you are striking down? Set bread and water before them that they may eat and drink and go to their lord.” 23 Accordingly he spread a great feast for them; and they began to eat and drink, after which he sent them away and they went to their lord. And not once did the marauding bands of the Syrians come again into the land of Israel.

24 And it came about afterward that Ben-ha′dad the king of Syria proceeded to collect all his camp together and to go up and besiege Sa·mar′i·a. 25 In time a great famine arose in Sa·mar′i·a, and, look! they were besieging it until an ass’s head got to be worth eighty silver pieces, and the fourth of a cab measure of dove’s dung was worth five silver pieces. 26 And it came about as the king of Israel was passing along upon the wall that a certain woman cried out to him, saying: “Do save, O my lord the king!” 27 To this he said: “If Jehovah does not save you, from what source shall I save you? either from the threshing floor or from the wine or oil press?” 28 And the king went on to say to her: “What is the matter with you?” So she said: “This very woman said to me, ‘Give your son that we may eat him today, and my own son we shall eat tomorrow.’ 29 Accordingly we boiled my son and ate him. Then I said to her on the next day, ‘Give your son that we may eat him.’ But she hid her son.”

30 And it came about that as soon as the king heard the woman’s words, he immediately ripped his garments apart; and as he was passing along upon the wall, the people got to see, and, look! sackcloth was underneath upon his flesh. 31 And he went on to say: “So may God do to me, and so may he add to it, if the head of E·li′sha the son of Sha′phat continues standing upon him today!”

32 And E·li′sha was sitting in his own house, and the older men were sitting with him, when he sent a man from before him. Before the messenger could come in to him, he himself said to the older men: “Have YOU seen how this son of a murderer has sent to take off my head? See to it: as soon as the messenger comes, close the door, and YOU must press him back with the door. Is there not the sound of the feet of his lord behind him?” 33 While he was yet speaking with them, here was the messenger coming down to him, and the king proceeded to say: “Here this is the calamity from Jehovah. Why should I wait any longer for Jehovah?”

2 Kings

9 And E·li′sha the prophet, for his part, called one of the sons of the prophets and then said to him: “Gird up your loins and take this flask of oil in your hand and go to Ra′moth-gil′e·ad. 2 When you have come in there, see Je′hu the son of Je·hosh′a·phat the son of Nim′shi there; and you must come in and make him get up from the midst of his brothers and bring him into the innermost chamber. 3 And you must take the flask of oil and pour it out upon his head and say, ‘This is what Jehovah has said: “I do anoint you as king over Israel.”’ And you must open the door and flee and not wait.”

4 And the attendant, the prophet’s attendant, got on his way to Ra′moth-gil′e·ad. 5 When he came in, why, there the chiefs of the military force were seated. He now said: “There is a word I have for you, O chief.” At this Je′hu said: “For which one of all of us?” Then he said: “For you, O chief.” 6 So he got up and came into the house; and he proceeded to pour the oil out upon his head and say to him: “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel has said, ‘I do anoint you as king over Jehovah’s people, that is, over Israel. 7 And you must strike down the house of A′hab your lord, and I must avenge the blood of my servants the prophets and the blood of all the servants of Jehovah at the hand of Jez′e·bel. 8 And the whole house of A′hab must perish; and I must cut off from A′hab anyone urinating against a wall and any helpless and worthless one in Israel. 9 And I must constitute the house of A′hab like the house of Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat and like the house of Ba′a·sha the son of A·hi′jah. 10 And Jez′e·bel the dogs will eat up in the tract of land at Jez′re·el, and there will be no one burying her.’” With that he opened the door and went fleeing.

11 As for Je′hu, he went out to the servants of his lord, and they began to say to him: “Is everything all right? Why did this crazy man come in to you?” But he said to them: “YOU yourselves well know the man and his sort of talk.” 12 But they said: “It is false! Tell us, please.” Then he said: “It was like this and like that that he talked to me, saying, ‘This is what Jehovah has said: “I do anoint you as king over Israel.”’” 13 At this they hurriedly took each one his garment and put it under him upon the bare steps, and they began to blow the horn and say: “Je′hu has become king!” 14 And Je′hu the son of Je·hosh′a·phat the son of Nim′shi proceeded to conspire against Je·ho′ram.

And Je·ho′ram himself had happened to be keeping guard at Ra′moth-gil′e·ad, he with all Israel, because of Haz′a·el the king of Syria. 15 Later Je·ho′ram the king returned to get healed at Jez′re·el from the wounds that the Syrians got to inflict upon him when he fought Haz′a·el the king of Syria.

Je′hu now said: “If YOUR soul agrees, do not let anyone go out in escape from the city to go and make report in Jez′re·el.” 16 And Je′hu began to ride and go to Jez′re·el; for Je·ho′ram was lying there, and A·ha·zi′ah the king of Judah himself had gone down to see Je·ho′ram. 17 And the watchman was standing upon the tower in Jez′re·el, and he got to see the heaving mass of Je′hu’s men as he was coming, and he at once said: “There is a heaving mass of men that I am seeing.” At that Je·ho′ram said: “Take a cavalryman and send him to meet them, and let him say, ‘Is there peace?’” 18 Accordingly a rider on a horse went to meet him and said: “This is what the king has said, ‘Is there peace?’” But Je′hu said: “What do you have to do with ‘peace’? Get around to my rear!”

And the watchman went on to report, saying: “The messenger came as far as to them, but he has not returned.” 19 So he sent out a second rider on a horse, who, when he came to them, proceeded to say: “This is what the king has said, ‘Is there peace?’” But Je′hu said: “What do you have to do with ‘peace’? Get around to my rear!”

20 And the watchman went on to report, saying: “He came as far as to them, but he has not returned; and the driving is like the driving of Je′hu the grandson of Nim′shi, for it is with madness that he drives.” 21 At that Je·ho′ram said: “Hitch up!” So his war chariot was hitched up and Je·ho′ram the king of Israel and A·ha·zi′ah the king of Judah went out, each in his own war chariot. As they continued on out to meet Je′hu, they got to find him in the tract of land of Na′both the Jez′re·el·ite.

22 And it came about that as soon as Je·ho′ram saw Je′hu, he immediately said: “Is there peace, Je′hu?” But he said: “What peace could there be as long as there are the fornications of Jez′e·bel your mother and her many sorceries?” 23 At once Je·ho′ram made a turn with his hands, that he might flee, and said to A·ha·zi′ah: “There is trickery, A·ha·zi′ah!” 24 And Je′hu himself filled his hand with a bow and proceeded to shoot Je·ho′ram between the arms, so that the arrow came out at his heart, and he collapsed in his war chariot. 25 He now said to Bid′kar his adjutant: “Lift him up; throw him into the tract of the field of Na′both the Jez′re·el·ite; for remember: I and you were riding teams behind A′hab his father, and Jehovah himself lifted up this pronouncement against him: 26 ‘“Certainly the blood of Na′both and the blood of his sons I saw yesterday,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “and I shall certainly repay you in this tract of land,” is the utterance of Jehovah.’ So now, lift him up; throw him into the tract of land according to the word of Jehovah.”

27 And A·ha·zi′ah the king of Judah himself saw it and took to flight by the way of the garden house. (Later Je′hu went in pursuit of him and said: “Him also! STRIKE him down!” So they struck him down while in the chariot on the way up to Gur, which is by Ib′le·am. And he continued his flight to Me·gid′do and got to die there. 28 Then his servants carried him in a chariot to Jerusalem, and so they buried him in his grave with his forefathers in the City of David. 29 And it was in the eleventh year of Je·ho′ram the son of A′hab that A·ha·zi′ah had become king over Judah.)

30 At length Je′hu came to Jez′re·el, and Jez′e·bel herself heard of it. And she proceeded to paint her eyes with black paint and do her head up beautifully and to look down through the window. 31 And Je′hu himself came in by the gate. She now said: “Did it go all right with Zim′ri the killer of his lord?” 32 At that he raised his face toward the window and said: “Who is with me? Who?” Immediately two or three court officials looked down at him. 33 So he said: “Let her drop!” Then they let her drop, and some of her blood went spattering upon the wall and upon the horses; and he now trampled upon her. 34 After that he came on in and ate and drank and then said: “YOU men, please, take care of this accursed one and bury her, for she is the daughter of a king.” 35 When they went to bury her, they did not find anything of her but the skull and the feet and the palms of the hands. 36 When they returned and told him, he went on to say: “It is the word of Jehovah that he spoke by means of his servant E·li′jah the Tish′bite, saying, ‘In the tract of land of Jez′re·el the dogs will eat the flesh of Jez′e·bel. 37 And the dead body of Jez′e·bel will certainly become as manure upon the face of the field in the tract of land of Jez′re·el, that they may not say: “This is Jez′e·bel.”’”

2 Kings

12 In the seventh year of Je′hu, Je·ho′ash became king, and for forty years he reigned in Jerusalem. And his mother’s name was Zib′i·ah from Be′er-she′ba. 2 And Je·ho′ash continued doing what was right in Jehovah’s eyes all the days of his that Je·hoi′a·da the priest instructed him. 3 It was only the high places that did not disappear. The people were still sacrificing and making sacrificial smoke on the high places.

4 And Je·ho′ash proceeded to say to the priests: “All the money for the holy offerings that is brought to the house of Jehovah, the money at which each one is assessed, the money for the souls according to individual valuation, all the money that it comes up on the heart of each one to bring to the house of Jehovah, 5 let the priests take for themselves, each one from his acquaintance; and let them, for their part, repair the cracks of the house wherever any crack is found.”

6 And it came about that by the twenty-third year of King Je·ho′ash, the priests had not yet repaired the cracks of the house. 7 So King Je·ho′ash called Je·hoi′a·da the priest and the priests and said to them: “Why is it that YOU are not repairing the cracks of the house? Now, then, do not take any more money from YOUR acquaintances, but for the cracks of the house YOU should give it.” 8 At that the priests consented not to take any more money from the people and not to repair the cracks of the house.

9 Je·hoi′a·da the priest now took a chest and bored a hole in its lid and put it beside the altar on the right as a person comes into the house of Jehovah, and there the priests, the doorkeepers, put all the money that was being brought into the house of Jehovah. 10 And it came about that as soon as they saw that there was a great deal of money in the chest, the secretary of the king and the high priest would come up, and they would bind it up and count the money that was being found at the house of Jehovah. 11 And they gave the money that had been counted off over to the hands of doers of the work that were appointed to the house of Jehovah. In turn they paid it out to the workers in wood and to the builders that were working at the house of Jehovah, 12 and to the masons and to the hewers of stone, and to buy timbers and hewn stones for repairing the cracks of the house of Jehovah and for all that was expended upon the house to repair it.

13 Only as respects the house of Jehovah there were not made basins of silver, extinguishers, bowls, trumpets, any sort of gold article and article of silver from the money that was being brought to the house of Jehovah; 14 for it was to the doers of the work that they would give it, and with it they repaired the house of Jehovah. 15 And they would not call for an accounting with the men into whose hand they would give the money to give to the doers of the work, because it was with faithfulness that they were working. 16 As for the money for guilt offerings and the money for sin offerings, it was not being brought to the house of Jehovah. So it came to belong to the priests.

17 Then it was that Haz′a·el the king of Syria proceeded to go up and fight against Gath and capture it, after which Haz′a·el set his face to go up against Jerusalem. 18 At that Je·ho′ash the king of Judah took all the holy offerings that Je·hosh′a·phat and Je·ho′ram and A·ha·zi′ah his forefathers, the kings of Judah, had sanctified and his own holy offerings and all the gold to be found in the treasures of the house of Jehovah and the house of the king and sent them to Haz′a·el the king of Syria. So he withdrew from against Jerusalem.

19 As for the rest of the affairs of Je·ho′ash and all that he did, are they not written in the book of the affairs of the days of the kings of Judah? 20 However, his servants rose up and leagued together in a conspiracy and struck Je·ho′ash down at the house of the Mound, on the way that goes down to Sil′la. 21 And Jo′za·car the son of Shim′e·ath and Je·hoz′a·bad the son of Sho′mer, his servants, were the ones that struck him down, so that he died. Accordingly they buried him with his forefathers in the City of David; and Am·a·zi′ah his son began to reign in place of him.

2 Kings

13 In the twenty-third year of Je·ho′ash the son of A·ha·zi′ah the king of Judah, Je·ho′a·haz the son of Je′hu became king over Israel in Sa·mar′i·a for seventeen years. 2 And he continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes and went walking in pursuit of the sin of Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat, with which he caused Israel to sin. He did not turn aside from it. 3 And Jehovah’s anger became hot against Israel, so that he gave them into the hand of Haz′a·el the king of Syria and into the hand of Ben-ha′dad the son of Haz′a·el all their days.

4 In time Je·ho′a·haz softened the face of Jehovah, so that Jehovah listened to him; for he had seen the oppression upon Israel, because the king of Syria had oppressed them. 5 Consequently Jehovah gave Israel a savior, so that they came out from under the hand of Syria, and the sons of Israel continued to dwell in their homes as formerly. 6 (Only they did not depart from the sin of the house of Jer·o·bo′am, with which he caused Israel to sin. In it he walked; and even the sacred pole itself stood in Sa·mar′i·a.) 7 For he had not left to Je·ho′a·haz any people but fifty horsemen and ten chariots and ten thousand men on foot, because the king of Syria had destroyed them, that he might make them like the dust at threshing.

8 As for the rest of the affairs of Je·ho′a·haz and all that he did and his mightiness, are they not written in the book of the affairs of the days of the kings of Israel? 9 Finally Je·ho′a·haz lay down with his forefathers, and they buried him in Sa·mar′i·a; and Je·ho′ash his son began to reign in place of him.

10 In the thirty-seventh year of Je·ho′ash the king of Judah, Je·ho′ash the son of Je·ho′a·haz became king over Israel in Sa·mar′i·a for sixteen years. 11 And he continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes. He did not depart from all the sins of Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat, with which he made Israel sin. In them he walked.

12 As for the rest of the affairs of Je·ho′ash and all that he did and his mightiness and how he fought against Am·a·zi′ah the king of Judah, are they not written in the book of the affairs of the days of the kings of Israel? 13 Finally Je·ho′ash lay down with his forefathers, and Jer·o·bo′am himself sat upon his throne. In turn Je·ho′ash was buried in Sa·mar′i·a with the kings of Israel.

14 As regards E·li′sha, he had taken sick with the sickness with which he was to die. So Je·ho′ash the king of Israel came down to him and began to weep over his face and say: “My father, my father, the war chariot of Israel and his horsemen!” 15 And E·li′sha proceeded to say to him: “Take a bow and arrows.” So he took to himself a bow and arrows. 16 And he went on to say to the king of Israel: “Put your hand to the bow.” Accordingly he put his hand to it, after which E·li′sha laid his hands upon the hands of the king. 17 Then he said: “Open the window to the east.” So he opened it. Finally E·li′sha said: “Shoot!” So he shot. He now said: “Jehovah’s arrow of salvation, even the arrow of salvation against Syria! And you will certainly strike down Syria at A′phek to the finishing point.”

18 And he went on to say: “Take the arrows.” At that he took them. Then he said to the king of Israel: “Strike on the earth.” So he struck three times and stopped. 19 And the man of the true God grew indignant at him; hence he said: “It was meant to strike five or six times! In that case you would certainly be striking down Syria to the finishing point, but now it is three times that you will strike down Syria.”

20 After that E·li′sha died and they buried him. And there were marauding bands of the Mo′ab·ites that regularly came into the land at the coming in of the year. 21 And it came about that as they were burying a man, why, here they saw the marauding band. At once they threw the man into E·li′sha’s burial place and went off. When the man touched the bones of E·li′sha, he immediately came to life and stood upon his feet.

22 As for Haz′a·el the king of Syria, he oppressed Israel all the days of Je·ho′a·haz. 23 However, Jehovah showed them favor and had mercy upon them and turned to them for the sake of his covenant with Abraham, Isaac and Jacob; and he did not want to bring them to ruin, and he did not cast them away from before his face until now. 24 Finally Haz′a·el the king of Syria died, and Ben-ha′dad his son began to reign in place of him. 25 And Je·ho′ash the son of Je·ho′a·haz proceeded to take back again from the hand of Ben-ha′dad the son of Haz′a·el the cities that he had taken from the hand of Je·ho′a·haz his father in war. Three times Je·ho′ash struck him down, and he got to recover the cities of Israel.

2 Kings

15 In the twenty-seventh year of Jer·o·bo′am the king of Israel, Az·a·ri′ah the son of Am·a·zi′ah the king of Judah became king. 2 Sixteen years old he happened to be when he began to reign, and for fifty-two years he reigned in Jerusalem. And his mother’s name was Je·co·li′ah of Jerusalem. 3 And he continued to do what was upright in Jehovah’s eyes, according to all that Am·a·zi′ah his father had done. 4 It was only that the high places did not disappear. The people were still sacrificing and making sacrificial smoke on the high places. 5 Finally Jehovah plagued the king, and he continued to be a leper until the day of his death, and he kept dwelling in his house exempt from duties, while Jo′tham the king’s son was over the house, judging the people of the land. 6 As for the rest of the affairs of Az·a·ri′ah and all that he did, are they not written in the book of the affairs of the days of the kings of Judah? 7 At length Az·a·ri′ah lay down with his forefathers, and they buried him with his forefathers in the City of David; and Jo′tham his son began to reign in place of him.

8 In the thirty-eighth year of Az·a·ri′ah the king of Judah, Zech·a·ri′ah the son of Jer·o·bo′am became king over Israel in Sa·mar′i·a for six months. 9 And he went on doing what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, just as his forefathers had done. He did not depart from the sins of Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat, with which he caused Israel to sin. 10 Then Shal′lum the son of Ja′besh conspired against him and struck him down at Ib′le·am and put him to death and began to reign in place of him. 11 As for the rest of the affairs of Zech·a·ri′ah, there they are written in the book of the affairs of the days of the kings of Israel. 12 That was Jehovah’s word that he had spoken to Je′hu, saying: “Sons themselves to the fourth generation will sit for you upon the throne of Israel.” And it came to be that way.

13 As for Shal′lum the son of Ja′besh, he became king in the thirty-ninth year of Uz·zi′ah the king of Judah, and he continued to reign for a full lunar month in Sa·mar′i·a. 14 Then Men′a·hem the son of Ga′di came up from Tir′zah and came to Sa·mar′i·a and struck down Shal′lum the son of Ja′besh in Sa·mar′i·a and put him to death; and he began to reign in place of him. 15 As for the rest of the affairs of Shal′lum and his conspiracy with which he conspired, there they are written in the book of the affairs of the days of the kings of Israel. 16 It was then that Men′a·hem proceeded to strike down Tiph′sah and all that was in it and its territory out from Tir′zah, because it did not open up, and he went striking it down. All its pregnant women he ripped up.

17 In the thirty-ninth year of Az·a·ri′ah the king of Judah, Men′a·hem the son of Ga′di became king over Israel for ten years in Sa·mar′i·a. 18 And he continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes. He did not depart from all the sins of Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat, with which he caused Israel to sin, all his days. 19 Pul the king of As·syr′i·a came into the land. Consequently Men′a·hem gave Pul a thousand talents of silver, that his hands might prove to be with him to strengthen the kingdom in his own hand. 20 So Men′a·hem brought forth the silver at the expense of Israel, at the expense of all the valiant, mighty men, to give to the king of As·syr′i·a fifty silver shekels for each man. At that the king of As·syr′i·a turned back, and he did not stay there in the land. 21 As for the rest of the affairs of Men′a·hem and all that he did, are they not written in the book of the affairs of the days of the kings of Israel? 22 Finally Men′a·hem lay down with his forefathers, and Pek·a·hi′ah his son began to reign in place of him.

23 In the fiftieth year of Az·a·ri′ah the king of Judah, Pek·a·hi′ah the son of Men′a·hem became king over Israel in Sa·mar′i·a for two years. 24 And he continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes. He did not depart from the sins of Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat, with which he caused Israel to sin. 25 Then Pe′kah the son of Rem·a·li′ah his adjutant conspired against him and struck him down in Sa·mar′i·a in the dwelling tower of the king’s house with Ar′gob and A·ri′eh, and with him there were fifty men of the sons of Gil′e·ad. So he put him to death and began to reign in place of him. 26 As for the rest of the affairs of Pek·a·hi′ah and all that he did, there they are written in the book of the affairs of the days of the kings of Israel.

27 In the fifty-second year of Az·a·ri′ah the king of Judah, Pe′kah the son of Rem·a·li′ah became king over Israel in Sa·mar′i·a for twenty years. 28 And he continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes. He did not depart from the sins of Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat, with which he caused Israel to sin. 29 In the days of Pe′kah the king of Israel, Tig′lath-pil·e′ser the king of As·syr′i·a came in and proceeded to take I′jon and A′bel-beth-ma′a·cah and Ja·no′ah and Ke′desh and Ha′zor and Gil′e·ad and Gal′i·lee, all the land of Naph′ta·li, and to carry them into exile in As·syr′i·a. 30 Finally Ho·she′a the son of E′lah formed a conspiracy against Pe′kah the son of Rem·a·li′ah and struck him and put him to death; and he began to reign in place of him in the twentieth year of Jo′tham the son of Uz·zi′ah. 31 As for the rest of the affairs of Pe′kah and all that he did, there they are written in the book of the affairs of the days of the kings of Israel.

32 In the second year of Pe′kah the son of Rem·a·li′ah the king of Israel, Jo′tham the son of Uz·zi′ah the king of Judah became king. 33 Twenty-five years old he happened to be when he began to reign, and for sixteen years he reigned in Jerusalem. And his mother’s name was Je·ru′sha the daughter of Za′dok. 34 And he continued to do what was right in Jehovah’s eyes. According to all that Uz·zi′ah his father had done, he did. 35 It was only that the high places did not disappear. The people were still sacrificing and making sacrificial smoke on the high places. He it was that built the upper gate of the house of Jehovah. 36 As for the rest of the affairs of Jo′tham, what he did, are they not written in the book of the affairs of the days of the kings of Judah? 37 In those days Jehovah started to send against Judah Re′zin the king of Syria and Pe′kah the son of Rem·a·li′ah. 38 Finally Jo′tham lay down with his forefathers and was buried with his forefathers in the City of David his forefather; and A′haz his son began to reign in place of him.

2 Kings

17 In the twelfth year of A′haz the king of Judah, Ho·she′a the son of E′lah became king in Sa·mar′i·a over Israel for nine years. 2 And he continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, only not as the kings of Israel that happened to be prior to him. 3 It was against him that Shal·man·e′ser the king of As·syr′i·a came up, and Ho·she′a came to be his servant and began to pay tribute to him. 4 However, the king of As·syr′i·a got to find conspiracy in Ho·she′a’s case, in that he had sent messengers to So the king of Egypt and did not bring the tribute up to the king of As·syr′i·a as in former years. Hence the king of As·syr′i·a shut him up and kept him bound in the house of detention.

5 And the king of As·syr′i·a proceeded to come up against all the land and to come up to Sa·mar′i·a and lay siege against it for three years. 6 In the ninth year of Ho·she′a, the king of As·syr′i·a captured Sa·mar′i·a and then led Israel into exile in As·syr′i·a and kept them dwelling in Ha′lah and in Ha′bor at the river Go′zan and in the cities of the Medes.

7 And it came about because the sons of Israel had sinned against Jehovah their God, who brought them up out of the land of Egypt from under the hand of Phar′aoh the king of Egypt, and they began to fear other gods; 8 and they kept walking in the statutes of the nations whom Jehovah had driven out from before the sons of Israel, and in the statutes of the kings of Israel that they had made; 9 and the sons of Israel went searching into the things that were not right toward Jehovah their God and kept building themselves high places in all their cities, from the tower of the watchmen clear to the fortified city; 10 and they kept setting up for themselves sacred pillars and sacred poles upon every high hill and under every luxuriant tree; 11 and there on all the high places they continued to make sacrificial smoke the same as the nations whom Jehovah had taken into exile because of them, and they kept doing bad things to offend Jehovah;

12 And they continued to serve dungy idols, concerning which Jehovah had said to them: “YOU must not do this thing”; 13 and Jehovah kept warning Israel and Judah by means of all his prophets and every visionary, saying: “Turn back from YOUR bad ways and keep my commandments, my statutes, according to all the law that I commanded YOUR forefathers and that I have sent to YOU by means of my servants the prophets”; 14 and they did not listen but kept hardening their necks like the necks of their forefathers that had not exercised faith in Jehovah their God; 15 and they continued rejecting his regulations and his covenant that he had concluded with their forefathers and his reminders with which he had warned them, and they went following vain idols and became vain themselves, even in imitation of the nations that were all around them, concerning whom Jehovah had commanded them not to do like them;

16 And they kept leaving all the commandments of Jehovah their God and proceeded to make for themselves molten statues, two calves, and to make a sacred pole, and they began to bow down to all the army of the heavens and to serve Ba′al; 17 and they continued to make their sons and their daughters pass through the fire and to practice divination and to look for omens, and they kept selling themselves to do what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah, to offend him;

18 Therefore Jehovah got very incensed against Israel, so that he removed them from his sight. He did not let any remain but the tribe of Judah alone.

19 Even Judah itself did not keep the commandments of Jehovah their God, but they went walking in the statutes of Israel that they had made. 20 Consequently Jehovah rejected all the seed of Israel and kept afflicting them and giving them into the hand of pillagers, until he had cast them away from before him. 21 For he ripped Israel off from the house of David, and they proceeded to make Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat king; and Jer·o·bo′am proceeded to part Israel from following Jehovah, and he caused them to sin with a great sin. 22 And the sons of Israel went walking in all the sins of Jer·o·bo′am that he had done. They did not depart from them, 23 until Jehovah removed Israel from his sight, just as he had spoken by means of all his servants the prophets. So Israel went off its own soil into exile in As·syr′i·a down to this day.

24 Subsequently the king of As·syr′i·a brought people from Babylon and Cu′thah and Av′va and Ha′math and Seph·ar·va′im and had them dwell in the cities of Sa·mar′i·a instead of the sons of Israel; and they began to take possession of Sa·mar′i·a and to dwell in its cities. 25 And it came about at the start of their dwelling there that they did not fear Jehovah. Therefore Jehovah sent lions among them, and they came to be killers among them. 26 So they sent word to the king of As·syr′i·a, saying: “The nations that you have taken into exile and then settled in the cities of Sa·mar′i·a have not known the religion of the God of the land, so that he keeps sending lions among them; and, look! they are putting them to death, inasmuch as there are none knowing the religion of the God of the land.”

27 At that the king of As·syr′i·a commanded, saying: “Have one of the priests go there whom YOU led into exile from there, that he may go and dwell there and teach them the religion of the God of the land.” 28 Accordingly one of the priests whom they had led into exile from Sa·mar′i·a came and began dwelling in Beth′el, and he came to be a teacher of them as to how they ought to fear Jehovah.

29 However, each different nation came to be a maker of its own god, which they then deposited in the house of the high places that the Sa·mar′i·tans had made, each different nation, in their cities where they were dwelling. 30 And the men of Babylon, for their part, made Suc′coth-be′noth, and the men of Cuth, for their part, made Ner′gal, and the men of Ha′math, for their part, made A·shi′ma. 31 As for the Av′vites, they made Nib′haz and Tar′tak; and the Se′phar·vites were burning their sons in the fire to A·dram′me·lech and A·nam′me·lech the gods of Seph·ar·va′im. 32 And they came to be fearers of Jehovah and went making for themselves from the people in general priests of high places, and they came to be functionaries for them in the house of the high places. 33 It was of Jehovah that they became fearers, but it was of their own gods that they proved to be worshipers, according to the religion of the nations from among whom they had led them into exile.

34 Down to this day they are doing according to their former religions. There were none fearing Jehovah and none doing according to his statutes and his judicial decisions and the law and the commandment that Jehovah had commanded the sons of Jacob, whose name he made Israel; 35 when Jehovah concluded a covenant with them and commanded them, saying: “YOU must not fear other gods, and YOU must not bow down to them nor serve them nor sacrifice to them. 36 But Jehovah, who brought YOU up out of the land of Egypt with great power and a stretched-out arm, is the One whom YOU should fear, and to him YOU should bow down, and to him YOU should sacrifice. 37 And the regulations and the judicial decisions and the law and the commandment that he wrote for YOU, YOU should take care to do always; and YOU must not fear other gods. 38 And the covenant that I have concluded with YOU, YOU must not forget; and YOU must not fear other gods. 39 But it is Jehovah YOUR God that YOU should fear, as he is the one that will deliver YOU out of the hand of all YOUR enemies.”

40 And they did not obey, but it was according to their former religion that they were doing. 41 And these nations came to be fearers of Jehovah, but it was their own graven images that they proved to be serving. As for both their sons and their grandsons, it was just as their forefathers had done that they themselves are doing down to this day.

2 Kings

18 And it came about in the third year of Ho·she′a the son of E′lah the king of Israel that Hez·e·ki′ah the son of A′haz the king of Judah became king. 2 Twenty-five years old he happened to be when he began to reign, and for twenty-nine years he reigned in Jerusalem. And his mother’s name was A′bi the daughter of Zech·a·ri′ah. 3 And he continued to do what was right in Jehovah’s eyes, according to all that David his forefather had done. 4 He it was that removed the high places and broke the sacred pillars to pieces and cut down the sacred pole and crushed to pieces the copper serpent that Moses had made; for down to those days the sons of Israel had continually been making sacrificial smoke to it, and it used to be called the copper serpent-idol. 5 In Jehovah the God of Israel he trusted; and after him there proved to be no one like him among all the kings of Judah, even those who had happened to be prior to him. 6 And he kept sticking to Jehovah. He did not turn aside from following him, but he continued keeping his commandments that Jehovah had commanded Moses. 7 And Jehovah proved to be with him. Wherever he would go out, he would act prudently; and he proceeded to rebel against the king of As·syr′i·a and did not serve him. 8 It was he that struck down the Phi·lis′tines clear to Ga′za and also its territories, from the tower of the watchmen clear to the fortified city.

9 And it came about in the fourth year of King Hez·e·ki′ah, that is, the seventh year of Ho·she′a the son of E′lah the king of Israel, that Shal·man·e′ser the king of As·syr′i·a came up against Sa·mar′i·a and began to lay siege to it. 10 And they got to capture it at the end of three years; in the sixth year of Hez·e·ki′ah, that is, the ninth year of Ho·she′a the king of Israel, Sa·mar′i·a was captured. 11 After that the king of As·syr′i·a took Israel into exile in As·syr′i·a and set them down in Ha′lah and in Ha′bor at the river Go′zan and in the cities of the Medes, 12 over the fact that they had not listened to the voice of Jehovah their God, but kept overstepping his covenant, even all that Moses the servant of Jehovah had commanded. They neither listened nor performed.

13 And in the fourteenth year of King Hez·e·ki′ah, Sen·nach′er·ib the king of As·syr′i·a came up against all the fortified cities of Judah and proceeded to seize them. 14 So Hez·e·ki′ah the king of Judah sent to the king of As·syr′i·a at La′chish, saying: “I have sinned. Turn back from against me. Whatever you may impose upon me I shall carry.” Accordingly the king of As·syr′i·a laid upon Hez·e·ki′ah the king of Judah three hundred silver talents and thirty gold talents. 15 Therefore Hez·e·ki′ah gave all the silver that was to be found at the house of Jehovah and in the treasures of the king’s house. 16 At that time Hez·e·ki′ah cut off the doors of the temple of Jehovah and the doorposts that Hez·e·ki′ah the king of Judah had overlaid and then gave them to the king of As·syr′i·a.

17 And the king of As·syr′i·a proceeded to send Tar′tan and Rab′sa·ris and Rab′sha·keh from La′chish to King Hez·e·ki′ah with a heavy military force to Jerusalem, that they might go up and come to Jerusalem. So they went up and came and stood still by the conduit of the upper pool, which is at the highway of the laundryman’s field. 18 And they began to call out to the king, but there came out to them E·li′a·kim the son of Hil·ki′ah, who was over the household, and Sheb′nah the secretary and Jo′ah the son of A′saph the recorder.

19 Accordingly Rab′sha·keh said to them: “Please, say to Hez·e·ki′ah, ‘This is what the great king, the king of As·syr′i·a, has said: “What is this confidence in which you have trusted? 20 You have said (but it is the word of lips), ‘There are counsel and mightiness for the war.’ Now in whom have you put your trust, that you have rebelled against me? 21 Now, look! you have put your trust in the support of this crushed reed, Egypt, which, if a man should brace himself upon it, would certainly enter into his palm and pierce it. That is the way Phar′aoh the king of Egypt is to all those putting their trust in him. 22 And in case YOU men should say to me, ‘It is Jehovah our God in whom we have put our trust,’ is he not the one whose high places and whose altars Hez·e·ki′ah has removed, while he says to Judah and Jerusalem, ‘Before this altar YOU should bow down in Jerusalem’?”’ 23 Now, then, make a wager, please, with my lord the king of As·syr′i·a, and let me give you two thousand horses to see whether you are able, on your part, to put riders upon them. 24 How, then, could you turn back the face of one governor of the smallest servants of my lord, while you, for your part, put your trust in Egypt for chariots and for horsemen? 25 Now is it without authorization from Jehovah that I have come up against this place to bring it to ruin? Jehovah himself said to me, ‘Go up against this land, and you must bring it to ruin.’”

26 At this E·li′a·kim the son of Hil·ki′ah and Sheb′nah and Jo′ah said to Rab′sha·keh: “Speak with your servants, please, in the Syrian language, for we can listen; and do not speak with us in the Jews’ language in the ears of the people that are on the wall.” 27 But Rab′sha·keh said to them: “Is it to your lord and to you that my lord has sent me to speak these words? Is it not to the men sitting upon the wall, that they may eat their own excrement and drink their own urine with YOU men?”

28 And Rab′sha·keh continued to stand and call out in a loud voice in the Jews’ language; and he went on to speak and say: “HEAR the word of the great king, the king of As·syr′i·a. 29 This is what the king has said, ‘Do not let Hez·e·ki′ah deceive YOU people, for he is not able to deliver YOU out of my hand. 30 And do not let Hez·e·ki′ah cause YOU to trust in Jehovah, saying: “Without fail Jehovah will deliver us, and this city will not be given into the hand of the king of As·syr′i·a.” 31 Do not listen to Hez·e·ki′ah; for this is what the king of As·syr′i·a has said: “Make a capitulation to me, and come out to me, and eat each one from his own vine and each one from his own fig tree and drink each one the water of his own cistern, 32 until I come and I actually take YOU to a land like YOUR own land, a land of grain and new wine, a land of bread and vineyards, a land of oil-olive trees and honey; and keep living that YOU may not die. And do not listen to Hez·e·ki′ah, for he allures YOU, saying, ‘Jehovah himself will deliver us.’ 33 Have the gods of the nations at all delivered each one his own land out of the hand of the king of As·syr′i·a? 34 Where are the gods of Ha′math and Ar′pad? Where are the gods of Seph·ar·va′im, He′na and Iv′vah? Have they delivered Sa·mar′i·a out of my hand? 35 Who are there among all the gods of the lands that have delivered their land out of my hand, so that Jehovah should deliver Jerusalem out of my hand?”’”

36 And the people kept silent and did not answer him a word, for the commandment of the king was, saying: “YOU must not answer him.” 37 But E·li′a·kim the son of Hil·ki′ah, who was over the household, and Sheb′nah the secretary and Jo′ah the son of A′saph the recorder came to Hez·e·ki′ah with their garments ripped apart and told him the words of Rab′sha·keh.

2 Kings

19 And it came about that as soon as King Hez·e·ki′ah heard, he immediately ripped his garments apart and covered himself with sackcloth and came into the house of Jehovah. 2 Further, he sent E·li′a·kim, who was over the household, and Sheb′nah the secretary and the older men of the priests covered with sackcloth to Isaiah the prophet the son of A′moz. 3 And they proceeded to say to him: “This is what Hez·e·ki′ah has said, ‘This day is a day of distress and of rebuke and of scornful insolence; for the sons have come as far as the womb’s mouth, and there is no power to give birth. 4 Perhaps Jehovah your God will hear all the words of Rab′sha·keh, whom the king of As·syr′i·a his lord sent to taunt the living God, and he will actually call him to account for the words that Jehovah your God has heard. And you must lift up prayer in behalf of the remnant that are to be found.’”

5 So the servants of King Hez·e·ki′ah came in to Isaiah. 6 Then Isaiah said to them: “This is what YOU should say to YOUR lord, ‘This is what Jehovah has said: “Do not be afraid because of the words that you have heard with which the attendants of the king of As·syr′i·a spoke abusively of me. 7 Here I am putting a spirit in him, and he must hear a report and return to his own land; and I shall certainly cause him to fall by the sword in his own land.”’”

8 After that Rab′sha·keh returned and found the king of As·syr′i·a fighting against Lib′nah; for he had heard that he had pulled away from La′chish. 9 He heard it said respecting Tir·ha′kah the king of E·thi·o′pi·a: “Here he has come out to fight against you.” Therefore he sent messengers again to Hez·e·ki′ah, saying: 10 “This is what YOU men should say to Hez·e·ki′ah the king of Judah, ‘Do not let your God in whom you are trusting deceive you, saying: “Jerusalem will not be given into the hand of the king of As·syr′i·a.” 11 Look! You yourself have heard what the kings of As·syr′i·a did to all the lands by devoting them to destruction; and will you yourself be delivered? 12 Have the gods of the nations that my forefathers brought to ruin delivered them, even Go′zan and Ha′ran and Re′zeph and the sons of E′den that were in Tel-as′sar? 13 Where is he—the king of Ha′math and the king of Ar′pad and the king of the cities of Seph·ar·va′im, He′na and Iv′vah?’”

14 Then Hez·e·ki′ah took the letters out of the hand of the messengers and read them, after which Hez·e·ki′ah went up to the house of Jehovah and spread it out before Jehovah. 15 And Hez·e·ki′ah began to pray before Jehovah and say: “O Jehovah the God of Israel, sitting upon the cherubs, you alone are the true God of all the kingdoms of the earth. You yourself have made the heavens and the earth. 16 Incline your ear, O Jehovah, and hear. Open your eyes, O Jehovah, and see, and hear the words of Sen·nach′er·ib that he has sent to taunt the living God. 17 It is a fact, O Jehovah, the kings of As·syr′i·a have devastated the nations and their land. 18 And they have consigned their gods to the fire, because they were no gods, but the workmanship of man’s hands, wood and stone; so that they destroyed them. 19 And now, O Jehovah our God, save us, please, out of his hand, that all the kingdoms of the earth may know that you, O Jehovah, are God alone.”

20 And Isaiah the son of A′moz proceeded to send to Hez·e·ki′ah, saying: “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel has said, ‘The prayer that you have made to me concerning Sen·nach′er·ib the king of As·syr′i·a I have heard. 21 This is the word that Jehovah has spoken against him:

“The virgin daughter of Zion has despised you, she has held you in derision.

Behind you the daughter of Jerusalem has wagged her head.

22 Whom have you taunted and spoken of abusively?

And against whom have you lifted up your voice

And do you raise your eyes on high?

It is against the Holy One of Israel!

23 By means of your messengers you have taunted Jehovah and you say,

‘With the multitude of my war chariots I myself—

I shall certainly ascend the height of mountainous regions,

The remotest parts of Leb′a·non;

And I shall cut down its lofty cedars, its choice juniper trees.

And I will enter its final lodging place, the forest of its orchard.

24 I myself shall certainly dig and drink strange waters,

And I shall dry up with the soles of my feet all the Nile canals of Egypt.’

25 Have you not heard? From remote times it is what I will do.

From bygone days I have even formed it.

Now I will bring it in.

And you will serve to make fortified cities desolate as piles of ruins.

26 And their inhabitants will be feeble-handed;

They will simply be terrified and will be ashamed.

They must become as vegetation of the field and green tender grass,

Grass of the roofs, when there is a scorching before the east wind.

27 And your sitting quiet and your going out and your coming in I well know,

And your exciting yourself against me,

28 Because your exciting yourself against me and your roaring have come up into my ears.

And I shall certainly put my hook in your nose and my bridle between your lips,

And I shall indeed lead you back by the way by which you have come.”

29 “‘And this will be the sign for you: There will be an eating this year of the growth from spilled kernels, and in the second year grain that shoots up of itself; but in the third year sow seed, YOU people, and reap and plant vineyards and eat their fruitage. 30 And those who escape of the house of Judah, those who are left, will certainly take root downward and produce fruitage upward. 31 For out of Jerusalem a remnant will go forth, and those who escape from Mount Zion. The very zeal of Jehovah of armies will do this.

32 “‘That is why this is what Jehovah has said concerning the king of As·syr′i·a: “He will not come into this city nor will he shoot an arrow there nor confront it with a shield nor cast up a siege rampart against it. 33 By the way by which he proceeded to come, he will return, and into this city he will not come, is the utterance of Jehovah. 34 And I shall certainly defend this city to save it for my own sake and for the sake of David my servant.”’”

35 And it came about on that night that the angel of Jehovah proceeded to go out and strike down a hundred and eighty-five thousand in the camp of the As·syr′i·ans. When people rose up early in the morning, why, there all of them were dead carcasses. 36 Therefore Sen·nach′er·ib the king of As·syr′i·a pulled away and went and returned, and he took up dwelling in Nin′e·veh. 37 And it came about that as he was bowing down at the house of Nis′roch his god, A·dram′me·lech and Shar·e′zer, his sons, themselves struck him down with the sword, and they themselves escaped to the land of Ar′a·rat. And E′sar-had′don his son began to reign in place of him.

2 Kings

20 In those days Hez·e·ki′ah got sick to the point of dying. Accordingly Isaiah the son of A′moz the prophet came in to him and said to him: “This is what Jehovah has said, ‘Give commands to your household, for you yourself will indeed die and will not live.’” 2 At that he turned his face to the wall and began to pray to Jehovah, saying: 3 “I beseech you, O Jehovah, remember, please, how I have walked before you in truthfulness and with a complete heart, and what was good in your eyes I have done.” And Hez·e·ki′ah began to weep profusely.

4 And it came about that Isaiah himself had not yet gone out to the middle court when Jehovah’s word itself came to him, saying: 5 “Go back, and you must say to Hez·e·ki′ah the leader of my people, ‘This is what Jehovah the God of David your forefather has said: “I have heard your prayer. I have seen your tears. Here I am healing you. On the third day you will go up to the house of Jehovah. 6 And I shall certainly add fifteen years to your days, and out of the palm of the king of As·syr′i·a I shall deliver you and this city, and I will defend this city for my own sake and for the sake of David my servant.”’”

7 And Isaiah went on to say: “YOU men, take a cake of pressed dried figs.” So they took and put it upon the boil, after which he gradually revived.

8 Meantime, Hez·e·ki′ah said to Isaiah: “What is the sign that Jehovah will heal me and I shall certainly go up on the third day to the house of Jehovah?” 9 To this Isaiah said: “This is the sign for you from Jehovah that Jehovah will perform the word that he has spoken: Shall the shadow actually go forward ten steps of the stairs or should it go back ten steps?” 10 Then Hez·e·ki′ah said: “It is an easy thing for the shadow to extend itself ten steps, but not that the shadow should go backward ten steps.” 11 At that Isaiah the prophet began to call out to Jehovah; and he made the shadow that had gone down gradually go back on the steps, that is, on the steps of the stairs of A′haz, ten steps backward.

12 At that time Be·ro′dach-bal′a·dan the son of Bal′a·dan the king of Babylon sent letters and a gift to Hez·e·ki′ah; for he had heard that Hez·e·ki′ah had been sick. 13 And Hez·e·ki′ah proceeded to listen to them and show them all his treasure-house, the silver and the gold and the balsam oil and the good oil and his armory and all that was to be found in his treasures. There proved to be nothing that Hez·e·ki′ah did not show them in his own house and in all his dominion.

14 After that Isaiah the prophet came in to King Hez·e·ki′ah and said to him: “What did these men say and from where did they proceed to come to you?” So Hez·e·ki′ah said: “From a distant land they came, from Babylon.” 15 And he went on to say: “What did they see in your house?” To this Hez·e·ki′ah said: “Everything that is in my house they saw. There proved to be nothing that I did not show them in my treasures.”

16 Isaiah now said to Hez·e·ki′ah: “Hear the word of Jehovah, 17 ‘“Look! Days are coming, and all that is in your own house and that your forefathers have stored up down to this day will actually be carried to Babylon. Nothing will be left,” Jehovah has said. 18 “And some of your own sons that will come forth from you to whom you will become father will themselves be taken and actually become court officials in the palace of the king of Babylon.”’”

19 At that Hez·e·ki′ah said to Isaiah: “The word of Jehovah that you have spoken is good.” And he went on to say: “Is it not so, if peace and truth themselves will continue in my own days?”

20 As for the rest of the affairs of Hez·e·ki′ah and all his mightiness and how he made the pool and the conduit and then brought the water into the city, are they not written in the book of the affairs of the days of the kings of Judah? 21 Finally Hez·e·ki′ah lay down with his forefathers; and Ma·nas′seh his son began to reign in place of him.

2 Kings

23 Then the king sent and they gathered together to him all the older men of Judah and Jerusalem. 2 After that the king went up to the house of Jehovah, and also all the men of Judah and all the inhabitants of Jerusalem with him, and also the priests and the prophets and all the people, from small to great; and he began to read in their ears all the words of the book of the covenant that had been found in the house of Jehovah. 3 And the king kept standing by the pillar and now concluded the covenant before Jehovah, to walk after Jehovah and to keep his commandments and his testimonies and his statutes with all the heart and with all the soul by carrying out the words of this covenant that were written in this book. Accordingly all the people took their stand in the covenant.

4 And the king went on to command Hil·ki′ah the high priest and the priests of the second rank and the doorkeepers to bring out from the temple of Jehovah all the utensils made for Ba′al and for the sacred pole and for all the army of the heavens. Then he burned them outside Jerusalem on the terraces of Kid′ron, and he brought the dust of them to Beth′el. 5 And he put out of business the foreign-god priests, whom the kings of Judah had put in that they might make sacrificial smoke on the high places in the cities of Judah and the surroundings of Jerusalem, and also those making sacrificial smoke to Ba′al, to the sun and to the moon and to the constellations of the zodiac and to all the army of the heavens. 6 Furthermore, he brought out the sacred pole from the house of Jehovah to the outskirts of Jerusalem, to the torrent valley of Kid′ron, and burned it in the torrent valley of Kid′ron and ground it to dust and cast its dust upon the burial place of the sons of the people. 7 Further, he pulled down the houses of the male temple prostitutes that were in the house of Jehovah, where the women were weaving tent shrines for the sacred pole.

8 Then he brought all the priests from the cities of Judah, that he might make unfit for worship the high places where the priests had made sacrificial smoke, from Ge′ba as far as Be′er-she′ba; and he pulled down the high places of the gates that were at the entrance of the gate of Joshua, the chief of the city, which was at the left as a person came into the gate of the city. 9 Only the priests of the high places would not come up to the altar of Jehovah in Jerusalem, but they ate unfermented cakes in among their brothers. 10 And he made unfit for worship To′pheth, which is in the valley of the sons of Hin′nom, that no one might make his son or his daughter pass through the fire to Mo′lech. 11 Further, he caused the horses that the kings of Judah had given to the sun to cease from entering the house of Jehovah by the dining room of Na′than-mel′ech the court official, which was in the porticoes; and the chariots of the sun he burned in the fire. 12 And the altars that were upon the roof of the roof chamber of A′haz that the kings of Judah had made, and the altars that Ma·nas′seh had made in two courtyards of the house of Jehovah, the king pulled down, after which he crushed them there, and he cast their dust into the torrent valley of Kid′ron. 13 And the high places that were in front of Jerusalem, that were to the right of the Mount of Ruination, that Sol′o·mon the king of Israel had built to Ash′to·reth the disgusting thing of the Si·do′ni·ans and to Che′mosh the disgusting thing of Mo′ab and to Mil′com the detestable thing of the sons of Am′mon, the king made unfit for worship. 14 And he broke the sacred pillars to pieces and went on to cut down the sacred poles and to fill their places with human bones. 15 And also the altar that was in Beth′el, the high place that Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat, who caused Israel to sin, had made, even that altar and the high place he pulled down. Then he burned the high place; he ground it to dust and burned the sacred pole.

16 When Jo·si′ah turned, he got to see the burial places that were there in the mountain. So he sent and took the bones from the burial places and burned them upon the altar, that he might make it unfit for worship, according to Jehovah’s word that the man of the true God had proclaimed, who proclaimed these things. 17 Then he said: “What is the gravestone over there that I am seeing?” At this the men of the city said to him: “It is the burial place of the man of the true God that came from Judah and proceeded to proclaim these things that you have done against the altar of Beth′el.” 18 So he said: “Let him rest. Do not let anyone disturb his bones.” Consequently they let his bones alone along with the bones of the prophet that had come from Sa·mar′i·a.

19 And also all the houses of the high places that were in the cities of Sa·mar′i·a that the kings of Israel had built to cause offense Jo·si′ah removed, and he went on to do to them according to all the doings that he had done at Beth′el. 20 Accordingly he sacrificed all the priests of the high places that were there upon the altars and burned human bones upon them. After that he returned to Jerusalem.

21 The king now commanded all the people, saying: “Hold a passover to Jehovah YOUR God according to what is written in this book of the covenant.” 22 For no passover like this had been held from the days of the judges that had judged Israel, nor all the days of the kings of Israel and the kings of Judah. 23 But in the eighteenth year of King Jo·si′ah this passover was held to Jehovah in Jerusalem.

24 And also the spirit mediums and the professional foretellers of events and the teraphim and the dungy idols and all the disgusting things that had appeared in the land of Judah and in Jerusalem Jo·si′ah cleared out, in order that he might actually carry out the words of the law that were written in the book that Hil·ki′ah the priest had found at the house of Jehovah. 25 And like him there did not prove to be a king prior to him who returned to Jehovah with all his heart and with all his soul and with all his vital force, according to all the law of Moses; neither after him has there risen up one like him.

26 Nevertheless, Jehovah did not turn back from the great burning of his anger, with which his anger burned against Judah over all the offensive things with which Ma·nas′seh had made them offend. 27 But Jehovah said: “Judah, too, I shall remove from my sight, just as I have removed Israel; and I shall certainly reject this city that I have chosen, even Jerusalem, and the house of which I have said, ‘My name will continue there.’”

28 As for the rest of the affairs of Jo·si′ah and all that he did, are they not written in the book of the affairs of the days of the kings of Judah? 29 In his days Phar′aoh Ne′choh the king of Egypt came up to the king of As·syr′i·a by the river Eu·phra′tes, and King Jo·si′ah proceeded to go to meet him; but he put him to death at Me·gid′do as soon as he saw him. 30 So his servants conveyed him dead in a chariot from Me·gid′do and brought him to Jerusalem and buried him in his grave. Then the people of the land took Je·ho′a·haz the son of Jo·si′ah and anointed him and made him king in place of his father.

31 Twenty-three years old was Je·ho′a·haz when he began to reign, and for three months he reigned in Jerusalem. And his mother’s name was Ha·mu′tal the daughter of Jeremiah from Lib′nah. 32 And he began to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, according to all that forefathers of his had done. 33 And Phar′aoh Ne′choh got to put him in bonds at Rib′lah in the land of Ha′math, to keep him from reigning in Jerusalem, and then imposed a fine upon the land of a hundred silver talents and a gold talent. 34 Furthermore, Phar′aoh Ne′choh made E·li′a·kim the son of Jo·si′ah king in place of Jo·si′ah his father and changed his name to Je·hoi′a·kim; and Je·ho′a·haz he took and then brought to Egypt, where he eventually died. 35 And the silver and the gold Je·hoi′a·kim gave to Phar′aoh. Only he taxed the land, to give the silver at the order of Phar′aoh. According to each one’s individual tax rate he exacted the silver and the gold from the people of the land, to give it to Phar′aoh Ne′choh.

36 Twenty-five years old was Je·hoi′a·kim when he began to reign, and for eleven years he reigned in Jerusalem. And his mother’s name was Ze·bi′dah the daughter of Pe·dai′ah from Ru′mah. 37 And he continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, according to all that forefathers of his had done.

2 Kings

25 And it came about in the ninth year of his being king, in the tenth month, on the tenth day of the month, that Neb·u·chad·nez′zar the king of Babylon came, yes, he and all his military force, against Jerusalem and began camping against it and building against it a siege wall all around. 2 And the city came to be under siege until the eleventh year of King Zed·e·ki′ah. 3 On the ninth day of the fourth month the famine was severe in the city, and there proved to be no bread for the people of the land. 4 And the city got to be breached, and all the men of war fled by night by the way of the gate between the double wall that is by the king’s garden, while the Chal·de′ans were all around against the city; and the king began to go in the direction of the Ar′a·bah. 5 And a military force of Chal·de′ans went chasing after the king, and they got to overtake him in the desert plains of Jer′i·cho; and all his own military force was scattered from his side. 6 Then they seized the king and brought him up to the king of Babylon at Rib′lah, that they might pronounce a judicial decision upon him. 7 And Zed·e·ki′ah’s sons they slaughtered before his eyes, and Zed·e·ki′ah’s eyes he blinded, after which he bound him with copper fetters and brought him to Babylon.

8 And in the fifth month on the seventh day of the month, that is to say, the nineteenth year of King Neb·u·chad·nez′zar the king of Babylon, Neb·u′zar·ad′an the chief of the bodyguard, the servant of the king of Babylon, came to Jerusalem. 9 And he proceeded to burn the house of Jehovah and the king’s house and all the houses of Jerusalem; and the house of every great man he burned with fire. 10 And the walls of Jerusalem, all around, the entire military force of Chal·de′ans that were with the chief of the bodyguard pulled down. 11 And the rest of the people that were left behind in the city and the deserters that had gone over to the king of Babylon and the rest of the crowd Neb·u′zar·ad′an the chief of the bodyguard took into exile. 12 And some of the lowly people of the land the chief of the bodyguard let remain as vinedressers and as compulsory laborers. 13 And the pillars of copper that were in the house of Jehovah, and the carriages and the copper sea that were in the house of Jehovah, the Chal·de′ans broke in pieces and went carrying the copper of them to Babylon. 14 And the cans and the shovels and the extinguishers and the cups and all the utensils of copper with which they used to minister they took. 15 And the chief of the bodyguard took the fire holders and the bowls that were of genuine gold and those that were of genuine silver. 16 As for the two pillars, the one sea and the carriages that Sol′o·mon had made for the house of Jehovah, there happened to be no way to tell the weight of the copper of all these utensils. 17 Eighteen cubits was the height of each pillar, and the capital upon it was of copper; and the height of the capital was three cubits; and the network and the pomegranates all around upon the capital, the whole of it, was copper; and the second pillar had the same as these upon the network.

18 Furthermore, the chief of the bodyguard took Se·rai′ah the chief priest and Zeph·a·ni′ah the second priest and three doorkeepers; 19 and from the city he took one court official that had a command over the men of war, and five men from those having access to the king that were found in the city; and the secretary of the chief of the army, the one mustering the people of the land, and sixty men of the people of the land that were to be found in the city; 20 and Neb·u′zar·ad′an the chief of the bodyguard then took them and conducted them to the king of Babylon at Rib′lah. 21 And the king of Babylon proceeded to strike them down and put them to death at Rib′lah in the land of Ha′math. Thus Judah went into exile from off its soil.

22 As for the people left behind in the land of Judah, whom Neb·u·chad·nez′zar the king of Babylon had left behind, he now appointed over them Ged·a·li′ah the son of A·hi′kam the son of Sha′phan. 23 When all the chiefs of the military forces, they and their men, heard that the king of Babylon had appointed Ged·a·li′ah, they immediately came to Ged·a·li′ah at Miz′pah, that is, Ish′ma·el the son of Neth·a·ni′ah and Jo·ha′nan the son of Ka·re′ah and Se·rai′ah the son of Tan·hu′meth the Ne·toph′a·thite and Ja·az·a·ni′ah the son of the Ma·ac′a·thite, they and their men. 24 Then Ged·a·li′ah swore to them and their men and said to them: “Do not be afraid of being servants to the Chal·de′ans. Dwell in the land and serve the king of Babylon, and it will go well with YOU.”

25 And it came about in the seventh month that Ish′ma·el the son of Neth·a·ni′ah the son of E·lish′a·ma of the royal offspring came, and also ten men with him, and they got to strike down Ged·a·li′ah, so that he died, and also the Jews and the Chal·de′ans that happened to be with him in Miz′pah. 26 After that all the people, from small to great, and the chiefs of the military forces rose up and came into Egypt; for they had become afraid because of the Chal·de′ans.

27 And it came about in the thirty-seventh year of the exile of Je·hoi′a·chin the king of Judah, in the twelfth month, on the twenty-seventh day of the month, that E′vil-mer′o·dach the king of Babylon, in the year of his becoming king, raised up the head of Je·hoi′a·chin the king of Judah out of the house of detention; 28 and he began to speak good things with him, and then put his throne higher than the thrones of the kings that were with him in Babylon. 29 And he took off his prison garments; and he ate bread constantly before him all the days of his life. 30 As for his allowance, an allowance was constantly given him from the king, daily as due, all the days of his life.

1 Chronicles

2 These were the sons of Israel: Reu′ben, Sim′e·on, Le′vi and Judah, Is′sa·char and Zeb′u·lun, 2 Dan, Joseph and Benjamin, Naph′ta·li, Gad and Ash′er.

3 The sons of Judah were Er and O′nan and She′lah. The three were born to him from Shu′a’s daughter, the Ca′naan·it·ess. And Er the firstborn of Judah came to be bad in the eyes of Jehovah, so that he put him to death. 4 And Ta′mar his daughter-in-law it was that bore to him Pe′rez and Ze′rah. All the sons of Judah were five.

5 The sons of Pe′rez were Hez′ron and Ha′mul.

6 And the sons of Ze′rah were Zim′ri and E′than and He′man and Cal′col and Da′ra. There were five of them in all.

7 And the sons of Car′mi were A′char the bringer of ostracism upon Israel, who committed an act of unfaithfulness respecting the thing devoted to destruction.

8 And the sons of E′than were Az·a·ri′ah.

9 And the sons of Hez′ron that were born to him were Je·rah′me·el and Ram and Che·lu′bai.

10 As for Ram, he became father to Am·min′a·dab. Am·min′a·dab, in turn, became father to Nah′shon the chieftain of the sons of Judah. 11 Nah′shon, in turn, became father to Sal′ma. Sal′ma, in turn, became father to Bo′az. 12 Bo′az, in turn, became father to O′bed. O′bed, in turn, became father to Jes′se. 13 Jes′se, in turn, became father to his firstborn E·li′ab, and A·bin′a·dab the second, and Shim′e·a the third, 14 Ne·than′el the fourth, Rad′dai the fifth, 15 O′zem the sixth, David the seventh. 16 And their sisters were Ze·ru′iah and Ab′i·gail; and the sons of Ze·ru′iah were A·bish′ai and Jo′ab and As′a·hel, three. 17 As for Ab′i·gail, she gave birth to A·ma′sa; and the father of A·ma′sa was Je′ther the Ish′ma·el·ite.

18 As for Ca′leb the son of Hez′ron, he became father to sons by A·zu′bah his wife and by Jer′i·oth; and these were her sons: Je′sher and Sho′bab and Ar′don. 19 Eventually A·zu′bah died. So Ca′leb took to himself Eph′rath, who in time bore Hur to him. 20 Hur, in turn, became father to U′ri. U′ri, in turn, became father to Bez′al·el.

21 And afterward Hez′ron had relations with the daughter of Ma′chir the father of Gil′e·ad. And he himself took her when he was sixty years old, but she bore Se′gub to him. 22 Se′gub, in turn, became father to Ja′ir, who came to have twenty-three cities in the land of Gil′e·ad. 23 Later Gesh′ur and Syria took Hav′voth-ja′ir from them, with Ke′nath and its dependent towns, sixty cities. All these were the sons of Ma′chir the father of Gil′e·ad.

24 And after the death of Hez′ron in Ca′leb-eph′ra·thah, with A·bi′jah being the wife of Hez′ron, she then bore him Ash′hur the father of Te·ko′a.

25 And the sons of Je·rah′me·el the firstborn of Hez′ron were Ram the firstborn and Bu′nah and O′ren and O′zem, A·hi′jah. 26 And Je·rah′me·el came to have another wife, whose name was At′a·rah. She was the mother of O′nam. 27 And the sons of Ram the firstborn of Je·rah′me·el came to be Ma′az and Ja′min and E′ker. 28 And the sons of O′nam came to be Sham′mai and Ja′da. And the sons of Sham′mai were Na′dab and A·bi′shur. 29 And the name of A·bi′shur’s wife was Ab′i·ha·il, who in time bore him Ah′ban and Mo′lid. 30 And the sons of Na′dab were Se′led and Ap′pa·im. But Se′led died without sons. 31 And the sons of Ap′pa·im were Ish′i. And the sons of Ish′i were She′shan; and the sons of She′shan, Ah′lai. 32 And the sons of Ja′da the brother of Sham′mai were Je′ther and Jon′a·than. But Je′ther died without sons. 33 And the sons of Jon′a·than were Pe′leth and Za′za. These became the sons of Je·rah′me·el.

34 And She′shan came to have no sons, but daughters. Now She′shan had an Egyptian servant whose name was Jar′ha. 35 So She′shan gave his daughter to Jar′ha his servant as a wife, who in time bore him At′tai. 36 At′tai, in turn, became father to Nathan. Nathan, in turn, became father to Za′bad. 37 Za′bad, in turn, became father to Eph′lal. Eph′lal, in turn, became father to O′bed. 38 O′bed, in turn, became father to Je′hu. Je′hu, in turn, became father to Az·a·ri′ah. 39 Az·a·ri′ah, in turn, became father to He′lez. He′lez, in turn, became father to El·e·a′sah. 40 El·e·a′sah, in turn, became father to Sis′mai. Sis′mai, in turn, became father to Shal′lum. 41 Shal′lum, in turn, became father to Jek·a·mi′ah. Jek·a·mi′ah, in turn, became father to E·lish′a·ma.

42 And the sons of Ca′leb the brother of Je·rah′me·el were Me′sha his firstborn, who was the father of Ziph, and the sons of Ma·re′shah the father of He′bron. 43 And the sons of He′bron were Ko′rah and Tap′pu·ah and Re′kem and She′ma. 44 She′ma, in turn, became father to Ra′ham the father of Jor′ke·am. Re′kem, in turn, became father to Sham′mai. 45 And the son of Sham′mai was Ma′on; and Ma′on was the father of Beth-zur. 46 As for E′phah the concubine of Ca′leb, she gave birth to Ha′ran and Mo′za and Ga′zez. As for Ha′ran, he became father to Ga′zez. 47 And the sons of Jah′dai were Re′gem and Jo′tham and Ge′shan and Pel′et and E′phah and Sha′aph. 48 As for Ca′leb’s concubine Ma′a·cah, she gave birth to She′ber and Tir′ha·nah. 49 In time she bore Sha′aph the father of Mad·man′nah, She′va the father of Mach·be′nah and the father of Gib′e·a. And Ca′leb’s daughter was Ach′sah. 50 These became the sons of Ca′leb.

The sons of Hur the firstborn of Eph′ra·thah: Sho′bal the father of Kir′i·ath-je′a·rim, 51 Sal′ma the father of Beth′le·hem, Ha′reph the father of Beth-ga′der. 52 And Sho′bal the father of Kir′i·ath-je′a·rim came to have sons: Ha·ro′eh, half of the Me·nu′hoth. 53 And the families of Kir′i·ath-je′a·rim were the Ith′rites and the Pu′thites and the Shu′math·ites and the Mish′ra·ites. It was from these that the Zo′rath·ites and the Esh′ta·ol·ites came out. 54 The sons of Sal′ma were Beth′le·hem and the Ne·toph′a·thites, At′roth-beth-jo′ab and half of the Man·a·ha′thites, the Zor′ites. 55 And the families of the scribes dwelling at Ja′bez were the Ti′rath·ites, the Shim′e·ath·ites, the Su′cath·ites. These were the Ken′ites that came from Ham′math the father of the house of Re′chab.

1 Chronicles

4 The sons of Judah were Pe′rez, Hez′ron and Car′mi and Hur and Sho′bal. 2 As for Re·a′iah the son of Sho′bal, he became father to Ja′hath; Ja′hath, in turn, became father to A·hu′mai and La′had. These were the families of the Zo′rath·ites. 3 And these were the sons of the father of E′tam: Jez′re·el and Ish′ma and Id′bash, (and the name of their sister was Haz·ze·lel·po′ni,) 4 and Pe·nu′el the father of Ge′dor and E′zer the father of Hu′shah. These were the sons of Hur the firstborn of Eph′ra·thah the father of Beth′le·hem. 5 And Ash′hur the father of Te·ko′a came to have two wives, He′lah and Na′a·rah. 6 In time Na′a·rah bore to him A·huz′zam and He′pher and Te′me·ni and Ha·a·hash′ta·ri. These were the sons of Na′a·rah. 7 And the sons of He′lah were Ze′reth, Iz′har and Eth′nan. 8 As for Koz, he became father to A′nub and Zo·be′bah and the families of A·har′hel the son of Ha′rum.

9 And Ja′bez came to be more honorable than his brothers; and it was his mother that called his name Ja′bez, saying: “I have given him birth in pain.” 10 And Ja′bez began to call upon the God of Israel, saying: “If you will without fail bless me and actually enlarge my territory and your hand really proves to be with me, and you really preserve me from calamity, that it may not hurt me,—” Accordingly God brought to pass what he had asked.

11 As for Che′lub the brother of Shu′hah, he became father to Me′hir, who was the father of Esh′ton. 12 Esh′ton, in turn, became father to Beth-ra′pha and Pa·se′ah and Te·hin′nah the father of Ir-na′hash. These were the men of Re′cah. 13 And the sons of Ke′naz were Oth′ni·el and Se·rai′ah, and the sons of Oth′ni·el, Ha′thath. 14 As for Me·o′no·thai, he became father to Oph′rah. As for Se·rai′ah, he became father to Jo′ab the father of Ge-har′a·shim; for craftsmen are what they became.

15 And the sons of Ca′leb the son of Je·phun′neh were I′ru, E′lah and Na′am; and the sons of E′lah, Ke′naz. 16 And the sons of Je·hal′le·lel were Ziph and Zi′phah, Tir′i·a and As′a·rel. 17 And the sons of Ez′rah were Je′ther and Me′red and E′pher and Ja′lon; and she got to conceive Mir′i·am and Sham′mai and Ish′bah the father of Esh·te·mo′a. 18 As for his Jewish wife, she gave birth to Je′red the father of Ge′dor and He′ber the father of So′co and Je·ku′thi·el the father of Za·no′ah. And these were the sons of Bi·thi′ah the daughter of Phar′aoh, whom Me′red took.

19 And the sons of Ho·di′ah’s wife, the sister of Na′ham, were the father of Kei′lah the Gar′mite and Esh·te·mo′a the Ma·ac′a·thite. 20 And the sons of Shi′mon were Am′non and Rin′nah, Ben-ha′nan and Ti′lon. And the sons of Ish′i were Zo′heth and Ben-zo′heth.

21 The sons of She′lah the son of Judah were Er the father of Le′cah and La′a·dah the father of Ma·re′shah and the families of the house of the workers of fine fabric of the house of Ash·be′a; 22 and Jo′kim and the men of Co·ze′ba and Jo′ash and Sa′raph, who became owners of Mo′ab·ite wives, and Jash′u·bi-le′hem. And the sayings are of old tradition. 23 They were the potters and the inhabitants of Ne·ta′im and Ge·de′rah. It was with the king in his work that they dwelt there.

24 The sons of Sim′e·on were Nem′u·el and Ja′min, Ja′rib, Ze′rah, Sha′ul, 25 Shal′lum his son, Mib′sam his son, Mish′ma his son. 26 And the sons of Mish′ma were Ham′mu·el his son, Zac′cur his son, Shim′e·i his son. 27 And Shim′e·i had sixteen sons and six daughters; but his brothers did not have many sons, and none of their families had as many as the sons of Judah. 28 And they continued to dwell in Be′er-she′ba and Mo·la′dah and Ha′zar-shu′al 29 and in Bil′hah and in E′zem and in To′lad 30 and in Be·thu′el and in Hor′mah and in Zik′lag 31 and in Beth-mar′ca·both and in Ha′zar-su′sim and in Beth-bir′i and in Sha′a·ra′im. These were their cities down till David reigned.

32 And their settlements were E′tam and A′in, Rim′mon and To′chen and A′shan, five cities. 33 And all their settlements that were all around these cities were as far as Ba′al. These were their dwelling places and their genealogical enrollments for them. 34 And Me·sho′bab and Jam′lech and Jo′shah the son of Am·a·zi′ah, 35 and Joel and Je′hu the son of Josh·i·bi′ah the son of Se·rai′ah the son of As′i·el, 36 and Eli·o·e′nai and Ja·a·ko′bah and Jesh·o·hai′ah and A·sai′ah and Ad′i·el and Je·sim′i·el and Be·nai′ah, 37 and Zi′za the son of Shi′phi the son of Al′lon the son of Je·da′iah the son of Shim′ri the son of She·mai′ah. 38 These who came in by names were the chieftains among their families, and the household itself of their forefathers increased in multitude. 39 And they proceeded to go to the entryway of Ge′dor, clear to the east of the valley, to look for pasturage for their flocks. 40 Eventually they found fat and good pasturage, and the land was quite wide and having no disturbance but at ease; for those dwelling there in former times were of Ham. 41 And these written down by their names proceeded to come in in the days of Hez·e·ki′ah the king of Judah and strike down the tents of the Ham′ites and the Me·u′nim that were to be found there, so that they devoted them to destruction down to this day; and they began to dwell in their place, because there was pasturage for their flocks there.

42 And from them there were some of the sons of Sim′e·on that went to Mount Se′ir, five hundred men, with Pel·a·ti′ah and Ne·a·ri′ah and Re·pha′iah and Uz′zi·el the sons of Ish′i at their head. 43 And they proceeded to strike down the remnant that had escaped of Am′a·lek, and they continued to dwell there down to this day.

1 Chronicles

5 And the sons of Reu′ben the firstborn of Israel—for he was the firstborn; but for his profaning the lounge of his father his right as firstborn was given to the sons of Joseph the son of Israel, so that he was not to be enrolled genealogically for the right of the firstborn. 2 For Judah himself proved to be superior among his brothers, and the one for leader was from him; but the right as firstborn was Joseph’s— 3 the sons of Reu′ben the firstborn of Israel were Ha′noch and Pal′lu, Hez′ron and Car′mi. 4 The sons of Joel were She·mai′ah his son, Gog his son, Shim′e·i his son, 5 Mi′cah his son, Re·a′iah his son, Ba′al his son, 6 Be·er′ah his son, whom Til′gath-pil·ne′ser the king of As·syr′i·a took into exile, he being a chieftain of the Reu′ben·ites. 7 And his brothers by their families in the genealogical enrollment by their descendants were, as the head, Je·i′el, and Zech·a·ri′ah, 8 and Be′la the son of A′zaz the son of She′ma the son of Joel—he was dwelling in A·ro′er and as far as Ne′bo and Ba′al-me′on. 9 Even to the east he dwelt as far as where one enters the wilderness at the river Eu·phra′tes, for their livestock itself had become numerous in the land of Gil′e·ad. 10 And in the days of Saul they made war upon the Hag′rites, who came to fall by their hand; and so they dwelt in their tents throughout all the country east of Gil′e·ad.

11 As for the sons of Gad in front of them, they dwelt in the land of Ba′shan as far as Sal′e·cah. 12 Joel was the head, and Sha′pham the second, and Ja′nai and Sha′phat in Ba′shan. 13 And their brothers belonging to the house of their forefathers were Mi′cha·el and Me·shul′lam and She′ba and Jo′rai and Ja′can and Zi′a and E′ber, seven. 14 These were the sons of Ab′i·ha·il the son of Hu′ri, the son of Ja·ro′ah, the son of Gil′e·ad, the son of Mi′cha·el, the son of Je·shish′ai, the son of Jah′do, the son of Buz; 15 A′hi the son of Ab′di·el, the son of Gu′ni, head of the house of their forefathers. 16 And they continued to dwell in Gil′e·ad, in Ba′shan and in its dependent towns and in all the pasture grounds of Shar′on as far as their terminations. 17 They were all of them enrolled genealogically in the days of Jo′tham the king of Judah and in the days of Jer·o·bo′am the king of Israel.

18 As for the sons of Reu′ben and the Gad′ites and the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh; of those who were valiant fellows, men carrying shield and sword and bending the bow and trained in war, there were forty-four thousand seven hundred and sixty going out to the army. 19 And they began to make war upon the Hag′rites, and Je′tur and Na′phish and No′dab. 20 And they came to be helped against them, so that the Hag′rites and all those who were with them were given into their hand, for it was to God that they called for aid in the war, and he let himself be entreated in their favor because they trusted in him. 21 And they got to take captive their livestock, their camels fifty thousand, and sheep two hundred and fifty thousand, and asses two thousand, and human souls a hundred thousand. 22 For there were many that had fallen slain, because it was on the part of the true God that the fighting was. And they continued to dwell in their place down to the time of the exile.

23 As for the sons of the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh, they dwelt in the land from Ba′shan to Ba′al-her′mon and Se′nir and Mount Her′mon. They themselves became numerous. 24 And these were the heads of the house of their forefathers: E′pher and Ish′i and E′li·el and Az′ri·el and Jeremiah and Hod·a·vi′ah and Jah′di·el, men that were valiant, mighty fellows, men of fame, heads of the house of their forefathers. 25 And they began to act unfaithfully toward the God of their forefathers and went having immoral intercourse with the gods of the peoples of the land, whom God had annihilated from before them. 26 Consequently the God of Israel stirred up the spirit of Pul the king of As·syr′i·a even the spirit of Til′gath-pil·ne′ser the king of As·syr′i·a, so that he took into exile those of the Reu′ben·ites and of the Gad′ites and of the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh and brought them to Ha′lah and Ha′bor and Ha′ra and the river Go′zan to continue until this day.

1 Chronicles

7 Now the sons of Is′sa·char were To′la and Pu′ah, Ja′shub and Shim′ron, four. 2 And the sons of To′la were Uz′zi and Re·pha′iah and Je′ri·el and Jah′mai and Ib′sam and She·mu′el, heads of the house of their forefathers. Of To′la there were valiant, mighty men, by their descendants. Their number in the days of David was twenty-two thousand six hundred. 3 And the sons of Uz′zi were Iz·ra·hi′ah; and the sons of Iz·ra·hi′ah were Mi′cha·el and O·ba·di′ah and Joel, Is·shi′ah, , five, all of them being heads. 4 And with them by their descendants, according to the house of their forefathers, there were troops of the army for war, thirty-six thousand, for they had many wives and sons. 5 And their brothers of all the families of Is′sa·char were valiant, mighty men, eighty-seven thousand by the genealogical enrollment of them all.

6 The sons of Benjamin were Be′la and Be′cher and Je·di′a·el, three. 7 And the sons of Be′la were Ez′bon and Uz′zi and Uz′zi·el and Jer′i·moth and I′ri, five, heads of the house of their forefathers, valiant, mighty men; and their genealogical enrollment was twenty-two thousand and thirty-four. 8 And the sons of Be′cher were Ze·mi′rah and Jo′ash and E·li·e′zer and Eli·o·e′nai and Om′ri and Jer′e·moth and A·bi′jah and An′a·thoth and Al′e·meth, all these the sons of Be′cher. 9 And their genealogical enrollment by their descendants as respects the heads of the house of their forefathers, valiant, mighty men, was twenty thousand two hundred. 10 And the sons of Je·di′a·el were Bil′han; and the sons of Bil′han were Je′ush and Benjamin and E′hud and Che·na′a·nah and Ze′than and Tar′shish and A·hish′a·har. 11 All these were the sons of Je·di′a·el, according to the heads of their forefathers, valiant, mighty men, seventeen thousand two hundred going out to the army for war.

12 And the Shup′pim and the Hup′pim were the sons of Ir; the Hu′shim were the sons of A′her.

13 The sons of Naph′ta·li were Jah′zi·el and Gu′ni and Je′zer and Shal′lum, the sons of Bil′hah.

14 The sons of Ma·nas′seh were As′ri·el, whom his Syrian concubine bore. (She bore Ma′chir the father of Gil′e·ad. 15 And Ma′chir himself took a wife for Hup′pim and for Shup′pim, and the name of his sister was Ma′a·cah.) And the name of the second was Ze·lo′phe·had, but Ze·lo′phe·had came to have daughters. 16 In time Ma′a·cah, Ma′chir’s wife, bore a son and called his name Pe′resh; and the name of his brother was She′resh; and his sons were U′lam and Re′kem. 17 And the sons of U′lam were Be′dan. These were the sons of Gil′e·ad the son of Ma′chir the son of Ma·nas′seh. 18 And his sister was Ham·mo′le·cheth. She gave birth to Ish′hod and Abi-e′zer and Mah′lah. 19 And the sons of She·mi′da came to be A·hi′an and She′chem and Lik′hi and A·ni′am.

20 And the sons of E′phra·im were Shu′the·lah and Be′red his son and Ta′hath his son and E·le·a′dah his son and Ta′hath his son, 21 and Za′bad his son and Shu′the·lah his son and E′zer and E′le·ad. And the men of Gath that were born in the land killed them because they came down to take their livestock. 22 And E′phra·im their father carried on mourning for many days, and his brothers kept coming in to comfort him. 23 Afterward he had relations with his wife, so that she became pregnant and gave birth to a son. But he called his name Be·ri′ah, because it was with calamity that she happened to be in his house. 24 And his daughter was She′e·rah, and she got to build Beth-ho′ron, the lower and the upper, and Uz′zen-she′e·rah. 25 And there was Re′phah his son, and Re′sheph, and Te′lah his son, and Ta′han his son, 26 La′dan his son, Am·mi′hud his son, E·lish′a·ma his son, 27 Nun his son, Je·hosh′u·a his son.

28 And their possession and their dwelling places were Beth′el and its dependent towns and, to the east, Na′a·ran and, to the west, Ge′zer and its dependent towns, and She′chem and its dependent towns clear to Ga′za and its dependent towns; 29 and by the side of the sons of Ma·nas′seh Beth-she′an and its dependent towns, Ta′a·nach and its dependent towns, Me·gid′do and its dependent towns, Dor and its dependent towns. In these the sons of Joseph the son of Israel dwelt.

30 The sons of Ash′er were Im′nah and Ish′vah and Ish′vi and Be·ri′ah; and Se′rah was their sister. 31 And the sons of Be·ri′ah were He′ber and Mal′chi·el, who was the father of Bir′za·ith. 32 As for He′ber, he became father to Japh′let and Sho′mer and Ho′tham, and to Shu′a their sister. 33 And the sons of Japh′let were Pa′sach and Bim′hal and Ash′vath. These were the sons of Japh′let. 34 And the sons of She′mer were A′hi and Roh′gah, Je·hub′bah and A′ram. 35 And the sons of He′lem his brother were Zo′phah and Im′na and She′lesh and A′mal. 36 The sons of Zo′phah were Su′ah and Har′ne·pher and Shu′al and Be′ri and Im′rah, 37 Be′zer and Hod and Sham′ma and Shil′shah and Ith′ran and Be·e′ra. 38 And the sons of Je′ther were Je·phun′neh and Pis′pah and A′ra. 39 And the sons of Ul′la were A′rah and Han′ni·el and Ri·zi′a. 40 All these were the sons of Ash′er, heads of the house of the forefathers, select, valiant, mighty men, heads of the chieftains; and their genealogical enrollment was in the army in the war. Their number was twenty-six thousand men.

1 Chronicles

9 As for all Israelites, they were enrolled genealogically; and there they are written in the Book of the Kings of Israel. And Judah itself was taken into exile at Babylon for their unfaithfulness. 2 And the first inhabitants that were in their possession in their cities were the Israelites, the priests, the Levites and the Neth′i·nim. 3 And in Jerusalem there dwelt some of the sons of Judah and some of the sons of Benjamin and some of the sons of E′phra·im and of Ma·nas′seh: 4 U′thai the son of Am·mi′hud the son of Om′ri the son of Im′ri the son of Ba′ni, of the sons of Pe′rez the son of Judah. 5 And of the Shi′lo·nites, A·sai′ah the firstborn and his sons. 6 And of the sons of Ze′rah, Je·u′el, and six hundred and ninety brothers of theirs.

7 And of the sons of Benjamin, Sal′lu the son of Me·shul′lam the son of Hod·a·vi′ah the son of Has·se·nu′ah, 8 and Ib·ne′iah the son of Je·ro′ham, and E′lah the son of Uz′zi the son of Mich′ri, and Me·shul′lam the son of Sheph·a·ti′ah the son of Reu′el the son of Ib·ni′jah. 9 And the brothers of theirs by their descendants were nine hundred and fifty-six. All these were men that were heads of the fathers by the house of their forefathers.

10 And of the priests there were Je·da′iah and Je·hoi′a·rib and Ja′chin, 11 and Az·a·ri′ah the son of Hil·ki′ah the son of Me·shul′lam the son of Za′dok the son of Me·ra′ioth the son of A·hi′tub, a leader of the house of the true God, 12 and A·dai′ah the son of Je·ro′ham the son of Pash′hur the son of Mal·chi′jah, and Ma′a·sai the son of Ad′i·el the son of Jah′ze·rah the son of Me·shul′lam the son of Me·shil′le·mith the son of Im′mer, 13 and their brothers, heads of the house of their forefathers, a thousand seven hundred and sixty, mighty men of ability for the work of the service of the house of the true God.

14 And of the Levites there were She·mai′ah the son of Has′shub the son of Az·ri′kam the son of Hash·a·bi′ah from the sons of Me·rar′i; 15 and Bak·bak′kar, He′resh and Ga′lal, and Mat·ta·ni′ah the son of Mi′ca the son of Zich′ri the son of A′saph, 16 and O·ba·di′ah the son of She·mai′ah the son of Ga′lal the son of Je·du′thun, and Ber·e·chi′ah the son of A′sa the son of El·ka′nah, who was dwelling in the settlements of the Ne·toph′a·thites.

17 And the gatekeepers were Shal′lum and Ak′kub and Tal′mon and A·hi′man and their brother Shal′lum the head, 18 and up till then he was in the king’s gate to the east. These were the gatekeepers of the camps of the sons of Le′vi. 19 And Shal′lum the son of Ko′re the son of E·bi′a·saph the son of Ko′rah and his brothers of the house of his father the Ko′rah·ites, over the work of the service, the doorkeepers of the tent, and their fathers over the camp of Jehovah, the keepers of the entryway. 20 And it was Phin′e·has the son of El·e·a′zar that happened to be leader over them in the past. Jehovah was with him. 21 Zech·a·ri′ah the son of Me·shel·e·mi′ah was the gatekeeper of the entrance of the tent of meeting.

22 All of them who were selected as gatekeepers at the thresholds were two hundred and twelve. They were in their settlements by their genealogical enrollment. These David and Samuel the seer ordained in their office of trust. 23 And they and their sons were over the gates of the house of Jehovah, even the house of the tent, for guard service. 24 It was to the four directions that the gatekeepers came to be, to the east, to the west, to the north and to the south. 25 And their brothers in their settlements were to come in for seven days, from time to time, along with these. 26 For in office of trust there were four mighty men of the gatekeepers. They were Levites, and they proved to be in charge of the dining rooms and of the treasures of the house of the true God. 27 And all around the house of the true God they would spend the night; for guard service was upon them, and they were in charge of the key, even to open up from morning to morning.

28 And some of them were in charge of the utensils of the service, for it was by number that they would bring them in and it was by number that they would take them out. 29 And some of them were men appointed over the utensils and over all the holy utensils and over the fine flour and the wine and the oil and the frankincense and the balsam oil. 30 And some of the sons of the priests were makers of the ointment mixture of balsam oil. 31 And Mat·ti·thi′ah of the Levites, who was the firstborn of Shal′lum the Ko′rah·ite, was in the office of trust over the things baked in pans. 32 And some of the sons of the Ko′hath·ites, their brothers, were in charge of the layer bread, to prepare it sabbath by sabbath.

33 And these were the singers, the heads of the fathers of the Levites in the dining rooms, those set free from duty; for by day and by night it was their responsibility to be in the work. 34 These were the heads of the fathers of the Levites by their descendants, headmen. These were the ones that dwelt in Jerusalem.

35 And in Gib′e·on was where the father of Gib′e·on, Je·i′el, dwelt. And his wife’s name was Ma′a·cah. 36 And his son, the firstborn, was Ab′don, and Zur and Kish and Ba′al and Ner and Na′dab, 37 and Ge′dor and A·hi′o and Zech·a·ri′ah and Mik′loth. 38 As for Mik′loth, he became father to Shim′e·am. And it was really they that dwelt in front of their brothers in Jerusalem along with brothers of theirs. 39 As for Ner, he became father to Kish; Kish, in turn, became father to Saul; Saul, in turn, became father to Jon′a·than and Mal′chi-shu′a and A·bin′a·dab and Esh·ba′al. 40 And the son of Jon′a·than was Mer′ib-ba′al. As for Mer′ib-ba′al, he became father to Mi′cah. 41 And the sons of Mi′cah were Pi′thon and Mel′ech and Tahr′e·a and A′haz. 42 As for A′haz, he became father to Ja′rah; Ja′rah, in turn, became father to Al′e·meth and Az′ma·veth and Zim′ri. Zim′ri, in turn, became father to Mo′za. 43 As for Mo′za, he became father to Bin′e·a and Re·pha′iah his son, El·e·a′sah his son, A′zel his son. 44 And A′zel had six sons, and these were their names: Az·ri′kam, Bo′che·ru and Ish′ma·el and She·a·ri′ah and O·ba·di′ah and Ha′nan. These were the sons of A′zel.

1 Chronicles

11 In time all the Israelites collected themselves together to David at He′bron, saying: “Look! We are your bone and your flesh. 2 Both yesterday and previously, even while Saul happened to be king, you were the one leading Israel out and bringing it in; and Jehovah your God proceeded to say to you, ‘You yourself will shepherd my people Israel, and you yourself will become leader over my people Israel.’” 3 So all the older men of Israel came to the king at He′bron and David concluded a covenant with them in He′bron before Jehovah; after which they anointed David as king over Israel, according to Jehovah’s word by means of Samuel.

4 Later David and all Israel went to Jerusalem, that is to say, Je′bus, where the Jeb′u·sites were the inhabitants of the land. 5 And the inhabitants of Je′bus began to say to David: “You will not come in here.” Just the same, David proceeded to capture the stronghold of Zion, that is to say, the City of David. 6 So David said: “Anyone striking the Jeb′u·sites first, he will become head and prince.” And Jo′ab the son of Ze·ru′iah got to go up first, and he came to be head. 7 And David took up dwelling in the place difficult to approach. That is why they called it the City of David. 8 And he began to build the city all around, from the Mound even to the parts round about, but Jo′ab himself brought to life the rest of the city. 9 And David went on getting greater and greater, for Jehovah of armies was with him.

10 Now these are the heads of the mighty men that belonged to David, holding strongly with him in his kingship together with all Israel, to make him king according to Jehovah’s word concerning Israel. 11 And this is the list of the mighty men that belonged to David: Ja·sho′be·am the son of a Hach′mon·ite, the head of the three. He was brandishing his spear over three hundred slain at one time. 12 And after him there was El·e·a′zar the son of Do′do the A·ho′hite. He was among the three mighty men. 13 He it was that happened to be with David at Pas-dam′mim, where the Phi·lis′tines had gathered themselves together for war. Now there happened to be a tract of the field full of barley, and the people, for their part, had fled because of the Phi·lis′tines. 14 But he took his stand in the middle of the tract and delivered it, and kept striking down the Phi·lis′tines, so that Jehovah saved with a great salvation.

15 And three of the thirty head ones proceeded to go down to the rock, to David at the cave of A·dul′lam, while a camp of the Phi·lis′tines was camping in the low plain of Reph′a·im. 16 And David was then in the place hard to approach; and a garrison of the Phi·lis′tines was then in Beth′le·hem. 17 After a while David showed his craving and said: “O that I might have a drink of the water from the cistern of Beth′le·hem, which is at the gate!” 18 At that the three forced their way into the camp of the Phi·lis′tines and drew water from the cistern of Beth′le·hem, which is at the gate, and came carrying and bringing it to David. And David did not consent to drink it, but poured it out to Jehovah. 19 And he went on to say: “It is unthinkable on my part, as regards my God, to do this! Is it the blood of these men that I should drink at the risk of their souls? For it was at the risk of their souls that they brought it.” And he did not consent to drink it. These are the things that the three mighty men did.

20 As for A·bish′ai the brother of Jo′ab, he himself became head of the three; and he was brandishing his spear over three hundred slain, and he had a reputation like the three. 21 Of the three he was more distinguished than the two others, and he came to be a chief to them; and yet he did not come up to the first three.

22 As for Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da, the son of a valiant man, who did many deeds in Kab′ze·el, he himself struck down the two sons of Ar′i·el of Mo′ab; and he himself descended and struck down a lion inside a waterpit in the day of snowfall. 23 And he it was that struck down the Egyptian man, a man of extraordinary size, of five cubits. And in the hand of the Egyptian there was a spear like the beam of loom workers; yet he went on down to him with a rod and snatched the spear away from the Egyptian’s hand and killed him with his own spear. 24 These things Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da did, and he had a name among the three mighty men. 25 Although he was more distinguished than the thirty, yet to the rank of the first three he did not come. However, David put him over his own bodyguard.

26 As for the mighty men of the military forces, there were As′a·hel the brother of Jo′ab, El·ha′nan the son of Do′do of Beth′le·hem, 27 Sham′moth the Ha′ro·rite, He′lez the Pel′o·nite, 28 I′ra the son of Ik′kesh the Te·ko′ite, Abi-e′zer the An′a·thoth·ite, 29 Sib′be·cai the Hu′shath·ite, I′lai the A·ho′hite, 30 Ma′ha·rai the Ne·toph′a·thite, He′led the son of Ba′a·nah the Ne·toph′a·thite, 31 I′thai the son of Ri′bai of Gib′e·ah of the sons of Benjamin, Be·nai′ah the Pir′a·thon·ite, 32 Hu′rai from the torrent valleys of Ga′ash, A·bi′el the Ar′bath·ite, 33 Az′ma·veth the Ba·ha′rum·ite, E·li′ah·ba the Sha·al′bo·nite, 34 the sons of Ha′shem the Gi′zo·nite, Jon′a·than the son of Sha′gee the Har′a·rite, 35 A·hi′am the son of Sa′car the Har′a·rite, E·li′phal the son of Ur, 36 He′pher the Me·che′rath·ite, A·hi′jah the Pel′o·nite, 37 Hez′ro the Car′mel·ite, Na′a·rai the son of Ez′bai, 38 Joel the brother of Nathan, Mib′har the son of Hag′ri, 39 Ze′lek the Am′mon·ite, Na′ha·rai the Be·roth′ite, the armor-bearer of Jo′ab the son of Ze·ru′iah, 40 I′ra the Ith′rite, Ga′reb the Ith′rite, 41 U·ri′ah the Hit′tite, Za′bad the son of Ah′lai, 42 Ad′i·na the son of Shi′za the Reu′ben·ite, a head of the Reu′ben·ites, by whom there were thirty; 43 Ha′nan the son of Ma′a·cah, and Josh′a·phat the Mith′nite, 44 Uz·zi′a the Ash′te·rath·ite, Sha′ma and Je·i′el, the sons of Ho′tham the A·ro′er·ite, 45 Je·di′a·el the son of Shim′ri, and Jo′ha his brother the Ti′zite, 46 E′li·el the Ma′ha·vite, and Jer′i·bai and Josh·a·vi′ah the sons of El′na·am, and Ith′mah the Mo′ab·ite. 47 E′li·el and O′bed and Ja·a·si′el the Me·zo′ba·ite.

1 Chronicles

18 And it came about afterward that David proceeded to strike down the Phi·lis′tines and subdue them and take Gath and its dependent towns out of the hand of the Phi·lis′tines. 2 Then he struck Mo′ab down, and the Mo′ab·ites came to be David’s servants bearing tribute.

3 And David went on to strike down Had·ad·e′zer the king of Zo′bah at Ha′math as he was going his way to set up his control at the river Eu·phra′tes. 4 Further, David captured from him a thousand chariots and seven thousand horsemen and twenty thousand men on foot. Then David hamstrung all the chariot horses, but he let a hundred chariot horses of them remain. 5 When Syria of Damascus came to help Had·ad·e′zer the king of Zo′bah, David went striking down among the Syrians twenty-two thousand men. 6 After that David put garrisons in Syria of Damascus, and the Syrians came to be David’s servants bearing tribute. And Jehovah kept giving salvation to David wherever he went. 7 Moreover, David took the circular shields of gold that happened to be on the servants of Had·ad·e′zer and brought them to Jerusalem. 8 And from Tib′hath and Cun, cities of Had·ad·e′zer, David took very much copper. With it Sol′o·mon made the copper sea and the pillars and the copper utensils.

9 When To′u the king of Ha′math heard that David had struck down all the military force of Had·ad·e′zer the king of Zo′bah, 10 he immediately sent Ha·do′ram his son to King David to ask him about his welfare and congratulate him over the fact that he had fought against Had·ad·e′zer so that he struck him down, (for Had·ad·e′zer had become trained in warfare against To′u,) and there were with him all sorts of articles of gold and silver and copper. 11 These also King David sanctified to Jehovah together with the silver and the gold that he had carried off from all the nations, from E′dom and from Mo′ab and from the sons of Am′mon and from the Phi·lis′tines and from Am′a·lek.

12 As for A·bish′ai the son of Ze·ru′iah, he struck down the E′dom·ites in the Valley of Salt, eighteen thousand. 13 So he put garrisons in E′dom, and all the E′dom·ites came to be David’s servants. And Jehovah kept saving David wherever he went. 14 And David continued to reign over all Israel, and he was continually rendering judicial decision and righteousness for all his people. 15 And Jo′ab the son of Ze·ru′iah was over the army, and Je·hosh′a·phat the son of A·hi′lud was recorder. 16 And Za′dok the son of A·hi′tub and A·him′e·lech the son of A·bi′a·thar were priests, and Shav′sha was secretary. 17 And Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da was over the Cher′e·thites and the Pel′e·thites; and the sons of David were the first in position at the side of the king.

1 Chronicles

20 And it came about at the time of the year’s return, at the time that kings sally forth, that Jo′ab proceeded to lead the combat force of the army and lay the land of the sons of Am′mon in ruin and to come and besiege Rab′bah, while David was dwelling in Jerusalem; and Jo′ab went on to strike Rab′bah and throw it down. 2 But David took the crown of Mal′cam off its head, and found it to be a talent of gold in weight, and in it there were precious stones; and it came to be on David’s head. And the spoil of the city that he brought out was very much. 3 And the people that were in it he brought out, and he kept them employed at sawing stones and at sharp instruments of iron and at axes; and that was the way David proceeded to do to all the cities of the sons of Am′mon. Finally David and all the people returned to Jerusalem.

4 And it came about after this that war began breaking out at Ge′zer with the Phi·lis′tines. It was then that Sib′be·cai the Hu′shath·ite struck down Sip′pai of those born of the Reph′a·im, so that they were subdued.

5 And there came to be war again with the Phi·lis′tines; and El·ha′nan the son of Ja′ir got to strike down Lah′mi the brother of Go·li′ath the Git′tite, the shaft of whose spear was like the beam of loom workers.

6 And there came to be war again at Gath, when there happened to be a man of extraordinary size whose fingers and toes were in sixes, twenty-four; and he, too, had been born to the Reph′a·im. 7 And he kept taunting Israel. Finally Jon′a·than the son of Shim′e·a the brother of David struck him down.

8 These were the ones that had been born to the Reph′a·im in Gath; and they came to fall by the hand of David and by the hand of his servants.

1 Chronicles

21 And Satan proceeded to stand up against Israel and to incite David to number Israel. 2 So David said to Jo′ab and the chiefs of the people: “Go, count Israel from Be′er-she′ba to Dan and bring it to me that I may know their number.” 3 But Jo′ab said: “May Jehovah add to his people a hundred times as many as they are. Do they not, O my lord the king, all of them belong to my lord as servants? Why does my lord seek this? Why should he become a cause of guilt to Israel?”

4 The king’s word, however, prevailed over Jo′ab, so that Jo′ab went out and walked through all Israel, after which he came to Jerusalem. 5 Jo′ab now gave the number of the registration of the people to David; and all Israel amounted to a million one hundred thousand men drawing sword, and Judah four hundred and seventy thousand men drawing sword. 6 And Le′vi and Benjamin he did not register in among them, because the king’s word had been detestable to Jo′ab.

7 Now this thing was bad in the eyes of the true God, and so he struck down Israel. 8 Consequently David said to the true God: “I have sinned very much in that I have done this thing. And now, please, cause your servant’s error to pass away; for I have acted very foolishly.” 9 And Jehovah proceeded to speak to Gad, David’s visionary, saying: 10 “Go, and you must speak to David, saying, ‘This is what Jehovah has said: “There are three things that I am directing against you. Choose for yourself one of them, that I may do it to you.”’” 11 Accordingly Gad went in to David and said to him: “This is what Jehovah has said, ‘Take your pick, 12 whether for three years there is to be a famine; or for three months there is to be a sweeping away from before your adversaries and for the sword of your enemies to overtake you, or for three days there is to be the sword of Jehovah, even pestilence, in the land, with Jehovah’s angel bringing ruin in all the territory of Israel.’ And now see what I should reply to the One sending me.” 13 So David said to Gad: “It is very distressing to me. Please, let me fall into the hand of Jehovah, for very many are his mercies; but into the hand of man do not let me fall.”

14 Then Jehovah gave a pestilence in Israel, so that out of Israel seventy thousand persons fell. 15 Moreover, the true God sent an angel to Jerusalem to bring ruin to it; and as soon as he began bringing the ruin, Jehovah saw it and began to feel regret over the calamity; and so he said to the angel that was bringing the ruin: “It is enough! Now let your hand drop.” And Jehovah’s angel was standing close by the threshing floor of Or′nan the Jeb′u·site.

16 When David raised his eyes, he got to see Jehovah’s angel standing between the earth and the heavens with his drawn sword in his hand extended toward Jerusalem; and David and the older men, covered with sackcloth, at once fell down upon their faces. 17 And David proceeded to say to the true God: “Was it not I that said to make a numbering of the people, and is it not I that have sinned and have unquestionably done bad? As for these sheep, what have they done? O Jehovah my God, let your hand, please, come to be upon me and my father’s house; but not upon your people, for a scourge.”

18 And Jehovah’s angel, for his part, said to Gad to say to David that David should go up to erect an altar to Jehovah on the threshing floor of Or′nan the Jeb′u·site. 19 Accordingly David went up at the word of Gad that he had spoken in the name of Jehovah. 20 Meantime, Or′nan turned back and saw the angel; and his four sons with him were hiding themselves. Now Or′nan had been threshing wheat. 21 So David came as far as Or′nan. When Or′nan looked and saw David, he immediately went out of the threshing floor and bowed down to David with his face to the earth. 22 Then David said to Or′nan: “Do give me the place of the threshing floor, that I may build in it an altar to Jehovah. For the money in full give it to me, that the scourge may be halted from upon the people.” 23 But Or′nan said to David: “Take it as your own, and let my lord the king do what is good in his own eyes. See, I do give the cattle for burnt offerings and the threshing sledge for the wood and the wheat as a grain offering. The whole I do give.”

24 However, King David said to Or′nan: “No, but without fail I shall make the purchase for the money in full, because I shall not carry what is yours to Jehovah to offer up burnt sacrifices without cost.” 25 So David gave Or′nan for the place gold shekels to the weight of six hundred. 26 Then David built there an altar to Jehovah and offered up burnt sacrifices and communion sacrifices, and he proceeded to call upon Jehovah, who now answered him with fire from the heavens upon the altar of burnt offering. 27 Moreover, Jehovah said the word to the angel, who accordingly returned his sword to its sheath. 28 At that time, when David saw that Jehovah had answered him at the threshing floor of Or′nan the Jeb′u·site, he continued to sacrifice there. 29 But the tabernacle of Jehovah that Moses had made in the wilderness and the altar of burnt offering were at that time on the high place at Gib′e·on. 30 And David had not been able to go before it to consult God, for he had been terrified because of the sword of Jehovah’s angel.

1 Chronicles

22 Then David said: “This is the house of Jehovah the true God, and this is an altar for burnt offering for Israel.”

2 David now said to bring together the alien residents that were in the land of Israel, and then he set them as stone hewers to hew squared stones for building the house of the true God. 3 And iron in great quantity for nails for the doors of the gates and for clamps David prepared, and also copper in such quantity as to be beyond weighing, 4 and also cedar timbers without number; for the Si·do′ni·ans and the Tyr′i·ans brought in cedar timbers in great quantity to David. 5 Accordingly David said: “Sol′o·mon my son is young and delicate, and the house to be built to Jehovah is to be surpassingly magnificent for beauteous distinction to all the lands. Let me, then, make preparation for him.” So David made preparation in great quantities before his death.

6 Moreover, he called Sol′o·mon his son that he might command him to build a house to Jehovah the God of Israel. 7 And David went on to say to Sol′o·mon his son: “As for myself, it became close to my heart to build a house to the name of Jehovah my God. 8 But Jehovah’s word came against me, saying, ‘Blood in great quantity you have spilled, and great wars you have waged. You will not build a house to my name, for a great deal of blood you have spilled on the earth before me. 9 Look! There is a son being born to you. He himself will prove to be a restful man, and I shall certainly give him rest from all his enemies all around; for Sol′o·mon is what his name will become, and peace and quietness I shall bestow upon Israel in his days. 10 It is he that will build a house to my name, and he himself will become a son to me, and I a father to him. And I shall certainly establish the throne of his kingship firmly over Israel to time indefinite.’

11 “Now, my son, may Jehovah prove to be with you, and you must prove successful and build the house of Jehovah your God, just as he has spoken concerning you. 12 Only may Jehovah give you discretion and understanding, and may he give you commandment concerning Israel even to keep the law of Jehovah your God. 13 In that case you will prove successful if you take care to carry out the regulations and the judicial decisions that Jehovah commanded Moses respecting Israel. Be courageous and strong. Do not be afraid nor be terrified. 14 And here during my affliction I have prepared for Jehovah’s house a hundred thousand talents of gold and a million talents of silver, and the copper and the iron there is no means of weighing because they have come to be in such quantity; and timbers and stones I have prepared, but to them you will make additions. 15 And with you there are in great number doers of work, stone hewers and workers in stone and wood and every one skillful in every sort of work. 16 The gold, the silver and the copper and the iron there is no means of numbering. Rise and act, and may Jehovah prove to be with you.”

17 And David went on to command all the princes of Israel to help Sol′o·mon his son: 18 “Is not Jehovah YOUR God with YOU, and has he not given YOU rest all around? For he has given into my hand the inhabitants of the land, and the land has been subdued before Jehovah and before his people. 19 Now set YOUR heart and YOUR soul to inquire after Jehovah YOUR God, and rise and build the sanctuary of Jehovah the true God, to bring the ark of the covenant of Jehovah and the holy utensils of the true God to the house built to the name of Jehovah.”

1 Chronicles

23 And David himself had grown old and satisfied with days, and so he made Sol′o·mon his son king over Israel. 2 And he proceeded to gather all the princes of Israel and the priests and the Levites. 3 Accordingly the Levites were numbered from the age of thirty years upward; and their number, head by head of them, able-bodied man by able-bodied man, came to be thirty-eight thousand. 4 Of these for acting as supervisors over the work of the house of Jehovah there were twenty-four thousand; and as officers and judges six thousand; 5 and four thousand gatekeepers and four thousand givers of praise to Jehovah on the instruments that David said “I have made for giving praise.”

6 Then David distributed them in divisions to the sons of Le′vi, to Ger′shon, Ko′hath and Me·rar′i. 7 To the Ger′shon·ites, La′dan and Shim′e·i. 8 The sons of La′dan were Je·hi′el the headman and Ze′tham and Joel, three. 9 The sons of Shim′e·i were She·lo′moth and Ha′zi·el and Ha′ran, three. These were the heads of the fathers for La′dan. 10 And the sons of Shim′e·i were Ja′hath, Zi′na and Je′ush and Be·ri′ah. These four were the sons of Shim′e·i. 11 And Ja′hath came to be the head, and Zi′zah the second. As for Je′ush and Be·ri′ah, they did not have many sons; so they became a paternal house for one official class.

12 The sons of Ko′hath were Am′ram, Iz′har, He′bron and Uz′zi·el, four. 13 The sons of Am′ram were Aaron and Moses. But Aaron was separated that he might sanctify the Most Holy, he and his sons to time indefinite, to make sacrificial smoke before Jehovah, to minister to him and to pronounce blessing in his name to time indefinite. 14 As for Moses the man of the true God, his sons themselves continued to be called among the tribe of the Levites. 15 The sons of Moses were Ger′shom and E·li·e′zer. 16 The sons of Ger′shom were Sheb′u·el the head. 17 And the sons of E·li·e′zer came to be Re·ha·bi′ah the head; and E·li·e′zer did not come to have other sons, but the sons of Re·ha·bi′ah did themselves become exceedingly many. 18 The sons of Iz′har were She·lo′mith the headman. 19 The sons of He′bron were Je·ri′ah the head, Am·a·ri′ah the second, Ja·ha·zi′el the third and Jek·a·me′am the fourth. 20 The sons of Uz′zi·el were Mi′cah the head and Is·shi′ah the second.

21 The sons of Me·rar′i were Mah′li and Mu′shi. The sons of Mah′li were El·e·a′zar and Kish. 22 But El·e·a′zar died; and he had come to have, not sons, but daughters. So the sons of Kish their brothers took them as wives. 23 The sons of Mu′shi were Mah′li and E′der and Jer′e·moth, three.

24 These were the sons of Le′vi by the house of their fathers, the heads of the fathers, by their commissioned ones, in the number of the names, head by head of them, the doers of the work for the service of the house of Jehovah, from the age of twenty years upward. 25 For David had said: “Jehovah the God of Israel has given rest to his people, and he will reside in Jerusalem to time indefinite. 26 And also the Levites will not have to carry the tabernacle or any of its utensils for its service.” 27 For by the last words of David these were the number of the sons of Le′vi from the age of twenty years upward. 28 For their function was at the disposition of the sons of Aaron for the service of the house of Jehovah over the courtyards and over the dining rooms and over the purification of every holy thing and the work of the service of the house of the true God, 29 even for the layer bread and for the fine flour for the grain offering and for the wafers of unfermented bread and for the griddle cakes and for the mixed dough and for all measures of quantity and size; 30 and for standing morning by morning to thank and praise Jehovah, and likewise at evening; 31 and for every offering up of the burnt sacrifices to Jehovah at the sabbaths, at the new moons and at the festival seasons, by number according to the rule concerning them, constantly before Jehovah. 32 And they took care of the guarding of the tent of meeting and the guarding of the holy place and the guarding of the sons of Aaron their brothers for the service of the house of Jehovah.

1 Chronicles

25 Further, David and the chiefs of the service groups separated for the service some of the sons of A′saph, He′man and Je·du′thun the ones prophesying with the harps, with the stringed instruments and with the cymbals. And from their number the official men for their service came to be. 2 Of the sons of A′saph, Zac′cur and Joseph and Neth·a·ni′ah and Ash·a·re′lah, the sons of A′saph under the control of A′saph the one prophesying under the control of the king. 3 Of Je·du′thun: the sons of Je·du′thun, Ged·a·li′ah and Ze′ri and Je·sha′iah, and Shim′e·i, Hash·a·bi′ah and Mat·ti·thi′ah, six, under the control of their father Je·du′thun, who was prophesying with the harp for thanking and praising Jehovah. 4 Of He′man: the sons of He′man, Buk·ki′ah, Mat·ta·ni′ah, Uz′zi·el, Sheb′u·el and Jer′i·moth, Han·a·ni′ah, Ha·na′ni, E·li′a·thah, Gid·dal′ti and Ro·mam′ti-e′zer, Josh·be·kash′ah, Mal·lo′thi, Ho′thir, Ma·ha′zi·oth. 5 All these were sons of He′man, a visionary of the king in the things of the true God to raise up his horn; thus the true God proceeded to give He′man fourteen sons and three daughters. 6 All these were under the control of their father in song at the house of Jehovah, with cymbals, stringed instruments and harps for the service of the house of the true God.

Under the control of the king were A′saph and Je·du′thun and He′man.

7 And the number of them together with their brothers trained in song to Jehovah, all experts, came to be two hundred and eighty-eight. 8 So they cast lots as to the things to be taken care of, the little being just the same as the great, the expert along with the learner.

9 And the lot proceeded to come out: the first belonging to A′saph for Joseph, for Ged·a·li′ah the second (he and his brothers and his sons were twelve); 10 the third for Zac′cur, his sons and his brothers, twelve; 11 the fourth for Iz′ri, his sons and his brothers, twelve; 12 the fifth for Neth·a·ni′ah, his sons and his brothers, twelve; 13 the sixth for Buk·ki′ah, his sons and his brothers, twelve; 14 the seventh for Jesh·a·re′lah, his sons and his brothers, twelve; 15 the eighth for Je·sha′iah, his sons and his brothers, twelve; 16 the ninth for Mat·ta·ni′ah, his sons and his brothers, twelve; 17 the tenth for Shim′e·i, his sons and his brothers, twelve; 18 the eleventh for Az′ar·el, his sons and his brothers, twelve; 19 the twelfth for Hash·a·bi′ah, his sons and his brothers, twelve; 20 for the thirteenth, Shu′ba·el, his sons and his brothers, twelve; 21 for the fourteenth, Mat·ti·thi′ah, his sons and his brothers, twelve; 22 for the fifteenth, for Jer′e·moth, his sons and his brothers, twelve; 23 for the sixteenth, for Han·a·ni′ah, his sons and his brothers, twelve; 24 for the seventeenth, for Josh·be·kash′ah, his sons and his brothers, twelve; 25 for the eighteenth, for Ha·na′ni, his sons and his brothers, twelve; 26 for the nineteenth, for Mal·lo′thi, his sons and his brothers, twelve; 27 for the twentieth, for E·li′a·thah, his sons and his brothers, twelve; 28 for the twenty-first, for Ho′thir, his sons and his brothers, twelve; 29 for the twenty-second, for Gid·dal′ti, his sons and his brothers, twelve; 30 for the twenty-third, for Ma·ha′zi·oth, his sons and his brothers, twelve; 31 for the twenty-fourth, for Ro·mam′ti-e′zer, his sons and his brothers, twelve.

2 Chronicles

7 Now as soon as Sol′o·mon finished praying, the fire itself came down from the heavens and proceeded to consume the burnt offering and the sacrifices, and Jehovah’s glory itself filled the house. 2 And the priests were unable to enter into the house of Jehovah because Jehovah’s glory had filled the house of Jehovah. 3 And all the sons of Israel were spectators when the fire came down and the glory of Jehovah was upon the house, and they immediately bowed low with their faces to the earth upon the pavement and prostrated themselves and thanked Jehovah, “for he is good, for his loving-kindness is to time indefinite.”

4 And the king and all the people were offering sacrifice before Jehovah. 5 And King Sol′o·mon went on offering the sacrifice of twenty-two thousand cattle and a hundred and twenty thousand sheep. Thus the king and all the people inaugurated the house of the true God. 6 And the priests were standing at their posts of duty, and the Levites with the instruments of song to Jehovah that David the king had made to thank Jehovah, “for his loving-kindness is to time indefinite,” when David would render praise by their hand; and the priests were loudly sounding the trumpets in front of them, while all the Israelites were standing.

7 Then Sol′o·mon sanctified the middle of the courtyard that was before the house of Jehovah, because there he rendered up the burnt offerings and the fat pieces of the communion sacrifices, for the copper altar that Sol′o·mon had made was itself not able to contain the burnt offering and the grain offering and the fat pieces. 8 And Sol′o·mon proceeded to hold the festival at that time for seven days, and all Israel with him, a very great congregation from the entering in of Ha′math down to the torrent valley of Egypt. 9 But on the eighth day they held a solemn assembly, because the inauguration of the altar they had held for seven days and the festival for seven days. 10 And on the twenty-third day of the seventh month he sent the people away to their homes, joyful and feeling good at heart over the goodness that Jehovah had performed toward David and toward Sol′o·mon and toward Israel his people.

11 Thus Sol′o·mon finished the house of Jehovah and the house of the king; and in everything that had come into Sol′o·mon’s heart to do regarding the house of Jehovah and his own house he proved successful. 12 Jehovah now appeared to Sol′o·mon during the night and said to him: “I have heard your prayer, and I have chosen this place for myself as a house of sacrifice. 13 When I shut up the heavens that no rain may occur and when I command the grasshoppers to eat up the land and if I send a pestilence among my people, 14 and my people upon whom my name has been called humble themselves and pray and seek my face and turn back from their bad ways, then I myself shall hear from the heavens and forgive their sin, and I shall heal their land. 15 Now my own eyes will prove to be opened and my ears attentive to prayer at this place. 16 And now I do choose and sanctify this house that my name may prove to be there to time indefinite, and my eyes and my heart will certainly prove to be there always.

17 “And if you yourself will walk before me, just as David your father walked, even by doing according to all that I have commanded you, and you will keep my regulations and my judicial decisions, 18 I will also establish the throne of your kingship, just as I covenanted with David your father, saying, ‘There will not a man of yours be cut off from ruling over Israel.’ 19 But if YOU yourselves turn back and actually leave my statutes and my commandments that I have put before YOU, and YOU actually go and serve other gods and bow down to them, 20 I will also uproot them from off my ground that I have given them; and this house that I have sanctified for my name, I shall throw away from before my face, and I shall make it a proverbial saying and a taunt among all the peoples. 21 As for this house that had become heaps of ruins, everyone passing by it will stare in amazement and be certain to say, ‘For what reason did Jehovah do like that to this land and to this house?’ 22 And they will have to say, ‘It was for the reason that they left Jehovah the God of their forefathers who had brought them out of the land of Egypt, and they proceeded to take hold of other gods and bow down to them and serve them. That is why he brought upon them all this calamity.’”

2 Chronicles

9 And the queen of She′ba herself heard the report about Sol′o·mon, and she proceeded to come to test Sol′o·mon with perplexing questions at Jerusalem, along with a very impressive train and camels carrying balsam oil, and gold in great quantity, and precious stones. At length she came in to Sol′o·mon and spoke with him about everything that happened to be close to her heart. 2 Sol′o·mon, in turn, went on to tell her all her matters, and no matter was hidden from Sol′o·mon that he did not tell her.

3 When the queen of She′ba got to see Sol′o·mon’s wisdom and the house that he had built, 4 and the food of his table and the sitting of his servants and the table service of his waiters and their attire and his drinking service and their attire, and his burnt sacrifices that he regularly offered up at the house of Jehovah, then there proved to be no more spirit in her. 5 So she said to the king: “True was the word that I heard in my own land about your matters and about your wisdom. 6 And I did not put faith in their words until I had come that my own eyes might see; and, look! there has not been told me the half of the abundance of your wisdom. You have surpassed the report that I have heard. 7 Happy are your men, and happy are these servants of yours who are standing before you constantly and listening to your wisdom. 8 May Jehovah your God come to be blessed, who has taken delight in you by putting you upon his throne as king for Jehovah your God; because your God loved Israel, to make it stand to time indefinite, so that he put you over them as king to execute judicial decision and righteousness.”

9 Then she gave the king a hundred and twenty talents of gold, and balsam oil in very great quantity, and precious stones; and there had not come to be the like of that balsam oil which the queen of She′ba gave to King Sol′o·mon.

10 And, besides, the servants of Hi′ram and the servants of Sol′o·mon who brought gold from O′phir brought timbers of algum trees and precious stones. 11 And the king proceeded to make out of the timbers of the algum trees stairs for the house of Jehovah and for the king’s house and also harps and stringed instruments for the singers, and the like of them had never been seen before in the land of Judah.

12 And King Sol′o·mon himself gave the queen of She′ba all her delight for which she had asked, besides the value of what she brought to the king. So she turned about and went to her own land, she together with her servants.

13 And the weight of the gold that came to Sol′o·mon in one year amounted to six hundred and sixty-six talents of gold, 14 aside from the men of travel and the merchants who were bringing in and all the kings of the Arabs and the governors of the land who were bringing in gold and silver to Sol′o·mon.

15 And King Sol′o·mon went on to make two hundred large shields of alloyed gold (six hundred shekels of alloyed gold he proceeded to lay upon each large shield), 16 and three hundred bucklers of alloyed gold (three mi′nas of gold he proceeded to lay upon each buckler). Then the king put them in the House of the Forest of Leb′a·non.

17 Further, the king made a great ivory throne and overlaid it with pure gold. 18 And there were six steps to the throne, and there was a footstool in gold to the throne (they were attached), and there were armrests on this side and on that side by the place of sitting, and two lions were standing beside the armrests. 19 And there were twelve lions standing there upon the six steps on this side and on that side. No other kingdom had any made just like it. 20 And all the drinking vessels of King Sol′o·mon were of gold, and all the vessels of the House of the Forest of Leb′a·non were of pure gold. There was nothing of silver; it was considered as nothing at all in the days of Sol′o·mon. 21 For ships belonging to the king were going to Tar′shish with the servants of Hi′ram. Once every three years ships of Tar′shish would come in, carrying gold and silver, ivory, and apes and peacocks.

22 So King Sol′o·mon was greater than all the other kings of the earth in riches and wisdom. 23 And all the kings of the earth were seeking the face of Sol′o·mon to hear his wisdom, which the true God had put in his heart. 24 And they were bringing each his gift, articles of silver and articles of gold and garments, armor and balsam oil, horses and mules as a yearly matter of course. 25 And Sol′o·mon came to have four thousand stalls of horses and chariots and twelve thousand steeds, and he kept them stationed in the chariot cities and close by the king in Jerusalem. 26 And he came to be ruler over all the kings from the River down to the land of the Phi·lis′tines and down to the boundary of Egypt. 27 Furthermore, the king made the silver in Jerusalem like the stones; and cedarwood he made like the sycamore trees that are in the She·phe′lah for abundance. 28 And there were those bringing out horses to Sol′o·mon from Egypt and from all the other lands.

29 As for the rest of the affairs of Sol′o·mon, the first and the last, are they not written among the words of Nathan the prophet and in the prophecy of A·hi′jah the Shi′lo·nite and in the record of visions of Id′do the visionary concerning Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat? 30 And Sol′o·mon continued to reign in Jerusalem over all Israel for forty years. 31 Finally Sol′o·mon lay down with his forefathers. So they buried him in the City of David his father; and Re·ho·bo′am his son began to reign in place of him.

2 Chronicles

10 And Re·ho·bo′am proceeded to go to She′chem, for it was to She′chem that all the Israelites came to make him king. 2 And it came about that as soon as Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat heard of it while he was yet in Egypt, (because he had run away on account of Sol′o·mon the king,) Jer·o·bo′am immediately came back from Egypt. 3 So they sent and called him, and Jer·o·bo′am and all Israel came and spoke to Re·ho·bo′am, saying: 4 “Your father, for his part, made our yoke hard; and now make the hard service of your father and the heavy yoke that he put upon us lighter, and we shall serve you.”

5 At this he said to them: “Let there be yet three days. Then return to me.” So the people went away. 6 And King Re·ho·bo′am began to take counsel with the older men that were continually attending upon Sol′o·mon his father while he continued alive, saying: “How are YOU advising to reply to this people?” 7 Accordingly they spoke to him, saying: “If you would prove yourself good to this people and actually be pleasing to them and indeed speak good words to them, they also will certainly become your servants always.”

8 However, he left the counsel of the older men with which they had advised him, and he began to take counsel with the young men that had grown up with him, who were the ones attending upon him. 9 And he went on to say to them: “What is it that YOU are offering in counsel that we may reply to this people who have spoken to me, saying, ‘Make the yoke that your father put upon us lighter’?” 10 In turn the young men that had grown up with him spoke with him, saying: “This is what you should say to the people who have spoken to you, saying, ‘Your father, for his part, made our yoke heavy, but, as for you, make it lighter upon us’; this is what you should say to them, ‘My own little finger will certainly be thicker than my father’s hips. 11 And now my father, for his part, loaded upon YOU a heavy yoke, but I, for my part, shall add to YOUR yoke. My father, for his part, chastised YOU with whips, but I, for my part, with scourges.’”

12 And Jer·o·bo′am and all the people proceeded to come to Re·ho·bo′am on the third day, just as the king had spoken, saying: “Return to me on the third day.” 13 And the king began to answer them harshly. Thus King Re·ho·bo′am left the counsel of the older men, 14 and he went on to speak to them according to the counsel of the young men, saying: “I shall make YOUR yoke heavier, and I, for my part, shall add to it. My father, for his part, chastised YOU with whips, but I, for my part, with scourges.” 15 And the king did not listen to the people; for it proved to be a turn of affairs from the true God in order that Jehovah might carry out his word that he had spoken by means of A·hi′jah the Shi′lo·nite to Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat.

16 As for all Israel, because the king did not listen to them, the people now replied to the king, saying: “What share do we have in David? And there is no inheritance in the son of Jes′se. Each one to your gods, O Israel! Now see to your own house, O David.” With that all Israel began to go to its tents.

17 As for the sons of Israel that were dwelling in the cities of Judah, Re·ho·bo′am continued to reign over them.

18 Subsequently King Re·ho·bo′am sent Ha·do′ram, who was over those conscripted for forced labor, but the sons of Israel pelted him with stones, so that he died. And King Re·ho·bo′am himself managed to get up into his chariot to flee to Jerusalem. 19 And the Israelites kept up their revolt against the house of David down to this day.

2 Chronicles

11 When Re·ho·bo′am arrived at Jerusalem, he immediately congregated the house of Judah and Benjamin, a hundred and eighty thousand choice men able-bodied for war, to fight against Israel so as to bring the kingdom back to Re·ho·bo′am. 2 Then the word of Jehovah came to She·mai′ah the man of the true God, saying: 3 “Say to Re·ho·bo′am the son of Sol′o·mon the king of Judah and to all Israel in Judah and Benjamin, saying, 4 ‘This is what Jehovah has said: “YOU must not go up and fight against YOUR brothers. Return each one to his house, for it is at my own instance that this thing has been brought about.”’” So they obeyed the word of Jehovah and returned from going against Jer·o·bo′am.

5 And Re·ho·bo′am continued to dwell in Jerusalem and proceeded to build fortified cities in Judah. 6 Thus he rebuilt Beth′le·hem and E′tam and Te·ko′a, 7 and Beth-zur and So′co and A·dul′lam, 8 and Gath and Ma·re′shah and Ziph, 9 and Ad·o·ra′im and La′chish and A·ze′kah, 10 and Zo′rah and Ai′ja·lon and He′bron, fortified cities, which were in Judah and Benjamin. 11 Further, he reinforced the fortified places and put leaders in them and supplies of food and oil and wine, 12 and in all the different cities large shields and lances; and he went on reinforcing them to a very great degree. And Judah and Benjamin continued his.

13 And the priests and the Levites themselves that were in all Israel took their stand by him out of all their territories. 14 For the Levites left their pasture grounds and their possession and then came to Judah and Jerusalem, because Jer·o·bo′am and his sons had discharged them from acting as priests to Jehovah. 15 And he proceeded to put in office for himself priests for the high places and for the goat-shaped demons and for the calves that he had made. 16 And following them from all the tribes of Israel those that were giving their heart to seek Jehovah the God of Israel came themselves to Jerusalem to sacrifice to Jehovah the God of their forefathers. 17 And they kept strengthening the kingship of Judah and confirming Re·ho·bo′am the son of Sol′o·mon for three years, for they walked in the way of David and Sol′o·mon for three years.

18 Then Re·ho·bo′am took as his wife Ma′ha·lath the daughter of Jer′i·moth the son of David, and of Ab′i·ha·il the daughter of E·li′ab the son of Jes′se. 19 In time she bore him sons, Je′ush and Shem·a·ri′ah and Za′ham. 20 And after her he took Ma′a·cah the granddaughter of Ab′sa·lom. In time she bore him A·bi′jah and At′tai and Zi′za and She·lo′mith. 21 And Re·ho·bo′am was more in love with Ma′a·cah the granddaughter of Ab′sa·lom than all his other wives and his concubines; for there were eighteen wives that he had taken, also sixty concubines, so that he became father to twenty-eight sons and sixty daughters. 22 Consequently Re·ho·bo′am put A·bi′jah the son of Ma′a·cah in office as head, as leader among his brothers, for he thought of making him king. 23 However, he acted understandingly and distributed some out of all his sons to all the lands of Judah and of Benjamin, to all the fortified cities, and gave them food in abundance and procured a multitude of wives for them.

2 Chronicles

16 In the thirty-sixth year of the reign of A′sa, Ba′a·sha the king of Israel came up against Judah and began to build Ra′mah, so as not to allow anyone to go out or come in to A′sa the king of Judah. 2 A′sa now brought out silver and gold from the treasures of Jehovah’s house and the king’s house and sent to Ben-ha′dad the king of Syria, who was dwelling at Damascus, saying: 3 “There is a covenant between me and you and between my father and your father. Here I do send you silver and gold. Go, break your covenant with Ba′a·sha the king of Israel, that he may withdraw from me.”

4 So Ben-ha′dad listened to King A′sa and sent the chiefs of the military forces that were his against the cities of Israel, so that they struck I′jon and Dan and A′bel-ma′im and all the storage places of the cities of Naph′ta·li. 5 And it came about that as soon as Ba′a·sha heard of it, he immediately quit building Ra′mah and stopped his work. 6 As for A′sa the king, he took all Judah, and they proceeded to carry away the stones of Ra′mah and its timbers with which Ba′a·sha had built, and he began to build with them Ge′ba and Miz′pah.

7 And at that time Ha·na′ni the seer came to A′sa the king of Judah and then said to him: “Because you leaned upon the king of Syria and did not lean upon Jehovah your God, for that reason the military force of the king of Syria has escaped out of your hand. 8 Did not the E·thi·o′pi·ans and the Lib′y·ans themselves happen to be a very great military force in multitude, in chariots and in horsemen; and because of your leaning upon Jehovah did he not give them into your hand? 9 For, as regards Jehovah, his eyes are roving about through all the earth to show his strength in behalf of those whose heart is complete toward him. You have acted foolishly respecting this, for from now on there will exist wars against you.”

10 However, A′sa became offended at the seer and put him in the house of the stocks, because he was in a rage at him over this. And A′sa began to crush some others of the people at that same time. 11 And, look! the affairs of A′sa, the first and the last, there they are written in the Book of the Kings of Judah and of Israel.

12 And A′sa in the thirty-ninth year of his reign developed an ailment in his feet until he was very sick; and even in his sickness he searched not for Jehovah but for the healers. 13 Finally A′sa lay down with his forefathers and died in the forty-first year of his reigning. 14 So they buried him in his grand burial place that he had excavated for himself in the City of David; and they laid him in the bed that had been filled with balsam oil and different sorts of ointment mixed in an ointment of special make. Further, they made an extraordinarily great funeral burning for him.

2 Chronicles

20 And it came about afterward that the sons of Mo′ab and the sons of Am′mon and with them some of the Am′mon·im came against Je·hosh′a·phat in war. 2 So people came and told Je·hosh′a·phat, saying: “There has come against you a large crowd from the region of the sea, from E′dom; and there they are in Haz′a·zon-ta′mar, that is to say, En-ge′di.” 3 At that Je·hosh′a·phat became afraid and set his face to search for Jehovah. So he proclaimed a fast for all Judah. 4 Eventually those of Judah were collected together to inquire of Jehovah. Even from all the cities of Judah they came to consult Jehovah.

5 Then Je·hosh′a·phat stood up in the congregation of Judah and of Jerusalem in the house of Jehovah before the new courtyard, 6 and he proceeded to say:

“O Jehovah the God of our forefathers, are you not God in the heavens, and are you not dominating over all the kingdoms of the nations, and are there not in your hand power and mightiness, with no one to hold his ground against you? 7 Did not you yourself, O God of ours, drive away the inhabitants of this land from before your people Israel and then give it to the seed of Abraham, your lover, to time indefinite? 8 And they took up dwelling in it, and they proceeded to build in it for you a sanctuary for your name, saying, 9 ‘If there should come upon us calamity, sword, adverse judgment, or pestilence or famine, let us stand before this house and before you (for your name is in this house), that we may call to you for aid out of our distress, and may you hear and save.’ 10 And now here the sons of Am′mon, and Mo′ab and the mountainous region of Se′ir, whom you did not allow Israel to invade when they were coming out of the land of Egypt, but they turned away from them and did not annihilate them, 11 yes, here they are rewarding us by coming in to drive us out from your possession that you caused us to possess. 12 O our God, will you not execute judgment upon them? For in us there is no power before this large crowd that is coming against us; and we ourselves do not know what we ought to do, but our eyes are toward you.”

13 All the while all those of Judah were standing before Jehovah, even their little ones, their wives and their sons.

14 Now as for Ja·ha·zi′el the son of Zech·a·ri′ah the son of Be·nai′ah the son of Je·i′el the son of Mat·ta·ni′ah the Levite of the sons of A′saph, the spirit of Jehovah came to be upon him in the middle of the congregation. 15 Consequently he said: “Pay attention, all Judah and YOU inhabitants of Jerusalem and King Je·hosh′a·phat! Here is what Jehovah has said to YOU, ‘Do not YOU be afraid or be terrified because of this large crowd; for the battle is not YOURS, but God’s. 16 Tomorrow go down against them. There they are coming up by the pass of Ziz; and YOU will be certain to find them at the end of the torrent valley in front of the wilderness of Je·ru′el. 17 YOU will not need to fight in this instance. Take YOUR position, stand still and see the salvation of Jehovah in YOUR behalf. O Judah and Jerusalem, do not be afraid or be terrified. Tomorrow go out against them, and Jehovah will be with YOU.’”

18 At once Je·hosh′a·phat bowed low with his face to the earth, and all Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem themselves fell down before Jehovah to do obeisance to Jehovah. 19 Then the Levites of the sons of the Ko′hath·ites and of the sons of the Ko′rah·ites rose up to praise Jehovah the God of Israel with an extraordinarily loud voice.

20 And they proceeded to rise early in the morning and go out to the wilderness of Te·ko′a. And as they went out, Je·hosh′a·phat stood up and then said: “Hear me, O Judah and YOU inhabitants of Jerusalem! Put faith in Jehovah YOUR God that YOU may prove yourselves of long duration. Put faith in his prophets and so prove successful.”

21 Further, he took counsel with the people and stationed singers to Jehovah and those offering praise in holy adornment as they went out ahead of the armed men, and saying: “GIVE praise to Jehovah, for to time indefinite is his loving-kindness.”

22 And at the time that they started off with the joyful cry and praise, Jehovah set men in ambush against the sons of Am′mon, Mo′ab and the mountainous region of Se′ir who were coming into Judah, and they went smiting one another. 23 And the sons of Am′mon and Mo′ab proceeded to stand up against the inhabitants of the mountainous region of Se′ir to devote them to destruction and annihilate them; and as soon as they finished with the inhabitants of Se′ir, they helped each one to bring his own fellow to ruin.

24 But as for Judah, it came to the watchtower of the wilderness. When they turned their faces toward the crowd, why, there they were, their carcasses fallen to the earth without anyone escaping. 25 So Je·hosh′a·phat and his people came to plunder the spoil on them, and they got to find among them in abundance both goods and clothing and desirable articles; and they went stripping them off for themselves until they could carry no more. And it came to be three days that they were plundering the spoil, for it was abundant. 26 And on the fourth day they congregated together at the low plain of Ber′a·cah, for there they blessed Jehovah. That is why they called the name of that place Low Plain of Ber′a·cah—until today.

27 Then all the men of Judah and Jerusalem returned, with Je·hosh′a·phat at their head, to return to Jerusalem with rejoicing, for Jehovah had made them rejoice over their enemies. 28 So they came to Jerusalem with stringed instruments and with harps and with trumpets to the house of Jehovah. 29 And the dread of God came to be upon all the kingdoms of the lands when they heard that Jehovah had fought against the enemies of Israel. 30 Thus the royal realm of Je·hosh′a·phat had no disturbance, and his God continued to give him rest all around.

31 And Je·hosh′a·phat went on reigning over Judah. Thirty-five years old he was when he began to reign, and for twenty-five years he reigned in Jerusalem. And his mother’s name was A·zu′bah the daughter of Shil′hi. 32 And he kept walking in the way of his father A′sa, and he did not turn aside from it, by doing what was right in Jehovah’s eyes. 33 Only the high places themselves did not disappear; and the people themselves had not yet prepared their heart for the God of their forefathers.

34 As for the rest of the affairs of Je·hosh′a·phat, the first and the last, there they are written among the words of Je′hu the son of Ha·na′ni, which were inserted in the Book of the Kings of Israel. 35 And after this Je·hosh′a·phat the king of Judah had partnership with A·ha·zi′ah the king of Israel, who acted wickedly. 36 So he made him a partner with himself in making ships to go to Tar′shish and they made ships in E′zi·on-ge′ber. 37 However, E·li·e′zer the son of Dod·av′a·hu of Ma·re′sha spoke prophetically against Je·hosh′a·phat, saying: “Inasmuch as you have had partnership with A·ha·zi′ah, Jehovah will certainly break down your works.” Accordingly the ships were wrecked, and they did not retain strength to go to Tar′shish.

2 Chronicles

23 And in the seventh year Je·hoi′a·da showed himself courageous and proceeded to take the chiefs of hundreds, namely, Az·a·ri′ah the son of Je·ro′ham, and Ish′ma·el the son of Je·ho·ha′nan and Az·a·ri′ah the son of O′bed and Ma·a·sei′ah the son of A·dai′ah and E·li·sha′phat the son of Zich′ri, with him into the covenant. 2 Afterward they went around throughout Judah and collected together the Levites from all the cities of Judah and the heads of the paternal houses of Israel. So they came to Jerusalem. 3 Then all the congregation concluded a covenant with the king in the house of the true God, after which he said to them:

“Look! The son of the king himself will reign, just as Jehovah promised concerning the sons of David. 4 This is the thing that YOU will do: one third of YOU who are coming in on the sabbath, of the priests and of the Levites, will be for doorkeepers; 5 and one third will be at the house of the king; and one third will be at the Gate of the Foundation; and all the people will be in the courtyards of the house of Jehovah. 6 And do not let anyone enter the house of Jehovah but the priests and those of the Levites ministering. These are the ones that will enter, because they are a holy group, and all the people themselves will keep the obligation to Jehovah. 7 And the Levites must encircle the king all around, each one with his weapons in his hands; and as for anyone coming into the house, he should be put to death. And continue with the king when he comes in and when he goes out.”

8 And the Levites and all Judah proceeded to do according to all that Je·hoi′a·da the priest had commanded. So they took each one his men that were coming in on the sabbath together with those going out on the sabbath, for Je·hoi′a·da the priest had not set the divisions free from duty. 9 Further, Je·hoi′a·da the priest gave the chiefs of hundreds the spears and the shields and the circular shields that had belonged to King David, which were in the house of the true God. 10 And he went on to station all the people, even each one with his missile in his hand, from the right side of the house clear to the left side of the house, by the altar and by the house, all around near the king. 11 Then they brought the king’s son out and put upon him the diadem and the Testimony and made him king, and so Je·hoi′a·da and his sons anointed him and said: “Let the king live!”

12 When Ath·a·li′ah heard the sound of the people running and praising the king, she at once came to the people at the house of Jehovah. 13 Then she saw, and there was the king standing by his pillar at the entry, and the princes and the trumpets by the king, and all the people of the land were rejoicing and blowing the trumpets, and the singers with the instruments of song and those giving the signal for offering praise. Immediately Ath·a·li′ah ripped her garments apart and said: “Conspiracy! Conspiracy!” 14 But Je·hoi′a·da the priest brought out the chiefs of hundreds, the appointed ones of the military force, and said to them: “Take her out from inside the rows; and as for anyone coming after her, he should be put to death with the sword!” For the priest had said: “YOU must not put her to death at the house of Jehovah.” 15 So they laid their hands upon her. When she came to the entry of the horse gate of the king’s house, they at once put her to death there.

16 Then Je·hoi′a·da concluded a covenant between himself and all the people and the king that they would continue as the people of Jehovah. 17 After that all the people came to the house of Ba′al and pulled it down; and his altars and his images they broke up, and Mat′tan the priest of Ba′al they killed before the altars. 18 Further, Je·hoi′a·da put the offices of the house of Jehovah in the hand of the priests and the Levites, whom David had put in divisions over the house of Jehovah to offer up the burnt sacrifices of Jehovah according to what is written in the law of Moses, with rejoicing and with song by the hands of David. 19 So he stationed the gatekeepers by the gates of the house of Jehovah that no one unclean in any respect might enter. 20 He now took the chiefs of hundreds and the lordly ones and the rulers over the people and all the people of the land and brought the king down from the house of Jehovah. Then they came right through the upper gate to the king’s house and seated the king upon the throne of the kingdom. 21 And all the people of the land continued to rejoice; and the city itself had no disturbance, and Ath·a·li′ah they had put to death with the sword.

2 Chronicles

25 At the age of twenty-five years Am·a·zi′ah became king, and for twenty-nine years he reigned in Jerusalem. And his mother’s name was Je·ho·ad′dan of Jerusalem. 2 And he continued to do what was right in Jehovah’s eyes, only not with a complete heart. 3 And it came about that as soon as the kingdom had become strong upon him, he promptly killed his servants who had struck down the king his father. 4 And their sons he did not put to death, but did according to what is written in the law, in the book of Moses, that Jehovah commanded, saying: “Fathers should not die for sons, neither should sons themselves die for fathers; but it is each one for his own sin that they should die.”

5 And Am·a·zi′ah proceeded to collect Judah together and to have them stand according to the house of the forefathers, by the chiefs of thousands and by the chiefs of hundreds for all Judah and Benjamin; and he went on to register them from twenty years of age upward, and finally he found them to be three hundred thousand choice men going out to the army, handling lance and large shield. 6 Further, he hired from Israel a hundred thousand valiant, mighty men for a hundred silver talents. 7 And a certain man of the true God came to him, saying: “O king, do not let the army of Israel come with you, for Jehovah is not with Israel, that is, all the sons of E′phra·im. 8 But come you yourself, act, be courageous for the war. The true God could cause you to stumble before an enemy; for there exists power with God to help and to cause stumbling.” 9 At this Am·a·zi′ah said to the man of the true God: “But what is there to do about the hundred talents that I have given to the troops of Israel?” To this the man of the true God said: “There exists with Jehovah the means to give you much more than this.” 10 Accordingly Am·a·zi′ah separated them, namely, the troops that had come to him from E′phra·im, to go to their own place. However, their anger got very hot against Judah, so that they returned to their own place in the heat of anger.

11 And Am·a·zi′ah, for his part, took courage and proceeded to lead his own people and go to the Valley of Salt; and he went striking down the sons of Se′ir, ten thousand of them. 12 And there were ten thousand that the sons of Judah captured alive. So they brought them to the top of the crag, and proceeded to throw them from the top of the crag; and they, one and all, burst apart. 13 As for the members of the troop whom Am·a·zi′ah had sent back from going with him to the war, they began making raids upon the cities of Judah, from Sa·mar′i·a clear to Beth-ho′ron, and went striking down three thousand of them and taking a great plunder.

14 But it occurred after Am·a·zi′ah came from striking down the E′dom·ites that he now brought the gods of the sons of Se′ir and set them up for himself as gods, and before them he began to bow down, and to them he began to make sacrificial smoke. 15 Consequently Jehovah’s anger became hot against Am·a·zi′ah, and so he sent a prophet to him and said to him: “Why have you searched for the people’s gods that did not deliver their own people out of your hand?” 16 And it came about when he spoke to him that the king immediately said to him: “Was it a counselor of the king that we constituted you? Quit for your own sake. Why should they strike you down?” Accordingly the prophet quit, but he said: “I certainly know that God has resolved to bring you to ruin, because you have done this and you have not listened to my counsel.”

17 Then Am·a·zi′ah the king of Judah took counsel and sent to Je·ho′ash the son of Je·ho′a·haz the son of Je′hu the king of Israel, saying: “Come! Let us look each other in the face.” 18 At that Je·ho′ash the king of Israel sent to Am·a·zi′ah the king of Judah, saying: “The thorny weed itself that was in Leb′a·non sent to the cedar that was in Leb′a·non, saying, ‘Do give your daughter to my son as a wife.’ However, a wild beast of the field that was in Leb′a·non passed by and trampled the thorny weed down. 19 You have said to yourself, Here you have struck down E′dom. And your heart has lifted you up to be glorified. Now do keep dwelling in your own house. Why should you engage in strife in a bad position and have to fall, you and Judah with you?”

20 But Am·a·zi′ah did not listen; for it was from the true God for the purpose of giving them into his hand, because they had searched for the gods of E′dom. 21 So Je·ho′ash the king of Israel went up, and they proceeded to look each other in the face, he and Am·a·zi′ah the king of Judah, at Beth-she′mesh, which belongs to Judah. 22 And Judah came to be defeated before Israel, so that they took to flight each one to his tent. 23 And it was Am·a·zi′ah the king of Judah, the son of Je·ho′ash the son of Je·ho′a·haz, that Je·ho′ash the king of Israel seized at Beth-she′mesh, after which he brought him to Jerusalem and made a breach in the wall of Jerusalem, from the Gate of E′phra·im clear to the Corner Gate, four hundred cubits. 24 And he took all the gold and the silver and all the articles that were to be found in the house of the true God with O′bed-e′dom and the treasures of the king’s house and the hostages, and then returned to Sa·mar′i·a.

25 And Am·a·zi′ah the son of Je·ho′ash the king of Judah continued to live after the death of Je·ho′ash the son of Je·ho′a·haz the king of Israel fifteen years. 26 As for the rest of the affairs of Am·a·zi′ah, the first and the last, look! are they not written in the Book of the Kings of Judah and Israel? 27 And from the time that Am·a·zi′ah turned aside from following Jehovah, they proceeded to form a conspiracy against him in Jerusalem. At length he fled to La′chish; but they sent after him to La′chish and put him to death there. 28 So they carried him upon horses and buried him with his forefathers in the city of Judah.

2 Chronicles

34 Eight years old was Jo·si′ah when he began to reign, and for thirty-one years he reigned in Jerusalem. 2 And he proceeded to do what was right in Jehovah’s eyes and walk in the ways of David his forefather; and he did not turn aside to the right or to the left.

3 And in the eighth year of his reigning, while he was still a boy, he started to search for the God of David his forefather; and in the twelfth year he started to cleanse Judah and Jerusalem from the high places and the sacred poles and the graven images and the molten statues. 4 Further, they pulled down before him the altars of the Ba′als; and the incense stands that were up above he cut down from off them; and the sacred poles and the graven images and the molten statues he broke in pieces and reduced to powder, and then sprinkled it upon the surface of the burial places of those that used to sacrifice to them. 5 And the bones of priests he burned upon their altars. Thus he cleansed Judah and Jerusalem.

6 Also, in the cities of Ma·nas′seh and E′phra·im and Sim′e·on and clear to Naph′ta·li, in their devastated places all around, 7 he even went pulling down the altars and the sacred poles, and the graven images he crushed and reduced to powder; and all the incense stands he cut down in all the land of Israel, after which he returned to Jerusalem.

8 And in the eighteenth year of his reigning, when he had cleansed the land and the house, he sent Sha′phan the son of Az·a·li′ah and Ma·a·sei′ah the chief of the city and Jo′ah the son of Jo′a·haz the recorder to repair the house of Jehovah his God. 9 And they proceeded to come to Hil·ki′ah the high priest and give the money that was being brought to the house of God, which the Levites the doorkeepers had gathered from the hand of Ma·nas′seh and E′phra·im and from all the rest of Israel and from all Judah and Benjamin and the inhabitants of Jerusalem. 10 Then they put it into the hand of the doers of the work that were appointed over the house of Jehovah. In turn the doers of the work who were active in the house of Jehovah applied it to mending and repairing the house. 11 So they gave it to the craftsmen and the builders to buy hewn stones and timbers for clamps and to build with beams the houses that the kings of Judah had brought to ruin.

12 And the men were acting in faithfulness in the work; and over them there were appointed Ja′hath and O·ba·di′ah the Levites, from the sons of Me·rar′i, and Zech·a·ri′ah and Me·shul′lam, from the sons of the Ko′hath·ites, to act as overseers. And the Levites, each of whom was expert with the instruments of song, 13 were over the burden bearers, and the overseers of all the doers of the work for the different services; and from the Levites there were secretaries and officers and gatekeepers.

14 Now while they were bringing out the money that was being brought to the house of Jehovah, Hil·ki′ah the priest found the book of Jehovah’s law by the hand of Moses. 15 So Hil·ki′ah answered and said to Sha′phan the secretary: “The very book of the law I have found in the house of Jehovah.” With that Hil·ki′ah gave the book to Sha′phan. 16 Then Sha′phan brought the book to the king and replied further to the king, saying: “All that has been put in the hand of your servants they are doing. 17 And they pour out the money that is found in the house of Jehovah and put it in the hand of the appointed men and into the hand of the doers of the work.” 18 And Sha′phan the secretary went on to report to the king, saying: “There is a book that Hil·ki′ah the priest gave me.” And Sha′phan began to read out of it before the king.

19 And it came about that as soon as the king heard the words of the law, he immediately ripped his garments apart. 20 Then the king commanded Hil·ki′ah and A·hi′kam the son of Sha′phan and Ab′don the son of Mi′cah and Sha′phan the secretary and A·sai′ah the king’s servant, saying: 21 “Go, inquire of Jehovah in my own behalf and in behalf of what is left in Israel and in Judah concerning the words of the book that has been found, for great is Jehovah’s rage that must be poured out against us because of the fact that our forefathers did not keep the word of Jehovah by doing according to all that is written in this book.”

22 Accordingly Hil·ki′ah along with those whom the king had said went to Hul′dah the prophetess, the wife of Shal′lum the son of Tik′vah the son of Har′has the caretaker of the garments, as she was dwelling in Jerusalem in the second quarter; and they proceeded to speak to her like this. 23 In turn she said to them:

“This is what Jehovah the God of Israel has said, ‘SAY to the man that sent YOU to me: 24 “This is what Jehovah has said, ‘Here I am bringing calamity upon this place and its inhabitants, all the curses that are written in the book that they read before the king of Judah, 25 due to the fact that they have left me and gone making sacrificial smoke to other gods, in order to offend me with all the doings of their hands and that my rage may pour forth upon this place and not be extinguished.’” 26 And to the king of Judah, who is sending YOU to inquire of Jehovah, this is what YOU should say to him: “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel has said, ‘As regards the words that you have heard, 27 for the reason that your heart was soft so that you humbled yourself because of God at your hearing his words concerning this place and its inhabitants, and you humbled yourself before me and ripped your garments apart and wept before me, I, even I, have heard, is the utterance of Jehovah. 28 Here I am gathering you to your forefathers, and you will certainly be gathered to your graveyard in peace, and your eyes will not look upon all the calamity that I am bringing upon this place and its inhabitants.’”’”

Then they brought the reply to the king. 29 And the king proceeded to send and gather all the older men of Judah and of Jerusalem. 30 The king now went up to the house of Jehovah with all the men of Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem and the priests and the Levites and all the people, the great as well as the small; and he began to read in their ears all the words of the book of the covenant, which had been found at the house of Jehovah. 31 And the king kept standing in his place and proceeded to conclude the covenant before Jehovah to go following Jehovah and to keep his commandments and his testimonies and his regulations with all his heart and with all his soul, to perform the words of the covenant that were written in this book. 32 Furthermore, he had all those who were found in Jerusalem and Benjamin to take their stand to it. And the inhabitants of Jerusalem proceeded to do according to the covenant of God, the God of their forefathers. 33 After that Jo·si′ah removed all the detestable things out of all the lands that belonged to the sons of Israel, and he had all who were found in Israel take up service, to serve Jehovah their God. All his days they did not turn aside from following Jehovah the God of their forefathers.

Ezra

2 And these were the sons of the jurisdictional district that went up out of the captivity of the exiled people whom Neb·u·chad·nez′zar the king of Babylon had taken into exile at Babylon and who later returned to Jerusalem and Judah, each one to his own city; 2 those who came with Ze·rub′ba·bel, Jesh′u·a, Ne·he·mi′ah, Se·rai′ah, Re·el·ai′ah, Mor′de·cai, Bil′shan, Mis′par, Big′vai, Re′hum, Ba′a·nah.

The number of the men of the people of Israel: 3 The sons of Pa′rosh, two thousand one hundred and seventy-two; 4 the sons of Sheph·a·ti′ah, three hundred and seventy-two; 5 the sons of A′rah, seven hundred and seventy-five; 6 the sons of Pa′hath-mo′ab, of the sons of Jesh′u·a and Jo′ab, two thousand eight hundred and twelve; 7 the sons of E′lam, a thousand two hundred and fifty-four; 8 the sons of Zat′tu, nine hundred and forty-five; 9 the sons of Zac′cai, seven hundred and sixty; 10 the sons of Ba′ni, six hundred and forty-two; 11 the sons of Be′bai, six hundred and twenty-three; 12 the sons of Az′gad, a thousand two hundred and twenty-two; 13 the sons of Ad·o·ni′kam, six hundred and sixty-six; 14 the sons of Big′vai, two thousand and fifty-six; 15 the sons of A′din, four hundred and fifty-four; 16 the sons of A′ter, of Hez·e·ki′ah, ninety-eight; 17 the sons of Be′zai, three hundred and twenty-three; 18 the sons of Jo′rah, a hundred and twelve; 19 the sons of Ha′shum, two hundred and twenty-three; 20 the sons of Gib′bar, ninety-five; 21 the sons of Beth′le·hem, a hundred and twenty-three; 22 the men of Ne·to′phah, fifty-six; 23 the men of An′a·thoth, a hundred and twenty-eight; 24 the sons of Az′ma·veth, forty-two; 25 the sons of Kir′i·ath-je′a·rim, Che·phi′rah and Be·er′oth, seven hundred and forty-three; 26 the sons of Ra′mah and Ge′ba, six hundred and twenty-one; 27 the men of Mich′mas, a hundred and twenty-two; 28 the men of Beth′el and A′i, two hundred and twenty-three; 29 the sons of Ne′bo, fifty-two; 30 the sons of Mag′bish, a hundred and fifty-six; 31 the sons of the other E′lam, a thousand two hundred and fifty-four; 32 the sons of Ha′rim, three hundred and twenty; 33 the sons of Lod, Ha′did and O′no, seven hundred and twenty-five; 34 the sons of Jer′i·cho, three hundred and forty-five; 35 the sons of Se·na′ah, three thousand six hundred and thirty.

36 The priests: The sons of Je·da′iah of the house of Jesh′u·a nine hundred and seventy-three; 37 the sons of Im′mer, a thousand and fifty-two; 38 the sons of Pash′hur, a thousand two hundred and forty-seven; 39 the sons of Ha′rim, a thousand and seventeen.

40 The Levites: The sons of Jesh′u·a and Kad′mi·el, of the sons of Hod·a·vi′ah, seventy-four. 41 The singers, the sons of A′saph, a hundred and twenty-eight. 42 The sons of the gatekeepers, the sons of Shal′lum, the sons of A′ter, the sons of Tal′mon, the sons of Ak′kub, the sons of Ha·ti′ta, the sons of Sho′bai, all together, a hundred and thirty-nine.

43 The Neth′i·nim: The sons of Zi′ha, the sons of Ha·su′pha, the sons of Tab·ba′oth, 44 the sons of Ke′ros, the sons of Si′a·ha, the sons of Pa′don, 45 the sons of Le·ba′nah, the sons of Hag′a·bah, the sons of Ak′kub, 46 the sons of Ha′gab, the sons of Sal′mai, the sons of Ha′nan, 47 the sons of Gid′del, the sons of Ga′har, the sons of Re·a′iah, 48 the sons of Re′zin, the sons of Ne·ko′da, the sons of Gaz′zam, 49 the sons of Uz′za, the sons of Pa·se′ah, the sons of Be′sai, 50 the sons of As′nah, the sons of Me·u′nim, the sons of Ne·phu′sim; 51 the sons of Bak′buk, the sons of Ha·ku′pha, the sons of Har′hur, 52 the sons of Baz′luth, the sons of Me·hi′da, the sons of Har′sha, 53 the sons of Bar′kos, the sons of Sis′e·ra, the sons of Te′mah, 54 the sons of Ne·zi′ah, the sons of Ha·ti′pha.

55 The sons of the servants of Sol′o·mon: The sons of So′tai, the sons of So·phe′reth, the sons of Pe·ru′da, 56 the sons of Ja′a·lah, the sons of Dar′kon, the sons of Gid′del, 57 the sons of Sheph·a·ti′ah, the sons of Hat′til, the sons of Po′che·reth-haz·ze·ba′im, the sons of A′mi.

58 All the Neth′i·nim and the sons of the servants of Sol′o·mon were three hundred and ninety-two.

59 And these were the ones going up from Tel-me′lah, Tel-har′sha, Che′rub, Ad′don and Im′mer, and they proved unable to tell the house of their fathers and their origin, whether they were of Israel: 60 the sons of De·la′iah, the sons of To·bi′ah, the sons of Ne·ko′da, six hundred and fifty-two. 61 And of the sons of the priests: the sons of Ha·bai′ah, the sons of Hak′koz, the sons of Bar·zil′lai, who took a wife from the daughters of Bar·zil′lai the Gil′e·ad·ite and came to be called by their name. 62 These were the ones that looked for their register to establish their genealogy publicly, and they did not find themselves, so that they were barred as polluted from the priesthood. 63 Consequently the Tir·sha′tha said to them that they could not eat from the most holy things until a priest stood up with U′rim and Thum′mim.

64 The entire congregation as one group was forty-two thousand three hundred and sixty, 65 apart from their men slaves and their slave girls, these being seven thousand three hundred and thirty-seven; and they had two hundred male singers and female singers. 66 Their horses were seven hundred and thirty-six, their mules two hundred and forty-five, 67 their camels four hundred and thirty-five, their asses six thousand seven hundred and twenty.

68 And certain ones of the heads of the paternal houses, on coming to the house of Jehovah, which was in Jerusalem, made voluntary offerings to the house of the true God, to cause it to stand on its own site. 69 According to their power they gave gold for the working supplies, sixty-one thousand drachmas, and silver, five thousand mi′nas, and a hundred robes of priests. 70 And the priests and the Levites and some of the people, and the singers and the gatekeepers and the Neth′i·nim took up dwelling in their cities, and all Israel in their cities.

Ezra

5 And Hag′gai the prophet and Zech·a·ri′ah the grandson of Id′do the prophet prophesied to the Jews who were in Judah and in Jerusalem, in the name of the God of Israel who was over them. 2 It was then that Ze·rub′ba·bel the son of She·al′ti·el and Jesh′u·a the son of Je·hoz′a·dak got up and started to rebuild the house of God, which was in Jerusalem; and with them there were God’s prophets giving them aid. 3 At that time Tat′te·nai the governor beyond the River and She′thar-boz′e·nai and their colleagues came to them, and this is what they were saying to them: “Who put an order through to YOU to build this house and to finish this beam structure?” 4 Then they said to them this: “What are the names of the able-bodied men that are building this building?” 5 And the eye of their God proved to be upon the older men of the Jews, and they did not stop them until the report could go to Da·ri′us and then an official document concerning this could be sent back.

6 Here is a copy of the letter that Tat′te·nai the governor beyond the River and She′thar-boz′e·nai and his colleagues, the lesser governors that were beyond the River, sent to Da·ri′us the king; 7 they sent the word to him, and the writing in it was in this manner:

“To Da·ri′us the king:

“All peace! 8 Let it become known to the king that we went to the jurisdictional district of Judah to the house of the great God, and it is being built with stones rolled into place, and timbers are being laid in the walls; and that work is being eagerly done and is making progress in their hands. 9 Then we asked these older men. This is what we said to them: ‘Who put an order through to YOU to build this house and to finish this beam structure?’ 10 And we also asked them their names, so as to let you know, that we might write the names of the able-bodied men that are at their head.

11 “And this is the word that they gave back to us, saying: ‘We are the servants of the God of the heavens and the earth, and we are rebuilding the house that had been built many years before this, which a great king of Israel built and finished. 12 However, because our fathers irritated the God of the heavens, he gave them into the hand of Neb·u·chad·nez′zar the king of Babylon, the Chal·de′an, and he demolished this house and took the people into exile at Babylon. 13 Nevertheless, in the first year of Cyrus the king of Babylon, Cyrus the king put an order through to rebuild this house of God. 14 And also the gold and silver vessels of the house of God that Neb·u·chad·nez′zar had taken out of the temple, which was in Jerusalem, and brought to the temple of Babylon, these Cyrus the king took out of the temple of Babylon, and they were given to Shesh·baz′zar, the name of the one whom he made governor. 15 And he said to him: “Take these vessels. Go, deposit them in the temple that is in Jerusalem, and let the house of God be rebuilt upon its place.” 16 When that Shesh·baz′zar came he laid the foundations of the house of God, which is in Jerusalem; and from then until now it is being rebuilt but it has not been completed.’

17 “And now if to the king it seems good, let there be an investigation in the king’s house of treasures that is there in Babylon, whether it is so that from Cyrus the king an order was put through to rebuild that house of God in Jerusalem; and the decision of the king concerning this let him send to us.”

Ezra

8 Now these were the heads of their paternal houses and the genealogical enrollment of those going up with me during the reign of Ar·ta·xerx′es the king out of Babylon: 2 Of the sons of Phin′e·has, Ger′shom; of the sons of Ith′a·mar, Daniel; of the sons of David, Hat′tush; 3 of the sons of Shec·a·ni′ah, of the sons of Pa′rosh, Zech·a·ri′ah, and with him there was an enrollment of a hundred and fifty males; 4 of the sons of Pa′hath-mo′ab, El′ie·ho-e′nai the son of Zer·a·hi′ah, and with him two hundred males; 5 of the sons of Zat′tu, Shec·a·ni′ah the son of Ja·ha·zi′el, and with him three hundred males; 6 and of the sons of A′din, E′bed the son of Jon′a·than, and with him fifty males; 7 and of the sons of E′lam, Je·sha′iah the son of Ath·a·li′ah, and with him seventy males; 8 and of the sons of Sheph·a·ti′ah, Zeb·a·di′ah the son of Mi′cha·el, and with him eighty males; 9 of the sons of Jo′ab, O·ba·di′ah the son of Je·hi′el, and with him two hundred and eighteen males; 10 and of the sons of Ba′ni, She·lo′mith the son of Jo·si·phi′ah, and with him a hundred and sixty males; 11 and of the sons of Be′bai, Zech·a·ri′ah the son of Be′bai, and with him twenty-eight males; 12 and of the sons of Az′gad, Jo·ha′nan the son of Hak′ka·tan, and with him a hundred and ten males; 13 and of the sons of Ad·o·ni′kam, those who were the last, and these were their names: E·liph′e·let, Je·i′el and She·mai′ah, and with them sixty males; 14 and of the sons of Big′vai, U′thai and Zab′bud, and with them seventy males.

15 And I proceeded to collect them at the river that comes to A·ha′va; and we kept encamped there three days, that I might scrutinize the people and the priests, but none of the sons of Le′vi did I find there. 16 Accordingly I sent for E·li·e′zer, Ar′i·el, She·mai′ah and El·na′than and Ja′rib and El·na′than and Nathan and Zech·a·ri′ah and Me·shul′lam, head ones, and for Joi′a·rib and El·na′than, instructors. 17 Then I gave them a command concerning Id′do the head one in the place Ca·si·phi′a, and I put in their mouth words to speak to Id′do and his brothers the Neth′i·nim in the place Ca·si·phi′a, to bring to us ministers for the house of our God. 18 So they brought to us, according to the good hand of our God upon us, a man of discretion from the sons of Mah′li the grandson of Le′vi the son of Israel, namely, She·re·bi′ah and his sons and his brothers, eighteen; 19 and Hash·a·bi′ah and with him Je·sha′iah from the sons of Me·rar′i, his brothers, and their sons, twenty. 20 And from the Neth′i·nim, whom David and the princes gave to the service of the Levites, two hundred and twenty Neth′i·nim, all of whom had been designated by their names.

21 Then I proclaimed a fast there at the river A·ha′va, to humble ourselves before our God, to seek from him the right way for us and for our little ones and for all our goods. 22 For I felt ashamed to ask a military force and horsemen from the king to help us against the enemy in the way, because we had said to the king: “The hand of our God is over all those seeking him for good, but his strength and his anger are against all those leaving him.” 23 Therefore we fasted and made request of our God concerning this, so that he let himself be entreated by us.

24 I now separated from the chiefs of the priests twelve, namely, She·re·bi′ah, Hash·a·bi′ah, and with them ten of their brothers. 25 And I proceeded to weigh out to them the silver and the gold and the utensils, the contribution to the house of our God that the king and his counselors and his princes and all the Israelites who were to be found had contributed. 26 Thus I weighed out into their hand six hundred and fifty talents of silver and a hundred silver utensils worth two talents, and gold a hundred talents, 27 and twenty small gold bowls worth a thousand darics and two utensils of good copper, gleaming red, as desirable as gold.

28 Then I said to them: “YOU are something holy to Jehovah, and the utensils are something holy, and the silver and the gold are a voluntary offering to Jehovah the God of YOUR forefathers. 29 Keep awake and be on guard until YOU weigh them out before the chiefs of the priests and the Levites and the princes of the fathers of Israel in Jerusalem, in the dining halls of the house of Jehovah.” 30 And the priests and the Levites received the weight of the silver and the gold and the utensils, to bring them to Jerusalem to the house of our God.

31 Finally we pulled away from the river A·ha′va on the twelfth day of the first month to go to Jerusalem, and the very hand of our God proved to be over us, so that he delivered us out of the palm of the enemy and the ambush by the way. 32 So we came to Jerusalem and dwelt there three days. 33 And on the fourth day we proceeded to weigh out the silver and the gold and the utensils in the house of our God into the hand of Mer′e·moth the son of U·ri′jah the priest and with him El·e·a′zar the son of Phin′e·has and with them Jo′za·bad the son of Jesh′u·a and No·a·di′ah the son of Bin′nu·i the Levites, 34 by number and by weight for everything, after which all the weight was written down at that time. 35 Those coming out of the captivity, the former exiles, themselves presented burnt sacrifices to the God of Israel, twelve bulls for all Israel, ninety-six rams, seventy-seven male lambs, twelve he-goats as a sin offering, everything as a burnt offering to Jehovah.

36 Then we gave the laws of the king to the satraps of the king and the governors beyond the River, and they assisted the people and the house of the true God.

Ezra

9 And as soon as these things were finished, the princes approached me, saying: “The people of Israel and the priests and the Levites have not separated themselves from the peoples of the lands as regards their detestable things, namely, the Ca′naan·ites, the Hit′tites, the Per′iz·zites, the Jeb′u·sites, the Am′mon·ites, the Mo′ab·ites, the Egyptians and the Am′or·ites. 2 For they have accepted some of their daughters for themselves and for their sons; and they, the holy seed, have become mingled with the peoples of the lands, and the hand of the princes and the deputy rulers has proved to be foremost in this unfaithfulness.”

3 Now as soon as I heard of this thing I ripped apart my garment and my sleeveless coat, and I began to pull out some of the hair of my head and of my beard, and I kept sitting stunned. 4 Also to me they came gathering themselves, everyone trembling because of the words of the God of Israel against the unfaithfulness of the exiled people, while I was sitting stunned until the grain offering of the evening.

5 And at the grain offering of the evening I stood up from my humiliation, with my garment and my sleeveless coat torn apart, and I proceeded to kneel upon my knees and spread out my palms to Jehovah my God. 6 And I went on to say: “O my God, I do feel ashamed and embarrassed to raise my face to you, O my God, for our errors themselves have multiplied over our head and our guiltiness has grown great even to the heavens. 7 From the days of our forefathers we have been in great guiltiness until this day; and because of our errors we have been given, we ourselves, our kings, our priests, into the hand of the kings of the lands with the sword, with the captivity and with the plunder and with shame of face, just as this day. 8 And now for a little moment favor from Jehovah our God has come by leaving over for us those who escape and by giving us a peg in his holy place, to make our eyes shine, O our God, and to give us a little reviving in our servitude. 9 For we are servants; and in our servitude our God has not left us, but he extends toward us loving-kindness before the kings of Persia, to give us a reviving so as to raise up the house of our God and to restore its desolated places and to give us a stone wall in Judah and in Jerusalem.

10 “And now what shall we say, O our God, after this? For we have left your commandments, 11 which you commanded by means of your servants the prophets, saying, ‘The land that YOU people are going in to take possession of is an impure land because of the impurity of the peoples of the lands, because of their detestable things with which they have filled it from end to end by their uncleanness. 12 And now YOUR daughters do not YOU people give to their sons, neither their daughters do YOU accept for YOUR sons; and to time indefinite YOU must not work for their peace and their prosperity, in order that YOU may grow strong and certainly eat the good of the land and indeed take possession of it for YOUR sons to time indefinite.’ 13 And after all that has come upon us for our bad deeds and our great guiltiness—for you yourself, O our God, have underestimated our error, and you have given us those who have escaped such as these— 14 shall we go breaking your commandments again and forming marriage alliances with the peoples of these detestable things? Will you not get incensed at us to the limit so that there will be none remaining and none escaping? 15 O Jehovah the God of Israel, you are righteous, because we have been left over as an escaped people as at this day. Here we are before you in our guiltiness, for it is impossible to stand before you on account of this.”

Ezra

10 Now as soon as Ez′ra had prayed and he had made confession while weeping and lying prostrate before the house of the true God, those of Israel collected themselves together to him, a very large congregation, men and women and children, for the people had wept profusely. 2 Then Shec·a·ni′ah the son of Je·hi′el of the sons of E′lam answered and said to Ez′ra: “We—we have acted unfaithfully against our God, so that we gave a dwelling to foreign wives from the peoples of the land. Yet now there exists a hope for Israel concerning this. 3 And now let us conclude a covenant with our God to put away all the wives and those born from them according to the counsel of Jehovah and of those trembling at the commandment of our God, that it may be done according to the law. 4 Get up, for the matter devolves upon you, and we are with you. Be strong and act.”

5 At that Ez′ra rose and had the chiefs of the priests, the Levites and all Israel take an oath to do according to this word. Accordingly they took an oath. 6 Ez′ra now rose from before the house of the true God and went to the dining hall of Je·ho·ha′nan the son of E·li′a·shib. Although he went there, he ate no bread and drank no water, for he was mourning over the unfaithfulness of the exiled people.

7 Then they caused a call to pass throughout Judah and Jerusalem for all the former exiles to collect themselves together at Jerusalem; 8 and anyone that did not come in three days’ time according to the counsel of the princes and the older men—all his goods would be put under a ban and he himself be separated from the congregation of the exiled people. 9 So all the men of Judah and Benjamin collected themselves together at Jerusalem within three days, that is, in the ninth month on the twentieth day of the month, and all the people kept sitting in the open place of the house of the true God, shivering because of the matter and on account of the showers of rain.

10 At length Ez′ra the priest rose and said to them: “YOU yourselves have acted unfaithfully in that YOU gave a dwelling to foreign wives so as to add to the guiltiness of Israel. 11 And now make confession to Jehovah the God of YOUR forefathers and do his pleasure and separate yourselves from the peoples of the land and from the foreign wives.” 12 To this all the congregation answered and said with a loud voice: “Exactly according to your word it devolves upon us to do. 13 However, the people are many, and it is the season of showers of rain, and it is not possible to stand outside; and the business will not take one day or two, for we have rebelled to a great extent in this matter. 14 So, please, let our princes act representatively for all the congregation; and, as for all in our cities who have given a dwelling to foreign wives, let them come at the times appointed and along with them the older men of each individual city and its judges, until we have turned back the burning anger of our God from us, on account of this matter.”

15 (However, Jon′a·than the son of As′a·hel and Jah·zei′ah the son of Tik′vah themselves stood up against this, and Me·shul′lam and Shab′be·thai the Levites were the ones that helped them.) 16 And the former exiles proceeded to do that way; and Ez′ra the priest and the men that were the heads of the fathers for their paternal house, even all of them by their names, now separated themselves and began sitting on the first day of the tenth month to inquire into the matter; 17 and gradually they finished with all the men that had given a dwelling to foreign wives by the first day of the first month. 18 And some of the sons of the priests came to be found that had given a dwelling to foreign wives; of the sons of Jesh′u·a the son of Je·hoz′a·dak and his brothers, Ma·a·sei′ah and E·li·e′zer and Ja′rib and Ged·a·li′ah. 19 But they promised by shaking hands to put their wives away, and that, they being guilty, there should be a ram of the flock for their guiltiness.

20 And of the sons of Im′mer there were Ha·na′ni and Zeb·a·di′ah; 21 and of the sons of Ha′rim, Ma·a·sei′ah and E·li′jah and She·mai′ah and Je·hi′el and Uz·zi′ah; 22 and of the sons of Pash′hur, Eli·o·e′nai, Ma·a·sei′ah, Ish′ma·el, Ne·than′el, Jo′za·bad and El·e·a′sah. 23 And of the Levites, Jo′za·bad and Shim′e·i and Ke·lai′ah (that is, Ke·li′ta), Peth·a·hi′ah, Judah and E·li·e′zer; 24 and of the singers, E·li′a·shib; and of the gatekeepers, Shal′lum and Te′lem and U′ri.

25 And of Israel, of the sons of Pa′rosh there were Ra·mi′ah and Iz·zi′ah and Mal·chi′jah and Mij′a·min and El·e·a′zar and Mal·chi′jah and Be·nai′ah; 26 and of the sons of E′lam, Mat·ta·ni′ah, Zech·a·ri′ah and Je·hi′el and Ab′di and Jer′e·moth and E·li′jah; 27 and of the sons of Zat′tu, Eli·o·e′nai, E·li′a·shib, Mat·ta·ni′ah and Jer′e·moth and Za′bad and A·zi′za; 28 and of the sons of Be′bai, Je·ho·ha′nan, Han·a·ni′ah, Zab′bai, Ath′lai; 29 and of the sons of Ba′ni, Me·shul′lam, Mal′luch and A·dai′ah, Ja′shub and She′al and Jer′e·moth; 30 and of the sons of Pa′hath-mo′ab, Ad′na and Che′lal, Be·nai′ah, Ma·a·sei′ah, Mat·ta·ni′ah, Bez′al·el and Bin′nu·i and Ma·nas′seh; 31 and of the sons of Ha′rim, E·li·e′zer, Is·shi′jah, Mal·chi′jah, She·mai′ah, Shim′e·on, 32 Benjamin, Mal′luch and Shem·a·ri′ah; 33 of the sons of Ha′shum, Mat·te′nai, Mat′tat·tah, Za′bad, E·liph′e·let, Jer′e·mai, Ma·nas′seh and Shim′e·i; 34 of the sons of Ba′ni, Ma·a·da′i, Am′ram and U′el, 35 Be·nai′ah, Be·dei′ah, Chel′u·hi, 36 Va·ni′ah, Mer′e·moth, E·li′a·shib, 37 Mat·ta·ni′ah, Mat·te′nai and Ja′a·su; 38 and of the sons of Bin′nu·i, Shim′e·i 39 and Shel·e·mi′ah and Nathan and A·dai′ah, 40 Mach·nad′e·bai, Sha′shai, Sha′rai, 41 Az′ar·el and Shel·e·mi′ah, Shem·a·ri′ah, 42 Shal′lum, Am·a·ri′ah, Joseph; 43 of the sons of Ne′bo, Je·i′el, Mat·ti·thi′ah, Za′bad, Ze·bi′na, Jad′dai and Joel and Be·nai′ah. 44 These all had accepted foreign wives, and they proceeded to send away wives along with sons.

Nehemiah

5 However, there came to be a great outcry of the people and their wives against their Jewish brothers. 2 And there were those who were saying: “Our sons and our daughters we are giving as security that we may get grain and eat and keep alive.” 3 And there were those who were saying: “Our fields and our vineyards and our houses we are giving as security that we may get grain during the food shortage.” 4 And there were those who were saying: “We have borrowed money for the king’s tribute on our fields and our vineyards. 5 And now our flesh is the same as the flesh of our brothers; our sons are the same as their sons, but here we are reducing our sons and our daughters to slaves, and there are some of our daughters already reduced; and there is no power in our hands while our fields and our vineyards belong to others.”

6 Now I became very angry as soon as I heard their outcry and these words. 7 So my heart took consideration within me, and I began finding fault with the nobles and the deputy rulers, and went on to say to them: “Usury is what YOU are exacting, each one from his own brother.”

Further, I arranged a great assembly on their account. 8 And I proceeded to say to them: “We ourselves have bought back our own Jewish brothers who were sold to the nations, as far as it was in our power; and at the same time will YOU yourselves sell YOUR own brothers, and must they be sold to us?” At this they became speechless, and they did not find a word. 9 And I went on to say: “The thing that YOU are doing is not good. Is it not in the fear of our God that YOU should walk because of the reproach of the nations, our enemies? 10 And also I, my brothers and my attendants are giving money and grain on loan among them. Let us, please, leave off this lending on interest. 11 Please, restore to them on this day their fields, their vineyards, their olive groves and their houses, and the hundredth of the money and the grain, the new wine and the oil that YOU are exacting as interest from them.”

12 To this they said: “We shall make restoration, and from them we shall ask nothing back. We shall do precisely as you are saying.” So I called the priests and made them swear to do according to this word. 13 Also, my bosom I shook out and then said: “In this manner may the true God shake out from his house and from his acquired property every man that does not carry out this word; and in this manner may he become shaken out and empty.” To this all the congregation said: “Amen!” And they began to praise Jehovah. And the people proceeded to do according to this word.

14 Another thing: From the day that he commissioned me to become their governor in the land of Judah, from the twentieth year to the thirty-second year of Ar·ta·xerx′es the king, twelve years, I myself and my brothers did not eat the bread due the governor. 15 As for the former governors that were prior to me, they had made it heavy upon the people, and they kept taking from them for bread and wine daily forty silver shekels. Also, their attendants themselves domineered over the people. As for me, I did not do that way on account of the fear of God.

16 And, what is more, in the work of this wall I took a hand, and not a field did we acquire; and all my attendants were collected together there for the work. 17 And the Jews and the deputy rulers, a hundred and fifty men, and those coming in to us from the nations that were around us were at my table. 18 As for that which happened to be made ready daily, one bull, six select sheep and birds were made ready for me, and once every ten days every sort of wine in abundance. And along with this the bread due the governor I did not demand, because the service upon this people was heavy. 19 Do remember for me, O my God, for good, all that I have done in behalf of this people.

Nehemiah

6 Now it came about that, as soon as it was told to San·bal′lat and To·bi′ah and to Ge′shem the Arabian and to the rest of our enemies that I had rebuilt the wall and there had not been left in it a gap (although up to that time the doors themselves I had not set up in the gates), 2 San·bal′lat and Ge′shem immediately sent to me, saying: “Do come, and let us meet together by appointment in the villages of the valley plain of O′no.” But they were scheming to do me harm. 3 So I sent messengers to them, saying: “It is a great work that I am doing, and I am not able to go down. Why should the work cease while I take off from it and have to go down to YOU?” 4 However, they sent me the same word four times, and I kept replying to them with the same word.

5 Finally San·bal′lat sent his attendant to me with the same word a fifth time, with an open letter in his hand. 6 There was written in it: “Among the nations it has been heard, and Ge′shem is saying it, that you and the Jews are scheming to rebel. That is why you are building the wall; and you are becoming a king to them, according to these words. 7 And there are even prophets that you have appointed to call out concerning you throughout Jerusalem, saying, ‘There is a king in Judah!’ And now things like these will be told to the king. So now do come, and let us consult together.”

8 However, I sent to him, saying: “Things such as you are saying have not been brought about, but it is out of your own heart that you are inventing them.” 9 For all of them were trying to make us afraid, saying: “Their hands will drop down from the work so that it will not be done.” But now strengthen my hands.

10 And I myself entered the house of She·mai′ah the son of De·la′iah the son of Me·het′a·bel while he was shut up. And he proceeded to say: “Let us meet by appointment at the house of the true God, within the temple, and let us close the doors of the temple; for they are coming in to kill you, even by night they are coming in to kill you.” 11 But I said: “Should a man like me run away? And who is there like me that could enter into the temple and live? I shall not enter!” 12 So I investigated, and here it was not God that had sent him, but he had spoken this prophecy against me as To·bi′ah and San·bal′lat themselves had hired him. 13 For this reason he had been hired in order that I might be afraid and do that way, and I should certainly sin and it should certainly become in their possession a bad reputation, in order that they might reproach me.

14 Do remember, O my God, To·bi′ah and San·bal′lat, according to these deeds of each one, and also No·a·di′ah the prophetess and the rest of the prophets that were continually trying to make me afraid.

15 At length the wall came to completion on the twenty-fifth day of E′lul, in fifty-two days.

16 And it came about that, as soon as all our enemies heard of it and all the nations that were around us got to see it, they at once fell very much in their own eyes, and they got to know that it was from our God that this work had been done. 17 In those days also the nobles of Judah were making numerous their letters that were going to To·bi′ah and those of To·bi′ah that were coming in to them. 18 For many in Judah were sworn to him, for a son-in-law he was to Shec·a·ni′ah the son of A′rah; and Je·ho·ha′nan his son had himself taken the daughter of Me·shul′lam the son of Ber·e·chi′ah. 19 Also, good things about him they were continually saying before me. And my own words they were continually taking out to him. There were letters that To·bi′ah sent to make me afraid.

Nehemiah

8 And all the people proceeded to gather themselves as one man at the public square that was before the Water Gate. Then they said to Ez′ra the copyist to bring the book of the law of Moses, which Jehovah had commanded Israel. 2 Accordingly Ez′ra the priest brought the law before the congregation of men as well as of women and of all intelligent enough to listen, on the first day of the seventh month. 3 And he continued to read aloud from it before the public square that is before the Water Gate, from daybreak till midday, in front of the men and the women and the other intelligent ones; and the ears of all the people were attentive to the book of the law. 4 And Ez′ra the copyist kept standing upon a wooden podium, which they had made for the occasion; and there were standing alongside him Mat·ti·thi′ah and She′ma and A·nai′ah and U·ri′ah and Hil·ki′ah and Ma·a·sei′ah to his right hand, and at his left Pe·dai′ah and Mish′a·el and Mal·chi′jah and Ha′shum and Hash-bad′da·nah, Zech·a·ri′ah and Me·shul′lam.

5 And Ez′ra proceeded to open the book before the eyes of all the people, for he happened to be above all the people; and as he opened it all the people stood up. 6 Then Ez′ra blessed Jehovah the true God, the great One, at which all the people answered, “Amen! Amen!” with the lifting up of their hands. They then bowed low and prostrated themselves to Jehovah with their faces to the earth. 7 And Jesh′u·a and Ba′ni and She·re·bi′ah, Ja′min, Ak′kub, Shab′be·thai, Ho·di′ah, Ma·a·sei′ah, Ke·li′ta, Az·a·ri′ah, Jo′za·bad, Ha′nan, Pe·la′iah, even the Levites, were explaining the law to the people, while the people were in a standing position. 8 And they continued reading aloud from the book, from the law of the true God, it being expounded, and there being a putting of meaning into it; and they continued giving understanding in the reading.

9 And Ne·he·mi′ah, that is, the Tir·sha′tha, and Ez′ra the priest, the copyist, and the Levites who were instructing the people proceeded to say to all the people: “This very day is holy to Jehovah YOUR God. Do not mourn or weep.” For all the people were weeping as they were hearing the words of the law. 10 And he went on to say to them: “Go, eat the fatty things and drink the sweet things, and send portions to the one for whom nothing has been prepared; for this day is holy to our Lord, and do not feel hurt, for the joy of Jehovah is YOUR stronghold.” 11 And the Levites were ordering all the people to be silent, saying: “Keep quiet! for this day is holy; and do not feel hurt.” 12 So all the people went away to eat and drink and to send out portions and to carry on a great rejoicing, for they had understood the words that had been made known to them.

13 And on the second day the heads of the fathers of all the people, the priests and the Levites, gathered themselves together to Ez′ra the copyist, even to gain insight into the words of the law. 14 Then they found written in the law that Jehovah had commanded by means of Moses that the sons of Israel should dwell in booths during the festival in the seventh month, 15 and that they should make proclamation and cause a call to pass throughout all their cities and throughout Jerusalem, saying: “Go out to the mountainous region and bring in olive leaves and the leaves of oil trees and myrtle leaves and palm leaves and the leaves of branchy trees to make booths, according to what is written.”

16 And the people proceeded to go out and bring them in and make booths for themselves, each one upon his own roof and in their courtyards and in the courtyards of the house of the true God and in the public square of the Water Gate and in the public square of the Gate of E′phra·im. 17 Thus all the congregation of those who had come back from the captivity made booths and took up dwelling in the booths; for the sons of Israel had not done that way from the days of Joshua the son of Nun until that day, so that there came to be very great rejoicing. 18 And there was a reading aloud of the book of the law of the true God day by day, from the first day until the last day; and they went on holding the festival seven days, and on the eighth day there was a solemn assembly, according to the rule.

Nehemiah

11 Now the princes of the people had their dwelling in Jerusalem; but as for the rest of the people, they cast lots to bring in one out of every ten to dwell in Jerusalem the holy city, and the nine other parts in the other cities. 2 Moreover, the people blessed all the men who volunteered to dwell in Jerusalem.

3 And these are the heads of the jurisdictional district who dwelt in Jerusalem; but in the cities of Judah there dwelt, each one in his own possession, in their cities, Israel, the priests and the Levites, and the Neth′i·nim and the sons of the servants of Sol′o·mon.

4 Also, in Jerusalem there dwelt some of the sons of Judah and some of the sons of Benjamin. Of the sons of Judah there were A·thai′ah the son of Uz·zi′ah the son of Zech·a·ri′ah the son of Am·a·ri′ah the son of Sheph·a·ti′ah the son of Ma·hal′a·lel of the sons of Pe′rez; 5 and Ma·a·sei′ah the son of Bar′uch the son of Col·ho′zeh the son of Ha·zai′ah the son of A·dai′ah the son of Joi′a·rib the son of Zech·a·ri′ah the son of the She·la′nite. 6 All the sons of Pe′rez who were dwelling in Jerusalem were four hundred and sixty-eight, capable men.

7 And these were the sons of Benjamin: Sal′lu the son of Me·shul′lam the son of Jo′ed the son of Pe·dai′ah the son of Ko·lai′ah the son of Ma·a·sei′ah the son of Ith′i·el the son of Je·sha′iah; 8 and after him Gab·ba′i and Sal·la′i, nine hundred and twenty-eight; 9 and Joel the son of Zich′ri, an overseer over them, and Judah the son of Has·se·nu′ah over the city as second.

10 Of the priests: Je·da′iah the son of Joi′a·rib, Ja′chin, 11 Se·rai′ah the son of Hil·ki′ah the son of Me·shul′lam the son of Za′dok the son of Me·ra′ioth the son of A·hi′tub, a leader of the house of the true God; 12 and their brothers the doers of the work of the house, eight hundred and twenty-two; and A·dai′ah the son of Je·ro′ham the son of Pel·a·li′ah the son of Am′zi the son of Zech·a·ri′ah the son of Pash′hur the son of Mal·chi′jah, 13 and his brothers, heads of paternal houses, two hundred and forty-two, and A·mash′sai the son of Az′ar·el the son of Ah′zai the son of Me·shil′le·moth the son of Im′mer, 14 and their brothers, mighty men of valor, a hundred and twenty-eight, and there was an overseer over them, Zab′di·el the son of the great ones.

15 And of the Levites: She·mai′ah the son of Has′shub the son of Az·ri′kam the son of Hash·a·bi′ah the son of Bun′ni, 16 and Shab′be·thai and Jo′za·bad, of the heads of the Levites, over the outside business of the house of the true God; 17 and Mat·ta·ni′ah himself, the son of Mi′cah the son of Zab′di the son of A′saph, the conductor of the praise singing, did the lauding at prayer, and Bak·bu·ki′ah was second of his brothers, and Ab′da the son of Sham·mu′a the son of Ga′lal the son of Je·du′thun. 18 All the Levites in the holy city were two hundred and eighty-four.

19 And the gatekeepers were Ak′kub, Tal′mon and their brothers who were keeping guard in the gates, a hundred and seventy-two.

20 And the rest of Israel, of the priests and of the Levites, were in all the other cities of Judah, each one in his own hereditary possession. 21 And the Neth′i·nim were dwelling in O′phel; and Zi′ha and Gish′pa were over the Neth′i·nim.

22 And the overseer of the Levites in Jerusalem was Uz′zi the son of Ba′ni the son of Hash·a·bi′ah the son of Mat·ta·ni′ah the son of Mi′ca of the sons of A′saph, the singers, concerning the work of the house of the true God. 23 For there was a commandment of the king in behalf of them, and there was a fixed provision for the singers as each day required. 24 And Peth·a·hi′ah the son of Me·shez′a·bel of the sons of Ze′rah the son of Judah was at the side of the king for every matter of the people.

25 And as regards the settlements in their fields, there were some of the sons of Judah that dwelt in Kir′i·ath-ar′ba and its dependent towns and in Di′bon and its dependent towns and in Je·kab′ze·el and its settlements, 26 and in Jesh′u·a and in Mo·la′dah and in Beth-pel′et 27 and in Ha′zar-shu′al and in Be′er-she′ba and its dependent towns 28 and in Zik′lag and in Me·co′nah and its dependent towns 29 and in En-rim′mon and in Zo′rah and in Jar′muth, 30 Za·no′ah, A·dul′lam and their settlements, La′chish and its fields, A·ze′kah and its dependent towns. And they took up camping from Be′er-she′ba clear to the valley of Hin′nom.

31 And the sons of Benjamin were from Ge′ba, Mich′mash and Ai′ja and Beth′el and its dependent towns, 32 An′a·thoth, Nob, A·na·ni′ah, 33 Ha′zor, Ra′mah, Git′ta·im, 34 Ha′did, Ze·bo′im, Ne·bal′lat, 35 Lod and O′no, the valley of the craftsmen. 36 And of the Levites there were divisions of Judah for Benjamin.

Esther

2 After these things, when the rage of King A·has·u·e′rus had subsided, he remembered Vash′ti and what she had done and what had been decided against her. 2 Then the king’s attendants, his ministers, said: “Let them seek young women, virgins, beautiful in appearance, for the king, 3 and let the king appoint commissioners in all the jurisdictional districts of his realm, and let them collect together all the young women, virgins, beautiful in appearance, at Shu′shan the castle, at the house of the women in charge of Heg′a·i the king’s eunuch, the guardian of the women; and let there be a giving of their massages. 4 And that young woman who seems pleasing in the king’s eyes will be queen instead of Vash′ti.” And the thing was pleasing in the king’s eyes, and he proceeded to do that way.

5 A certain man, a Jew, happened to be in Shu′shan the castle, and his name was Mor′de·cai the son of Ja′ir the son of Shim′e·i the son of Kish a Ben′ja·min·ite, 6 who had been taken into exile from Jerusalem with the deported people who were taken into exile with Jec·o·ni′ah the king of Judah whom Neb·u·chad·nez′zar the king of Babylon took into exile. 7 And he came to be the caretaker of Ha·das′sah, that is, Esther, the daughter of his father’s brother, for she had neither father nor mother; and the young woman was pretty in form and beautiful in appearance, and at the death of her father and her mother Mor′de·cai took her as his daughter. 8 And it came about that, when the king’s word and his law were heard, and when many young women were collected together at Shu′shan the castle in charge of Heg′a·i, then Esther was taken to the king’s house in charge of Heg′a·i the guardian of the women.

9 Now the young woman was pleasing in his eyes, so that she gained loving-kindness before him and he made haste to give her her massages and her appropriate food, and to give her seven selected young women from the king’s house, and he proceeded to transfer her and her young women to the best place of the house of the women. 10 Esther had not told about her people or about her relatives, for Mor′de·cai himself had laid the command upon her that she should not tell. 11 And day after day Mor′de·cai was walking before the courtyard of the house of the women to know of Esther’s welfare and what was being done with her.

12 And when the turn of each young woman arrived to go in to King A·has·u·e′rus after it had happened to her according to the women’s regulation for twelve months, for that was the way the days of their massage procedure were gradually fulfilled, six months with oil of myrrh and six months with balsam oil and with the massages of the women; 13 then on these conditions the young woman herself came in to the king. Everything that she would mention would be given her, to come with her from the house of the women to the king’s house. 14 In the evening she herself came in, and in the morning she herself returned to the second house of the women in charge of Sha·ash′gaz the king’s eunuch, the guardian of the concubines. She would not come in anymore to the king unless the king had taken delight in her and she had been called by name.

15 And when the turn of Esther the daughter of Ab′i·ha·il the uncle of Mor′de·cai, whom he had taken as his daughter, arrived to come in to the king, she did not request anything except what Heg′a·i the king’s eunuch, the guardian of the women, proceeded to mention (all the while Esther was continually gaining favor in the eyes of everyone seeing her). 16 Then Esther was taken to King A·has·u·e′rus at his royal house in the tenth month, that is, the month Te′beth, in the seventh year of his reign. 17 And the king came to love Esther more than all the other women, so that she gained more favor and loving-kindness before him than all the other virgins. And he proceeded to put the royal headdress upon her head and make her queen instead of Vash′ti. 18 And the king went on to hold a great banquet for all his princes and his servants, the banquet of Esther; and an amnesty for the jurisdictional districts he granted, and he kept giving presents according to the means of the king.

19 Now when virgins were collected together a second time, Mor′de·cai was sitting in the king’s gate. 20 Esther was not telling about her relatives and her people, just as Mor′de·cai had laid the command upon her; and the saying of Mor′de·cai Esther was performing, just as when she happened to be under care by him.

21 In those days while Mor′de·cai was sitting in the king’s gate, Big′than and Te′resh, two court officials of the king, doorkeepers, became indignant and kept seeking to lay hand on King A·has·u·e′rus. 22 And the thing came to be known to Mor′de·cai, and he immediately told Esther the queen. In turn Esther talked to the king in Mor′de·cai’s name. 23 So the matter was sought out and eventually found out, and both of them got to be hanged on a stake; after which it was written in the book of the affairs of the days before the king.

Esther

7 Then the king and Ha′man came in to banquet with Esther the queen. 2 The king now said to Esther also on the second day during the banquet of wine: “What is your petition, O Esther the queen? Let it even be given to you. And what is your request? To the half of the kingship—let it even be done!” 3 At this Esther the queen answered and said: “If I have found favor in your eyes, O king, and if to the king it does seem good, let there be given me my own soul at my petition and my people at my request. 4 For we have been sold, I and my people, to be annihilated, killed and destroyed. Now if we had been sold for mere men slaves and for mere maidservants, I should have kept silent. But the distress is not appropriate when with damage to the king.”

5 King A·has·u·e′rus now said, yes, he went on to say to Esther the queen: “Who is this, and just where is the one who has emboldened himself to do that way?” 6 Then Esther said: “The man, the adversary and enemy, is this bad Ha′man.”

As for Ha′man, he became terrified because of the king and the queen. 7 As for the king, he rose up in his rage from the banquet of wine to go to the garden of the palace; and Ha′man himself stood up to make request for his soul from Esther the queen, for he saw that bad had been determined against him by the king. 8 And the king himself returned from the garden of the palace to the house of the wine banquet; and Ha′man was fallen upon the couch on which Esther was. Consequently the king said: “Is there also to be a raping of the queen, with me in the house?” The word itself went out of the king’s mouth, and Ha′man’s face they covered. 9 Har·bo′na, one of the court officials before the king, now said: “Also, there is the stake that Ha′man made for Mor′de·cai, who had spoken good concerning the king, standing in Ha′man’s house—fifty cubits high.” At that the king said: “YOU men, hang him on it.” 10 And they proceeded to hang Ha′man on the stake that he had prepared for Mor′de·cai; and the king’s rage itself subsided.

Job

1 There happened to be a man in the land of Uz whose name was Job; and that man proved to be blameless and upright, and fearing God and turning aside from bad. 2 And seven sons and three daughters came to be born to him. 3 And his livestock got to be seven thousand sheep and three thousand camels and five hundred spans of cattle and five hundred she-asses, along with a very large body of servants; and that man came to be the greatest of all the Orientals.

4 And his sons went and held a banquet at the house of each one on his own day; and they sent and invited their three sisters to eat and drink with them. 5 And it would occur that when the banquet days had gone round the circuit, Job would send and sanctify them; and he got up early in the morning and offered up burnt sacrifices according to the number of all of them; for, said Job, “maybe my sons have sinned and have cursed God in their heart.” That is the way Job would do always.

6 Now it came to be the day when the sons of the true God entered to take their station before Jehovah, and even Satan proceeded to enter right among them.

7 Then Jehovah said to Satan: “Where do you come from?” At that Satan answered Jehovah and said: “From roving about in the earth and from walking about in it.” 8 And Jehovah went on to say to Satan: “Have you set your heart upon my servant Job, that there is no one like him in the earth, a man blameless and upright, fearing God and turning aside from bad?” 9 At that Satan answered Jehovah and said: “Is it for nothing that Job has feared God? 10 Have not you yourself put up a hedge about him and about his house and about everything that he has all around? The work of his hands you have blessed, and his livestock itself has spread abroad in the earth. 11 But, for a change, thrust out your hand, please, and touch everything he has and see whether he will not curse you to your very face.” 12 Accordingly Jehovah said to Satan: “Look! Everything that he has is in your hand. Only against him himself do not thrust out your hand!” So Satan went out away from the person of Jehovah.

13 Now it came to be the day when his sons and his daughters were eating and drinking wine in the house of their brother the firstborn. 14 And there came a messenger to Job, and he proceeded to say: “The cattle themselves happened to be plowing and the she-asses were grazing at the side of them 15 when the Sa·be′ans came making a raid and taking them, and the attendants they struck down with the edge of the sword; and I got to escape, only I by myself, to tell you.”

16 While this one was yet speaking that one came and proceeded to say: “The very fire of God fell from the heavens and went blazing among the sheep and the attendants and eating them up; and I got to escape, only I by myself, to tell you.”

17 While that one was yet speaking another one came and proceeded to say: “The Chal·de′ans made up three bands and went dashing against the camels and taking them, and the attendants they struck down with the edge of the sword; and I got to escape, only I by myself, to tell you.”

18 While this other one was yet speaking, still another one came and proceeded to say: “Your sons and your daughters were eating and drinking wine in the house of their brother the firstborn. 19 And, look! there came a great wind from the region of the wilderness, and it went striking the four corners of the house, so that it fell upon the young people and they died. And I got to escape, only I by myself, to tell you.”

20 And Job proceeded to get up and rip his sleeveless coat apart and cut the hair off his head and fall to the earth and bow down 21 and say:

“Naked I came out of my mother’s belly,

And naked shall I return there.

Jehovah himself has given, and Jehovah himself has taken away.

Let the name of Jehovah continue to be blessed.”

22 In all this Job did not sin or ascribe anything improper to God.

Job

6 And Job proceeded to answer and say:

2 “O that my vexation were altogether weighed,

And that at the same time my adversity they would put on scales themselves!

3 For now it is heavier even than the sands of the seas.

That is why my own words have been wild talk.

4 For the arrows of the Almighty are with me,

The venom of which my spirit is drinking;

The terrors from God range themselves up against me.

5 Will a zebra cry out over grass,

Or a bull low over its fodder?

6 Will tasteless things be eaten without salt,

Or is there any taste in the slimy juice of marshmallow?

7 My soul has refused to touch anything.

They are like disease in my food.

8 O that my request would come

And that God would grant even my hope!

9 And that God would go ahead and crush me,

That he would release his hand and cut me off!

10 Even it would still be my comfort;

And I should leap for joy at my labor pains,

Though he would have no compassion, for I have not hidden the sayings of the Holy One.

11 What is my power, that I should keep waiting?

And what is my end, that I should keep prolonging my soul?

12 Is my power the power of stones?

Or is my flesh of copper?

13 Is it that self-assistance is not in me,

And effectual working itself has been chased away from me?

14 As regards anyone who withholds loving-kindness from his own fellow,

He will also leave off even the fear of the Almighty.

15 My own brothers have dealt treacherously, like a winter torrent,

Like the channel of winter torrents that keep passing away.

16 They are dark from ice,

Upon them snow hides itself.

17 In due season they become waterless, they have been silenced;

When it grows hot they are dried up from their place.

18 The paths of their way are turned aside;

They go up into the empty place and perish.

19 The caravans of Te′ma have looked,

The traveling company of Sa·be′ans have waited for them.

20 They certainly are ashamed because they had trusted;

They have come clear to the place and they get disappointed.

21 For now YOU men have amounted to nothing;

YOU see terror, and YOU become afraid.

22 Is it because I have said, ‘GIVE me something,

Or from some of the power of YOU men make a present in my behalf;

23 And rescue me out of the hand of an adversary,

And out of the hand of tyrants YOU men should redeem me’?

24 Instruct me, and I, for my part, shall be silent;

And what mistake I have committed make me understand.

25 The sayings of uprightness have been—O not painful!

But what does reproving on the part of YOU men reprove?

26 Is it to reprove words that YOU men scheme,

When the sayings of one in despair are for mere wind?

27 How much more will YOU cast lots even over someone fatherless,

And barter over YOUR companion!

28 And now GO ahead, pay attention to me,

And see whether I shall lie to YOUR very faces.

29 Return, please—let no unrighteousness arise—

Yes, return—my righteousness is yet in it.

30 Is there unrighteousness on my tongue,

Or does my own palate not discern adversity?

Job

12 And Job proceeded to answer and say:

2 “For a fact YOU men are the people,

And with YOU wisdom will die out!

3 I too have a heart as well as YOU.

I am not inferior to YOU,

And with whom are there not things like these?

4 One who is a laughingstock to his fellowman I become,

One calling to God that he should answer him.

A laughingstock is the righteous, unblamable one.

5 In thought, the carefree one has contempt for extinction itself;

It is made ready for those of wobbling feet.

6 The tents of the despoilers are unworried,

And the ones enraging God have the safety

Belonging to one who has brought a god in his hand.

7 However, ask, please, the domestic animals, and they will instruct you;

Also the winged creatures of the heavens, and they will tell you.

8 Or show your concern to the earth, and it will instruct you;

And the fishes of the sea will declare it to you.

9 Who among all these does not well know

That the hand of Jehovah itself has done this,

10 In whose hand is the soul of everyone alive

And the spirit of all flesh of man?

11 Does not the ear itself test out words

As the palate tastes food?

12 Is there not wisdom among the aged

And understanding in length of days?

13 With him there are wisdom and mightiness;

He has counsel and understanding.

14 Look! He tears down, that there may be no building up;

He makes it shut to man, that it may not be opened up.

15 Look! He puts a restraint upon the waters and they dry up;

And he sends them, and they change the earth.

16 With him there are strength and practical wisdom;

To him belong the one making a mistake and the one leading astray;

17 He is making counselors go barefoot,

And he makes judges themselves go crazy.

18 The bonds of kings he actually loosens,

And he binds a belt upon their hips.

19 He is making priests walk barefoot,

And permanently seated ones he subverts;

20 He is removing speech from the faithful ones,

And the sensibleness of old men he takes away;

21 He is pouring out contempt upon nobles,

And the girdle of powerful ones he actually weakens;

22 He is uncovering deep things from the darkness,

And he brings forth to the light deep shadow;

23 Making the nations grow great, that he may destroy them;

Spreading out the nations, that he may lead them away;

24 Taking away the heart of the head ones of the people of the land,

That he may make them wander about in an empty place, where there is no way.

25 They grope in darkness, where there is no light,

That he may make them wander about like a drunken man.

Job

17 “My very spirit has been broken, my own days have been extinguished;

The graveyard is for me.

2 Certainly there is mockery at me,

And amid their rebellious behavior my eye lodges.

3 Please, do put my security with yourself.

Who else is there that will shake hands with me in pledge?

4 For their heart you have closed to discretion.

That is why you do not exalt them.

5 He may tell companions to take their shares,

But the very eyes of his sons will fail.

6 And he has set me forth as a proverbial saying of peoples,

So that I become someone into whose face to spit.

7 And from vexation my eye grows dimmer

And my members are all of them like the shadow.

8 Upright people stare in amazement at this,

And even the innocent one gets excited over the apostate.

9 The righteous one keeps holding fast to his way,

And the one with clean hands keeps increasing in strength.

10 However, YOU men may all of YOU resume. So come on, please,

As I do not find anyone wise among YOU.

11 My own days have passed along, my own plans have been torn apart,

The wishes of my heart.

12 Night they keep putting for day:

‘Light is near on account of darkness.’

13 If I keep waiting, She′ol is my house;

In the darkness I shall have to spread out my lounge.

14 To the pit I shall have to call out, ‘You are my father!’

To the maggot, ‘My mother and my sister!’

15 So where, then, is my hope?

And my hope—who is it that beholds it?

16 To the bars of She′ol they will go down,

When we, all together, must descend to the very dust.”

Job

24 “Why is it that times have not been stored up by the Almighty himself,

And the very ones knowing him have not beheld his days?

2 There are those who move back boundary marks;

A drove they have snatched away, that they may shepherd it.

3 They drive off even the male ass of fatherless boys;

They seize the widow’s bull as a pledge.

4 They turn aside the poor ones from the way;

At the same time the afflicted of the earth have kept themselves hidden.

5 Look! As zebras in the wilderness

They have gone forth in their activity, looking for food.

The desert plain gives to each one bread for the boys.

6 In the field its fodder they harvest,

And the vineyard of the wicked one they hastily despoil.

7 Naked, they pass the night without a garment,

And without any covering in the cold.

8 From the rainstorm of the mountains they get drenched,

And because there is no shelter they have to hug a rock.

9 They snatch away a fatherless boy even from the breast,

And what is on the afflicted one they take as a pledge.

10 Naked, they have to go about without a garment,

And, hungry, they have to carry the reaped ears.

11 Between the terrace walls they pass the noontime;

Winepresses they have to tread, and yet they go thirsty.

12 From out of the city the dying keep groaning,

And the soul of deadly wounded ones cries for help;

And God himself considers it not as anything improper.

13 As for them, they proved to be among the rebels against light;

They did not recognize its ways,

And they did not dwell in its roadways.

14 At daylight the murderer gets up,

He proceeds to slay the afflicted and the poor one;

And during the night he becomes a regular thief.

15 As for the eye of the adulterer, it has watched for evening darkness,

Saying, ‘No eye will behold me!’

And over his face he puts a covering.

16 In the darkness he has dug into houses;

By day they must keep themselves locked in.

They have not known daylight.

17 For morning is the same as deep shadow for them,

For they recognize what the sudden terrors of deep shadow are.

18 He is swift on the surface of the waters.

Their tract of land will be cursed in the earth.

He will not turn toward the way of the vineyards.

19 The drought, also the heat, snatch away the snow waters;

So does She′ol those who have sinned!

20 The womb will forget him, the maggot will sweetly suck him,

He will be remembered no more.

And unrighteousness will be broken just like a tree.

21 He is having dealings with a barren woman who does not bear,

And with a widow, to whom he does no good.

22 And he will certainly draw away strong people by his power;

He will rise up and not be sure of his life.

23 He will grant him to become confident that he may support himself;

And his eyes will be upon their ways.

24 They have become high up a little while, then they are no more,

And they have been brought low; like everyone else they are plucked off,

And like the head of an ear of grain they are cut off.

25 So really now, who will make me out a liar

Or reduce my word to nothing?”

Job

28 “Indeed, for silver there exists a place to find it

And a place for gold that they refine;

2 Iron itself is taken from the very dust

And from stone copper is being poured out.

3 An end to the darkness he has set;

And to every limit he is searching out

Stone in the gloom and deep shadow.

4 He has sunk a shaft far from where people reside as aliens,

Places forgotten far from the foot;

Some of mortal men have swung down, they have dangled.

5 As for the earth, out of it food goes forth;

But underneath it, it has been upturned as if by fire.

6 Its stones are the place of the sapphire,

And it has gold dust.

7 A pathway—no bird of prey has known it,

Nor has the eye of a black kite caught sight of it.

8 The majestic wild beasts have not trodden it down solid;

The young lion has not paced over it.

9 Upon the flint he has thrust out his hand;

He has overthrown mountains from their root;

10 Into the rocks he has channeled water-filled galleries,

And all precious things his eye has seen.

11 The places from which rivers trickled he has dammed up,

And the concealed thing he brings forth to the light.

12 But wisdom—where can it be found,

And where, now, is the place of understanding?

13 Mortal man has not come to know its valuation,

And it is not found in the land of those living.

14 The watery deep itself has said,

‘It is not in me!’

The sea too has said, ‘It is not with me!’

15 Pure gold cannot be given in exchange for it,

And silver cannot be weighed out as its price.

16 It cannot be paid for with gold of O′phir,

With the rare onyx stone and the sapphire.

17 Gold and glass cannot be compared to it,

Nor is any vessel of refined gold an exchange for it.

18 Coral and rock crystal themselves will not be mentioned,

But a bagful of wisdom is worth more than one full of pearls.

19 The topaz of Cush cannot be compared to it;

It cannot be paid for even with gold in its purity.

20 But wisdom itself—from where does it come,

And where, now, is the place of understanding?

21 It has been hidden even from the eyes of everyone alive,

And from the flying creatures of the heavens it has been concealed.

22 Destruction and death themselves have said,

‘With our ears we have heard a report of it.’

23 God is the One who has understood its way,

And he himself has known its place,

24 For he himself looks to the very ends of the earth;

Under the whole heavens he sees,

25 To make a weight for the wind,

While he has proportioned the waters themselves by a measure;

26 When he made for the rain a regulation,

And a way for the thunderous storm cloud,

27 Then it was that he saw wisdom and proceeded to tell about it;

He prepared it and also searched it through.

28 And he went on to say to man,

‘Look! The fear of Jehovah—that is wisdom,

And to turn away from bad is understanding.’”

Job

29 And Job proceeded again to lift up his proverbial utterance and went on to say:

2 “O that I were as in the lunar months of long ago,

As in the days when God was guarding me;

3 When he caused his lamp to shine upon my head,

When I would walk through darkness by his light;

4 Just as I happened to be in the days of my prime,

When intimacy with God was at my tent;

5 When the Almighty was yet with me,

When my attendants were all around me!

6 When I washed my steps in butter,

And the rock kept pouring out streams of oil for me;

7 When I went forth to the gate by the town,

In the public square I would prepare my seat!

8 The boys saw me and hid themselves,

And even the aged ones rose up, they stood.

9 Princes themselves restrained words,

And the palm they would put upon their mouth.

10 The voice of the leaders themselves was hidden,

And their very tongue cleaved to their palate.

11 For the ear itself listened and proceeded to pronounce me happy,

And the eye itself saw and proceeded to bear witness for me.

12 For I would rescue the afflicted one crying for help,

And the fatherless boy and anyone that had no helper.

13 The blessing of the one about to perish—upon me it would come,

And the heart of the widow I would make glad.

14 With righteousness I clothed myself, and it was clothing me.

My justice was like a sleeveless coat—and a turban.

15 Eyes I became to the blind one;

And feet to the lame one I was.

16 I was a real father to the poor ones;

And the legal case of one whom I did not know—I would examine it.

17 And I would break the jawbones of the wrongdoer,

And from his teeth I would tear away the prey.

18 And I used to say, ‘Within my nest I shall expire,

And like the grains of sand I shall multiply my days.

19 My root is opened for the waters,

And dew itself will stay overnight upon my bough.

20 My glory is fresh with me,

And my bow in my hand will shoot repeatedly.’

21 To me they listened; and they waited,

And they would keep silent for my counsel.

22 After my word they would not speak again,

And upon them my word would drip.

23 And they waited for me as for the rain,

And their mouth they opened wide for the spring rain.

24 I would smile at them—they would not believe it—

And the light of my face they would not cast down.

25 I would choose the way for them, and I was sitting as head;

And I resided as a king among his troops,

As one who comforts the mourners.

Job

30 “And now they have laughed at me,

Those younger in days than I am,

Whose fathers I would have refused

To place with the dogs of my flock.

2 Even the power of their hands—of what use was it to me?

In them vigor has perished.

3 Because of want and hunger they are sterile,

Gnawing at a waterless region,

Where yesterday there were storm and desolation.

4 They were plucking the salt herb by the bushes,

And the root of broom trees was their food.

5 From the community they would be driven away;

People would shout at them as at a thief.

6 They have to reside on the very slope of torrent valleys,

In holes of the dust and in rocks.

7 Among the bushes they would cry out;

Under the nettles they would huddle together.

8 Sons of the senseless one, also sons of the nameless one,

They have been scourged out of the land.

9 And now I have become even the theme of their song,

And I am to them for a byword.

10 They have detested me, they have kept themselves far from me;

And from my face they did not hold back their spit.

11 For he loosened my own bowstring and proceeded to humble me,

And the bridle they left loose on my account.

12 At my right hand they rise up as a brood;

My feet they have let go,

But they proceeded to cast up against me their disastrous barriers.

13 They have torn down my roadways;

They were beneficial only for adversity to me,

Without their having any helper.

14 As through a wide gap they proceed to come;

Under a storm they have rolled along.

15 Sudden terrors have been turned upon me;

My noble bearing is chased like the wind,

And like a cloud my salvation has passed away.

16 And now my soul is poured out within me;

Days of affliction take hold upon me.

17 At night my very bones have been bored through and dropped from off me,

And pains gnawing me do not take any rest.

18 By the abundance of power my garment takes on a change;

Like the collar of my long garment it engirdles me.

19 He has brought me down to the clay,

So that I show myself like dust and ashes.

20 I cry to you for help, but you do not answer me;

I have stood, that you might show yourself attentive to me.

21 You change yourself to become cruel to me;

With the full might of your hand you harbor animosity toward me.

22 You lift me to the wind, you cause me to ride it;

Then you dissolve me with a crash.

23 For I well know that to death you will make me turn back,

And to the house of meeting for everyone living.

24 Only no one thrusts his hand out against a mere heap of ruins,

Nor during one’s decay is there a cry for help respecting those things.

25 Certainly I have wept for the one having a hard day;

My soul has grieved for the poor one.

26 Although for good I waited, yet bad came;

And I kept awaiting the light, but gloom came.

27 My own intestines were made to boil and did not keep silent;

Days of affliction confronted me.

28 Saddened I walked about when there was no sunlight;

I got up in the congregation, I kept crying for help.

29 A brother to jackals I became,

And a companion to the daughters of the ostrich.

30 My very skin became black and dropped off me,

And my very bones became hot from dryness.

31 And my harp came to be merely for mourning,

And my pipe for the voice of weeping ones.

Job

35 And E·li′hu continued answering and saying:

2 “Is this what you have regarded as justice?

You have said, ‘My righteousness is more than God’s.’

3 For you say, ‘Of what use is it to you?

What benefit do I have more than by my sinning?’

4 I myself shall reply to you

And to your companions with you.

5 Look up to heaven and see,

And behold the clouds, that they are indeed higher than you.

6 If you actually sin, what do you accomplish against him?

And if your revolts actually increase, what do you do to him?

7 If you are really in the right, what do you give him,

Or what does he receive from your own hand?

8 Your wickedness may be against a man like you,

And your righteousness to a son of earthling man.

9 Because of the multitude of oppressions they keep calling for aid;

They keep crying for help because of the arm of the great ones.

10 And yet no one has said, ‘Where is God my Grand Maker,

The One giving melodies in the night?’

11 He is the One teaching us more than the beasts of the earth,

And he makes us wiser than even the flying creatures of the heavens.

12 There they keep crying out, but he does not answer,

Because of the pride of the bad ones.

13 Only the untruth God does not hear,

And the Almighty himself does not behold it.

14 How much less, then, when you say you do not behold him!

The legal case is before him, and so you should wait anxiously for him.

15 And now because his anger has not called for an accounting,

He has also not taken note of the extreme rashness.

16 And Job himself opens his mouth wide simply for nothing;

Without knowledge he multiplies mere words.”

Job

37 “Indeed at this my heart begins to tremble,

And it leaps up from its place.

2 Listen attentively, YOU men, to the rumbling of his voice,

And the growling that goes forth from his mouth.

3 Under the whole heavens he lets it loose,

And his lightning is to the extremities of the earth.

4 After it a sound roars;

He thunders with the sound of his superiority,

And he does not hold them back when his voice is heard.

5 God thunders with his voice in a wonderful way,

Doing great things that we cannot know.

6 For to the snow he says, ‘Fall earthward,’

And to the downpour of rain, even to the downpour of his strong rains.

7 On the hand of every earthling man he puts a seal

For every mortal man to know his work.

8 And the wild beast comes into the ambush,

And in its hiding places it dwells.

9 Out of the interior room comes the storm wind

And out of the north winds the cold.

10 By the breath of God the ice is given

And the breadth of waters is under constraint.

11 Yes, with moisture he burdens the cloud,

His light scatters the cloud mass,

12 And it is being turned round about by his steering them for their performance

Wherever he commands them upon the face of the productive land of the earth.

13 Whether for a rod or for his land

Or for loving-kindness, he makes it produce effects.

14 Do give ear to this, O Job;

Stand still and show yourself attentive to the wonderful works of God.

15 Do you know when God laid an appointment upon them,

And when he caused the light of his cloud to beam?

16 Do you know about the poisings of the cloud,

The wonderful works of the One perfect in knowledge?

17 How your garments are hot

When the earth shows quietness from the south?

18 With him can you beat out the skies

Hard like a molten mirror?

19 Let us know what we should say to him;

We cannot produce words because of darkness.

20 Should it be related to him that I would speak?

Or has any man said that it will be communicated?

21 And now they do not really see the light;

It is brilliant in the skies,

When a wind itself has passed by and proceeded to cleanse them.

22 Out of the north golden splendor comes.

Upon God dignity is fear-inspiring.

23 As for the Almighty, we have not found him out;

He is exalted in power,

And justice and abundance of righteousness he will not belittle.

24 Therefore let men fear him.

He does not regard any who are wise in their own heart.”

Psalms

A mik′tam of David.

16 Keep me, O God, for I have taken refuge in you.

2 I have said to Jehovah: “You are Jehovah; my goodness is, not for your sake,

3 But to the holy ones that are in the earth.

They, even the majestic ones, are the ones in whom is all my delight.”

4 Pains become many to those who, when there is someone else, do hurry after him.

I shall not pour out their drink offerings of blood,

And I shall not carry their names upon my lips.

5 Jehovah is the portion of my allotted share and of my cup.

You are holding fast my lot.

6 The measuring lines themselves have fallen for me in pleasant places.

Really, my own possession has proved agreeable to me.

7 I shall bless Jehovah, who has given me advice.

Really, during the nights my kidneys have corrected me.

8 I have placed Jehovah in front of me constantly.

Because he is at my right hand, I shall not be made to totter.

9 Therefore my heart does rejoice, and my glory is inclined to be joyful.

Also, my own flesh will reside in security.

10 For you will not leave my soul in She′ol.

You will not allow your loyal one to see the pit.

11 You will cause me to know the path of life.

Rejoicing to satisfaction is with your face;

There is pleasantness at your right hand forever.

Psalms

A melody of David.

29 Ascribe to Jehovah, O YOU sons of strong ones,

Ascribe to Jehovah glory and strength.

2 Ascribe to Jehovah the glory of his name.

Bow down to Jehovah in holy adornment.

3 The voice of Jehovah is over the waters;

The glorious God himself has thundered.

Jehovah is over many waters.

4 The voice of Jehovah is powerful;

The voice of Jehovah is splendid.

5 The voice of Jehovah is breaking the cedars;

Yes, Jehovah breaks the cedars of Leb′a·non in pieces,

6 And he makes them skip about like a calf,

Leb′a·non and Sir′i·on like the sons of wild bulls.

7 The voice of Jehovah is hewing with the flames of fire;

8 The voice of Jehovah itself makes the wilderness writhe,

Jehovah makes the wilderness of Ka′desh writhe.

9 The voice of Jehovah itself makes the hinds writhe with birth pains

And strips bare the forests.

And in his temple each one is saying: “Glory!”

10 Upon the deluge Jehovah has seated himself;

And Jehovah sits as king to time indefinite.

11 Jehovah himself will give strength indeed to his people.

Jehovah himself will bless his people with peace.

Psalms

To the director. Of Jehovah’s servant, David.

36 The utterance of transgression to the wicked one is in the midst of his heart;

There is no dread of God in front of his eyes.

2 For he has acted too smoothly to himself in his own eyes

To find out his error so as to hate it.

3 The words of his mouth are hurtfulness and deception;

He has ceased to have insight for doing good.

4 Hurtfulness is what he keeps scheming upon his bed.

He stations himself on a way that is not good.

What is bad he does not reject.

5 O Jehovah, your loving-kindness is in the heavens;

Your faithfulness is up to the clouds.

6 Your righteousness is like mountains of God;

Your judicial decision is a vast watery deep.

Man and beast you save, O Jehovah.

7 How precious your loving-kindness is, O God!

And in the shadow of your wings the sons of men themselves take refuge.

8 They drink their fill of the fatness of your house;

And of the torrent of your pleasures you cause them to drink.

9 For with you is the source of life;

By light from you we can see light.

10 Continue your loving-kindness to those knowing you,

And your righteousness to those upright in heart.

11 O may not the foot of haughtiness come against me;

As for the hand of wicked people, let it not make me a wanderer.

12 There the practicers of hurtfulness have fallen;

They have been pushed down and have been unable to get up.

Psalms

To the director of Je·du′thun. A melody of David.

39 I said: “I will guard my ways

To keep from sinning with my tongue.

I will set a muzzle as a guard to my own mouth,

As long as anyone wicked is in front of me.”

2 I became speechless with silence;

I kept quiet from what is good,

And my being pained was ostracized.

3 My heart grew hot inside me;

During my sighing the fire kept burning.

I spoke with my tongue:

4 “Cause me, O Jehovah, to know my end,

And the measure of my days—what it is,

That I may know how transient I am.

5 Look! You have made my days just a few;

And my life’s duration is as nothing in front of you.

Surely every earthling man, though standing firm, is nothing but an exhalation. Se′lah.

6 Surely in a semblance man walks about.

Surely they are boisterous in vain.

One piles up things and does not know who will be gathering them.

7 And now for what have I hoped, O Jehovah?

My expectation is toward you.

8 From all my transgressions deliver me.

Do not set me as a reproach of the senseless one.

9 I kept speechless; I could not open my mouth,

For you yourself acted.

10 Remove from off me your plague.

Due to the hostility of your hand I myself have come to an end.

11 By reproofs against error you have corrected man,

And you consume his desirable things just as a moth does.

Surely every earthling man is an exhalation. Se′lah.

12 Do hear my prayer, O Jehovah,

And to my cry for help do give ear.

At my tears do not keep silent.

For I am but an alien resident with you,

A settler the same as all my forefathers.

13 Look away from me, that I may brighten up

Before I go away and I am not.”

Psalms

To the director. A melody of David.

64 Hear, O God, my voice in my concern.

From the dreadfulness of the enemy may you safeguard my life.

2 May you conceal me from the confidential talk of evildoers,

From the tumult of practicers of hurtfulness,

3 Who have sharpened their tongue just like a sword,

Who have aimed their arrow, bitter speech,

4 To shoot from concealed places at someone blameless.

All of a sudden they shoot at him and do not fear.

5 They hold themselves down to bad speech;

They make statements about hiding traps.

They have said: “Who sees them?”

6 They keep searching out unrighteous things;

They have hidden a shrewd device well searched out,

And the inward part of each one, even his heart, is deep.

7 But God will shoot at them with an arrow suddenly.

Wounds have resulted to them,

8 And they cause one to stumble.

But their tongue is against their own selves.

All those looking upon them will shake their head,

9 And all earthling men will become afraid;

And they will tell of the activity of God,

And they will certainly have insight into his work.

10 And the righteous one will rejoice in Jehovah and will indeed take refuge in him;

And all the upright in heart will boast.

Psalms

To the director. A melody of David. A song.

65 For you there is praise—silence—, O God, in Zion;

And to you the vow will be paid.

2 O Hearer of prayer, even to you people of all flesh will come.

3 Things of error have proved mightier than I am.

As for our transgressions, you yourself will cover them.

4 Happy is the one you choose and cause to approach,

That he may reside in your courtyards.

We will certainly be satisfied with the goodness of your house,

The holy place of your temple.

5 With fear-inspiring things in righteousness you will answer us,

O God of our salvation,

The Trust of all the borders of the earth and those far away on the sea.

6 He is firmly establishing the mountains with his power;

He is indeed girded with mightiness.

7 He is stilling the noise of the seas,

The noise of their waves and the turmoil of the national groups.

8 And the inhabitants of the uttermost parts will be afraid of your signs;

The goings forth of the morning and evening you cause to cry out joyfully.

9 You have turned your attention to the earth, that you may give it abundance;

You enrich it very much.

The stream from God is full of water.

You prepare their grain,

For that is the way you prepare the earth.

10 There is a drenching of its furrows, a leveling off of its clods;

With copious showers you soften it; you bless its very sprouts.

11 You have crowned the year with your goodness,

And your very tracks drip with fatness.

12 The pasture grounds of the wilderness keep dripping,

And with joyfulness the very hills gird themselves.

13 The pastures have become clothed with flocks,

And the low plains themselves are enveloped with grain.

They shout in triumph, yes, they sing.

Psalms

To the director on stringed instruments. A melody. Of A′saph. A song.

76 God is known in Judah;

In Israel his name is great.

2 And his covert proves to be in Sa′lem itself,

And his dwelling place in Zion.

3 There he broke the flaming shafts of the bow,

The shield and the sword and the battle. Se′lah.

4 You are enveloped with light, more majestic than the mountains of prey.

5 The ones powerful in heart have been despoiled,

They have drowsed away to their sleep,

And none of all the valiant men have found their hands.

6 From your rebuke, O God of Jacob, both the charioteer and the horse have fallen fast asleep.

7 You—fear-inspiring you are,

And who can stand before you because of the strength of your anger?

8 From heaven you caused the legal contest to be heard;

The earth itself feared and kept quiet

9 When God rose up to judgment,

To save all the meek of the earth. Se′lah.

10 For the very rage of man will laud you;

The remainder of raging you will gird upon yourself.

11 Vow and pay to Jehovah YOUR God, all YOU who are round about him.

Let them bring a gift in fear.

12 He will humble the spirit of leaders;

Fear-inspiring he is to the kings of the earth.

Psalms

For the director. Of the sons of Ko′rah. A melody.

85 You have taken pleasure, O Jehovah, in your land;

You have brought back the ones taken captive of Jacob.

2 You have pardoned the error of your people;

You have covered all their sin. Se′lah.

3 You have controlled all your fury;

You have turned back from the heat of your anger.

4 Gather us back, O God of our salvation,

And break off your vexation with us.

5 Is it to time indefinite that you will be incensed at us?

Will you draw out your anger to generation after generation?

6 Will you yourself not enliven us again,

That your people themselves may rejoice in you?

7 Show us, O Jehovah, your loving-kindness,

And your salvation may you give to us.

8 I will hear what the true God Jehovah will speak,

For he will speak peace to his people and to his loyal ones,

But let them not return to self-confidence.

9 Surely his salvation is near to those fearing him,

For glory to reside in our land.

10 As for loving-kindness and trueness, they have met each other;

Righteousness and peace—they have kissed each other.

11 Trueness itself will sprout out of the very earth,

And righteousness itself will look down from the very heavens.

12 Also, Jehovah, for his part, will give what is good,

And our own land will give its yield.

13 Before him righteousness itself will walk,

And it will make a way by his steppings.

Psalms

A melody, a song, for the sabbath day.

92 It is good to give thanks to Jehovah

And to make melody to your name, O Most High;

2 To tell in the morning about your loving-kindness

And about your faithfulness during the nights,

3 Upon a ten-stringed instrument and upon the lute,

By resounding music on the harp.

4 For you have made me rejoice, O Jehovah, because of your activity;

Because of the works of your hands I cry out joyfully.

5 How great your works are, O Jehovah!

Very deep your thoughts are.

6 No unreasoning man himself can know them,

And no one stupid can understand this.

7 When the wicked ones sprout as the vegetation

And all the practicers of what is hurtful blossom forth,

It is that they may be annihilated forever.

8 But you are on high to time indefinite, O Jehovah.

9 For, look! your enemies, O Jehovah,

For, look! your own enemies will perish;

All the practicers of what is hurtful will be separated from one another.

10 But you will exalt my horn like that of a wild bull;

I shall moisten myself with fresh oil.

11 And my eye will look on my foes;

My ears will hear about the very ones who rise up against me, the evildoers.

12 The righteous himself will blossom forth as a palm tree does;

As a cedar in Leb′a·non does, he will grow big.

13 Those who are planted in the house of Jehovah,

In the courtyards of our God, they will blossom forth.

14 They will still keep on thriving during gray-headedness,

Fat and fresh they will continue to be,

15 To tell that Jehovah is upright.

He is my Rock, in whom there is no unrighteousness.

Psalms

106 Praise Jah, YOU people!

Give thanks to Jehovah, for he is good;

For his loving-kindness is to time indefinite.

2 Who can utter the mighty performances of Jehovah,

Or can make all his praise to be heard?

3 Happy are those observing justice,

Doing righteousness all the time.

4 Remember me, O Jehovah, with the goodwill toward your people.

Take care of me with your salvation,

5 That I may see the goodness to your chosen ones,

That I may rejoice with the rejoicing of your nation,

That I may make my boast with your inheritance.

6 We have sinned just the same as our forefathers;

We have done wrong; we have acted wickedly.

7 As for our forefathers in Egypt,

They did not show any insight into your wonderful works.

They did not remember the abundance of your grand loving-kindness,

But they behaved rebelliously at the sea, by the Red Sea.

8 And he proceeded to save them for the sake of his name,

So as to make his mightiness known.

9 Accordingly he rebuked the Red Sea, and it was gradually dried up;

And he went walking them through the watery deep as through the wilderness;

10 And so he saved them from the hand of the hater

And reclaimed them from the hand of the enemy.

11 And the waters came covering their adversaries;

Not one of them was left.

12 Then they had faith in his word;

They began to sing his praise.

13 Quickly they forgot his works;

They did not wait for his counsel.

14 But they showed their selfish desire in the wilderness

And went putting God to the proof in the desert.

15 And he proceeded to give them their request

And to send a wasting disease into their soul.

16 And they began to envy Moses in the camp,

Even Aaron the holy one of Jehovah.

17 The earth then opened up and swallowed down Da′than,

And covered over the assembly of A·bi′ram.

18 And a fire went burning among their assembly;

A flame itself went devouring the wicked ones.

19 Furthermore, they made a calf in Ho′reb

And bowed down to a molten image,

20 So that they exchanged my glory

For a representation of a bull, an eater of vegetation.

21 They forgot God their Savior,

The Doer of great things in Egypt,

22 Wonderful works in the land of Ham,

Fear-inspiring things at the Red Sea.

23 And he was about to say to annihilate them,

If it had not been for Moses his chosen one,

Who stood in the gap before him,

To turn back his rage from bringing them to ruin.

24 And they got to contemning the desirable land;

They had no faith in his word.

25 And they kept grumbling in their tents;

They did not listen to the voice of Jehovah.

26 So he proceeded to raise his hand in an oath concerning them,

That he would make them fall in the wilderness,

27 And that he would make their offspring fall among the nations,

And that he would scatter them among the lands.

28 And they began to attach themselves to Ba′al of Pe′or

And to eat the sacrifices of the dead ones.

29 As they were causing offense by their dealings,

A scourge now broke out among them.

30 When Phin′e·has stood up and intervened,

Then the scourge was halted.

31 And it came to be counted to him as righteousness

For generation after generation to time indefinite.

32 Further, they caused provocation at the waters of Mer′i·bah,

So that it went badly with Moses by reason of them.

33 For they embittered his spirit

And he began to speak rashly with his lips.

34 They did not annihilate the peoples,

As Jehovah had said to them.

35 And they went mingling with the nations

And took up learning their works.

36 And they kept serving their idols,

And these came to be a snare to them.

37 And they would sacrifice their sons

And their daughters to demons.

38 So they kept spilling innocent blood,

The blood of their sons and their daughters,

Whom they sacrificed to the idols of Ca′naan;

And the land came to be polluted with bloodshed.

39 And they got to be unclean by their works

And kept having immoral intercourse by their dealings.

40 And the anger of Jehovah began to blaze against his people,

And he came to detest his inheritance.

41 And he repeatedly gave them into the hand of the nations,

That those hating them might rule over them,

42 And that their enemies might oppress them,

And that they might be subdued under their hand.

43 Many times he would deliver them,

But they themselves would behave rebelliously in their disobedient course,

And they would be brought low for their error.

44 And he would see the distress of theirs

When he heard their entreating cry.

45 And he would remember concerning them his covenant,

And he would feel regret according to the abundance of his grand loving-kindness.

46 And he would grant them to be objects of pity

Before all those holding them captive.

47 Save us, O Jehovah our God,

And collect us together from the nations

To give thanks to your holy name,

To speak exultingly in your praise.

48 Blessed be Jehovah the God of Israel

From time indefinite even to time indefinite;

And all the people must say Amen.

Praise Jah, YOU people!

Psalms

116 I do love, because Jehovah hears

My voice, my entreaties.

2 For he has inclined his ear to me,

And throughout my days I shall call.

3 The ropes of death encircled me

And the distressing circumstances of She′ol themselves found me.

Distress and grief I kept finding.

4 But upon the name of Jehovah I proceeded to call:

“Ah, Jehovah, do provide my soul with escape!”

5 Jehovah is gracious and righteous;

And our God is One showing mercy.

6 Jehovah is guarding the inexperienced ones.

I was impoverished, and he proceeded to save even me.

7 Return to your resting-place, O my soul,

For Jehovah himself has acted appropriately toward you.

8 For you have rescued my soul from death,

My eye from tears, my foot from stumbling.

9 I will walk before Jehovah in the lands of those living.

10 I had faith, for I proceeded to speak.

I myself was very much afflicted.

11 I, for my part, said, when I became panicky:

“Every man is a liar.”

12 What shall I repay to Jehovah

For all his benefits to me?

13 The cup of grand salvation I shall take up,

And on the name of Jehovah I shall call.

14 My vows I shall pay to Jehovah,

Yes, in front of all his people.

15 Precious in the eyes of Jehovah

Is the death of his loyal ones.

16 Ah, now, O Jehovah,

For I am your servant.

I am your servant, the son of your slave girl.

You have loosened my bands.

17 To you I shall offer the sacrifice of thanksgiving,

And on the name of Jehovah I shall call.

18 My vows I shall pay to Jehovah,

Yes, in front of all his people,

19 In the courtyards of the house of Jehovah,

In the midst of you, O Jerusalem.

Praise Jah, YOU people!

Psalms

A Song of the Ascents.

132 Remember, O Jehovah, concerning David

All his humiliations;

2 How he swore to Jehovah,

How he vowed to the Powerful One of Jacob:

3 “I will not go into the tent of my house.

I will not go up on the divan of my grand lounge,

4 I will not give sleep to my eyes,

Nor slumber to my own beaming eyes,

5 Until I find a place for Jehovah,

A grand tabernacle for the Powerful One of Jacob.”

6 Look! We have heard it in Eph′ra·thah,

We have found it in the fields of the forest.

7 Let us come into his grand tabernacle;

Let us bow down at his footstool.

8 Do arise, O Jehovah, to your resting-place,

You and the Ark of your strength.

9 Let your priests themselves be clothed with righteousness,

And let your own loyal ones cry out joyfully.

10 On account of David your servant,

Do not turn back the face of your anointed one.

11 Jehovah has sworn to David,

Truly he will not draw back from it:

“Of the fruitage of your belly

I shall set on your throne.

12 If your sons will keep my covenant

And my reminders that I shall teach them,

Their sons also forever

Will sit upon your throne.”

13 For Jehovah has chosen Zion;

He has longed for it as a dwelling for himself:

14 “This is my resting-place forever;

Here I shall dwell, for I have longed for it.

15 Its provisions I shall bless without fail.

Its poor ones I shall satisfy with bread.

16 And its priests I shall clothe with salvation;

And its loyal ones will without fail cry out joyfully.

17 There I shall cause the horn of David to grow.

I have set in order a lamp for my anointed one.

18 His enemies I shall clothe with shame;

But upon him his diadem will flourish.”

Proverbs

7 My son, keep my sayings, and may you treasure up my own commandments with you. 2 Keep my commandments and continue living, and my law like the pupil of your eyes. 3 Tie them upon your fingers, and write them upon the tablet of your heart. 4 Say to wisdom: “You are my sister”; and may you call understanding itself “Kinswoman,” 5 to guard you against the woman stranger, against the foreigner who has made her own sayings smooth. 6 For at the window of my house, through my lattice I looked down, 7 that I might peer upon the inexperienced ones. I was interested in discerning among the sons a young man in want of heart, 8 passing along on the street near her corner, and in the way to her house he marches, 9 in the twilight, in the evening of the day, at the approach of the night and the gloom. 10 And, look! there was a woman to meet him, with the garment of a prostitute and cunning of heart. 11 She is boisterous and stubborn. In her house her feet do not keep residing. 12 Now she is outdoors, now she is in the public squares, and near every corner she lies in wait. 13 And she has grabbed hold of him and given him a kiss. She has put on a bold face, and she begins to say to him:

14 “Communion sacrifices were incumbent upon me. Today I have paid my vows. 15 That is why I have come out to meet you, to look for your face, that I may find you. 16 With coverlets I have bedecked my divan, with many-colored things, linen of Egypt. 17 I have besprinkled my bed with myrrh, aloes and cinnamon. 18 Do come, let us drink our fill of love until the morning; do let us enjoy each other with love expressions. 19 For the husband is not in his house; he has gone traveling on a way of some distance. 20 A bag of money he has taken in his hand. On the day of the full moon he will come to his house.”

21 She has misled him by the abundance of her persuasiveness. By the smoothness of her lips she seduces him. 22 All of a sudden he is going after her, like a bull that comes even to the slaughter, and just as if fettered for the discipline of a foolish man, 23 until an arrow cleaves open his liver, just as a bird hastens into the trap, and he has not known that it involves his very soul.

24 And now, O sons, listen to me and pay attention to the sayings of my mouth. 25 May your heart not turn aside to her ways. Do not wander into her roadways. 26 For many are the ones she has caused to fall down slain, and all those being killed by her are numerous. 27 The ways to She′ol her house is; they are descending to the interior rooms of death.

Proverbs

11 A cheating pair of scales is something detestable to Jehovah, but a complete stone-weight is a pleasure to him.

2 Has presumptuousness come? Then dishonor will come; but wisdom is with the modest ones.

3 The integrity of the upright ones is what leads them, but distortion by those dealing treacherously will despoil them.

4 Valuable things will be of no benefit on the day of fury, but righteousness itself will deliver from death.

5 The righteousness of the blameless one is what will make his way straight, but in his own wickedness the wicked one will fall. 6 The righteousness of the upright ones is what will deliver them, but by their craving those dealing treacherously will themselves be caught.

7 When a wicked man dies, his hope perishes; and even expectation based on powerfulness has perished.

8 The righteous is the one rescued even from distress, and the wicked one comes in instead of him.

9 By his mouth the one who is an apostate brings his fellowman to ruin, but by knowledge are the righteous rescued.

10 Because of the goodness of the righteous ones a town is elated, but when the wicked ones perish there is a joyful cry.

11 Because of the blessing of the upright ones a town is exalted, but because of the mouth of the wicked ones it gets torn down.

12 The one in want of heart has despised his own fellowman, but the man of broad discernment is one that keeps silent.

13 The one walking about as a slanderer is uncovering confidential talk, but the one faithful in spirit is covering over a matter.

14 When there is no skillful direction, the people fall; but there is salvation in the multitude of counselors.

15 One will positively fare badly because he has gone surety for a stranger, but the one hating handshaking is keeping carefree.

16 A woman of charm is the one that takes hold of glory; but the tyrants, for their part, take hold of riches.

17 A man of loving-kindness is dealing rewardingly with his own soul, but the cruel person is bringing ostracism upon his own organism.

18 The wicked one is making false wages, but the one sowing righteousness, true earnings.

19 The one firmly standing for righteousness is in line for life, but the one chasing after what is bad is in line for his own death.

20 Those crooked at heart are something detestable to Jehovah, but the ones blameless in their way are a pleasure to him.

21 Though hand be to hand, a bad person will not go unpunished; but the offspring of the righteous ones will certainly escape.

22 As a gold nose ring in the snout of a pig, so is a woman that is pretty but that is turning away from sensibleness.

23 The desire of the righteous ones is surely good; the hope of the wicked ones is fury.

24 There exists the one that is scattering and yet is being increased; also the one that is keeping back from what is right, but it results only in want.

25 The generous soul will itself be made fat, and the one freely watering others will himself also be freely watered.

26 The one holding back grain—the populace will execrate him, but there is a blessing for the head of the one letting it be bought.

27 He that is looking for good will keep seeking goodwill; but as for the one searching for bad, it will come upon him.

28 The one trusting in his riches—he himself will fall; but just like foliage the righteous ones will flourish.

29 As for anyone bringing ostracism upon his own house, he will take possession of wind; and a foolish person will be a servant to the one wise in heart.

30 The fruitage of the righteous one is a tree of life, and he that is winning souls is wise.

31 Look! The righteous one—in the earth he will be rewarded. How much more should the wicked one and the sinner be!

Proverbs

25 These also are the proverbs of Sol′o·mon that the men of Hez·e·ki′ah the king of Judah transcribed:

2 The glory of God is the keeping of a matter secret, and the glory of kings is the searching through a matter.

3 The heavens for height and the earth for depth, and the heart of kings, that is unsearchable.

4 Let there be a removing of scummy dross from the silver, and all of it will come forth refined.

5 Let there be the removing of the wicked one before the king, and his throne will be firmly established by righteousness itself.

6 Do not do yourself honor before the king, and in the place of great ones do not stand. 7 For it is better for him to say to you: “Come up here,” than to abase you before a noble whom your eyes have seen.

8 Do not go forth to conduct a legal case hastily, that it may not be a question of what you will do in the culmination of it when your fellowman now humiliates you. 9 Plead your own cause with your fellowman, and do not reveal the confidential talk of another; 10 that the one listening may not put you to shame and the bad report by you can have no recall.

11 As apples of gold in silver carvings is a word spoken at the right time for it.

12 An earring of gold, and an ornament of special gold, is a wise reprover upon the hearing ear.

13 Just like the coolness of snow in the day of harvest is the faithful envoy to those sending him, for he restores the very soul of his masters.

14 As vaporous clouds and a wind without any downpour is a man boasting himself about a gift in falsehood.

15 By patience a commander is induced, and a mild tongue itself can break a bone.

16 Is it honey that you have found? Eat what is sufficient for you, that you may not take too much of it and have to vomit it up.

17 Make your foot rare at the house of your fellowman, that he may not have his sufficiency of you and certainly hate you.

18 As a war club and a sword and a sharpened arrow is a man testifying against his fellowman as a false witness.

19 As a broken tooth and a wobbling foot is the confidence in one proving treacherous in the day of distress.

20 He that is removing a garment on a cold day is as vinegar upon alkali and as a singer with songs upon a gloomy heart.

21 If the one hating you is hungry, give him bread to eat; and if he is thirsty, give him water to drink. 22 For coals are what you are raking together upon his head, and Jehovah himself will reward you.

23 The wind from the north brings forth as with labor pains a downpour; and a tongue giving away a secret, a denounced face.

24 Better is it to dwell upon a corner of a roof than with a contentious wife, although in a house in common.

25 As cold water upon a tired soul, so is a good report from a distant land.

26 A fouled spring and a ruined well is the righteous one when staggering before the wicked one.

27 The eating of too much honey is not good; and for people to search out their own glory, is it glory?

28 As a city broken through, without a wall, is the man that has no restraint for his spirit.

Ecclesiastes

11 Send out your bread upon the surface of the waters, for in the course of many days you will find it again. 2 Give a portion to seven, or even to eight, for you do not know what calamity will occur on the earth.

3 If the clouds are filled with water, they empty out a sheer downpour upon the earth; and if a tree falls to the south or if to the north, in the place where the tree falls there it will prove to be.

4 He that is watching the wind will not sow seed; and he that is looking at the clouds will not reap.

5 Just as you are not aware of what is the way of the spirit in the bones in the belly of her that is pregnant, in like manner you do not know the work of the true God, who does all things.

6 In the morning sow your seed and until the evening do not let your hand rest; for you are not knowing where this will have success, either here or there, or whether both of them will alike be good.

7 The light is also sweet, and it is good for the eyes to see the sun; 8 for if a man should live even many years, in all of them let him rejoice. And let him remember the days of darkness, though they could be many; every day that has come in is vanity.

9 Rejoice, young man, in your youth, and let your heart do you good in the days of your young manhood, and walk in the ways of your heart and in the things seen by your eyes. But know that on account of all these the true God will bring you into judgment. 10 So remove vexation from your heart, and ward off calamity from your flesh; for youth and the prime of life are vanity.

Song of Solomon

6 “Where has your dear one gone, O most beautiful one among women? Where has your dear one turned, that we may seek him with you?”

2 “My own dear one has gone down to his garden, to the garden beds of spice plants, to shepherd among the gardens, and to pick lilies. 3 I am my dear one’s, and my dear one is mine. He is shepherding among the lilies.”

4 “You are beautiful, O girl companion of mine, like Pleasant City, comely like Jerusalem, awesome as companies gathered around banners. 5 Turn your eyes away from in front of me, for they themselves have alarmed me. Your hair is like a drove of goats that have hopped down from Gil′e·ad. 6 Your teeth are like a drove of ewes that have come up from the washing, all of which are bearing twins, none among them having lost its young ones. 7 Like a segment of pomegranate are your temples behind your veil. 8 There may be sixty queens and eighty concubines and maidens without number. 9 One there is who is my dove, my blameless one. One there is who belongs to her mother. She is the pure one of the one giving birth to her. The daughters have seen her, and they proceeded to pronounce her happy; queens and concubines, and they proceeded to praise her, 10 ‘Who is this woman that is looking down like the dawn, beautiful like the full moon, pure like the glowing sun, awesome as companies gathered around banners?’”

11 “To the garden of nut trees I had gone down, to see the buds in the torrent valley, to see whether the vine had sprouted, whether the pomegranate trees had blossomed. 12 Before I knew it, my own soul had put me at the chariots of my willing people.”

13 “Come back, come back, O Shu′lam·mite! Come back, come back, that we may behold you!”

“What do YOU people behold in the Shu′lam·mite?”

“Something like the dance of two camps!”

Song of Solomon

8 “O that you were like a brother of mine, sucking the breasts of my mother! Should I find you outside, I would kiss you. People would not even despise me. 2 I would lead you, I would bring you into the house of my mother, who used to teach me. I would give you a drink of spiced wine, the fresh juice of pomegranates. 3 His left hand would be under my head; and his right hand—it would embrace me.

4 “I have put YOU under oath, O daughters of Jerusalem, that YOU try not to awaken or arouse love in me until it feels inclined.”

5 “Who is this woman coming up from the wilderness, leaning upon her dear one?”

“Under the apple tree I aroused you. There your mother was in birth pangs with you. There she that was giving birth to you experienced birth pangs.

6 “Place me as a seal upon your heart, as a seal upon your arm; because love is as strong as death is, insistence on exclusive devotion is as unyielding as She′ol is. Its blazings are the blazings of a fire, the flame of Jah. 7 Many waters themselves are not able to extinguish love, nor can rivers themselves wash it away. If a man would give all the valuable things of his house for love, persons would positively despise them.”

8 “We have a little sister that does not have any breasts. What shall we do for our sister on the day that she will be spoken for?”

9 “If she should be a wall, we shall build upon her a battlement of silver; but if she should be a door, we shall block her up with a cedar plank.”

10 “I am a wall, and my breasts are like towers. In this case I have become in his eyes like her that is finding peace.

11 “There was a vineyard that Sol′o·mon happened to have in Ba′al-ha′mon. He gave the vineyard over to the keepers. Each one would bring in for its fruitage a thousand silver pieces.

12 “My vineyard, which belongs to me, is at my disposal. The thousand belong to you, O Sol′o·mon, and two hundred to those keeping its fruitage.”

13 “O you who are dwelling in the gardens, the partners are paying attention to your voice. Let me hear it.”

14 “Run away, my dear one, and make yourself like a gazelle or like a young one of the stags upon the mountains of spices.”

Isaiah

3 For, look! the true Lord, Jehovah of armies, is removing from Jerusalem and from Judah support and stay, the whole support of bread and the whole support of water, 2 mighty man and warrior, judge and prophet, and practicer of divination and elderly man, 3 chief of fifty and highly respected man and counselor and expert in magical arts, and the skilled charmer. 4 And I shall certainly make boys their princes, and mere arbitrary power will rule over them. 5 And the people will actually tyrannize one over the other, even each one over his fellowman. They will storm, the boy against the old man, and the lightly esteemed one against the one to be honored. 6 For each one will lay hold of his brother in the house of his father, saying: “You have a mantle. A dictator you ought to become to us, and this overthrown mass should be under your hand.” 7 He will raise his voice in that day, saying: “I shall not become a wound dresser; and in my house there is neither bread nor a mantle. YOU men must not set me as dictator over the people.”

8 For Jerusalem has stumbled, and Judah itself has fallen, because their tongue and their dealings are against Jehovah, in behaving rebelliously in the eyes of his glory. 9 The very expression of their faces actually testifies against them, and of their sin like that of Sod′om they do tell. They have not hidden it. Woe to their soul! For they have dealt out to themselves calamity.

10 Say, YOU men, that it will be well with the righteous one, for they will eat the very fruitage of their dealings. 11 Woe to the wicked one!—Calamity; for the treatment rendered by his own hands will be rendered to him! 12 As for my people, its task assigners are dealing severely, and mere women actually rule over it. O my people, those leading you on are causing you to wander, and the way of your paths they have confused.

13 Jehovah is stationing himself to contend and is standing up to pass sentence upon peoples. 14 Jehovah himself will enter into judgment with the elderly ones of his people and its princes.

“And YOU yourselves have burned down the vineyard. What was taken by robbery from the afflicted one is in YOUR houses. 15 What do YOU men mean in that YOU crush my people, and that YOU grind the very faces of the afflicted ones?” is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord, Jehovah of armies.

16 And Jehovah says: “For the reason that the daughters of Zion have become haughty and they walk with their throats stretched forth and ogling with their eyes, they go walking with tripping steps, and with their feet they make a tinkling sound, 17 Jehovah also will actually make the crown of the head of the daughters of Zion scabby, and Jehovah himself will lay their very forehead bare. 18 In that day Jehovah will take away the beauty of the bangles and the headbands and the moon-shaped ornaments, 19 the eardrops and the bracelets and the veils, 20 the headdresses and the step chains and the breastbands and the ‘houses of the soul’ and the ornamental humming shells, 21 the finger rings and the nose rings, 22 the robes of state and the overtunics and the cloaks and the purses, 23 and the hand mirrors and the undergarments and the turbans and the large veils.

24 “And it must occur that instead of balsam oil there will come to be merely a musty smell; and instead of a belt, a rope; and instead of an artistic hair arrangement, baldness; and instead of a rich garment, a girding of sackcloth; a brand mark instead of prettiness. 25 By the sword your own men will fall, and your mightiness by war. 26 And her entrances will have to mourn and express sorrow, and she will certainly be cleaned out. She will sit down on the very earth.”

Isaiah

5 Let me sing, please, to my beloved one a song of my loved one concerning his vineyard. There was a vineyard that my beloved one came to have on a fruitful hillside. 2 And he proceeded to dig it up and to rid it of stones and to plant it with a choice red vine, and to build a tower in the middle of it. And there was also a winepress that he hewed out in it. And he kept hoping for it to produce grapes, but it gradually produced wild grapes.

3 “And now, O YOU inhabitants of Jerusalem and YOU men of Judah, please judge between me and my vineyard. 4 What is there yet to do for my vineyard that I have not already done in it? Why is it that I hoped for it to produce grapes, but it gradually produced wild grapes? 5 And now, please, may I make known to YOU men what I am doing to my vineyard: There will be a removing of its hedge, and it must be destined for burning down. There must be a breaking down of its stone wall, and it must be destined for a place of trampling. 6 And I shall set it as a thing destroyed. It will not be pruned, nor will it be hoed. And it must come up with the thornbush and weeds; and upon the clouds I shall lay a command to keep from precipitating any rain upon it. 7 For the vineyard of Jehovah of armies is the house of Israel, and the men of Judah are the plantation of which he was fond. And he kept hoping for judgment, but, look! the breaking of law; for righteousness, but, look! an outcry.”

8 Woe to the ones joining house to house, and those who annex field to field until there is no more room and YOU men have been made to dwell all by yourselves in the midst of the land! 9 In my ears Jehovah of armies has sworn that many houses, though great and good, will become an outright object of astonishment, without an inhabitant. 10 For even ten acres of vineyard will produce but one bath measure, and even a ho′mer measure of seed will produce but an e′phah measure.

11 Woe to those who are getting up early in the morning that they may seek just intoxicating liquor, who are lingering till late in the evening darkness so that wine itself inflames them! 12 And there must prove to be harp and stringed instrument, tambourine and flute, and wine at their feasts; but the activity of Jehovah they do not look at, and the work of his hands they have not seen.

13 Therefore my people will have to go into exile for lack of knowledge; and their glory will be famished men, and their crowd will be parched with thirst. 14 Therefore She′ol has made its soul spacious and has opened its mouth wide beyond bounds; and what is splendid in her, also her crowd and her uproar and the exultant one, will certainly go down into it. 15 And earthling man will bow down, and man will become low, and even the eyes of the high ones will become low. 16 And Jehovah of armies will become high through judgment, and the true God, the Holy One, will certainly sanctify himself through righteousness. 17 And the male lambs will actually graze as in their pasture; and the desolate places of well-fed animals alien residents will eat.

18 Woe to those drawing error with ropes of untruth, and as with wagon cords sin; 19 those who are saying: “Let his work hasten; do let it come quickly, in order that we may see it; and let the counsel of the Holy One of Israel draw near and come, that we may know it!”

20 Woe to those who are saying that good is bad and bad is good, those who are putting darkness for light and light for darkness, those who are putting bitter for sweet and sweet for bitter!

21 Woe to those wise in their own eyes and discreet even in front of their own faces!

22 Woe to those who are mighty in drinking wine, and to the men with vital energy for mixing intoxicating liquor, 23 those who are pronouncing the wicked one righteous in consideration of a bribe, and who take away even the righteousness of the righteous one from him!

24 Therefore just as a tongue of fire eats up the stubble and into the flames mere dried grass sinks down, their very rootstock will become just like a musty smell, and their blossom itself will go up just like powder, because they have rejected the law of Jehovah of armies, and the saying of the Holy One of Israel they have disrespected. 25 That is why the anger of Jehovah has grown hot against his people, and he will stretch out his hand against them and strike them. And the mountains will be agitated, and their dead bodies will become like the offal in the midst of the streets.

In view of all this his anger has not turned back, but his hand is stretched out still. 26 And he has raised up a signal to a great nation far away, and he has whistled to it at the extremity of the earth; and, look! in haste it will swiftly come in. 27 There is no one tired nor is anyone stumbling among them. No one is drowsy and no one sleeps. And the belt around their loins will certainly not be opened, nor the laces of their sandals be torn in two; 28 because their arrows are sharpened and all their bows are bent. The very hoofs of their horses will have to be accounted as flint itself, and their wheels as a storm wind. 29 The roaring of theirs is like that of a lion, and they roar like maned young lions. And they will growl and grab hold of the prey and bring it safely away, and there will be no deliverer. 30 And they will growl over it in that day as with the growling of the sea. And one will actually gaze at the land, and, look! there is distressing darkness; and even the light has grown dark because of the drops falling on it.

Isaiah

7 Now it came about in the days of A′haz the son of Jo′tham the son of Uz·zi′ah, the king of Judah, that Re′zin the king of Syria and Pe′kah the son of Rem·a·li′ah, the king of Israel, came up to Jerusalem for war against it, and he proved unable to war against it. 2 And a report was made to the house of David, saying: “Syria has leaned upon E′phra·im.”

And his heart and the heart of his people began to quiver, like the quivering of the trees of the forest because of a wind.

3 And Jehovah proceeded to say to Isaiah: “Go out, please, to meet A′haz, you and She′ar-ja′shub your son, to the end of the conduit of the upper pool by the highway of the laundryman’s field. 4 And you must say to him, ‘Watch yourself and keep undisturbed. Do not be afraid, and do not let your heart itself be timid because of the two tail ends of these smoking logs, because of the hot anger of Re′zin and Syria and the son of Rem·a·li′ah, 5 for the reason that Syria with E′phra·im and the son of Rem·a·li′ah has advised what is bad against you, saying: 6 “Let us go up against Judah and tear it apart and by breakthroughs take it for ourselves; and let us make another king reign inside it, the son of Tab′e·el.”

7 “‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “It will not stand, neither will it take place. 8 For the head of Syria is Damascus, and the head of Damascus is Re′zin; and within just sixty-five years E′phra·im will be shattered to pieces so as not to be a people. 9 And the head of E′phra·im is Sa·mar′i·a, and the head of Sa·mar′i·a is the son of Rem·a·li′ah. Unless YOU people have faith, YOU will in that case not be of long duration.”’”

10 And Jehovah went on speaking some more to A′haz, saying: 11 “Ask for yourself a sign from Jehovah your God, making it as deep as She′ol or making it high as the upper regions.” 12 But A′haz said: “I shall not ask, neither shall I put Jehovah to the test.”

13 And he proceeded to say: “Listen, please, O house of David. Is it such a little thing for YOU to tire out men, that YOU should also tire out my God? 14 Therefore Jehovah himself will give YOU men a sign: Look! The maiden herself will actually become pregnant, and she is giving birth to a son, and she will certainly call his name Im·man′u·el. 15 Butter and honey he will eat by the time that he knows how to reject the bad and choose the good. 16 For before the boy will know how to reject the bad and choose the good, the ground of whose two kings you are feeling a sickening dread will be left entirely. 17 Jehovah will bring against you and against your people and against the house of your father days such as have not come since the day of E′phra·im’s turning away from alongside Judah, namely, the king of As·syr′i·a.

18 “And it must occur in that day that Jehovah will whistle for the flies that are at the extremity of the Nile canals of Egypt and for the bees that are in the land of As·syr′i·a, 19 and they will certainly come in and settle down, all of them, upon the precipitous torrent valleys and upon the clefts of the crags and upon all the thorn thickets and upon all the watering places.

20 “In that day, by means of a hired razor in the region of the River, even by means of the king of As·syr′i·a, Jehovah will shave the head and the hair of the feet, and it will sweep away even the beard itself.

21 “And it must occur in that day that an individual will preserve alive a young cow of the herd and two sheep. 22 And it must occur that, due to the abundance of the producing of milk, he will eat butter; because butter and honey are what everyone left remaining in the midst of the land will eat.

23 “And it must occur in that day that every place where there used to be a thousand vines, worth a thousand pieces of silver, will come to be—for the thornbushes and for the weeds it will come to be. 24 With arrows and the bow he will come there, because all the land will become mere thornbushes and weeds. 25 And all the mountains that used to be cleared of troublesome plants with a hoe—you will not come there for fear of thornbushes and weeds; and it will certainly become a place for letting bulls loose and a trampling ground of sheep.”

Isaiah

9 However, the obscureness will not be as when the land had stress, as at the former time when one treated with contempt the land of Zeb′u·lun and the land of Naph′ta·li and when at the later time one caused it to be honored—the way by the sea, in the region of the Jordan, Gal′i·lee of the nations. 2 The people that were walking in the darkness have seen a great light. As for those dwelling in the land of deep shadow, light itself has shone upon them. 3 You have made the nation populous; for it you have made the rejoicing great. They have rejoiced before you as with the rejoicing in the harvesttime, as those who are joyful when they divide up the spoil.

4 For the yoke of their load and the rod upon their shoulders, the staff of the one driving them to work, you have shattered to pieces as in the day of Mid′i·an. 5 For every boot of the one tramping with tremors and the mantle rolled in blood have even come to be for burning as food for fire. 6 For there has been a child born to us, there has been a son given to us; and the princely rule will come to be upon his shoulder. And his name will be called Wonderful Counselor, Mighty God, Eternal Father, Prince of Peace. 7 To the abundance of the princely rule and to peace there will be no end, upon the throne of David and upon his kingdom in order to establish it firmly and to sustain it by means of justice and by means of righteousness, from now on and to time indefinite. The very zeal of Jehovah of armies will do this.

8 There was a word that Jehovah sent against Jacob, and it fell upon Israel. 9 And the people will certainly know it, even all of them, E′phra·im and the inhabitant of Sa·mar′i·a, because of their haughtiness and because of their insolence of heart in saying: 10 “Bricks are what have fallen, but with hewn stone we shall build. Sycamore trees are what have been cut down, but with cedars we shall make replacement.” 11 And Jehovah will set the adversaries of Re′zin on high against him, and the enemies of that one he will goad on, 12 Syria from the east and the Phi·lis′tines from behind, and they will eat up Israel with open mouth. In view of all this his anger has not turned back, but his hand is stretched out still.

13 And the people themselves have not returned to the One striking them, and Jehovah of armies they have not sought. 14 And Jehovah will cut off from Israel head and tail, shoot and rush, in one day. 15 The aged and highly respected one is the head, and the prophet giving false instruction is the tail. 16 And those who are leading this people on prove to be the ones causing them to wander; and those of them who are being led on, the ones who are being confused. 17 That is why Jehovah will not rejoice even over their young men, and upon their fatherless boys and upon their widows he will have no mercy; because all of them are apostates and evildoers and every mouth is speaking senselessness. In view of all this his anger has not turned back, but his hand is stretched out still.

18 For wickedness has become aflame just like a fire; thornbushes and weeds it will eat up. And it will catch fire in the thickets of the forest, and they will be borne aloft as the billowing of smoke. 19 In the fury of Jehovah of armies the land has been set afire, and the people will become as food for the fire. No one will show compassion even on his brother. 20 And one will cut down on the right and will certainly be hungry; and one will eat on the left, and they will certainly not be satisfied. They will each one eat the flesh of his own arm, 21 Ma·nas′seh E′phra·im, and E′phra·im Ma·nas′seh. Together they will be against Judah. In view of all this his anger has not turned back, but his hand is stretched out still.

Isaiah

10 Woe to those who are enacting harmful regulations and those who, constantly writing, have written out sheer trouble, 2 in order to push away the lowly ones from a legal case and to wrest away justice from the afflicted ones of my people, for the widows to become their spoil, and that they may plunder even the fatherless boys! 3 And what will YOU men do at the day of being given attention and at the ruin, when it comes from far away? Toward whom will YOU flee for assistance, and where will YOU leave YOUR glory, 4 except it be that one must bow down under the prisoners and that people keep falling under those who have been killed? In view of all this his anger has not turned back, but his hand is stretched out still.

5 “Aha, the As·syr′i·an, the rod for my anger, and the stick that is in their hand for my denunciation! 6 Against an apostate nation I shall send him, and against the people of my fury I shall issue a command to him, to take much spoil and to take much plunder and to make it a trampling place like the clay of the streets. 7 Though he may not be that way, he will feel inclined; though his heart may not be that way, he will scheme, because to annihilate is in his heart, and to cut off nations not a few. 8 For he will say, ‘Are not my princes at the same time kings? 9 Is not Cal′no just like Car′che·mish? Is not Ha′math just like Ar′pad? Is not Sa·mar′i·a just like Damascus? 10 Whenever my hand has reached the kingdoms of the valueless god whose graven images are more than those at Jerusalem and at Sa·mar′i·a, 11 will it not be that just as I shall have done to Sa·mar′i·a and to her valueless gods, even so I shall do to Jerusalem and to her idols?’

12 “And it must occur that when Jehovah terminates all his work in Mount Zion and in Jerusalem, I shall make an accounting for the fruitage of the insolence of the heart of the king of As·syr′i·a and for the self-importance of his loftiness of eyes. 13 For he has said, ‘With the power of my hand I shall certainly act, and with my wisdom, for I do have understanding; and I shall remove the boundaries of peoples, and their things stored up I shall certainly pillage, and I shall bring down the inhabitants just like a powerful one. 14 And just as if a nest, my hand will reach the resources of the peoples; and just as when one gathers eggs that have been left, I myself will gather up even all the earth, and there will certainly be no one fluttering his wings or opening his mouth or chirping.’”

15 Will the ax enhance itself over the one chopping with it, or the saw magnify itself over the one moving it back and forth, as though the staff moved back and forth the ones raising it on high, as though the rod raised on high the one who is not wood? 16 Therefore the true Lord, Jehovah of armies, will keep sending upon his fat ones a wasting disease, and under his glory a burning will keep burning away like the burning of a fire. 17 And Israel’s Light must become a fire, and his Holy One a flame; and it must blaze up and eat up his weeds and his thornbushes in one day. 18 And the glory of his forest and of his orchard He will bring to an end, even from the soul clear to the flesh, and it must become like the melting away of one that is ailing. 19 And the rest of the trees of his forest—they will become such a number that a mere boy will be able to write them down.

20 And it will certainly occur in that day that those remaining over of Israel and those who have escaped of the house of Jacob will never again support themselves upon the one striking them, and they will certainly support themselves upon Jehovah, the Holy One of Israel, in trueness. 21 A mere remnant will return, the remnant of Jacob, to the Mighty God. 22 For although your people, O Israel, would prove to be like the grains of sand of the sea, a mere remnant among them will return. An extermination decided upon will be flooding through in righteousness, 23 because an exterminating and a strict decision the Sovereign Lord, Jehovah of armies, will be executing in the midst of the whole land.

24 Therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord, Jehovah of armies, has said: “Do not be afraid, O my people who are dwelling in Zion, because of the As·syr′i·an, who with the rod used to strike you and who used to lift up his own staff against you in the way that Egypt did. 25 For yet a very little while—and the denunciation will have come to an end, and my anger, in their wearing away. 26 And Jehovah of armies will certainly brandish against him a whip as at the defeat of Mid′i·an by the rock O′reb; and his staff will be upon the sea, and he will certainly lift it up in the way that he did with Egypt.

27 “And it must occur in that day that his load will depart from upon your shoulder, and his yoke from upon your neck, and the yoke will certainly be wrecked because of the oil.”

28 He has come upon Ai′ath; he has passed along through Mig′ron; at Mich′mash he deposits his articles. 29 They have passed over the ford, Ge′ba is a place for them to spend the night, Ra′mah has trembled, Gib′e·ah of Saul itself has fled. 30 Let your voice out in shrill cries, O daughter of Gal′lim. Pay attention, O La′i·shah. O you afflicted one, An′a·thoth! 31 Mad·me′nah has run away. The inhabitants of Ge′bim themselves have taken to shelter. 32 It is yet day in Nob to make a halt. He waves his hand threateningly at the mountain of the daughter of Zion, the hill of Jerusalem.

33 Look! The true Lord, Jehovah of armies, is lopping off boughs with a terrible crash; and those tall in growth are being cut down, and the high ones themselves become low. 34 And he has struck down the thickets of the forest with an iron tool, and by a powerful one Leb′a·non itself will fall.

Isaiah

11 And there must go forth a twig out of the stump of Jes′se; and out of his roots a sprout will be fruitful. 2 And upon him the spirit of Jehovah must settle down, the spirit of wisdom and of understanding, the spirit of counsel and of mightiness, the spirit of knowledge and of the fear of Jehovah; 3 and there will be enjoyment by him in the fear of Jehovah.

And he will not judge by any mere appearance to his eyes, nor reprove simply according to the thing heard by his ears. 4 And with righteousness he must judge the lowly ones, and with uprightness he must give reproof in behalf of the meek ones of the earth. And he must strike the earth with the rod of his mouth; and with the spirit of his lips he will put the wicked one to death. 5 And righteousness must prove to be the belt of his hips, and faithfulness the belt of his loins.

6 And the wolf will actually reside for a while with the male lamb, and with the kid the leopard itself will lie down, and the calf and the maned young lion and the well-fed animal all together; and a mere little boy will be leader over them. 7 And the cow and the bear themselves will feed; together their young ones will lie down. And even the lion will eat straw just like the bull. 8 And the sucking child will certainly play upon the hole of the cobra; and upon the light aperture of a poisonous snake will a weaned child actually put his own hand. 9 They will not do any harm or cause any ruin in all my holy mountain; because the earth will certainly be filled with the knowledge of Jehovah as the waters are covering the very sea.

10 And it must occur in that day that there will be the root of Jes′se that will be standing up as a signal for the peoples. To him even the nations will turn inquiringly, and his resting-place must become glorious.

11 And it must occur in that day that Jehovah will again offer his hand, a second time, to acquire the remnant of his people who will remain over from As·syr′i·a and from Egypt and from Path′ros and from Cush and from E′lam and from Shi′nar and from Ha′math and from the islands of the sea. 12 And he will certainly raise up a signal for the nations and gather the dispersed ones of Israel; and the scattered ones of Judah he will collect together from the four extremities of the earth.

13 And the jealousy of E′phra·im must depart, and even those showing hostility to Judah will be cut off. E′phra·im itself will not be jealous of Judah, nor will Judah show hostility toward E′phra·im. 14 And they must fly at the shoulder of the Phi·lis′tines to the west; together they will plunder the sons of the East. E′dom and Mo′ab will be those upon whom they will thrust out their hand, and the sons of Am′mon will be their subjects. 15 And Jehovah will certainly cut off the tongue of the Egyptian sea, and wave his hand at the River in the glow of his spirit. And he must strike it in its seven torrents, and he will actually cause people to walk in their sandals. 16 And there must come to be a highway out of As·syr′i·a for the remnant of his people who will remain over, just as there came to be one for Israel in the day of his coming up out of the land of Egypt.

Isaiah

15 The pronouncement against Mo′ab: Because in the night it has been despoiled, Ar of Mo′ab itself has been silenced. Because in the night it has been despoiled, Kir of Mo′ab itself has been silenced. 2 He has gone up to The House and to Di′bon, to the high places, to a weeping. Over Ne′bo and over Med′e·ba Mo′ab itself howls. On all heads in it there is baldness; every beard is clipped. 3 In its streets they have girded on sackcloth. Upon the roofs thereof and in the public squares thereof everyone thereof howls, going down with weeping. 4 And Hesh′bon and E·le·a′leh cry out. As far as Ja′haz their voice has been heard. That is why the armed men of Mo′ab themselves keep shouting. His very soul has quivered within him.

5 My own heart cries out over Mo′ab himself. The runaways thereof are as far along as Zo′ar and Eg′lath-she·li′shi·yah. For on the ascent of Lu′hith—with weeping each one goes up on it; for on the way to Hor·o·na′im they arouse the outcry about the catastrophe. 6 For the very waters of Nim′rim become sheer desolations. For the green grass has dried up, the grass has come to an end; nothing has become green. 7 That is why the leftovers and their stored goods that they have put up, they keep carrying them away right over the torrent valley of the poplars. 8 For the outcry has gone around the territory of Mo′ab. The howling thereof is clear to Eg·la′im; the howling thereof is clear to Be′er-e′lim, 9 because the very waters of Di′mon have become full of blood. For upon Di′mon I shall place additional things, such as a lion for the escapees of Mo′ab who escape and for the remaining ones of the ground.

Isaiah

16 Send a ram, YOU men, to the ruler of the land, from Se′la toward the wilderness, to the mountain of the daughter of Zion.

2 And it must occur that like a fleeing winged creature, chased away from its nest, the daughters of Mo′ab will become at the fords of Ar′non.

3 “Bring in counsel, YOU men, execute the decision.

“Make your shadow just like the night in the midst of noontime. Conceal the dispersed ones; do not betray anyone fleeing. 4 May my dispersed ones reside as aliens even in you, O Mo′ab. Become a place of concealment to them because of the despoiler. For the oppressor has reached his end; the despoiling has terminated; those trampling down others have been finished off the earth.

5 “And in loving-kindness a throne will certainly be firmly established; and one must sit down upon it in trueness in the tent of David, judging and seeking justice and being prompt in righteousness.”

6 We have heard of the pride of Mo′ab, that he is very proud; his haughtiness and his pride and his fury—his empty talk will not be so. 7 Therefore Mo′ab will howl for Mo′ab; even all of it will howl. For the raisin cakes of Kir-har′e·seth the stricken ones indeed will moan, 8 because the terraces themselves of Hesh′bon have withered. The vine of Sib′mah—the owners of the nations themselves have smitten down its bright-red branches. As far as Ja′zer they had reached; they had wandered about in the wilderness. Its own shoots had been left to luxuriate for themselves; they had gone over to the sea.

9 That is why I shall weep with the weeping of Ja′zer over the vine of Sib′mah. With my tears I shall drench you, O Hesh′bon and E·le·a′leh, because shouting even over your summer and over your harvest has fallen down. 10 And rejoicing and joyfulness have been taken away from the orchard; and in the vineyards there is no joyful crying out, there is no shouting done. No wine in the presses does the treader tread out. Shouting I have caused to cease.

11 That is why my very inwards are boisterous just like a harp even over Mo′ab, and the midst of me over Kir-har′e·seth.

12 And it occurred that it was seen that Mo′ab was made weary upon the high place; and he came to his sanctuary to pray, and he could not accomplish anything.

13 This is the word that Jehovah spoke concerning Mo′ab formerly. 14 And now Jehovah has spoken, saying: “Within three years, according to the years of a hired laborer, the glory of Mo′ab must also be disgraced with much commotion of every sort, and those who remain over will be a trifling few, not mighty.”

Isaiah

25 O Jehovah, you are my God. I exalt you, I laud your name, for you have done wonderful things, counsels from early times, in faithfulness, in trustworthiness. 2 For you have made a city a pile of stones, a fortified town a crumbling ruin, a dwelling tower of strangers to be no city, which will not be rebuilt even to time indefinite. 3 That is why those who are a strong people will glorify you; the town of the tyrannical nations, they will fear you. 4 For you have become a stronghold to the lowly one, a stronghold to the poor one in the distress that he has, a refuge from the rainstorm, a shade from the heat, when the blast of the tyrannical ones is like a rainstorm against a wall. 5 Like the heat in a waterless country, the noise of strangers you subdue, the heat with the shadow of a cloud. The melody itself of the tyrannical ones becomes suppressed.

6 And Jehovah of armies will certainly make for all the peoples, in this mountain, a banquet of well-oiled dishes, a banquet of wine kept on the dregs, of well-oiled dishes filled with marrow, of wine kept on the dregs, filtered. 7 And in this mountain he will certainly swallow up the face of the envelopment that is enveloping over all the peoples, and the woven work that is interwoven upon all the nations. 8 He will actually swallow up death forever, and the Sovereign Lord Jehovah will certainly wipe the tears from all faces. And the reproach of his people he will take away from all the earth, for Jehovah himself has spoken it.

9 And in that day one will certainly say: “Look! This is our God. We have hoped in him, and he will save us. This is Jehovah. We have hoped in him. Let us be joyful and rejoice in the salvation by him.”

10 For the hand of Jehovah will settle down on this mountain, and Mo′ab must be trodden down in its place as when a straw heap is trodden down in a manure place. 11 And he must slap out his hands in the midst of it as when a swimmer slaps them out to swim, and he must abase its haughtiness with the tricky movements of his hands. 12 And the fortified city, with your high walls of security, he must lay low; he must abase it, bring it into contact with the earth, to the dust.

Isaiah

32 Look! A king will reign for righteousness itself; and as respects princes, they will rule as princes for justice itself. 2 And each one must prove to be like a hiding place from the wind and a place of concealment from the rainstorm, like streams of water in a waterless country, like the shadow of a heavy crag in an exhausted land.

3 And the eyes of those seeing will not be pasted together, and the very ears of those hearing will pay attention. 4 And the heart itself of those who are overhasty will consider knowledge, and even the tongue of the stammerers will be quick in speaking clear things. 5 The senseless one will no longer be called generous; and as for the unprincipled man, he will not be said to be noble; 6 because the senseless one himself will speak mere senselessness, and his very heart will work at what is hurtful, to work at apostasy and to speak against Jehovah what is wayward, to cause the soul of the hungry one to go empty, and he causes even the thirsty one to go without drink itself. 7 As for the unprincipled man, his instruments are bad; he himself has given counsel for acts of loose conduct, to wreck the afflicted ones with false sayings, even when someone poor speaks what is right.

8 As regards the generous one, it is for generous things that he has given counsel; and in favor of generous things he himself will rise up.

9 “YOU women who are at ease, rise up, listen to my voice! YOU careless daughters, give ear to my saying! 10 Within a year and some days YOU careless ones will be agitated, because the grape picking will have come to an end but no fruit gathering will come in. 11 Tremble, YOU women who are at ease! Be agitated, YOU careless ones! Undress and make yourselves naked, and gird sackcloth upon the loins. 12 Beat yourselves upon the breasts in lamentation over the desirable fields, over the fruit-bearing vine. 13 Upon the ground of my people merely thorns, spiny bushes come up, for they are upon all the houses of exultation, yes, the highly elated town. 14 For the dwelling tower itself has been forsaken, the very hubbub of the city has been abandoned; O′phel and the watchtower themselves have become bare fields, for time indefinite the exultation of zebras, the pasture of droves; 15 until upon us the spirit is poured out from on high, and the wilderness will have become an orchard, and the orchard itself is accounted as a real forest.

16 “And in the wilderness justice will certainly reside, and in the orchard righteousness itself will dwell. 17 And the work of the true righteousness must become peace; and the service of the true righteousness, quietness and security to time indefinite. 18 And my people must dwell in a peaceful abiding place and in residences of full confidence and in undisturbed resting-places. 19 And it will certainly hail when the forest goes down and the city becomes low in an abased state.

20 “Happy are YOU people who are sowing seed alongside all waters, sending forth the feet of the bull and of the ass.”

Isaiah

36 Now it came about in the fourteenth year of King Hez·e·ki′ah that Sen·nach′er·ib the king of As·syr′i·a came up against all the fortified cities of Judah and proceeded to seize them. 2 And the king of As·syr′i·a finally sent Rab′sha·keh from La′chish to Jerusalem, to King Hez·e·ki′ah, with a heavy military force, and he proceeded to stand still by the conduit of the upper pool at the highway of the laundryman’s field. 3 Then there came out to him E·li′a·kim the son of Hil·ki′ah, who was over the household, and Sheb′na the secretary and Jo′ah the son of A′saph the recorder.

4 Accordingly Rab′sha·keh said to them: “Please, say to Hez·e·ki′ah, ‘This is what the great king, the king of As·syr′i·a, has said: “What is this confidence in which you have trusted? 5 You have said (but it is the word of lips), ‘There are counsel and mightiness for the war.’ Now in whom have you put trust, that you have rebelled against me? 6 Look! You have trusted in the support of this crushed reed, in Egypt, which, if a man should brace himself upon it, would certainly enter into his palm and pierce it. That is the way Phar′aoh the king of Egypt is to all those putting their trust in him. 7 And in case you should say to me, ‘It is Jehovah our God in whom we have trusted,’ is he not the one whose high places and whose altars Hez·e·ki′ah has removed, while he says to Judah and Jerusalem, ‘Before this altar YOU should bow down’?”’ 8 Now, then, make a wager, please, with my lord the king of As·syr′i·a, and let me give you two thousand horses to see whether you are able, on your part, to put riders upon them. 9 How, then, could you turn back the face of one governor of the smallest servants of my lord, while you, for your part, put your trust in Egypt for chariots and for horsemen? 10 And now is it without authorization from Jehovah that I have come up against this land to bring it to ruin? Jehovah himself said to me, ‘Go up against this land, and you must bring it to ruin.’”

11 At this E·li′a·kim and Sheb′na and Jo′ah said to Rab′sha·keh: “Speak, please, to your servants in the Syrian language, for we are listening; and do not speak to us in the Jews’ language in the ears of the people that are on the wall.” 12 But Rab′sha·keh said: “Is it to your lord and to you that my lord has sent me to speak these words? Is it not to the men sitting upon the wall, that they may eat their own excrement and drink their own urine with YOU men?”

13 And Rab′sha·keh continued to stand and call out in a loud voice in the Jews’ language, and he went on to say: “HEAR the words of the great king, the king of As·syr′i·a. 14 This is what the king has said, ‘Do not let Hez·e·ki′ah deceive YOU people, for he is not able to deliver YOU. 15 And do not let Hez·e·ki′ah cause YOU to trust in Jehovah, saying: “Without fail Jehovah will deliver us. This city will not be given into the hand of the king of As·syr′i·a.” 16 Do not listen to Hez·e·ki′ah, for this is what the king of As·syr′i·a has said: “Make a capitulation to me and come out to me and eat each one from his own vine and each one from his own fig tree and drink each one the water of his own cistern, 17 until I come and actually take YOU to a land like YOUR own land, a land of grain and new wine, a land of bread and vineyards; 18 in order that Hez·e·ki′ah may not allure YOU, saying, ‘Jehovah himself will deliver us.’ Have the gods of the nations delivered each one his own land out of the hand of the king of As·syr′i·a? 19 Where are the gods of Ha′math and Ar′pad? Where are the gods of Seph·ar·va′im? And have they delivered Sa·mar′i·a out of my hand? 20 Who are there among all the gods of these lands that have delivered their land out of my hand so that Jehovah should deliver Jerusalem out of my hand?”’”

21 And they continued to keep silent and did not answer him a word, for the commandment of the king was, saying: “YOU must not answer him.” 22 But E·li′a·kim the son of Hil·ki′ah, who was over the household, and Sheb′na the secretary and Jo′ah the son of A′saph the recorder came to Hez·e·ki′ah with their garments ripped apart, and told him the words of Rab′sha·keh.

Isaiah

38 In those days Hez·e·ki′ah got sick to the point of dying. Accordingly Isaiah the son of A′moz the prophet came in to him and said to him: “This is what Jehovah has said, ‘Give commands to your household, for you yourself will indeed die and will not live.’” 2 At that Hez·e·ki′ah turned his face to the wall and began to pray to Jehovah 3 and to say: “I beseech you, O Jehovah, remember, please, how I have walked before you in truthfulness and with a complete heart, and what was good in your eyes I have done.” And Hez·e·ki′ah began to weep profusely.

4 And the word of Jehovah now occurred to Isaiah, saying: 5 “Go, and you must say to Hez·e·ki′ah, ‘This is what Jehovah the God of David your forefather has said: “I have heard your prayer. I have seen your tears. Here I am adding onto your days fifteen years; 6 and out of the palm of the king of As·syr′i·a I shall deliver you and this city, and I will defend this city. 7 And this is the sign for you from Jehovah that Jehovah will perform this word that he has spoken: 8 Here I am making the shadow of the steps that had gone down on the steps of the stairs of A′haz by the sun retrace backward ten steps.”’” And the sun gradually went back ten steps on the steps of the stairs that it had gone down.

9 A writing of Hez·e·ki′ah the king of Judah, when he got sick and revived from his sickness.

10 I myself said: “In the midst of my days I will go into the gates of She′ol.

I must be deprived of the remainder of my years.”

11 I have said: “I shall not see Jah, even Jah, in the land of the living ones.

I shall no more look on mankind—with the inhabitants of the land of cessation.

12 My own habitation has been pulled out and removed from me like the tent of shepherds.

I have rolled up my life just like a loom worker;

One proceeds to cut me off from the very threads of the warp.

From daylight till night you keep handing me over.

13 I have soothed myself until the morning.

Like a lion, so he keeps breaking all my bones;

From daylight till night you keep handing me over.

14 Like the swift, the bulbul, so I keep chirping;

I keep cooing like the dove.

My eyes have looked languishingly to the height:

‘O Jehovah, I am under oppression. Stand good for me.’

15 What shall I speak, and what will he actually say to me?

He himself has also acted.

I keep walking solemnly all my years in the bitterness of my soul.

16 ‘O Jehovah, on that account they keep living; and as with everybody, thereby is the life of my spirit.

And you will restore me to health and certainly preserve me alive.

17 Look! For peace I had what was bitter, yes, bitter;

And you yourself have become attached to my soul and kept it from the pit of disintegration.

For you have thrown behind your back all my sins.

18 For it is not She′ol that can laud you; death itself cannot praise you.

Those going down into the pit cannot look hopefully to your trueness.

19 The living, the living, he is the one that can laud you,

Just as I can this day.

The father himself can give knowledge to his own sons concerning your trueness.

20 O Jehovah, undertake to save me, and we shall play my string selections

All the days of our life at the house of Jehovah.’”

21 And Isaiah proceeded to say: “Let them take a cake of pressed dried figs and rub it in upon the boil, that he may revive.” 22 Meantime, Hez·e·ki′ah said: “What is the sign that I shall go up to the house of Jehovah?”

Isaiah

40 “COMFORT, comfort my people,” says the God of YOU men. 2 “SPEAK to the heart of Jerusalem and call out to her that her military service has been fulfilled, that her error has been paid off. For from the hand of Jehovah she has received a full amount for all her sins.”

3 Listen! Someone is calling out in the wilderness: “Clear up the way of Jehovah, YOU people! MAKE the highway for our God through the desert plain straight. 4 Let every valley be raised up, and every mountain and hill be made low. And the knobby ground must become level land, and the rugged ground a valley plain. 5 And the glory of Jehovah will certainly be revealed, and all flesh must see it together, for the very mouth of Jehovah has spoken it.”

6 Listen! Someone is saying: “Call out!” And one said: “What shall I call out?”

“All flesh is green grass, and all their loving-kindness is like the blossom of the field. 7 The green grass has dried up, the blossom has withered, because the very spirit of Jehovah has blown upon it. Surely the people are green grass. 8 The green grass has dried up, the blossom has withered; but as for the word of our God, it will last to time indefinite.”

9 Make your way up even onto a high mountain, you woman bringing good news for Zion. Raise your voice even with power, you woman bringing good news for Jerusalem. Raise it. Do not be afraid. Say to the cities of Judah: “Here is YOUR God.” 10 Look! The Sovereign Lord Jehovah himself will come even as a strong one, and his arm will be ruling for him. Look! His reward is with him, and the wage he pays is before him. 11 Like a shepherd he will shepherd his own drove. With his arm he will collect together the lambs; and in his bosom he will carry them. Those giving suck he will conduct with care.

12 Who has measured the waters in the mere hollow of his hand, and taken the proportions of the heavens themselves with a mere span and included in a measure the dust of the earth, or weighed with an indicator the mountains, and the hills in the scales? 13 Who has taken the proportions of the spirit of Jehovah, and who as his man of counsel can make him know anything? 14 With whom did he consult together that one might make him understand, or who teaches him in the path of justice, or teaches him knowledge, or makes him know the very way of real understanding?

15 Look! The nations are as a drop from a bucket; and as the film of dust on the scales they have been accounted. Look! He lifts the islands themselves as mere fine dust. 16 Even Leb′a·non is not sufficient for keeping a fire burning, and its wild animals are not sufficient for a burnt offering. 17 All the nations are as something nonexistent in front of him; as nothing and an unreality they have been accounted to him.

18 And to whom can YOU people liken God, and what likeness can YOU put alongside him? 19 The craftsman has cast a mere molten image, and with gold the metalworker overlays it, and silver chains he is forging. 20 A certain tree as a contribution, a tree that is not rotten, he chooses. A skillful craftsman he searches out for himself, to prepare a carved image that may not be made to totter.

21 Do YOU people not know? Do YOU not hear? Has it not been told to YOU from the outset? Have YOU not applied understanding from the foundations of the earth? 22 There is One who is dwelling above the circle of the earth, the dwellers in which are as grasshoppers, the One who is stretching out the heavens just as a fine gauze, who spreads them out like a tent in which to dwell, 23 the One who is reducing high officials to nothing, who has made the very judges of the earth as a mere unreality.

24 Never yet have they been planted; never yet have they been sown; never yet has their stump taken root in the earth. And one has only to blow upon them and they dry up; and like stubble the windstorm itself will carry them away.

25 “But to whom can YOU people liken me so that I should be made his equal?” says the Holy One. 26 “Raise YOUR eyes high up and see. Who has created these things? It is the One who is bringing forth the army of them even by number, all of whom he calls even by name. Due to the abundance of dynamic energy, he also being vigorous in power, not one of them is missing.

27 “For what reason do you say, O Jacob, and do you speak out, O Israel, ‘My way has been concealed from Jehovah, and justice to me eludes my God himself’? 28 Have you not come to know or have you not heard? Jehovah, the Creator of the extremities of the earth, is a God to time indefinite. He does not tire out or grow weary. There is no searching out of his understanding. 29 He is giving to the tired one power; and to the one without dynamic energy he makes full might abound. 30 Boys will both tire out and grow weary, and young men themselves will without fail stumble, 31 but those who are hoping in Jehovah will regain power. They will mount up with wings like eagles. They will run and not grow weary; they will walk and not tire out.”

Isaiah

41 “Attend to me in silence, YOU islands; and let national groups themselves regain power. Let them approach. At that time let them speak. Let us come up close together for the judgment itself.

2 “Who has roused up someone from the sunrise? Who proceeded in righteousness to call him to His feet, to give before him the nations, and to make him go subduing even kings? Who kept giving them like dust to his sword, so that they have been driven about like mere stubble with his bow? 3 Who kept pursuing them, kept peacefully passing along on his feet over the path by which he did not proceed to come? 4 Who has been active and has done this, calling out the generations from the start?

“I, Jehovah, the First One; and with the last ones I am the same.”

5 The islands saw and began to fear. The very extremities of the earth began trembling. They drew near and kept coming. 6 They went helping each one his companion, and one would say to his brother: “Be strong.” 7 So the craftsman went strengthening the metalworker; the one doing the smoothing out with the forge hammer him that is hammering away at the anvil, saying regarding the soldering: “It is good.” Finally one fastened it with nails that it could not be made to totter.

8 “But you, O Israel, are my servant, you, O Jacob, whom I have chosen, the seed of Abraham my friend; 9 you, whom I have taken hold of from the extremities of the earth, and you, whom I have called even from the remote parts of it. And so I said to you, ‘You are my servant; I have chosen you, and I have not rejected you. 10 Do not be afraid, for I am with you. Do not gaze about, for I am your God. I will fortify you. I will really help you. I will really keep fast hold of you with my right hand of righteousness.’

11 “Look! All those getting heated up against you will become ashamed and be humiliated. The men in a quarrel with you will become as nothing and will perish. 12 You will search for them, but you will not find them, those men in a struggle with you. They will become as something nonexistent and as nothing, those men at war with you. 13 For I, Jehovah your God, am grasping your right hand, the One saying to you, ‘Do not be afraid. I myself will help you.’

14 “Do not be afraid, you worm Jacob, YOU men of Israel. I myself will help you,” is the utterance of Jehovah, even your Repurchaser, the Holy One of Israel. 15 “Look! I have made you a threshing sledge, a new threshing instrument having double-edged teeth. You will tread down the mountains and crush them; and the hills you will make just like the chaff. 16 You will winnow them, and a wind itself will carry them away, and a windstorm itself will drive them different ways. And you yourself will be joyful in Jehovah. In the Holy One of Israel you will boast about yourself.”

17 “The afflicted ones and the poor ones are seeking for water, but there is none. Because of thirst their very tongue has become dry. I myself, Jehovah, shall answer them. I, the God of Israel, shall not leave them. 18 Upon bare hills I shall open up rivers, and in the midst of the valley plains, springs. I shall make the wilderness into a reedy pool of water, and the waterless land into sources of water. 19 In the wilderness I shall set the cedar tree, the acacia and the myrtle and the oil tree. In the desert plain I shall place the juniper tree, the ash and the cypress at the same time; 20 in order that people may see and know and pay heed and have insight at the same time, that the very hand of Jehovah has done this, and the Holy One of Israel has himself created it.”

21 “Bring YOUR controversial case forward,” says Jehovah. “Produce YOUR arguments,” says the King of Jacob. 22 “Produce and tell to us the things that are going to happen. The first things—what they were—do tell, that we may apply our heart and know the future of them. Or cause us to hear even the things that are coming. 23 Tell the things that are to come afterward, that we may know that YOU are gods. Yes, YOU ought to do good or do bad, that we may gaze about and see it at the same time. 24 Look! YOU are something nonexistent, and YOUR achievement is nothing. A detestable thing is anyone that chooses YOU.

25 “I have roused up someone from the north, and he will come. From the rising of the sun he will call upon my name. And he will come upon deputy rulers as if they were clay and just as a potter that tramples down the moist material.

26 “Who has told anything from the start, that we may know, or from times past, that we may say, ‘He is right’? Really there is no one telling. Really there is no one causing one to hear. Really there is no one that is hearing any sayings of YOU men.”

27 There is one first, saying to Zion: “Look! Here they are!” and to Jerusalem I shall give a bringer of good news.

28 And I kept seeing, and there was not a man; and out of these there was also no one that was giving counsel. And I kept asking them, that they might make a reply. 29 Look! All of them are something nonexistent. Their works are nothing. Their molten images are wind and unreality.

Isaiah

46 Bel has bent down, Ne′bo is stooping over; their idols have come to be for the wild beasts and for the domestic animals, their loads, pieces of luggage, a burden for the tired animals. 2 They must stoop over; they must each alike bend down; they are simply unable to furnish escape for the burden, but into captivity their own soul must go.

3 “Listen to me, O house of Jacob, and all YOU remaining ones of the house of Israel, YOU the ones conveyed by me from the belly, the ones carried from the womb. 4 Even to one’s old age I am the same One; and to one’s gray-headedness I myself shall keep bearing up. I myself shall certainly act, that I myself may carry and that I myself may bear up and furnish escape.

5 “To whom will YOU people liken me or make me equal or compare me that we may resemble each other? 6 There are those who are lavishing out the gold from the purse, and with the scale beam they weigh out the silver. They hire a metalworker, and he makes it into a god. They prostrate themselves, yes, they bow down. 7 They carry it upon the shoulder, they bear it and deposit it in its place that it may stand still. From its standing place it does not move away. One even cries out to it, but it does not answer; out of one’s distress it does not save one.

8 “Remember this, that YOU people may muster up courage. Lay it to heart, YOU transgressors. 9 Remember the first things of a long time ago, that I am the Divine One and there is no other God, nor anyone like me; 10 the One telling from the beginning the finale, and from long ago the things that have not been done; the One saying, ‘My own counsel will stand, and everything that is my delight I shall do’; 11 the One calling from the sunrising a bird of prey, from a distant land the man to execute my counsel. I have even spoken it; I shall also bring it in. I have formed it, I shall also do it.

12 “Listen to me, YOU the ones powerful at heart, YOU the ones far away from righteousness. 13 I have brought near my righteousness. It is not far away, and my own salvation will not be late. And I will give in Zion salvation, to Israel my beauty.”

Isaiah

50 This is what Jehovah has said: “Where, then, is the divorce certificate of the mother of YOU people, whom I sent away? Or which one of my creditors is it to whom I have sold YOU people? Look! Because of YOUR own errors YOU have been sold, and because of YOUR own transgressions YOUR mother has been sent away. 2 Why is it that, when I came in, there was no one? When I called, there was nobody answering? Has my hand become in fact so short that it cannot redeem, or is there in me no power to deliver? Look! With my rebuke I dry up the sea; I make rivers a wilderness. Their fish stink due to there being no water, and they die because of thirst. 3 I clothe the heavens with obscurity, and I make sackcloth itself their covering.”

4 The Sovereign Lord Jehovah himself has given me the tongue of the taught ones, that I may know how to answer the tired one with a word. He awakens morning by morning; he awakens my ear to hear like the taught ones. 5 The Sovereign Lord Jehovah himself has opened my ear, and I, for my part, was not rebellious. I did not turn in the opposite direction. 6 My back I gave to the strikers, and my cheeks to those plucking off the hair. My face I did not conceal from humiliating things and spit.

7 But the Sovereign Lord Jehovah himself will help me. That is why I shall not have to feel humiliated. That is why I have set my face like a flint, and I know that I shall not be ashamed. 8 The One declaring me righteous is near. Who can contend with me? Let us stand up together. Who is my judicial antagonist? Let him approach me. 9 Look! The Sovereign Lord Jehovah himself will help me. Who is there that can pronounce me wicked? Look! All of them, like a garment, will wear out. A mere moth will eat them up.

10 Who among YOU people is in fear of Jehovah, listening to the voice of his servant, who has walked in continual darkness and for whom there has been no brightness? Let him trust in the name of Jehovah and support himself upon his God.

11 “Look! All YOU who are igniting a fire, making sparks light up, walk in the light of YOUR fire, and amid the sparks that YOU have set ablaze. From my hand YOU will certainly come to have this: In sheer pain YOU will lie down.

Isaiah

59 Look! The hand of Jehovah has not become too short that it cannot save, nor has his ear become too heavy that it cannot hear. 2 No, but the very errors of YOU people have become the things causing division between YOU and YOUR God, and YOUR own sins have caused the concealing of his face from YOU to keep from hearing. 3 For YOUR own palms have become polluted with blood, and YOUR fingers with error. YOUR own lips have spoken falsehood. YOUR own tongue kept muttering sheer unrighteousness. 4 There is no one calling out in righteousness, and no one at all has gone to court in faithfulness. There has been a trusting in unreality, and a speaking of worthlessness. There has been a conceiving of trouble, and a bringing of what is hurtful to birth.

5 The eggs of a poisonous snake are what they have hatched, and they kept weaving the mere cobweb of a spider. Anyone eating some of their eggs would die, and the egg that was smashed would be hatched into a viper. 6 Their mere cobweb will not serve as a garment, nor will they cover themselves with their works. Their works are hurtful works, and the activity of violence is in their palms. 7 Their own feet keep running to sheer badness, and they are in a hurry to shed innocent blood. Their thoughts are hurtful thoughts; despoiling and breakdown are in their highways. 8 The way of peace they have ignored, and there is no justice in their tracks. Their roadways they have made crooked for themselves. No one at all treading in them will actually know peace.

9 That is why justice has come to be far away from us, and righteousness does not catch up with us. We keep hoping for light, but, look! darkness; for brightness, but in continuous gloom we kept walking. 10 We keep groping for the wall just like blind men, and like those without eyes we keep groping. We have stumbled at high noon just as in evening darkness; among the stout ones we are just like dead people. 11 We keep groaning, all of us, just like bears; and like doves we mournfully keep cooing. We kept hoping for justice, but there was none; for salvation, but it has stayed far away from us. 12 For our revolts have become many in front of you; and as for our sins, each one has testified against us. For our revolts are with us; and as for our errors, we well know them. 13 There have been transgressing and a denying of Jehovah; and there was a moving back from our God, a speaking of oppression and revolt, a conceiving and a muttering of words of falsehood from the very heart. 14 And justice was forced to move back, and righteousness itself kept standing simply far off. For truth has stumbled even in the public square, and what is straightforward is unable to enter. 15 And the truth proves to be missing, and anyone turning away from badness is being despoiled.

And Jehovah got to see, and it was bad in his eyes that there was no justice. 16 And when he saw that there was no man, he began to show himself astonished that there was no one interposing. And his arm proceeded to save for him, and his own righteousness was the thing that supported him. 17 Then he put on righteousness as a coat of mail, and the helmet of salvation upon his head. Furthermore, he put on the garments of vengeance as raiment and enwrapped himself with zeal as if a sleeveless coat. 18 In accordance with the dealings he will reward correspondingly, rage to his adversaries, due treatment to his enemies. To the islands he will recompense due treatment. 19 And from the sunset they will begin to fear the name of Jehovah, and from the rising of the sun the glory of him, for he will come in like a distressing river, which the very spirit of Jehovah has driven along.

20 “And to Zion the Repurchaser will certainly come, and to those turning from transgression in Jacob,” is the utterance of Jehovah.

21 “And as for me, this is my covenant with them,” Jehovah has said.

“My spirit that is upon you and my words that I have put in your mouth—they will not be removed from your mouth or from the mouth of your offspring or from the mouth of the offspring of your offspring,” Jehovah has said, “from now on even to time indefinite.”

Isaiah

61 The spirit of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah is upon me, for the reason that Jehovah has anointed me to tell good news to the meek ones. He has sent me to bind up the brokenhearted, to proclaim liberty to those taken captive and the wide opening of the eyes even to the prisoners; 2 to proclaim the year of goodwill on the part of Jehovah and the day of vengeance on the part of our God; to comfort all the mourning ones; 3 to assign to those mourning over Zion, to give them a headdress instead of ashes, the oil of exultation instead of mourning, the mantle of praise instead of the downhearted spirit; and they must be called big trees of righteousness, the planting of Jehovah, for him to be beautified. 4 And they must rebuild the long-standing devastated places; they will raise up even the desolated places of former times, and they will certainly make anew the devastated cities, the places desolate for generation after generation.

5 “And strangers will actually stand and shepherd the flocks of YOU people, and the foreigners will be YOUR farmers and YOUR vinedressers. 6 And as for YOU, the priests of Jehovah YOU will be called; the ministers of our God YOU will be said to be. The resources of the nations YOU people will eat, and in their glory YOU will speak elatedly about yourselves. 7 Instead of YOUR shame there will be a double portion, and instead of humiliation they will cry out joyfully over their share. Therefore in their land they will take possession of even a double portion. Rejoicing to time indefinite is what will come to be theirs. 8 For I, Jehovah, am loving justice, hating robbery along with unrighteousness. And I will give their wages in trueness, and an indefinitely lasting covenant I shall conclude toward them. 9 And their offspring will actually be known even among the nations, and their descendants in among the peoples. All those seeing them will recognize them, that they are the offspring whom Jehovah has blessed.”

10 Without fail I shall exult in Jehovah. My soul will be joyful in my God. For he has clothed me with the garments of salvation; with the sleeveless coat of righteousness he has enwrapped me, like the bridegroom who, in a priestly way, puts on a headdress, and like the bride who decks herself with her ornamental things. 11 For as the earth itself brings forth its sprout, and as the garden itself makes the things that are sown in it sprout, in like manner the Sovereign Lord Jehovah will cause the sprouting of righteousness and of praise in front of all the nations.

Isaiah

62 For the sake of Zion I shall not keep still, and for the sake of Jerusalem I shall not stay quiet until her righteousness goes forth just like the brightness, and her salvation like a torch that burns.

2 “And the nations will certainly see your righteousness, O woman, and all kings your glory. And you will actually be called by a new name, which the very mouth of Jehovah will designate. 3 And you must become a crown of beauty in the hand of Jehovah, and a kingly turban in the palm of your God. 4 No more will you be said to be a woman left entirely; and your own land will no more be said to be desolate; but you yourself will be called My Delight Is in Her, and your land Owned as a Wife. For Jehovah will have taken delight in you, and your own land will be owned as a wife. 5 For just as a young man takes ownership of a virgin as his wife, your sons will take ownership of you as a wife. And with the exultation of a bridegroom over a bride, your God will exult even over you. 6 Upon your walls, O Jerusalem, I have commissioned watchmen. All day long and all night long, constantly, let them not keep still.

“YOU who are making mention of Jehovah, let there be no silence on YOUR part, 7 and do not give him any silence until he fixes solidly, yes, until he sets Jerusalem as a praise in the earth.”

8 Jehovah has sworn with his right hand and with his strong arm: “I will no more give your grain as food to your enemies, nor will foreigners drink your new wine, for which you have toiled. 9 But the very ones gathering it will eat it, and they will be certain to praise Jehovah; and the very ones collecting it will drink it in my holy courtyards.”

10 Pass out, pass out through the gates, YOU men. Clear the way of the people. Bank up, bank up the highway. Rid it of stones. Raise up a signal for the peoples.

11 Look! Jehovah himself has caused it to be heard to the farthest part of the earth: “Say, YOU people, to the daughter of Zion, ‘Look! Your salvation is coming. Look! The reward he gives is with him, and the wages he pays are before him.’”

12 And men will certainly call them the holy people, those repurchased by Jehovah; and you yourself will be called Searched For, a City Not Left Entirely.

Jeremiah

1 The words of Jeremiah the son of Hil·ki′ah, one of the priests that were in An′a·thoth in the land of Benjamin; 2 to whom the word of Jehovah occurred in the days of Jo·si′ah the son of A′mon, the king of Judah, in the thirteenth year of his reigning. 3 And it kept on occurring in the days of Je·hoi′a·kim the son of Jo·si′ah, the king of Judah, until the completion of the eleventh year of Zed·e·ki′ah the son of Jo·si′ah, the king of Judah, until Jerusalem went into exile in the fifth month.

4 And the word of Jehovah began to occur to me, saying: 5 “Before I was forming you in the belly I knew you, and before you proceeded to come forth from the womb I sanctified you. Prophet to the nations I made you.”

6 But I said: “Alas, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah! Here I actually do not know how to speak, for I am but a boy.”

7 And Jehovah went on to say to me: “Do not say, ‘I am but a boy.’ But to all those to whom I shall send you, you should go; and everything that I shall command you, you should speak. 8 Do not be afraid because of their faces, for ‘I am with you to deliver you,’ is the utterance of Jehovah.”

9 At that Jehovah thrust his hand out and caused it to touch my mouth. Then Jehovah said to me: “Here I have put my words in your mouth. 10 See, I have commissioned you this day to be over the nations and over the kingdoms, in order to uproot and to pull down and to destroy and to tear down, to build and to plant.”

11 And the word of Jehovah continued to occur to me, saying: “What are you seeing, Jeremiah?”

So I said: “An offshoot of an almond tree is what I am seeing.”

12 And Jehovah went on to say to me: “You have seen well, for I am keeping awake concerning my word in order to carry it out.”

13 And the word of Jehovah proceeded to occur to me the second time, saying: “What are you seeing?”

So I said: “A widemouthed cooking pot blown upon is what I am seeing, and its mouth is away from the north.”

14 At this Jehovah said to me: “Out of the north the calamity will be loosened against all the inhabitants of the land. 15 For ‘here I am calling for all the families of the kingdoms of the north,’ is the utterance of Jehovah; ‘and they will certainly come and place each one his throne at the entrance of the gates of Jerusalem, and against all her walls round about and against all the cities of Judah. 16 And I will speak with them my judgments over all their badness, in that they have left me and they keep making sacrificial smoke to other gods and bowing down to the works of their own hands.’

17 “And as for you, you should gird up your hips, and you must rise up and speak to them everything that I myself command you. Do not be struck with any terror because of them, in order that I may not strike you with terror before them. 18 But as for me, here I have made you today a fortified city and an iron pillar and copper walls against all the land, toward the kings of Judah, toward her princes, toward her priests and toward the people of the land. 19 And they will be certain to fight against you, but they will not prevail against you, for ‘I am with you,’ is the utterance of Jehovah, ‘to deliver you.’”

Jeremiah

2 And the word of Jehovah proceeded to occur to me, saying: 2 “Go, and you must call out in the ears of Jerusalem, saying, ‘This is what Jehovah has said: “I well remember, on your part, the loving-kindness of your youth, the love during your being engaged to marry, your walking after me in the wilderness, in a land not sown with seed. 3 Israel was something holy to Jehovah, the first yield to Him.”’ ‘Any persons devouring him would make themselves guilty. Calamity itself would come upon them,’ was the utterance of Jehovah.”

4 Hear the word of Jehovah, O house of Jacob, and all YOU families of the house of Israel. 5 This is what Jehovah has said: “What have YOUR fathers found in me that was unjust, so that they have become far off from me, and they kept walking after the vain idol and becoming vain themselves? 6 And they have not said, ‘Where is Jehovah, the One bringing us up out of the land of Egypt, the One walking us through the wilderness, through a land of desert plain and pit, through a land of no water and of deep shadow, through a land through which no man passed and in which no earthling man dwelt?’

7 “And I gradually brought YOU to a land of the orchard, to eat its fruitage and its good things. But YOU came in and defiled my land; and my own inheritance YOU made something detestable. 8 The priests themselves did not say, ‘Where is Jehovah?’ And the very ones handling the law did not know me; and the shepherds themselves transgressed against me, and even the prophets prophesied by Ba′al, and after those who could bring no benefit they walked.

9 “‘Therefore I shall contend further with YOU people,’ is the utterance of Jehovah, ‘and with the sons of YOUR sons I shall contend.’

10 “‘But pass over to the coastlands of the Kit′tim and see. Yes, send even to Ke′dar and give YOUR special consideration, and see whether anything like this has happened. 11 Has a nation exchanged gods, even for those that are no gods? But my own people have exchanged my glory for what can bring no benefit. 12 Stare in amazement, O YOU heavens, at this; and bristle up in very great horror,’ is the utterance of Jehovah, 13 ‘because there are two bad things that my people have done: They have left even me, the source of living water, in order to hew out for themselves cisterns, broken cisterns, that cannot contain the water.’

14 “‘Is Israel a servant, or a slave born in the household? Why is it that he has come to be for plunder? 15 Against him maned young lions roar; they have given out their voice. And they went making his land an object of astonishment. His own cities have been set afire, so that there is no inhabitant. 16 Even the sons of Noph and Tah′pan·es themselves kept feeding on you at the crown of the head. 17 Is not this what you proceeded to do to yourself by your leaving Jehovah your God during the time of his walking you in the way? 18 And now what concern should you have for the way of Egypt in order to drink the waters of Shi′hor? And what concern should you have for the way of As·syr′i·a in order to drink the waters of the River? 19 Your badness should correct you, and your own acts of unfaithfulness should reprove you. Know, then, and see that your leaving Jehovah your God is something bad and bitter, and no dread of me has resulted to you,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord, Jehovah of armies.

20 “‘For long ago I broke your yoke to pieces; I tore your bands apart. But you said: “I am not going to serve,” for upon every high hill and under every luxuriant tree you were lying sprawled out, prostituting yourself. 21 And as for me, I had planted you as a choice red vine, all of it a true seed. So how have you been changed toward me into the degenerate shoots of a foreign vine?’

22 “‘But though you should do the washing with alkali and take to yourself large quantities of lye, your error would certainly be a stain before me,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah. 23 How can you say, ‘I have not defiled myself. After the Ba′als I have not walked’? See your way in the valley. Take note of what you have done. A swift young she-camel aimlessly running to and fro in her ways; 24 a zebra accustomed to the wilderness, at the craving of her soul, snuffing up the wind; at her time for copulation, who can turn her back? All those who are looking for her will not go tiring themselves out. In her month they will find her. 25 Hold your foot back from becoming barefoot, and your throat from thirst. But you proceeded to say, ‘It is hopeless! No, but I have fallen in love with strangers, and after them I am going to walk.’

26 “As with the shame of a thief when he is found out, so those of the house of Israel have felt shame, they, their kings, their princes and their priests and their prophets. 27 They are saying to a tree, ‘You are my father,’ and to a stone, ‘You yourself brought me to birth.’ But to me they have turned the back of the neck and not the face. And in the time of their calamity they will say, ‘Do rise up and save us!’

28 “But where are your gods that you have made for yourself? Let them rise up if they can save you in the time of your calamity. For as the number of your cities your gods have become, O Judah.

29 “‘Why do YOU people keep contending against me? Why have YOU transgressed, all of YOU, against me?’ is the utterance of Jehovah. 30 To no effect I have struck YOUR sons. No discipline did they take. YOUR sword has devoured YOUR prophets, like a lion that is causing ruin. 31 O generation, see for yourselves the word of Jehovah.

“Have I become a mere wilderness to Israel or a land of intense darkness? Why is it that these, my people, have said, ‘We have roamed. We shall come to you no more’? 32 Can a virgin forget her ornaments, a bride her breastbands? And yet my own people—they have forgotten me days without number.

33 “Why do you, O woman, improve your way in order to look for love? Therefore it has also been in bad things that you have taught your ways. 34 Also, in your skirts there have been found the blood marks of the souls of the innocent poor ones. Not in the act of breaking in have I found them, but they are upon all these.

35 “But you say, ‘I have remained innocent. Surely his anger has turned back from me.’

“Here I am entering into controversy with you on account of your saying, ‘I have not sinned.’ 36 Why do you treat as very insignificant the changing of your way? Of Egypt, too, you will become ashamed, just as you became ashamed of As·syr′i·a. 37 For this cause also you will go forth with your hands upon your head, because Jehovah has rejected the objects of your confidence, and you will have no success with them.”

Jeremiah

3 There is a saying: “If a man should send away his wife and she should actually go away from him and become another man’s, should he return to her anymore?”

Has that land not positively been polluted?

“And you yourself have committed prostitution with many companions; and should there be a returning to me?” is the utterance of Jehovah. 2 “Raise your eyes to the beaten paths and see. Where is it that you have not been raped? Alongside the ways you have sat for them, like an Arabian in the wilderness; and you keep polluting the land with your acts of prostitution and with your badness. 3 So copious showers are withheld, and not even a spring rain has occurred. And the forehead of a wife committing prostitution is what has become yours. You have refused to feel humiliated. 4 Have you from now on called out to me, ‘My Father, you are the confidential friend of my youth! 5 Should one stay resentful to time indefinite, or keep watching something forever?’ Look! You have spoken, and you went on to do bad things and prevail.”

6 And Jehovah proceeded to say to me in the days of Jo·si′ah the king: “‘Have you seen what unfaithful Israel has done? She is going upon every high mountain and underneath every luxuriant tree, that she may commit prostitution there. 7 And after her doing all these things I kept saying that she should return even to me, but she did not return; and Judah kept looking at her own treacherous sister. 8 When I got to see that, for the very reason that unfaithful Israel had committed adultery, I sent her away and proceeded to give the certificate of her full divorce to her, yet treacherously dealing Judah her sister did not become afraid, but she herself also began to go and commit prostitution. 9 And her prostitution occurred because of her frivolous view, and she kept polluting the land and committing adultery with stones and with trees; 10 and even for all this her treacherous sister Judah did not return to me with all her heart, only falsely,’ is the utterance of Jehovah.”

11 And Jehovah went on to say to me: “Unfaithful Israel has proved her own soul to be more righteous than treacherously dealing Judah. 12 Go, and you must proclaim these words to the north and say:

“‘“Do return, O renegade Israel,” is the utterance of Jehovah.’ ‘“I shall not have my face drop angrily upon YOU people, for I am loyal,” is the utterance of Jehovah.’ ‘“I shall not stay resentful to time indefinite. 13 Only take note of your error, for it is against Jehovah your God that you have transgressed. And you continued scattering your ways to the strangers under every luxuriant tree, but to my voice YOU people did not listen,” is the utterance of Jehovah.’”

14 “Return, O YOU renegade sons,” is the utterance of Jehovah. “For I myself have become the husbandly owner of YOU people; and I will take YOU, one out of a city and two out of a family, and I will bring YOU to Zion. 15 And I will give YOU shepherds in agreement with my heart, and they will certainly feed YOU with knowledge and insight. 16 And it must occur that YOU will become many and certainly bear fruit in the land in those days,” is the utterance of Jehovah. “No more will they say, ‘The ark of the covenant of Jehovah!’ nor will it come up into the heart, nor will they remember it or miss it, and no more will it be made. 17 In that time they will call Jerusalem the throne of Jehovah; and to her all the nations must be brought together to the name of Jehovah at Jerusalem, and they will no more walk after the stubbornness of their bad heart.”

18 “In those days they will walk, the house of Judah alongside the house of Israel, and together they will come out of the land of the north into the land that I gave as a hereditary possession to YOUR forefathers. 19 And I myself have said, ‘O how I proceeded to place you among the sons and to give you the desirable land, the hereditary possession of the ornament of the armies of the nations!’ And I further said, ‘“My Father!” YOU people will call out to me, and from following me YOU people will not turn back.’ 20 ‘Truly as a wife has treacherously gone from her companion, so YOU, O house of Israel, have dealt treacherously with me,’ is the utterance of Jehovah.”

21 On the beaten paths there has been heard a sound, the weeping, the entreaties of the sons of Israel. For they have twisted their way; they have forgotten Jehovah their God.

22 “Return, YOU renegade sons. I shall heal YOUR renegade condition.”

“Here we are! We have come to you, for you, O Jehovah, are our God. 23 Truly the hills as well as the turmoil on the mountains belong to falsehood. Truly in Jehovah our God is the salvation of Israel. 24 But the shameful thing itself has eaten up the toil of our forefathers from our youth, their flocks and their herds, their sons and their daughters. 25 We lie down in our shame, and our humiliation keeps covering us; for it is toward Jehovah our God that we have sinned, we and our fathers from our youth on and down to this day, and we have not obeyed the voice of Jehovah our God.”

Jeremiah

4 “If you would return, O Israel,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “you may return even to me. And if you will take away your disgusting things on my account, then you will not go as a fugitive. 2 And if you will certainly swear, ‘As Jehovah is alive in truth, in justice and in righteousness!’ then in him the nations will actually bless themselves, and in him they will boast about themselves.”

3 For this is what Jehovah has said to the men of Judah and to Jerusalem: “Plow for yourselves arable land, and do not keep sowing among thorns. 4 Get yourselves circumcised to Jehovah, and take away the foreskins of YOUR hearts, YOU men of Judah and inhabitants of Jerusalem; that my rage may not go forth just like a fire, and it certainly burn with no one to do the extinguishing, on account of the badness of YOUR dealings.”

5 Tell it in Judah, YOU men, and publish it even in Jerusalem, and say it out, and blow a horn throughout the land. Call out loudly and say: “Gather yourselves together, and let us enter into the fortified cities. 6 Raise a signal toward Zion. Make provision for shelter. Do not stand still.” For there is a calamity that I am bringing in from the north, even a great crash. 7 He has gone up as a lion out of his thicket, and the one who is bringing the nations to ruin has pulled away; he has gone forth from his place in order to render your land as an object of astonishment. Your own cities will fall in ruins so that there will be no inhabitant. 8 On this account gird on sackcloth, YOU people. Beat YOUR breasts and howl, because the burning anger of Jehovah has not turned back from us.

9 “And it must occur in that day,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “that the heart of the king will perish, also the heart of the princes; and the priests will certainly be driven to astonishment, and the prophets themselves will be amazed.”

10 And I proceeded to say: “Alas, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah! Truly you have absolutely deceived this people and Jerusalem, saying, ‘Peace itself will become YOURS,’ and the sword has reached clear to the soul.”

11 At that time it will be said to this people and to Jerusalem: “There is a searing wind of the beaten paths through the wilderness on the way to the daughter of my people; it is not for winnowing, nor for cleansing. 12 The full wind itself comes even from these to me. Now I myself also shall speak forth the judgments with them. 13 Look! Like rain clouds he will come up, and his chariots are like a storm wind. His horses are swifter than eagles. Woe to us, because we have been despoiled! 14 Wash your heart clean of sheer badness, O Jerusalem, in order that you may be saved. How long will your erroneous thoughts lodge within you? 15 For a voice is telling from Dan and is publishing something hurtful from the mountainous region of E′phra·im. 16 Make mention of it, YOU people, yes, to the nations. Publish it against Jerusalem.”

“Watchers are coming from a land far away, and they will let out their voice against the very cities of Judah. 17 Like guards of the open field they have become against her on all sides, because she has rebelled even against me,” is the utterance of Jehovah. 18 “Your way and your dealings—there will be a rendering of these to you. This is the calamity upon you, for it is bitter; because it has reached clear to your heart.”

19 O my intestines, my intestines! I am in severe pains in the walls of my heart. My heart is boisterous within me. I cannot keep silent, for the sound of the horn is what my soul has heard, the alarm signal of war. 20 Crash upon crash is what has been called out, for the whole land has been despoiled. Suddenly my tents have been despoiled, in a moment my tent cloths. 21 How long shall I keep seeing the signal, keep hearing the sound of the horn? 22 For my people is foolish. Of me they have not taken note. They are unwise sons; and they are not those having understanding. Wise they are for doing bad, but for doing good they actually have no knowledge.

23 I saw the land, and, look! it was empty and waste; and into the heavens, and their light was no more. 24 I saw the mountains, and, look! they were rocking, and the hills themselves were all given a shaking. 25 I saw, and, look! there was not an earthling man, and the flying creatures of the heavens had all fled. 26 I saw, and, look! the orchard itself was a wilderness, and the very cities of it had all been torn down. It was because of Jehovah, because of his burning anger.

27 For this is what Jehovah has said: “A desolate waste is what the whole land will become, and shall I not carry out a sheer extermination? 28 On this account the land will mourn, and the heavens above will certainly become dark. It is because I have spoken, I have considered, and I have not felt regret, nor shall I turn back from it. 29 Because of the sound of the horsemen and bow shooters the entire city is running away. They have entered into the thickets, and into the rocks they have gone up. Every city is left, and there is no man dwelling in them.”

30 Now that you are despoiled, what will you do, since you used to clothe yourself with scarlet, since you used to deck yourself with ornaments of gold, since you used to enlarge your eyes with black paint? It is in vain that you used to make yourself pretty. Those lusting after you have rejected you; they keep seeking for your very soul. 31 For a voice like that of a sick woman I have heard, the distress like that of a woman giving birth to her first child, the voice of the daughter of Zion who keeps gasping for breath. She keeps spreading out her palms: “Woe, now, to me, for my soul is tired of the killers!”

Jeremiah

6 Take shelter, O YOU sons of Benjamin, from the midst of Jerusalem; and in Te·ko′a blow the horn. And over Beth-hac·che′rem raise a fire signal; because calamity itself has looked down out of the north, even a great crash. 2 The daughter of Zion has resembled indeed a comely and daintily bred woman. 3 To her the shepherds and their droves proceeded to come. Against her they pitched their tents all around. They grazed off each one his own part. 4 Against her they have sanctified war: “Rise up, and let us go up at midday!”

“Woe to us, for the day has declined, for the shadows of evening keep extending themselves!”

5 “Rise up, and let us go up during the night and bring to ruin her dwelling towers.”

6 For this is what Jehovah of armies has said: “Cut down wood and throw up against Jerusalem a siege rampart. She is the city with which an accounting must be held. She is nothing but oppression in the midst of her. 7 As a cistern keeps its waters cool, so she has kept her badness cool. Violence and despoiling are heard in her; sickness and plague are before my face constantly. 8 Be corrected, O Jerusalem, that my soul may not turn away disgusted from you; that I may not set you as a desolate waste, a land not inhabited.”

9 This is what Jehovah of armies has said: “They will without fail glean the remnant of Israel just like a vine. Put your hand back like one that is gathering grapes upon the vine tendrils.”

10 “To whom shall I speak and give warning, that they may hear? Look! Their ear is uncircumcised, so that they are unable to pay attention. Look! The very word of Jehovah has become to them a reproach, in which word they can take no delight. 11 And with the rage of Jehovah I have become full. I have become weary with holding in.”

“Pour it out upon the child in the street and upon the intimate group of young men at the same time; for they will also be caught, a man along with his wife, an old man along with one that is full of days. 12 And their houses will certainly be turned over to others for possession, the fields and the wives at the same time. For I shall stretch my hand out against the inhabitants of the land,” is the utterance of Jehovah.

13 “For from the least one of them even to the greatest one of them, every one is making for himself unjust gain; and from the prophet even to the priest, each one is acting falsely. 14 And they try to heal the breakdown of my people lightly, saying, ‘There is peace! There is peace!’ when there is no peace. 15 Did they feel shame because it was something detestable that they had done? For one thing, they positively do not feel any shame; for another thing, they have not come to know even how to feel humiliated. Therefore they will fall among those who are falling; in the time that I must hold an accounting with them they will stumble,” Jehovah has said.

16 This is what Jehovah has said: “Stand still in the ways, YOU people, and see, and ask for the roadways of long ago, where, now, the good way is; and walk in it, and find ease for YOUR souls.” But they kept saying: “We are not going to walk.” 17 “And I raised up over YOU people watchmen, ‘Pay attention to the sound of the horn!’” But they kept saying: “We are not going to pay attention.” 18 “Therefore hear, O YOU nations! And know, O you assembly, what will be among them. 19 Listen, O earth! Here I am bringing in calamity upon this people as the fruitage of their thoughts, for they paid no attention to my very own words; and my law—they also kept rejecting it.”

20 “What does this matter to me that you bring in even frankincense from She′ba and the good cane from the land far away? The whole burnt offerings of YOU people serve for no pleasure, and YOUR very sacrifices have not been gratifying to me.” 21 Therefore this is what Jehovah has said: “Here I am setting for this people stumbling blocks, and they will certainly stumble over them, fathers and sons together; the neighbor and his companion—they will perish.”

22 This is what Jehovah has said: “Look! A people is coming from the land of the north, and there is a great nation that will be awakened from the remotest parts of the earth. 23 The bow and the javelin they will grab hold of. It is a cruel one, and they will have no pity. Their very voice will resound just like the sea, and upon horses they will ride. It is drawn up in battle order like a man of war against you, O daughter of Zion.”

24 We have heard the report about it. Our hands have dropped. Distress itself has seized hold of us, labor pains like those of a woman giving birth. 25 Do not go out into the field, and do not walk even in the way; for there is the sword belonging to the enemy, there is fright all around. 26 O daughter of my people, gird on sackcloth and wallow in the ashes. Make your mourning that for an only son, the wailing of bitterness; because suddenly the despoiler will come upon us.

27 “I have made you a metal tester among my people, one making a thorough search; and you will take note and you must examine their way. 28 All of them are the most stubborn men, walking about as slanderers—copper and iron. They are all of them ruinous. 29 The bellows have been scorched. Out from their fire there is lead. One has kept refining intensely simply for nothing, and those who are bad have not been separated. 30 Rejected silver is what people will certainly call them, for Jehovah has rejected them.”